<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosntds</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1935-2735</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0007385</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PNTD-D-19-00225</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Viewpoints</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Eukaryota</subject><subj-group><subject>Protozoans</subject><subj-group><subject>Parasitic protozoans</subject><subj-group><subject>Acanthamoeba</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemical compounds</subject><subj-group><subject>Organic compounds</subject><subj-group><subject>Carbohydrates</subject><subj-group><subject>Monosaccharides</subject><subj-group><subject>Galactose</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Organic chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Organic compounds</subject><subj-group><subject>Carbohydrates</subject><subj-group><subject>Monosaccharides</subject><subj-group><subject>Galactose</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemical compounds</subject><subj-group><subject>Organic compounds</subject><subj-group><subject>Carbohydrates</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Organic chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Organic compounds</subject><subj-group><subject>Carbohydrates</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemical compounds</subject><subj-group><subject>Organic compounds</subject><subj-group><subject>Carbohydrates</subject><subj-group><subject>Monosaccharides</subject><subj-group><subject>Glucose</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Organic chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Organic compounds</subject><subj-group><subject>Carbohydrates</subject><subj-group><subject>Monosaccharides</subject><subj-group><subject>Glucose</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pharmacology</subject><subj-group><subject>Pharmacokinetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Drug metabolism</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Parasitology</subject><subj-group><subject>Parasite groups</subject><subj-group><subject>Apicomplexa</subject><subj-group><subject>Trophozoites</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Metabolism</subject><subj-group><subject>Carbohydrate metabolism</subject><subj-group><subject>Glucose metabolism</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemical compounds</subject><subj-group><subject>Organic compounds</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellulose</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Organic chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Organic compounds</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellulose</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Galactose as novel target against <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cysts</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8638-3193</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Anwar</surname>
<given-names>Ayaz</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>Naveed A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Siddiqui</surname>
<given-names>Ruqaiyyah</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><addr-line>Department of Biological Sciences, School of Science and Technology, Sunway University, Subang Jaya, Selangor, Malaysia</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>Kevin SW</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>National University of Singapore, SINGAPORE</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">ayazanwar@sunway.edu.my</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>26</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>7</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<elocation-id>e0007385</elocation-id>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Anwar et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0007385"/>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="1"/>
<table-count count="1"/>
<page-count count="4"/>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p><italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> spp. are the common free-living amoebae known to be associated with brain infections and sight-intimidating keratitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref001">1</xref>]. <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> spp. have two stages in their life cycle: metabolically active trophozoite and dormant cyst [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref002">2</xref>]. A major challenge in the treatment of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> infections is degradation of resistant cysts. The process of conversion of trophozoite to cyst is called encystation, which is usually triggered by harsh conditions such as nutrition deprivation, extremes in environment, chemotherapy, etc. Once the treatment is stopped, cysts convert back into the infective trophozoites stage, resulting in infection recurrence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref003">3</xref>]. It is imperative to target the cyst stage for successful prognosis. During encystation, the trophozoites efflux excessive food and enclose themselves in minimal metabolic activity by formation of double-walled (ectocyst and endocyst) protected cysts. The chemical composition of cyst walls of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> belonging to the T4 genotype consists of 35% carbohydrates and 33% proteins, and the rest is a mixture of lipids, ash, and some unidentified materials. Among the carbohydrates, galactose and glucose monosaccharides are present in combined 96%, while 3-linked galactopyranose is the most abundant glycosyl linkage in cyst walls, making up to 29% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0007385.t001">Table 1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref004">4</xref>]. Hence, carbohydrates affecting agents are potential drug targets against cysts. In this regard, galactose has not gained deserved attention as a therapeutic target as compared to glucose. The product of glucose in the cyst walls has been identified as cellulose, and an extensive cellulose-targeting agent has been tested and found effective in either controlling encystation and/or a development of combination therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref005">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref007">7</xref>]. Recently, Garajová and colleagues studied the effects of cytoskeletal elements such as microtubular networks and actin filaments in the last stages of encystment of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic>. Cellulose fibrils, which are the main component of endocyst, were demonstrated in endocystic space as well as in the ectocyst. They further detected the intramembranous particles (IMPs) to form clusters in the cytoplasmic membrane during encystment by using a variety of microscopic techniques. Cyst wall impermeability due to the presence of complex polysaccharides has been shown to be responsible for the resistance of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cysts against therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref008">8</xref>]. In another report, Lloyd reviewed the aerophilic biochemical processes involved in the ecystment of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic>, while also highlighting the effects of the most commonly used drugs, natural compounds, and contact lens solutions against cysts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref009">9</xref>]. However, the most abundant carbohydrate, i.e., galactose, has been neglected. In this contribution, we highlight the importance of this untapped research area for specific drug development by identifying potential products of galactose.</p>
<table-wrap id="pntd.0007385.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0007385.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Comparative carbohydrates composition in the cyst walls of <italic>Acanthamoeba castellanii</italic>.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pntd.0007385.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0007385.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Monosaccharide</th>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left">Glycoside linkage</th>
<th align="left">%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Glucose</td>
<td align="left">53.4</td>
<td align="left">4-linked glucopyranose</td>
<td align="left">22.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Galactose</td>
<td align="left">43.7</td>
<td align="left">3-linked galactopyranose</td>
<td align="left">28.6</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Possible products of galactose in <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cysts</title>
<p>Galactose is synthesized by the human body, in which it forms part of glycolipids and glycoproteins in several tissues. It is also an important component of cerebrosides, which are glycosphingolipids that are important components in animal muscle and nerve cell membranes. Myelin is the most known cerebroside. Galactocerebrosides are typically found in neural tissue, while glucocerebrosides are found in other tissues. Moreover, in the human body, glucose is changed into galactose in order to enable the mammary glands to secrete lactose. One of the known products of galactose in <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cyst is galactose-alpha-1→3-galactose (alpha-gal) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref004">4</xref>]. It is a disease-causing sugar that has been recognized as a potential allergen present in mammal meat. Alpha-gal is hydrolyzed into two units of galactose by alpha-galactosidase; however, unlike chemical hydrolysis of most of the sugars by using acid/base reactions, it is an unfeasible option for biological system. Another known product is polymeric galactose that is known as galactan, which is found in hemicellulose. Lipophosphonoglycan analysis of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> has shown the presence of galactose in the glycans both in the neutral form as well as in the amino form [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref010">10</xref>]. The cellulosome structure of various bacteria including <italic>Clostridium thermocellum</italic>, <italic>Roseovarius albus</italic>, etc., which are reviewed by Lakhundi and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref011">11</xref>], has been studied via a combination of various biochemical, structural, and genetic analysis. It is also important to note that cellulosomal components of these microbes do not only include cellulases but hemicellulases as well. Galactans can also be degraded by hemicellulases. These are typically specific toward a particular sugar; therefore, we can find β-D-galactanases, β-D-mannanases, and β-D-oxylanases. Unlike cellulose, hemicellulose is easier to degrade, but strangely, none of the hemicellulases have been tested against amoebae, while cellulase has shown potential in combination therapy against <italic>A</italic>. <italic>castellanii</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref005">5</xref>]. In a recent report, <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> is shown to possess different enzymes for the utilization of plant cell wall polysaccharides. This galactan degradation cascade includes a gene cluster containing galactan degradation genes (<italic>ganA</italic> and <italic>ganB</italic>), two transporter component genes (<italic>ganQ</italic> and <italic>ganP</italic>), and the sugar-binding lipoprotein-encoding gene <italic>ganS</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref012">12</xref>]. Another product of naturally occurring galactose was identified by chemical structural analysis of the carbohydrate chains in the glycoproteins of fungi <italic>Fusarium</italic> spp. M7-1 demonstrated that the backbone of the polysaccharide chain is beta-1→6-galactofuranoside linkages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref013">13</xref>]. However, the presence of these suggested galactose products in <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> as well as in other parasites are all not biochemically proven to be present, which needs to be addressed urgently. The abundance of galactose found in cyst walls suggest the presence of various compounds, which might be completely unknown as well. Therefore, the galactose component of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cysts should be subjected to thorough spectroscopic and chromatographic identification so that further understanding of the possible pathways could be developed, which will lead to novel drug targets. Some of the possible biologically known products of galactose are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0007385.g001">Fig 1</xref> below. Based on the highlighted product, the next section deals with some of the important galactose targeting strategies that can be utilized to target <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cysts.</p>
<fig id="pntd.0007385.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0007385.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Galactose products most probably present in cyst walls of <italic>Acanthamoeba castellanii</italic>.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0007385.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Glycoside-targeting biomolecules</title>
<p>Alpha-galactosidase hydrolyses the terminal alpha-galactosyl sugars from glycolipids and glycoproteins and may be a useful enzyme to target biosynthesis and/or degradation of galactose in <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic>, which may result in compromised cyst walls integrity. Another enzyme lactase may be useful against <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cysts, as this is essential to metabolize the lactose sugar into glucose and galactose, primary subunits in cyst walls of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic>. Previously, biomolecules including cellulase, glycogen phosphorylase–signaling RNA, etc. are known to alter formation, degradation, and viability of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cysts; however, these biomolecules are restricted to target glucose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref014">14</xref>]. Endo-β-galactofuranosidase has been used to degrade beta-1→6 galactofuranoside linkages present in the fungi of <italic>Fusarium</italic> spp. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref011">11</xref>]. These biomolecules can be potential candidates for targeting galactose in the cyst walls of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> species. Furthermore, the knowledge extracted from allergic reactions involving metabolism of galactose can be applied to target <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cysts. Antihistamine drugs such as diphenhydramine and epinephrine are usually given to control the reaction of alpha-gal allergy. Small molecule activators of glycoside hydrolases are another interesting candidate that may be effective with or without the enzyme to accelerate the catalysis of the targeting sugar [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref015">15</xref>]. Furthermore, formulating nanoparticles conjugated with the above mentioned molecules to specifically target galactose may exhibit improved cysticidal effects against <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic>. Nanoparticles are reported to deliver drugs effectively at the target site which enhance drug efficacy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0007385.ref016">16</xref>]. If proven successful, the proposed strategy would offer a viable option for broadening the molecular targeting of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cysts and a major step forward in tackling the drug resistance in <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> species.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>We anticipate that galactose-targeting approaches will open new horizons in the drug development against <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cysts. Although, some common products of galactose are identified here that are known to be present in biological systems of parasites; however, there can be a lot more different compounds that are not known yet and need further identification. Hence, isolation and structural analysis of complex glycosides present in cyst walls by spectroscopic techniques guarantees further understanding of resistant <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cysts. Furthermore, galactose-targeting molecules and nanomaterials suggested here can provide a novel therapeutic target against <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> cysts.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>Authors would like to acknowledge Sunway University Malaysia for their support.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marciano-Cabral</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabral</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title><italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> spp. as agents of disease in humans</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1128/CMR.16.2.273-307.2003" xlink:type="simple">10.1128/CMR.16.2.273-307.2003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12692099</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>. <article-title><italic>Acanthamoeba</italic>: biology and increasing importance in human health</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6976.2006.00023.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2006.00023.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16774587</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biology and pathogenesis of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic></article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>6</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudley</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jarroll</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Carbohydrate analysis of <italic>Acanthamoeba castellanii</italic></article-title>. <source>Exp Parasitol</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>338</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.exppara.2009.04.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.exppara.2009.04.009</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19389397</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abjani</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yousuf</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Targeting cyst wall is an effective strategy in improving the efficacy of marketed contact lens disinfecting solutions against <italic>Acanthamoeba castellanii</italic> cysts</article-title>. <source>Cont Lens Anter Eye</source>. <year>2016</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzo-Morales</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kliescikova</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Carretero</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Pablos</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Profotova</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nohynkova</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Glycogen phosphorylase in <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> spp.: determining the role of the enzyme during the encystment process using RNA interference</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>517</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1128/EC.00316-07" xlink:type="simple">10.1128/EC.00316-07</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18223117</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudley</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alsam</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cellulose biosynthesis pathway is a potential target in the improved treatment of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> keratitis</article-title>. <source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00253-006-0793-8" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00253-006-0793-8</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17225099</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garajová</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mrva</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaškovicová</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinka</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melicherová</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valigurová</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cellulose fibrils formation and organisation of cytoskeleton during encystment are essential for Acanthamoeba cyst wall architecture</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2019</year>; <volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>4466</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-41084-6" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/s41598-019-41084-6</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">30872791</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Encystment in <italic>Acanthamoeba castellanii</italic>: A review</article-title>. <source>Exp Parasitol</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>S20</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.exppara.2014.03.026" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.exppara.2014.03.026</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24726698</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Korn</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dearborn</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>PL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Lipophosphonoglycan of the Plasma Membrane of <italic>Acanthamoeba castellanii</italic>. Isolation from whole amoebae and identification of the water-soluble products of acid hydrolysis</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>1974</year>; <volume>249</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>3335</fpage>–<lpage>3341</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">4831216</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakhundi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cellulose degradation: a therapeutic strategy in the improved treatment of <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> infections</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>23</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watzlawick</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heravi</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altenbuchner</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Role of the <italic>ganSPQAB</italic> operon in degradation of galactan by <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>2016</year>; <volume>198</volume>: <fpage>2887</fpage>–<lpage>2896</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1128/JB.00468-16" xlink:type="simple">10.1128/JB.00468-16</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27501980</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwahara</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mishima</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramli</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takegawa</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Degradation of β 1→ 6 Galactofuranoside Linkages in the Polysaccharide of <italic>Fusarium</italic> sp. M7-1 by Endo-β-galactofuranosidase from <italic>Bacillus</italic> sp</article-title>. <source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source>. <year>1996</year>; <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>957</fpage>–<lpage>961</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8695912</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anwar</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Combating <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> spp. cysts: what are the options?</article-title> <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>26</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13071-017-2572-z" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/s13071-017-2572-z</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">29316961</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darby</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landström</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hubbard</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Discovery of selective small-molecule activators of a bacterial glycoside hydrolase</article-title>. <source>Angew Chem Int Ed</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>13419</fpage>–<lpage>13423</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0007385.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anwar</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rajendran</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raza Shah</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Clinically-approved drugs against CNS diseases as potential therapeutic agents to target brain-eating amoebae</article-title>. <source>ACS Chem Neurosci</source>. <year>2019</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>658</fpage>–<lpage>666</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acschemneuro.8b00484" xlink:type="simple">10.1021/acschemneuro.8b00484</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">30346711</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>