<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosntds</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1935-2735</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PNTD-D-13-01600</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003100</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Fungal diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Histoplasmosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Viral diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>AIDS</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Infectious disease control</subject><subject>Sexually transmitted diseases</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Tropical diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Neglected tropical diseases</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>HIV-Associated Histoplasmosis Early Mortality and Incidence Trends: From Neglect to Priority</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">HIV-Associated Histoplasmosis Early Mortality</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adenis</surname><given-names>Antoine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nacher</surname><given-names>Mathieu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanf</surname><given-names>Matthieu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vantilcke</surname><given-names>Vincent</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boukhari</surname><given-names>Rachida</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blachet</surname><given-names>Denis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demar</surname><given-names>Magalie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aznar</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carme</surname><given-names>Bernard</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Couppie</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Inserm CIC 1424, Centre d'Investigation Clinique Antilles Guyane, Centre Hospitalier de Cayenne, Cayenne, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Equipe EA3593, Epidémiologie des Parasitoses et des Mycoses Tropicales, Université des Antilles et de la Guyane, Cayenne, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Service de Médecine Interne, Centre Hospitalier de l'Ouest Guyanais, Saint Laurent du Maroni, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Laboratoire de Biologie Médicale, Centre Hospitalier de l'Ouest Guyanais, Saint Laurent du Maroni, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Laboratoire Hospitalo-Universitaire de Parasitologie-Mycologie, Centre Hospitalier de Cayenne, Cayenne, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>Unité des Maladies Infectieuses et Tropicales, Centre Hospitalier de Cayenne, Cayenne, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><addr-line>Service de Dermatologie Vénérologie, Centre Hospitalier de Cayenne, Cayenne, France</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamill</surname><given-names>Richard James</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Baylor College of Medicine, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">antoine.adenis@gmail.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AA MN PC. Performed the experiments: AA MN MH VV RB DB MD CA BC PC. Analyzed the data: AA MN MH PC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RB DB MD CA BC. Wrote the paper: AA MN MH VV RB DB MD CA BC PC.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e3100</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Adenis et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract><sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p>Histoplasmosis is an endemic fungal infection in French Guiana. It is the most common AIDS-defining illness and the leading cause of AIDS-related deaths. Diagnosis is difficult, but in the past 2 decades, it has improved in this French overseas territory which offers an interesting model of Amazonian pathogen ecology. The objectives of the present study were to describe the temporal trends of incidence and mortality indicators for HIV-associated histoplasmosis in French Guiana.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>A retrospective study was conducted to describe early mortality rates observed in persons diagnosed with incident cases of HIV-associated <italic>Histoplasma capsulatum</italic> var. <italic>capsulatum</italic> histoplasmosis admitted in one of the three main hospitals in French Guiana between 1992 and 2011. Early mortality was defined by death occurring within 30 days after antifungal treatment initiation. Data were collected on standardized case report forms and analysed using standard statistical methods.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Results</title>
<p>There were 124 deaths (45.3%) and 46 early deaths (16.8%) among 274 patients. Three time periods of particular interest were identified: 1992–1997, 1998–2004 and 2005–2011. The two main temporal trends were: the proportion of early deaths among annual incident histoplasmosis cases significantly declined four fold (χ2, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001) and the number of annual incident histoplasmosis cases increased three fold between 1992–1997 and 1998–2004, and subsequently stabilized.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>From an occasional exotic diagnosis, AIDS-related histoplasmosis became the top AIDS-defining event in French Guiana. This was accompanied by a spectacular decrease of early mortality related to histoplasmosis, consistent with North American reference center mortality rates. The present example testifies that rapid progress could be at reach if awareness increases and leads to clinical and laboratory capacity building in order to diagnose and treat this curable disease.</p>
</sec></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>Histoplasmosis is an endemic fungal infection in French Guiana. It is the most common AIDS-defining illness and the leading cause of AIDS-related deaths. Diagnosis is difficult, but in the past 2 decades, it has improved. The objectives of the present study were to describe the temporal trends of incidence and mortality indicators for HIV-associated histoplasmosis in French Guiana. A retrospective study was conducted to describe early mortality rates observed in persons diagnosed with incident cases of HIV-associated histoplasmosis admitted in one of the three main hospitals of French Guiana between 1992 and 2011. Early mortality was defined by death occurring within 30 days after antifungal treatment initiation. Data were collected on standardized case report forms and analysed using standard statistical methods. Among 274 patients there were 46 early deaths (16.8%). The two main temporal trends were: the proportion of early deaths significantly divided four fold and the number of annual incident histoplasmosis cases increased three fold. The present example testifies that rapid progress could be at reach if awareness increases and leads to clinical and laboratory capacity building in order to diagnose and treat this curable disease.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work has benefited from an “Investissement d'Avenir” grant managed by Agence Nationale de la Recherche (CEBA, ref. ANR-10-LABX-0025). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="5"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>French Guiana is a French overseas territory, located in the North-Eastern part of South America. The Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) epidemic there is the most preoccupying among French territories <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Nacher1">[1]</xref>. During the Highly Active AntiRetroviral Therapy (HAART) era, disseminated histoplasmosis has remained the most common Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome (AIDS) defining illness with an incidence of 15.4/1000 person-years in HIV-infected patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Nacher2">[2]</xref>.</p>
<p>In immunocompetent patients, <italic>Histoplasma capsulatum</italic> var. <italic>capsulatum</italic> infection is typically asymptomatic or pauci-symptomatic and spontaneous resolution is the rule in the great majority of cases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Kauffman1">[3]</xref>. On the contrary, in HIV-infected patients it presents mostly as a disseminated infection. With the worsening of the immunosuppression, the disease progression is often rapid and always fatal in the absence of treatment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Wheat1">[4]</xref>.</p>
<p>Thus, different studies have observed up to 39% of deaths following diagnosis in endemic areas, where it is supposedly well known, and 58% in non endemic areas, where it is perhaps less known <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Antinori1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Couppie1">[6]</xref>. In endemic areas, although there are different outcome measures and inclusion criteria, the death rates observed in AIDS-associated histoplasmosis differ between the USA (12–23%) and South America (19–39%) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Couppie1">[6]</xref>. Hypotheses advanced to explain these differences are a delayed recognition due to the lack of awareness of physicians, a delayed diagnosis due to the lack of diagnostic facilities and the late presentation of HIV-infected patients in resource limited settings <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Couppie1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Karimi1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Colombo1">[8]</xref>. Delayed treatment due to the unavailability of the most effective therapy in severe cases, the impossibility of monitoring drug concentrations and/or drug-drug interactions with antituberculosis treatments are other possible explanations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Couppie1">[6]</xref>.</p>
<p>In French Guiana, disseminated histoplasmosis has also been the leading cause of death among HIV-infected patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Lewden1">[9]</xref>. Despite HIV care and treatment standards close to those in Mainland France, the mortality rate of AIDS-associated histoplasmosis remains high in the HAART era (30.7% at 6 months and 17.5 at 1 month), whereas in Mainland France, a non-endemic area, this mortality rate was divided by two <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Huber1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Peigne1">[11]</xref>.</p>
<p>The objective of this study was to describe the temporal trends of incidence and mortality indicators for AIDS-associated histoplasmosis in French Guiana. This knowledge is important to guide and improve AIDS-associated histoplasmosis diagnosis, care and treatment, and to illustrate that awareness and standard practices in mycology can dramatically change prognosis.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Ethics Statement</title>
<p>Since 1992, an anonymized database compiles retrospectively and continuously <italic>Histoplasma capsulatum var. capsulatum</italic> histoplasmosis confirmed incident cases diagnosed in HIV-infected patients according to the case definition of the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer/Invasive Fungal Infections Cooperative Group and the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases Mycoses Study Group (EORTC/MSG) Consensus Group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-DePauw1">[12]</xref>. The revised EORTC/MSG criteria defining a proven case of histoplasmosis are: recovery in culture from a specimen obtained from the affected site or from blood; and/or histopathologic or direct microscopic demonstration of appropriate morphologic forms with a truly distinctive appearance characteristic such as intracellular yeasts forms in a phagocyte in a peripheral blood smear or in tissue macrophages. By contrast, molecular methods of detecting fungi in clinical specimens, such as Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR), were not included in the classifications of “proven,” “probable,” and “possible” invasive fungal disease (IFD) definitions because there is as yet no standard, and none of the techniques has been clinically validated.</p>
<p>All HIV-infected patients hospitalized or seen in the outpatient department before admission, suspicious for histoplasmosis and receiving antifungal therapy in one of the three main hospitals of French Guiana (the Centre Hospitalier de Cayenne (CHC), the Centre Hospitalier Médico-Chirurgical de Kourou (CMCK) and the Centre Hospitalier de l'Ouest Guyanais in Saint Laurent du Maroni (CHOG), were identified and checked for a confirmed diagnosis of histoplasmosis in all laboratories where biological samples were sent. Then, they were finally enrolled according to the following inclusion criteria: age &gt;18 years, admission in one of the three hospitals (the inclusion date corresponding to the date of antifungal treatment initiation), confirmed HIV infection (by Western blot), confirmed incident histoplasmosis infection (EORTC/MSG criteria), and baseline blood screening within 7 days prior to antifungal therapy initiation. Non inclusion criteria were: histoplasmosis relapse or diagnosis of histoplasmosis relying only on Histoplasma Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR). Data were collected on a standardized form and included sociodemographic, clinical, biologic, radiologic, therapeutic and survival information. These data were then entered in an anonymized database. Ethical approval was obtained for the database and related studies (IRB0000388, FWA00005831). A descriptive study of the patients included in this database until April 2007 was published elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Huber1">[10]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>An observational, retrospective and multicentric study was conducted from 01/01/1992 to 09/30/2011, using the French Guiana HIV-Histoplasmosis database described above.</p>
<p>In this study, the primary endpoint was the vital status on day 30 following antifungal therapy initiation. Patients lost to follow up within 30 days following antifungal therapy initiation, or deceased with an unknown date of death, or presenting a relapse of histoplasmosis were excluded from the analysis.</p>
<p>This early death criterion appeared as a good compromise to attribute mortality to the histoplasmosis infectious episode under consideration, in a context of severe immunosuppression favouring multiple opportunistic pathogens, ensuring simplicity and reproducibility of the study.</p>
<p>The statistical analysis was performed using STATA 10.0 (College Station, Texas, USA) (38). Descriptive analysis used proportions, medians and trend χ<sup>2</sup> test.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>There were 278 patients with AIDS-associated histoplasmosis. Four cases were excluded before the analysis (3 because they were lost to follow up and one because of an unknown date of death). Their socio-demographic characteristics and median CD4 count did not differ from the 274 patients finally selected in this study (data not shown).</p>
<p>Among the 274 patients selected for whom the vital status at 30 days after antifungal therapy initiation was known, there were 124 deaths (45.3%). The median time to death was 110 days (Interquartile Range [IQR] = 13–481) and the median age at the time of death was 39 years (IQR = 33–47). Early death occurred in 46 patients (16.8%) with a median survival time of 7 days (IQR = 3–16) after antifungal treatment initiation. The median age at the time of early death was 37 years (IQR = 32–47).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0003100-g001">Figure 1</xref> shows that the proportion of deaths occurring the same year as the diagnosis of incident histoplasmosis cases remained stable around 5 deaths per year until 2005/2006 and then stabilized around 3 deaths per year. Among these deaths cases, almost half were early deaths until 2004. From 2005 onwards there was a notable decline of early deaths along with the overall decline of mortality. In addition, starting in 1998, the number of histoplasmosis cases diagnoses increased, and subsequently the number of incident cases oscillated between 14 and 22 cases per year. Data were incomplete for 2011, the study considering cases only until 09/30/2011.</p>
<fig id="pntd-0003100-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003100.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Number of deaths and early deaths observed among annual incident histoplasmosis cases diagnosed in the three main hospitals of French Guiana between 01/01/1992 and 09/30/2011.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0003100.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Thus, three time periods of particular interest have been identified: 1992–1997, 1998–2004 and 2005–2011. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0003100-g002">Figure 2</xref> summarizes the two main temporal trends observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0003100-g001">Figure 1</xref>. First, the proportion of early deaths among annual incident histoplasmosis cases was significantly divided four fold (χ<sup>2</sup>, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001). Second, the number of annual incident histoplasmosis cases increased three fold between 1992–1997 and 1998–2004, and subsequently stabilized at the same level.</p>
<fig id="pntd-0003100-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003100.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Incident histoplasmosis cases (n) and proportion of early deaths (%) observed in the three main hospitals of French Guiana between 01/01/1992 and 09/30/2011.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0003100.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0003100-t001">Table 1</xref> showed that early deaths associated with histoplasmosis occurred mainly in men, late presenters with HIV infection (CD4 count &lt;50/mm3) among whom 10% were on HAART on admission. The incident histoplasmosis cases were mainly disseminated and often recognized as the first AIDS-defining illness in the course of HIV infection. Fungal culture and direct examination were the main methods used for the diagnosis of histoplasmosis cases. The Real Time Polymerase Chain Reaction (RT-PCR) detection method for <italic>Histoplasma</italic> only became available during the 2005–2011 period. Amphotericin B and itraconazole were the first line antifungal regimen used to treat these patients. During the study period, liposomal amphotericin B and itraconazole became the standard antifungal regimen over deoxycholate amphotericin B and fluconazole, respectively.</p>
<table-wrap id="pntd-0003100-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003100.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Description of baseline HIV infection and histoplasmosis infection characteristics and treatments in patients with AIDS-related histoplasmosis incident cases early death, in French Guiana, between 01/01/1992 and 09/30/2011.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0003100-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0003100.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Study time period</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1992–1997</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998–2004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2005–2011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 46</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Demographics and HIV characteristics on admission</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex male, <italic>n</italic>(%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (69)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (67)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (56)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (65)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean age +/− SD, years</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (13)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (11)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIV diagnosis &lt;1 year, <italic>n</italic>/N(%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/4 (25)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/7 (57)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/9 (67)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/20 (55)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histoplasmosis as the first AIDS-defining illness, <italic>n</italic>(%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (69)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (71)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (89)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (74)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concomitant opportunistic infection, <italic>n</italic>(%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (44)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (38)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (33)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (19)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient on HAART, <italic>n</italic>(%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (10)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median CD4 count (IQR 25–75%),/mm3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (5–30)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (8–54)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (15–52)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (7–50)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Histoplasmosis infection disease Classification</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Progressive disseminated histoplasmosis, <italic>n</italic>(%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (87)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (95)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (100)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (93)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulmonary histoplasmosis, <italic>n</italic>(%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (13)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Histoplasmsosis infection diagnostic methods</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungal culture, <italic>n</italic>/N (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/15 (53)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19/20 (95)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/9 (89)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35/44 (80)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direct examination (MGG), <italic>n</italic>/N (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/16 (81)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/21 (76)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/9 (67)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35/46 (76)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathology (PAS and silver staining), n/N (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/10 (70)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/6 (67)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1 (100)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/17 (71)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT-PCR, <italic>n</italic>/N (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0 (0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0 (0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/4 (100)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/4 (100)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serology (Immunodiffusion), <italic>n</italic>/N (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0 (0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1 (0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1 (0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2 (0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>First-line antifungal regimen for histoplasmosis</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">‡</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deoxycholate amphotericin B (IV), <italic>n</italic>(%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (63)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (43)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (41)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Itraconazole (oral), <italic>n</italic>(%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (25)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (43)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (56)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (39)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liposomal amphotericin B (IV), <italic>n</italic>(%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (19)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (56)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (20)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluconazole (oral or IV), <italic>n</italic>(%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (12)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>* One CD4 count missing value during the 1992–1997 period.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>†</label><p>Good practices for fungal culture and serology were implemented in 1997–1998 and RT-PCR (Polymerase Chain Reaction using a Real-Time detection method) was implemented in 2006 in Cayenne General Hospital.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>‡</label><p>3 patients received amphotericin B (liposomal or deoxycholate) and itraconazole or fluconazole simultaneously.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>SD: Standard Deviation, IQR 25–75%: Interquartile range 25%–75%, HIV: Human Immunodeficiency Virus, HAART: Highly Active Antiretroviral Therapy, MGG: May Grünwald Giemsa, IV: Intravenously.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This study described 19 years of experience in French Guiana. Three periods of interest and two main trends could be observed from 1998 onwards: the spectacular decrease of early deaths among incident histoplasmosis cases, and a simultaneous marked increase of the annual incidence of histoplasmosis cases. Whereas, during the same period, HIV prevalence in pregnant women was quite stable &gt;1% since the 1990's: 0.8%–1.4% between 1992–1997, 1.2%–1.4% between 1998–2004 and 1.0%–1.2% between 2005–2011 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Nacher1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Nacher3">[13]</xref>.</p>
<p>The increased number of annual histoplasmosis cases can be attributed to the development of medical mycology skills in hospitals laboratories, notably a reference university laboratory specialized in parasitology-mycology established since 1997 in Cayenne Hospital. By the same time, highly active antiretroviral therapy was introduced, which could have led to more patent cases of histoplasmosis due to the immune reconstitution inflammatory syndrome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Nacher4">[14]</xref>. In addition, a PCR diagnostic method became available for histoplasmosis in 2006 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Simon1">[15]</xref>. Unfortunately, urinary antigen detection for histoplasmosis is still unavailable in French Guiana.</p>
<p>The sharp decline of the proportion of early deaths can be attributed to the improvement of the diagnostic capacity along with the improvement of the clinical management of HIV-infected patients following French recommendations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Yeni1">[16]</xref>. Thus, French Guiana reached HIV-virological suppression levels comparable to those in Mainland France by 2004. In addition, this trend can also be attributed to the improvement of the clinical management of AIDS-related disseminated histoplasmosis cases. The accurate recognition of severe cases and the supply of liposomal amphotericin B since 1998, an effective and less nephrotoxic treatment recommended for severe disseminated histoplasmosis cases, were two important factors behind the progress.</p>
<p>This study had limitations. Data were collected retrospectively, which might have led to selection biases. Determining retrospectively if death was related to AIDS-associated histoplasmosis incident cases under study is challenging, considering the high percentage of concomitant opportunistic infections. Thus, we chose early death as the primary outcome because we thought that retrospectively it was the simplest and most reproducible indicator of histoplasmosis AIDS-related deaths.</p>
<p>Despite its limitations, this study showed that capacity building both in laboratory and clinical practice, effective drug availability both for HIV and histoplasmosis infections, and an effective bench to bed collaboration between actors progressively helped in reducing the burden of overall deaths and early deaths. Mortality indicators are now consistent with those described in North America, where the most effective and non invasive histoplasmosis diagnostic method is available. To further reduce early mortality, reducing diagnostic delays and antifungal therapy initiation is still a major objective. To reach it, a diagnostic method that meets the World Healh Organization's A.S.S.U.R.E.D. (Affordable, Sensitive, Specific, User-friendly, Rapid/Robust, Equipment-free and Delivered) should be developed.</p>
<p>Although our results may seem parochial, they illustrate the rapid progress that took place within a decade. The increased awareness of clinicians, who became more aggressive in their investigations, and the increased laboratory capacity led to find and treat a disease that was present but probably not identified and not treated in time. Thus, histoplasmosis, previously known as a mild disease in immunocompetent individuals, became a public health problem in HIV-infected patients, known by almost all health practitioners in French Guiana. By dealing with the mycology diagnostic tool box limitations and starting prompt presumptive antifungal treatment in HIV-infected patients it was possible to reduce early deaths considerably.</p>
<p>The historical 40% of early deaths observed in French Guiana, where histoplasmosis was known, plausibly reflects a low estimate of what happens in the Amazon region and probably beyond, where histoplasmosis is endemic but probably still widely misdiagnosed for tuberculosis and/or neglected <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Nacher5">[17]</xref>. Although cost effective strategies to prevent the disease and very effective diagnostic methods have been developed and are well known by scattered medical teams in Latin America <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Nacher6">[18]</xref>, this knowledge does not percolate to too many HIV care units and hospital laboratories <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0003100-Nacher7">[19]</xref>.</p>
<p>The present example testifies that rapid progress could be at reach if awareness increased and led to implement clinical and laboratory capacity building in order to diagnose and treat this curable disease before it is too late.</p>
</sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Nacher1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vantilcke</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parriault</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Melle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>What is driving the HIV epidemic in French Guiana?</article-title> <source>Int J STD AIDS</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Nacher2"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adenis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adriouch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>What is AIDS in the Amazon and the Guianas? Establishing the burden of disseminated histoplasmosis</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Kauffman1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Histoplasmosis</article-title>. <source>Clin Chest Med</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>225, v</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Wheat1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheat</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Connolly-Stringfield</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Curfman</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eads</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Disseminated histoplasmosis in the acquired immune deficiency syndrome: clinical findings, diagnosis and treatment, and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Antinori1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antinori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nebuloni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parravicini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corbellino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Histoplasmosis among human immunodeficiency virus-infected people in Europe: report of 4 cases and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Couppie1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Couppie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aznar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carme</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>American histoplasmosis in developing countries with a special focus on patients with HIV: diagnosis, treatment, and prognosis</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Infect Dis</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>449</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Karimi1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wheat</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cloud</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hajjeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Differences in histoplasmosis in patients with acquired immunodeficiency syndrome in the United States and Brazil</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source> <volume>186</volume>: <fpage>1655</fpage>–<lpage>1660</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Colombo1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tobon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Restrepo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Queiroz-Telles</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology of endemic systemic fungal infections in Latin America</article-title>. <source>Med Mycol</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>785</fpage>–<lpage>798</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Lewden1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewden</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sobesky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couppie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boulard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Causes of death among HIV infected adults in French Guyana and the French West Indies in the era of highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART)</article-title>. <source>Med Mal Infect</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>292</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Huber1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aznar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pierre-Demar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El Guedj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>AIDS-related Histoplasma capsulatum var. capsulatum infection: 25 years experience of French Guiana</article-title>. <source>AIDS</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1047</fpage>–<lpage>1053</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Peigne1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peigne</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dromer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lidove</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lortholary</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Imported acquired immunodeficiency syndrome-related histoplasmosis in metropolitan France: a comparison of pre-highly active anti-retroviral therapy and highly active anti-retroviral therapy eras</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>934</fpage>–<lpage>941</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-DePauw1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Pauw</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Revised definitions of invasive fungal disease from the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer/Invasive Fungal Infections Cooperative Group and the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases Mycoses Study Group (EORTC/MSG) Consensus Group</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1813</fpage>–<lpage>1821</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Nacher3"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Nacher M (2013) Rapport d'activités 2012 du Comité de Coordination Régionale de la Lutte contre l'Infection par le VIH de Guyane. Cayenne: Centre Hospitalier de Cayenne. 1–48 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Nacher4"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarazin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El Guedj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Increased incidence of disseminated histoplasmosis following highly active antiretroviral therapy initiation</article-title>. <source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>468</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Simon1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veron</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boukhari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aznar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Detection of Histoplasma capsulatum DNA in human samples by real-time polymerase chain reaction</article-title>. <source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>268</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Yeni1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Yeni P (2010) Prise en charge médicale des personnes infectées par le VIH : recommandations du groupe d'expert, rapport 2010. Paris: Ministère de la Santé et des Sports. 417 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Nacher5"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adenis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mc Donald</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Do Socorro Mendonca Gomes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Disseminated Histoplasmosis in HIV-Infected Patients in South America: A Neglected Killer Continues on Its Rampage</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e2319</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Nacher6"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adenis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basurko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vantilcke</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Primary prophylaxis of disseminated histoplasmosis in HIV patients in French Guiana: arguments for cost effectiveness</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>1195</fpage>–<lpage>1198</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pntd.0003100-Nacher7"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adenis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aznar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vantilcke</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>How many have died from undiagnosed human immunodeficiency virus-associated histoplasmosis, a treatable disease? Time to act</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>