<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosntds</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1935-2735</issn><publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PNTD-RA-1575R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Immunology/Cellular Microbiology and Pathogenesis</subject><subject>Immunology/Immunity to Infections</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Neglected Tropical Diseases</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Viral Infections</subject><subject>Virology</subject><subject>Virology/Mechanisms of Resistance and Susceptibility, including Host Genetics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Immunological and Viral Determinants of Dengue Severity in Hospitalized Adults in Ha Noi, Viet Nam</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Virology and Immunology of Dengue in Ha Noi</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>Annette</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoa</surname><given-names>Le Nguyen Minh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>Cameron P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolbers</surname><given-names>Marcel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wertheim</surname><given-names>Heiman F. L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khuong</surname><given-names>Pham Thi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ninh</surname><given-names>Tran Thi Hai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lien</surname><given-names>Trinh Thi Minh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lien</surname><given-names>Nguyen Thi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trung</surname><given-names>Nguyen Vu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hien</surname><given-names>Nguyen Duc</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>Jeremy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horby</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>Walter R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Kinh</surname><given-names>Nguyen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Oxford University Clinical Research Unit, Wellcome Trust Major Overseas Programme, Hanoi, Socialist Republic of Vietnam</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Centre for Tropical Medicine, Nuffield Department of Clinical Medicine, University of Oxford, Oxford, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>South East Asia Infectious Diseases Clinical Research Network, Jakarta, Indonesia</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>National Hospital for Tropical Diseases, Hanoi, Socialist Republic of Vietnam</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rico-Hesse</surname><given-names>Rebeca</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Southwest Foundation for Biomedical Research, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">afox@oucru.org</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AF CPS NDH JF WRT. Performed the experiments: AF LNMH TTHN TTML NTL NVK. Analyzed the data: AF MW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CPS HFLW NVT PH. Wrote the paper: AF. Critical manuscript review: CPS MW HFLW JF PH WRT. Patient recruitment, assessment, and care: PTK TTML NTL. Clinical coordinator: TTHN. Clinical management and data collection: NVK WRT.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e967</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2010</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Fox et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p>The relationships between the infecting dengue serotype, primary and secondary infection, viremia and dengue severity remain unclear. This cross-sectional study examined these interactions in adult patients hospitalized with dengue in Ha Noi.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methods and Findings</title>
<p>158 patients were enrolled between September 16 and November 11, 2008. Quantitative RT-PCR, serology and NS1 detection were used to confirm dengue infection, determine the serotype and plasma viral RNA concentration, and categorize infections as primary or secondary. 130 (82%) were laboratory confirmed. Serology was consistent with primary and secondary infection in 34% and 61%, respectively. The infecting serotype was DENV-1 in 42 (32%), DENV-2 in 39 (30%) and unknown in 49 (38%). Secondary infection was more common in DENV-2 infections (79%) compared to DENV-1 (36%, p&lt;0.001). The proportion that developed dengue haemorrhagic fever (DHF) was 32% for secondary infection compared to 18% for primary infection (p = 0.14), and 26% for DENV-1 compared to 28% for DENV-2. The time until NS1 and plasma viral RNA were undetectable was shorter for DENV-2 compared to DENV-1 (p≤0.001) and plasma viral RNA concentration on day 5 was higher for DENV-1 (p = 0.03). Plasma viral RNA concentration was higher in secondary infection on day 5 of illness (p = 0.046). We didn't find an association between plasma viral RNA concentration and clinical severity.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Dengue is emerging as a major public health problem in Ha Noi. DENV-1 and DENV-2 were the prevalent serotypes with similar numbers and clinical presentation. Secondary infection may be more common amongst DENV-2 than DENV-1 infections because DENV-2 infections resulted in lower plasma viral RNA concentrations and viral RNA concentrations were higher in secondary infection. The drivers of dengue emergence in northern Viet Nam need to be elucidated and public health measures instituted.</p>
</sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>Dengue is estimated to affect 50 million people each year and can occur as explosive outbreaks that overwhelm health systems. Despite significant advances the available knowledge is not sufficient to predict the outcome of individual infections or the occurrence of epidemics. Studies from low dengue transmission settings are lacking but offer the potential to better understand the contribution of age, primary versus secondary infection and serotype because there are likely to be more adult and primary infection patients and fewer serotypes circulating compared to high transmission settings. This is the first reported study of clinical dengue in Ha Noi, the largest urban area of Northern Viet Nam. Records kept by the Preventive Medicine Center indicate that &lt;2500 clinical dengue cases attended government health care facilities in Ha Noi each year from 1999 until 2007. Patients in Ha Noi were older than in high transmission settings, the contribution of primary infection to overt and severe illness was greater and associations between serotype, plasma viral RNA concentration and overt and severe illness were distinct. The dengue situation in Ha Noi provides an opportunity to further examine the roles of serotype and prior immunity in dengue severity and epidemic emergence.</p>
</abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Wellcome Trust United Kingdom (grant 077078/Z/05/Z). At the time of this study, WT and HW were supported by the South East Asian Clinical Infectious Disease Network (N01- A0-50042). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Dengue virus (DENV) infections range in severity from asymptomatic to a syndrome characterized by a haemorrhagic tendency and vascular permeability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Halstead1">[1]</xref>. The events that precipitate endothelial cell dysfunction and vascular leak are incompletely understood. Numerous studies including several prospective cohorts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Sangkawibha1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Burke1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Thein1">[4]</xref> demonstrate that the risk of severe dengue is higher during a secondary infection with a new serotype in children <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Halstead2">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Guzman1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Wichmann1">[7]</xref>. Severe dengue has also been associated with high viral loads <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Vaughn1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Libraty1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Wang1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Endy1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Avirutnan1">[12]</xref>, prolonged viremia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Wang2">[13]</xref> and high NS1 antigen levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Avirutnan1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Libraty2">[14]</xref>. At sub-neutralizing concentrations, dengue specific antibodies can enhance dengue virus infection of mononuclear phagocytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Halstead3">[15]</xref>. In addition, antibodies to pre-membrane protein appear to enhance infection of all serotypes, even when present at high concentration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Dejnirattisai1">[16]</xref>. It has therefore been proposed that antibody-dependent enhancement (ADE) of viremia is a risk factor for severe dengue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Halstead1">[1]</xref>. However, ADE may not fully account for severe dengue as several studies have found no association between severity and secondary infection in adults <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Wichmann1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Kuberski1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Harris1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Guilarde1">[19]</xref>, or severity and viral load <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Gubler1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Sudiro1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Chen1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Simmons1">[23]</xref>. In one study dengue virus titers were higher prior to defervescence in patients with secondary infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Vaughn1">[8]</xref> but most other studies have found that titers are either similar or higher in primary infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Wang1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Kuberski1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Gubler1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Murgue1">[24]</xref>. Demonstration of a link between enhancing antibody levels, viral load and disease severity in humans also remains elusive.</p>
<p>The emerging picture is that multiple factors including prior immunity, viral load, age of the patient and infecting serotype and genotype may contribute to the severity of dengue infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Sangkawibha1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Burke1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Guzman2">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-RicoHesse1">[26]</xref> but the nature of these interactions remains unclear. Dengue pathogenesis has largely been studied in dengue hyper-endemic regions where analysis is “confounded by a multiplicity of preexisting immunity patterns coupled with co-circulation of multiple serotypes” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Burke1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Alvarez1">[27]</xref>. Studies in low transmission settings, where few dengue serotypes circulate and primary infection in adults is common, potentially offer an opportunity to better identify factors associated with severity across serotype and immunity groups. We conducted a prospective study in Ha Noi, Viet Nam, to examine the association between primary and secondary infections, serotype, plasma viral RNA concentration, and the development of dengue haemorrhagic fever (DHF) in a low transmission setting.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Patient recruitment and clinical investigations</title>
<p>The protocol for this study was approved by the scientific and ethical committees at the National Hospital of Tropical Diseases and The Oxford University Tropical Research Ethics Committee (OXTREC). Patients provided written informed consent to participate in this study.</p>
<p>Patients were eligible for recruitment if they were admitted to the National Hospital of Tropical Diseases (NHTD) in Ha Noi, Viet Nam between September and November 2008 with a clinical diagnosis of dengue according to the WHO criteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-WHO1">[28]</xref>. These criteria were fever plus two or more of the following: headache; retro-orbital pain; myalgia/arthralgia; rash; bleeding or leukopenia. The study protocol included children but the number attending the National Hospital of Pediatrics (NHP) in Ha Noi during the study period was too low to warrant investigation. The NHTD is a 160 bed tertiary care center for adult patients with infectious diseases and also serves as a referral center for dengue in Northern Viet Nam. The NHP is the coordinating center for pediatric care in the country, receives patients from all Northern provinces and sees on average 40,000 in-patients and 350,000 out-patients per year.</p>
<p>Patients were examined daily during hospitalization by a dedicated team of physicians with experience in dengue diagnosis and treatment. Signs and symptoms of hemorrhage, capillary permeability and shock along with other relevant clinical data were prospectively recorded using standardized case record forms. Ultrasound of the chest and abdomen was performed at study enrolment and additionally when clinically indicated. Full blood counts were performed daily for at least 6 days during admission, as well as at discharge and approximately 10 days after discharge. Other investigations and clinical management were at the discretion of the attending physicians. CRFs and laboratory results were reviewed to identify patients that fulfilled the WHO criteria for dengue hemorrhagic fever (DHF), i.e. plasma leakage, plus thrombocytopenia and hemorrhagic signs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-WHO1">[28]</xref>. Plasma leakage was said to be evident if pleural effusion and/or ascites were detected by ultrasound, or if a haematocrit during admission was ≥20% higher than at follow-up. If the patient did not attend follow-up, the average of follow-up values for males (n = 60, average  = 44) or females (n = 56, average  = 38) was used. This compares to a normal haematocrit value of 38% with a range of 35–41% set by the Ministry of Health of Viet Nam. Thrombocytopenia was defined as a platelet count less than 100,000/mm<sup>3</sup>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Dengue Diagnostics</title>
<p>An in-house IgM &amp; IgG capture ELISA using antigens from DENV 1-4 and monoclonal antibodies provided by Venture Technologies (Sarawak, Malaysia) was performed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Cardosa1">[29]</xref>. A sample was considered IgM or IgG positive if the units were at least 6 times higher than the negative control sera. An internally controlled, serotype-specific, real-time reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) assay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Simmons2">[30]</xref> was used to identify the infecting serotype and determine viral RNA concentrations expressed as cDNA equivalents/ml of plasma. The sequences of the dengue serotype-specific primers and probes have been published previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Simmons2">[30]</xref>. They amplify and detect parts of the NS5 coding region that were first identified by Laue et al as being highly conserved within each dengue serotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Laue1">[31]</xref>. The assay limit of detection was 10 cDNA equivalents per reaction. Dengue NS1 antigen was detected using a commercial ELISA (BIO-RAD Platelia™ Dengue NS1 Ag) according to the manufacturer's instructions. A diagnosis of confirmed dengue was made using a previously described reference algorithm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Hang1">[32]</xref> that has been adapted to include NS1 ELISA and remove the indirect recombinant membrane protein ELISA, which was not used in this study (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0000967.s001">Figure S1</xref>). Using this algorithm a patient is considered to have confirmed dengue if either RT-PCR or NS1 ELISA is positive, if there is an increase in the level of IgM detected by ELISA or an IgG ELISA conversion in the presence of a positive IgM ELISA. Serology was considered to be consistent with primary dengue infection if on or after day 6 of illness IgM levels were at least 1.78 times higher than IgG levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Guzman3">[33]</xref>, or with secondary infection if IgM levels were less than 1.2 times higher than IgG levels.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>Illness day was calculated from the first date that the patient recalled having fever, which was assigned as day 1. Proportions were compared using odds ratios and Chi-Square or Fishers exact test when any expected cell count was less than 5. Continuous variables were presented as medians and interquartile ranges (IQR) and compared using Kruskal-Wallis and Mann Whitney tests. Data for study patients was compared to records kept by the Ha Noi Preventive Medicine Center (Ha Noi PMC), which includes age, gender, province and district of people attending government health care facilities with a clinical diagnosis of dengue by month and year.</p>
<p>We modelled dengue severity as depending on serological definition of prior infection/immunity and infecting serotype (and a potential interaction) using simple and multiple logistic regression analyses. The probability of a positive NS1 result and the log-10 plasma viral RNA measurements on day 5 of illness (i.e. the median illness day when patients were admitted) were modelled using logistic and linear regression models, respectively, depending on serological definition of prior infection, infecting serotype and dengue severity. In a sensitivity analysis, the model was additionally adjusted for age and gender. The time from illness onset to the first undetectable NS1 and viral RNA measurement, respectively, were modelled using Weibull accelerated failure time regression models for interval censored data, i.e. patients were treated as reaching undetectable levels in the interval between their last positive and their first undetectable measurement and patients for whom the first measurement was undetectable were treated as first reaching undetectable levels between illness day 1 and the day of this first measurement.</p>
<p>Analyses were performed with the statistical software R version 2.9.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-R1">[34]</xref> and SPSS for Windows, Rel. 14.0.0.245, 2005 (SPSS Inc. Chicago IL.).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Characteristics of patients admitted with confirmed dengue</title>
<p>158 of 206 eligible patients consented and enrolled in an 8 week period commencing on September 16 2008. During this time approximately 1240 clinical dengue cases attended government health care facilities in Ha Noi out of a total of 2371 for the whole of 2008 of which 975 (41%) were admitted to NHTD. 139 patients were from Ha Noi province, 11 were from 4 neighboring provinces and 6 were from more distant provinces, the farthest being Nhge An, Son La and Quang Ninh which are more than 100 km from Ha Noi. None of the patients were from provinces north of Ha Noi. Laboratory diagnosis of dengue was made for 130 patients. A further 18 with probable dengue were not included in this analysis as these were recruited significantly later in their illness and 61% had already defervesced. 26% of all enrolled patients and 23% of those with confirmed dengue had been transferred from another hospital. The age and gender distribution of confirmed dengue patients (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000967-t001">Table 1</xref>) were similar to that for dengue cases attending any government health care facility in Ha Noi in 2008 (median age 23 years, IQR 18–31, 52% male). The geographic distribution was also similar to that for all reported cases in Ha Noi (data not shown). Amongst confirmed cases serology was indicative of secondary infection in 61% and of primary infection in 34% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000967-t001">Table 1</xref>). The infecting serotype could be defined by real-time-RT-PCR for 81 patients of which 52% had DENV-1 and 48% had DENV-2 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000967-t001">Table 1</xref>). Viral RNA could not be detected by RT-PCR in 49 confirmed dengue patients. The median admission day for these patients was 1 day later than for those with virus RNA detectable by RT-PCR (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000967-t001">Table 1</xref>). The E genes of 9 DENV-2 (GenBank: GU908512- GU908520) and 20 DENV-1 (GenBank: HQ591537-HQ591556) viruses were sequenced and belong phylogenetically to the Asian 1 genotype and Genotype I, respectively (unpublished findings). Secondary infection was significantly more common in DENV-2 patients (79%) compared to DENV-1 patients (36%, p&lt;0.001). Age, sex and course of illness were similar across serotype and serology subgroups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000967-t001">Table 1</xref>). Most patients (91, 70%) were classified as dengue fever (DF) and 36 (28%) developed DHF, of which 5 were classified as grade I, 30 as grade II and 1 as grade III. All patients were well at discharge except one patient who was transferred to the surgical hospital.</p>
<table-wrap id="pntd-0000967-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Characteristics of confirmed cases categorized by prior immunity and serotype.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0000967-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Patient Group</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n (%)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">% male</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">age</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Admission day</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days febrile</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days in hospital</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DHF n (%)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>All confirmed dengue</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.5 (21–31)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (5–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (28)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Primary serology</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (34)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (21–32)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (18)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Secondary serology</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79 (61)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (20–31)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (5–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–7)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (32)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>DENV-1</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (32)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (21–32)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (4–5)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (5–7)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (26)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>DENV-2</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39 (30)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (21–40)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (4–5)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (5–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–7)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (28)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Serotype-unknown</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (38)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (20–30)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (5–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (5–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (29)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>DENV-1</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Primary</bold> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (18)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.5 (21–32)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (21)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Secondary</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (11)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (22–32)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (5–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (5–7)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (33)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>DENV-2</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Primary</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (22–26)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (25)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Secondary</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (24)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (20–42)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (4–5)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (5–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–7)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (29)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Serotype-unknown</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Primary</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (9)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.5 (20–33)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (5–7)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (3–5)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Secondary</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (25)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (20–28)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (4–5)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (5–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (4–6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (33)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>*Serology to define prior infection status was indeterminate for 7 patients (5%) including 3 DENV-1 and 4 serotype-unknown patients.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Characteristics of patients with DHF</title>
<p>In patients with DHF platelet counts fell to their lowest levels and haematocrits increased by the greatest percentage over baseline on days 5–7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0000967-g001">Figure 1</xref>). DHF rates were similar for DENV-1 and DENV-2 patients (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000967-t001">Table 1</xref>). There was a non-significant trend of higher DHF rates in patients with secondary compared to primary infection (Odds Ratio 1.96, 95% CI 0.80 – 4.85, p = 0.14). Results were consistent when including both serotype and serological definition of primary versus secondary infection in a logistic model and after adjusting for age and sex (data not shown), and there was no evidence of an interaction between serotype and primary/secondary infection status in the development of DHF (Likelihood ratio p = 0.48).</p>
<fig id="pntd-0000967-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Daily platelet and haematocrit measurements in DF and DHF patients.</title>
<p>The number of DF (94 in total) and DHF patients (36 in total) assessed each day is shown above or below each box. Haematocrits were assessed on at least 4 days for 125 of 130 confirmed dengue patients.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.g001" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Association between serotype, serology and NS1</title>
<p>The proportion NS1 positive on day 5 of illness was significantly higher for DENV-1 compared to DENV-2 patients and the time to undetectable NS1 was shorter for DENV-2 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000967-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0000967-g002">Figure 2</xref>). The proportion NS1 positive on day 5 was similar for patients with primary and secondary infection but the time to undetectable was shorter for secondary infection. There was no evidence of an interaction between serotype and primary/secondary infection status (Likelihood ratio  = 0.24) and effects were consistent when the analysis was additionally adjusted for age and gender. There was also no evidence of any association between NS1 and DHF (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000967-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pntd-0000967-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>NS1 measurements in DF and DHF patients stratified by serotype and primary versus secondary infection.</title>
<p>Plasma samples collected daily during admission and at follow-up from DF (pink) and DHF (blue) patients were tested by NS1 ELISA and results presented as OD<sub>450</sub> sample/OD<sub>450</sub> cutoff control.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.g002" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pntd-0000967-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Multiple regression models for prediction of NS1 detection.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0000967-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Covariate</td>
<td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Undetectable NS1 on day 5</td>
<td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Time to undetectable NS1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR (95%CI) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Effect (95%CI)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DENV-2 versus DENV-1</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.88 (1.40 to 137.12)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.51 (0.41 to 0.63)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unknown versus DENV-1</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.13 (2.54 to 381.97)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61 (0.50 to 0.75)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Secondary versus primary</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74 (0.14 to 3.86)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.72</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.82 (0.69 to 0.98)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DHF versus DF</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.57 (0.36 to 6.86)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.55</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97 (0.82 to 1.15)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Logistic regression for modeling the probability of undetectable NS1 on day 5, Weibull regression for time to undetectable NS1. Plasma samples from all (130) confirmed dengue patients were assessed but only 67 had plasma collected on day 5 of illness including 30 DENV-2, 27 DENV-1 patients and 24 with primary infection and 40 with secondary infection.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>*Multiplicative effect, i.e., the odds for DENV-2 patients to have undetectable NS1 on day 5 is estimated to be by a factor of 13.88 higher than for DENV-1 and the time to undetectable NS1 for patients with DENV-2 is estimated to be shorter by factor of 0.51.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Association between serotype, serology and plasma viral RNA concentration</title>
<p>Log10 viral RNA concentration in plasma on day 5 was estimated to be 0.96 lower for DENV-2 than for DENV-1 patients and the time taken until viral RNA was undetectable in plasma was estimated to be 0.89 times shorter for DENV-2 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000967-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0000967-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Plasma viral RNA concentration on day 5 was significantly higher in patients with secondary infection, but the time taken until viral RNA was undetectable in plasma was not significantly different. Results were consistent after adjusting for age and sex (data not shown) and likelihood ratio tests showed no evidence of interaction between serotype and primary/secondary infection status for either viral RNA concentration on day 5 (p = 0.96) or time taken until viral RNA was undetectable (p = 0.85). We couldn't establish a clear association between DHF and plasma viral RNA concentration on day 5 or time taken until viral RNA was undetectable in plasma.</p>
<fig id="pntd-0000967-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Viral RNA concentration in DF and DHF patients stratified by serotype and primary versus secondary infection.</title>
<p>Plasma samples collected daily during admission from DF (pink) and DHF (blue) patients were tested by RT-PCR for viral RNA and results expressed as Log10 cDNA equivalents/ml of plasma.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.g003" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pntd-0000967-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Multiple regression models for prediction of plasma log10 viral RNA concentration and time to undetectable.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0000967-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Covariate</td>
<td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">log10-viral RNA concentration on day 5</td>
<td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Time until viral RNA is undetectable in plasma</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Effect (95%CI) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Effect (95%CI)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">**</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DENV-2 versus DENV-1</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.96 (−1.78 to −0.13)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89 (0.83 to 0.96)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Secondary versus primary infection</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+0.86 (0.01 to 1.71)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.046</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06 (0.99 to 1.14)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DHF versus DF</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.21 (−1.03 to 0.61)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03 (0.96 to 1.11)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.38</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>Linear regression for modeling the viral RNA concentration in plasma on day 5, Weibull regression for time to undetectable viral RNA. Plasma samples from all (130) confirmed dengue patients were assessed but only 67 had plasma collected on day 5 of illness as described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000967-t002">Table 2</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>*Additive effect.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label/><p>**Multiplicative effect.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Hospitalized dengue patients in Ha Noi in 2008 were predominantly adults with high rates of primary infection compared to Southern Vietnam <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Tricou1">[35]</xref> and other hyper-endemic regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Nisalak1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Anantapreecha1">[37]</xref>. DENV-1 and DENV-2 were the only serotypes identified, consistent with national dengue surveillance data for Ha Noi (Le Quynh Mai, personal communication), whereas in Southern Viet Nam all serotypes were detected during clinical dengue surveillance in 2008 but DENV-1 was predominant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Vu1">[38]</xref>. Overall case numbers and clinical presentation were similar for DENV-1 and DENV-2. However, while primary infection predominated amongst DENV-1 patients suggesting that a substantial proportion of adults are dengue naïve, secondary infection predominated in DENV-2. This suggests that primary DENV-2 infections may be less likely to present clinically.</p>
<p>A limitation of this study is that patients were recruited from only one hospital in Hanoi. However, the patients studied represented ∼12% of dengue cases seeking treatment for dengue at government health care centers in Ha Noi during the study period and had similar epidemiology. We did not include children as originally intended because only 5 were admitted to the National Hospital of Pediatrics with clinically suspected dengue while the study was being conducted. This may be expected if transmission is low such that secondary infections mainly occur in adulthood. However it is not clear why children with primary infection do not present given that 34% of adult patients had primary infection. Others report that DHF rates during primary infection are higher for adults and suggest that primary infection is more severe in adults <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Egger1">[39]</xref>. Patients that admitted late were not precluded from this study in order to obtain a comprehensive description of clinical dengue, however this limited our ability to detect viral RNA in plasma and determine peak concentrations. The infecting serotype was unknown for 38% of confirmed dengue patients most of whom admitted 5 to 6 days after illness onset, and by day 6 viral RNA could be detected in only 39 of 100 confirmed patients tested. We suspect that DENV-2 will be the predominant infecting serotype in this group because viral RNA clearance from plasma was faster for DENV-2 than for DENV-1 patients in our study.</p>
<p>Similar to the findings of this study, records kept since 1988 indicate that Dengue case numbers have been low in Ha Noi and that dengue has predominated in adults (Horby P. et al, in preparation). This may not reflect transmission because the proportion of infections that present clinically can be low and the proportion and age-distribution depends on the prevalent serotypes and the age-associated prevalence of past infection with each serotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Burke1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Egger2">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Honorio1">[41]</xref>. However, the age of clinical dengue cases generally increases with decreasing transmission intensity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Thammapalo1">[42]</xref>, and the epidemiology of hospitalized dengue in this study is similar to that in Singapore where transmission has decreased due to effective vector control but the age and proportion of cases with primary dengue has increased, presumably because adults are more prone to present clinically upon primary infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Egger2">[40]</xref>.</p>
<p>Others have reported that primary DENV-2 infections are rarely symptomatic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Guzman1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Nisalak1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Anantapreecha1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Vaughn2">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Balmaseda1">[44]</xref>. The reason for this has not been established but our data shows that viral RNA concentration is low and NS1 detection brief in the plasma of DENV-2 compared to DENV-1 patients, factors that could be considered important in disease pathogenesis leading to severe dengue. Furthermore, the relatively high prevalence of secondary DENV-2 coincided with higher plasma viral RNA concentrations in secondary infection. It is important to note that the DENV-2 viruses sequenced in this study belonged to the Asian I genotype, which has been associated with more severe disease compared to the American genotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-RicoHesse1">[26]</xref> and with higher plasma viral RNA concentrations compared to Asian/American genotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Vu1">[38]</xref>. While the results suggest that primary infection with DENV-1 is more likely to lead to clinically overt disease than with DENV-2, we can not exclude the possibility that secondary infection contributes to overt DENV-1 or the possibility that DENV-2 infections are more likely to be enhanced than DENV-1 infections. The latter has been suggested elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Burke1">[3]</xref> and is supported by several studies showing that in children with secondary infection DHF is more common for DENV-2 compared to DENV-1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Thein1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Nisalak1">[36]</xref>. DHF was approximately twice as common in secondary compared to primary infection in our cohort, but the number of patients with DHF was small and this did not reach statistical significance or permit analysis within each serotype. However, in a study of hospitalized patients in Thailand the association between secondary infection and DHF was greater for DENV-2 than DENV-1 because DHF was less common in DENV-2 compared to DENV-1 during primary infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-R1">[34]</xref>. As in our study, this suggests that primary DENV-2 infections may be less virulent than DENV-1. As discussed above, we suspect that DENV-2 would have been the predominant infecting serotype amongst confirmed dengue patients in which the infecting serotype was unknown. NS1 measurements and prior infection status were similar for serotype-unknown and DENV-2 patients and distinct from DENV-1 patients providing further indication that DENV-1 may be distinct in terms of virulence during primary infection.</p>
<p>There was a non-significant trend of increased DHF in secondary infection, but 22% of DHF cases had primary infection. Thus secondary infection was not essential for DHF in this cohort. Secondary infection was associated with higher viral RNA concentration in plasma on day 5 of illness, but we did not find an association between viral RNA concentration and DHF. Interpretation of the effect of viral RNA concentration on DHF in our patients is limited by the relatively low proportion that developed DHF and perhaps also the high proportion that presented after day 3 of illness. Several of the studies that find an association between viremia and DHF recruit children within the first 3 days of illness and suggest that DHF is positively associated with peak viremia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Vaughn1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Libraty1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Endy1">[11]</xref>. It remains controversial whether virus clearance times also differ. In one study clearance of infectious virus determined by mosquito inoculation was faster in children with DHF compared to DF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Vaughn1">[8]</xref> but studies of adults with DENV-2 or DENV-3 infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Wang1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Wang2">[13]</xref> and children with DENV-2 infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Murgue1">[24]</xref> have found longer times to virus RNA or virus-RNA containing immune complex clearance amongst those with DHF<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Wang1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Wang2">[13]</xref>. It is also possible that we did not detect an association between DHF and plasma viral RNA concentration because a relatively high proportion of our patients had primary DENV-1 and studies where DHF has been associated with viremia rarely include primary DENV-1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Libraty1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Wang1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Endy1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Wang2">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Libraty2">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Murgue1">[24]</xref> or reported that there was no association in patients with primary DENV-1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Vaughn1">[8]</xref>. The contribution of plasma viral RNA concentration to the development of DHF may be not be discernable in primary DENV-1 because plasma viral RNA concentration is generally high in DENV-1, but this would imply that high viral RNA concentration alone is not sufficient to cause DHF.</p>
<p>The time until NS1 was undetectable was longer for DENV-1 compared to DENV-2, similar to findings of an earlier study in Southern Viet Nam <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Hang1">[32]</xref>. We previously suggested that this reflected a predominance of primary infection in DENV-1 and that NS1 clearance is faster in secondary infection due to sequestration by IgG <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Hang1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Kumarasamy1">[45]</xref>. In the current study there were sufficient primary cases for a stratified analysis, which demonstrated that serotype is the main determinant of the sensitivity of NS1 tests, and this should be considered when interpreting NS1-based diagnostics.</p>
<p>In conclusion our results indicate an association between secondary infection and clinically overt DENV-2 infection. Higher plasma viral RNA concentration in secondary infection may underlie the association between secondary infection and overt DENV-2. We could not detect an association between DHF and secondary infection or plasma viral RNA concentration but this may be due to the relatively high proportion of patients with primary DENV-1, a situation that may change if dengue emerges and the proportion and age of the population that is dengue naïve declines.</p>
<p>The number of countries affected by dengue has increased six-fold in the last 30 years with potential for further spread through temperate, subtropical and tropical areas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Mackenzie1">[46]</xref>. The Ha Noi Preventive Medicine Centre reported a 7-fold increase in the number of clinical dengue cases from 2008 to 2009 and this unforeseen epidemic overwhelmed the health system. A similar problem is faced in regions where dengue has been endemic for decades due to large multi-annual peaks in severe disease incidence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000967-Cummings1">[47]</xref>. Current understanding of the drivers of dengue epidemics is inadequate to predict their occurrence and inform public health prevention and preparedness measures. The dengue situation in Ha Noi provides an opportunity to further examine the roles of serotype infection sequence and prior immunity in dengue severity and emergence.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pntd.0000967.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000967.s001" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p>Dengue lab algorithm</p>
<p>(TIFF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank the patients for agreeing to participate in the study. We thank the Ministry of Health of the Socialist Republic of Viet Nam and the staff of the National Hospital of Tropical diseases for their continued support for our work and for their dedication to high quality research into infectious diseases in Viet Nam. We particularly acknowledge the doctors and nurses on the dengue ward for their hard work in patient care. We thank Cuong Hoang Quoc for collating dengue surveillance data from the Ha Noi Preventive Medicine Center.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Halstead1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>Pathogenesis of dengue: challenges to molecular biology.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>239</volume>             <fpage>476</fpage>             <lpage>481</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Sangkawibha1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sangkawibha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rojanasuphot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ahandrik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Viriyapongse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jatanasen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1984</year>             <article-title>Risk factors in dengue shock syndrome: a prospective epidemiologic study in Rayong, Thailand. I. The 1980 outbreak.</article-title>             <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>             <volume>120</volume>             <fpage>653</fpage>             <lpage>669</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Burke1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nisalak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>A prospective study of dengue infections in Bangkok.</article-title>             <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>             <volume>38</volume>             <fpage>172</fpage>             <lpage>180</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Thein1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aung</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shwe</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zaw</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Risk factors in dengue shock syndrome.</article-title>             <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>566</fpage>             <lpage>572</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Halstead2"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Udomsakdi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simasthien</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singharaj</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sukhavachana</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1970</year>             <article-title>Observations related to pathogenesis of dengue hemorrhagic fever. I. Experience with classification of dengue viruses.</article-title>             <source>Yale J Biol Med</source>             <volume>42</volume>             <fpage>261</fpage>             <lpage>275</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Guzman1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kouri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Valdes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Epidemiologic studies on Dengue in Santiago de Cuba, 1997.</article-title>             <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>             <volume>152</volume>             <fpage>793</fpage>             <lpage>799; discussion 804</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Wichmann1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wichmann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hongsiriwon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bowonwatanuwong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chotivanich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sukthana</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Risk factors and clinical features associated with severe dengue infection in adults and children during the 2001 epidemic in Chonburi, Thailand.</article-title>             <source>Trop Med Int Health</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>1022</fpage>             <lpage>1029</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Vaughn1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kalayanarooj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Innis</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nimmannitya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Dengue viremia titer, antibody response pattern, and virus serotype correlate with disease severity.</article-title>             <source>J Infect Dis</source>             <volume>181</volume>             <fpage>2</fpage>             <lpage>9</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Libraty1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Libraty</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Endy</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Houng</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kalayanarooj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Differing influences of virus burden and immune activation on disease severity in secondary dengue-3 virus infections.</article-title>             <source>J Infect Dis</source>             <volume>185</volume>             <fpage>1213</fpage>             <lpage>1221</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Wang1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>High levels of plasma dengue viral load during defervescence in patients with dengue hemorrhagic fever: implications for pathogenesis.</article-title>             <source>Virology</source>             <volume>305</volume>             <fpage>330</fpage>             <lpage>338</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Endy1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Endy</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nisalak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chunsuttitwat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Relationship of preexisting dengue virus (DV) neutralizing antibody levels to viremia and severity of disease in a prospective cohort study of DV infection in Thailand.</article-title>             <source>J Infect Dis</source>             <volume>189</volume>             <fpage>990</fpage>             <lpage>1000</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Avirutnan1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Avirutnan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Punyadee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Noisakran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Komoltri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thiemmeca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Vascular leakage in severe dengue virus infections: a potential role for the nonstructural viral protein NS1 and complement.</article-title>             <source>J Infect Dis</source>             <volume>193</volume>             <fpage>1078</fpage>             <lpage>1088</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Wang2"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Juan</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Slower rates of clearance of viral load and virus-containing immune complexes in patients with dengue hemorrhagic fever.</article-title>             <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>             <volume>43</volume>             <fpage>1023</fpage>             <lpage>1030</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Libraty2"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Libraty</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Endy</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kalayanarooj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>High circulating levels of the dengue virus nonstructural protein NS1 early in dengue illness correlate with the development of dengue hemorrhagic fever.</article-title>             <source>J Infect Dis</source>             <volume>186</volume>             <fpage>1165</fpage>             <lpage>1168</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Halstead3"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>O'Rourke</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1977</year>             <article-title>Dengue viruses and mononuclear phagocytes. I. Infection enhancement by non-neutralizing antibody.</article-title>             <source>J Exp Med</source>             <volume>146</volume>             <fpage>201</fpage>             <lpage>217</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Dejnirattisai1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dejnirattisai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jumnainsong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Onsirisakul</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fitton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vasanawathana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Cross-reacting antibodies enhance dengue virus infection in humans.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>328</volume>             <fpage>745</fpage>             <lpage>748</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Kuberski1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kuberski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mataika</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1977</year>             <article-title>Clinical and laboratory observations on patients with primary and secondary dengue type 1 infections with hemorrhagic manifestations in Fiji.</article-title>             <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>775</fpage>             <lpage>783</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Harris1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Videa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sandoval</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tellez</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Clinical, epidemiologic, and virologic features of dengue in the 1998 epidemic in Nicaragua.</article-title>             <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>             <volume>63</volume>             <fpage>5</fpage>             <lpage>11</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Guilarde1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guilarde</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Turchi</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Siqueira</surname><given-names>JB</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Feres</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Dengue and dengue hemorrhagic fever among adults: clinical outcomes related to viremia, serotypes, and antibody response.</article-title>             <source>J Infect Dis</source>             <volume>197</volume>             <fpage>817</fpage>             <lpage>824</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Gubler1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Suharyono</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abidin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>Viraemia in patients with naturally acquired dengue infection.</article-title>             <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>             <volume>59</volume>             <fpage>623</fpage>             <lpage>630</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Sudiro1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sudiro</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zivny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ishiko</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Analysis of plasma viral RNA levels during acute dengue virus infection using quantitative competitor reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction.</article-title>             <source>J Med Virol</source>             <volume>63</volume>             <fpage>29</fpage>             <lpage>34</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Chen1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Altered T helper 1 reaction but not increase of virus load in patients with dengue hemorrhagic fever.</article-title>             <source>FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol</source>             <volume>44</volume>             <fpage>43</fpage>             <lpage>50</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Simmons1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thuy</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tuan</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hoang</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Maternal antibody and viral factors in the pathogenesis of dengue virus in infants.</article-title>             <source>J Infect Dis</source>             <volume>196</volume>             <fpage>416</fpage>             <lpage>424</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Murgue1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murgue</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chungue</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Deparis</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Prospective study of the duration and magnitude of viraemia in children hospitalised during the 1996-1997 dengue-2 outbreak in French Polynesia.</article-title>             <source>J Med Virol</source>             <volume>60</volume>             <fpage>432</fpage>             <lpage>438</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Guzman2"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kouri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Dengue and dengue hemorrhagic fever in the Americas: lessons and challenges.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Virol</source>             <volume>27</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>13</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-RicoHesse1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rico-Hesse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Salas</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tovar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nisalak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Origins of dengue type 2 viruses associated with increased pathogenicity in the Americas.</article-title>             <source>Virology</source>             <volume>230</volume>             <fpage>244</fpage>             <lpage>251</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Alvarez1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Roche</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vazquez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Dengue hemorrhagic Fever caused by sequential dengue 1-3 virus infections over a long time interval: Havana epidemic, 2001-2002.</article-title>             <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>             <volume>75</volume>             <fpage>1113</fpage>             <lpage>1117</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-WHO1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">WHO</collab>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Dengue haemorrhagic fever: diagnosis, treatment, prevention and control. 2nd edition.</article-title>             <source>Geneva: World Health Organization. 1997. 2 ed</source>             <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Cardosa1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cardosa</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sum</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tio</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Antibodies against prM protein distinguish between previous infection with dengue and Japanese encephalitis viruses.</article-title>             <source>BMC Microbiol</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>9</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Simmons2"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Popper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dolocek</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Patterns of host genome-wide gene transcript abundance in the peripheral blood of patients with acute dengue hemorrhagic fever.</article-title>             <source>J Infect Dis</source>             <volume>195</volume>             <fpage>1097</fpage>             <lpage>1107</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Laue1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Laue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Emmerich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Detection of dengue virus RNA in patients after primary or secondary dengue infection by using the TaqMan automated amplification system.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>             <volume>37</volume>             <fpage>2543</fpage>             <lpage>2547</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Hang1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hang</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyet</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Trung</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tricou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoksan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Diagnostic accuracy of NS1 ELISA and lateral flow rapid tests for dengue sensitivity, specificity and relationship to viraemia and antibody responses.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>e360</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Guzman3"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kouri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Dengue diagnosis, advances and challenges.</article-title>             <source>Int J Infect Dis</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>69</fpage>             <lpage>80</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-R1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <comment>R DCTf A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing</comment>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Tricou1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tricou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Van</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>A randomized controlled trial of chloroquine for the treatment of dengue in vietnamese adults.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e785</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Nisalak1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nisalak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Endy</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nimmannitya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kalayanarooj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thisayakorn</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Serotype-specific dengue virus circulation and dengue disease in Bangkok, Thailand from 1973 to 1999.</article-title>             <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>             <volume>68</volume>             <fpage>191</fpage>             <lpage>202</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Anantapreecha1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anantapreecha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chanama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Naemkhunthot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sa-Ngasang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Serological and virological features of dengue fever and dengue haemorrhagic fever in Thailand from 1999 to 2002.</article-title>             <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>             <volume>133</volume>             <fpage>503</fpage>             <lpage>507</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Vu1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Duong</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TQ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Emergence of the Asian 1 genotype of dengue virus serotype 2 in viet nam: in vivo fitness advantage and lineage replacement in South-East Asia.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e757</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Egger1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Age and clinical dengue illness.</article-title>             <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>924</fpage>             <lpage>925</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Egger2"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Woolhouse</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Reconstructing historical changes in the force of infection of dengue fever in Singapore: implications for surveillance and control.</article-title>             <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>             <volume>86</volume>             <fpage>187</fpage>             <lpage>196</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Honorio1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Honorio</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Codeco</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Spatial evaluation and modeling of Dengue seroprevalence and vector density in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>e545</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Thammapalo1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thammapalo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nagao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saengtharatip</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tsujitani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Relationship between transmission intensity and incidence of dengue hemorrhagic fever in Thailand.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>e263</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Vaughn2"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Invited commentary: Dengue lessons from Cuba.</article-title>             <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>             <volume>152</volume>             <fpage>800</fpage>             <lpage>803</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Balmaseda1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Balmaseda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tellez</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saborio</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Serotype-specific differences in clinical manifestations of dengue.</article-title>             <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>             <volume>74</volume>             <fpage>449</fpage>             <lpage>456</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Kumarasamy1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumarasamy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wahab</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chem</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Evaluation of a commercial dengue NS1 antigen-capture ELISA for laboratory diagnosis of acute dengue virus infection.</article-title>             <source>J Virol Methods</source>             <volume>140</volume>             <fpage>75</fpage>             <lpage>79</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Mackenzie1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Emerging flaviviruses: the spread and resurgence of Japanese encephalitis, West Nile and dengue viruses.</article-title>             <source>Nat Med</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>S98</fpage>             <lpage>109</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0000967-Cummings1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Endy</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nisalak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Travelling waves in the occurrence of dengue haemorrhagic fever in Thailand.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>427</volume>             <fpage>344</fpage>             <lpage>347</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
</ref-list>

</back>
</article>