<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosntds</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1935-2735</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PNTD-D-15-00765</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Shaking the Tree: Multi-locus Sequence Typing Usurps Current Onchocercid (Filarial Nematode) Phylogeny</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Phylogeny of Onchocercidae</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lefoulon</surname>
<given-names>Emilie</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" deceased="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bain</surname>
<given-names>Odile</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bourret</surname>
<given-names>Jérôme</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Junker</surname>
<given-names>Kerstin</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Guerrero</surname>
<given-names>Ricardo</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Cañizales</surname>
<given-names>Israel</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff003" ref-type="aff"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Kuzmin</surname>
<given-names>Yuriy</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff004" ref-type="aff"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Satoto</surname>
<given-names>Tri Baskoro T.</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff005" ref-type="aff"><sup>5</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Cardenas-Callirgos</surname>
<given-names>Jorge Manuel</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff006" ref-type="aff"><sup>6</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>de Souza Lima</surname>
<given-names>Sueli</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff007" ref-type="aff"><sup>7</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Raccurt</surname>
<given-names>Christian</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff008" ref-type="aff"><sup>8</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Mutafchiev</surname>
<given-names>Yasen</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff009" ref-type="aff"><sup>9</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Gavotte</surname>
<given-names>Laurent</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff010" ref-type="aff"><sup>10</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>Coralie</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Unité Molécules de Communication et Adaptation des Microorganismes, Sorbonne Universités, Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle, Paris, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>ARC-Onderstepoort Veterinary Institute, Onderstepoort, South Africa</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Laboratorio de Biologia de Vectores y Parásitos, Instituto de Zoologia y Ecologia Tropical, Facultad de Ciencias, Universidad Central de Venezuela, Caracas, Venezuela</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>Institute of Zoology, Ukrainian National Academy of Sciences, Kiev, Ukraine</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff005"><label>5</label> <addr-line>Center For Tropical Medicine, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Jl Teknika Utara Yogyakarta, Indonesia</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff006"><label>6</label> <addr-line>Asociación Peruana de Helmintologia e Invertebrados Afines (APHIA), Peru</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff007"><label>7</label> <addr-line>LTEH ODILE BAIN, Departamento de Zoologia, Instituto de Ciências Biológicas Universidade Federal de Juiz de Fora, Minas Gerais, Brasil</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff008"><label>8</label> <addr-line>Laboratoire National de Santé Publique, Port-au-Prince, Haiti</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff009"><label>9</label> <addr-line>Institute of Biodiversity and Ecosystem Research, Bulgarian Academy of Sciences, Sofia, Bulgaria</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff010"><label>10</label> <addr-line>Université Montpellier, place Eugène Bataillon, Montpellier, France</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Dalton</surname>
<given-names>John Pius</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>McGill University, CANADA</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CM OB LG EL. Performed the experiments: EL JB. Analyzed the data: EL LG. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: EL CM KJ RG YK YM CR IC TBTS SdSL JMCC. Wrote the paper: EL CM LG.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">cmartin@mnhn.fr</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>20</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>11</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<elocation-id>e0004233</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>5</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>23</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Lefoulon et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<p>During the past twenty years, a number of molecular analyses have been performed to determine the evolutionary relationships of Onchocercidae, a family of filarial nematodes encompassing several species of medical or veterinary importance. However, opportunities for broad taxonomic sampling have been scarce, and analyses were based mainly on 12S rDNA and <italic>coxI</italic> gene sequences. While being suitable for species differentiation, these mitochondrial genes cannot be used to infer phylogenetic hypotheses at higher taxonomic levels. In the present study, 48 species, representing seven of eight subfamilies within the Onchocercidae, were sampled and sequences of seven gene loci (nuclear and mitochondrial) analysed, resulting in the hitherto largest molecular phylogenetic investigation into this family. Although our data support the current hypothesis that the Oswaldofilariinae, Waltonellinae and Icosiellinae subfamilies separated early from the remaining onchocercids, Setariinae was recovered as a well separated clade. <italic>Dirofilaria</italic>, <italic>Loxodontofilaria</italic> and <italic>Onchocerca</italic> constituted a strongly supported clade despite belonging to different subfamilies (Onchocercinae and Dirofilariinae). Finally, the separation between Splendidofilariinae, Dirofilariinae and Onchocercinae will have to be reconsidered.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary">
<title>Author Summary</title>
<p>Filariae are predominantly tissue-dwelling nematodes of the Onchocercidae (Spirurida). They are parasites of terrestrial vertebrates and some of them are particularly well known as agents of human diseases in tropical environments (<italic>e</italic>.<italic>g</italic>. onchocercosis, lymphatic filariosis, loaosis). Because of their predilection for host tissue sites, filariae are difficult to collect and their diversity is far from being well-investigated. Given the lack of fossilized material, it is not possible to formulate a comprehensive evolutionary hypothesis for this group based exclusively on morphological studies. Molecular analyses on the other hand have so far been based on a limited number of filarial species only or have used genetic markers convenient for species differentiation but not for retracing filarial history. Thus a consistent evolutionary framework for this family is still not in place. The originality and strength of the present study rest within its ability to access an unusually large range of biological samples, comprising 48 species representing seven of the eight onchocercid subfamilies. Using a new multi-gene dataset analysis, five major clades within the family were defined, including i) a group of ancestrally-derived subfamilies, ii) Setariinae as a sister group to all remaining subfamilies and iii) one large clade comprising genera of the Dirofilariinae, Onchocercinae and Splendidofilariinae.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This work was supported by the Interdisciplinary Programs of the MNHN (ATM Biodiversité actuelle et fossile. Crises, stress, restaurations et panchronisme: le message systématique and ATM Taxonomie moléculaire: DNA Barcode et gestion durable des collections) and by an European Community grant FP7- HEALTH-EPIAF-243121. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="4"/>
<table-count count="1"/>
<page-count count="19"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All 345 sequences were deposited in the GenBank Data Library: accession numbers KP760116 to KP760460</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The Onchocercidae (Spirurida), commonly referred to as filariae, are a family of parasitic nematodes characterised by a wide host-range in squamates, crocodilians, amphibians, mammals and birds [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. As several filarial species are agents of human and veterinary diseases [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], the Onchocercidae have been the subject of numerous studies. Presently, the family is divided into eight subfamilies, including 88 genera [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>–<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. They are nematodes with an evolved life cycle, involving blood- or skin-inhabiting first-stage larvae transmitted by haematophagous arthropods vectors [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p>
<p>A pronounced regression of morphological features and a number of convergences resulting from a parasitic life style, as well as the absence of fossilised material, make it difficult to produce phylogenetic hypotheses for this family [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Thus, major questions regarding the classification of the Onchocercidae, their origin and evolution remain as yet unresolved. In numerous morphological and biological studies an attempt has been made to elucidate the evolution of the Onchocercidae [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. First drawn up by Wehr in 1935 [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], the classification of the family has been reconstructed several times [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], with the most comprehensive analysis being that of Anderson and Bain in 1976 [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p>
<p>In 1994 [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], the development of molecular techniques made the construction of the first molecular phylogeny of the Onchocercidae, based on the 5S rDNA sequences, possible. This pioneering study focused on ten species from six genera, representing two subfamilies (Dirofilariinae and Onchocercinae). With the rise of the DNA barcoding approach to distinguish between species, studies on filarial nematode phylogeny have been predominantly based on 12S rDNA and <italic>coxI</italic> gene analyses [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>–<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], and phylogenies for selected onchocercid species have been proposed. However, biological material has been scarce, impeding broad taxonomic sampling, and the markers used were not suitable to resolve the internal nodes which describe the evolution of the Onchocercidae [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Finally, a few studies have been conducted using alternative genes, but were either focused on nematodes in general [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], a specific genus [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] or based on the mitochondrial genome [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], all including a limited number of species.</p>
<p>The aim of the present study was to propose a robust phylogenetic hypothesis of the relationships within the Onchocercidae based on the concatenation of seven loci (two mitochondrial and five nuclear genes) of 48 belonging to seven subfamilies. This hitherto most comprehensive sampling of the Onchocercidae casts doubt on the biological validity of some of the classically defined subfamilies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Material</title>
<p>Sixty-two specimens comprising 48 species belonging to 25 genera and representing seven of eight onchocercid subfamilies were analysed (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and <xref rid="pntd.0004233.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Due to a lack of material, the Lemdaninae could not be included in this study. All procedures were conducted in compliance with the rules and regulations of the respective competent national ethical bodies (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). Nematode specimens and DNA samples were deposited in the National Nematode collection of the Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle (MNHN), Paris, France; accession numbers are recorded in Tables <xref rid="pntd.0004233.t001" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="pntd.0004233.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>. Below we briefly list the specimens used in this study, followed by the source/collector in parentheses. For the author(s) and year of parasite and host (authors only) species, the reader is referred to <xref rid="pntd.0004233.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and <xref rid="pntd.0004233.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Appendix</xref>.</p>
<p>DNA, L3, microfilariae.</p>
<table-wrap id="pntd.0004233.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>List of filarial species used in phylogenetic analyses in this study.</title> <p>The onchocercid subfamilies are indicated in the first column. The name of the species as well as the author(s) and date are given in the second column. Columns 3 to 5 contain sample information, <italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. host species, MNHN accession number and collection locality.</p></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pntd.0004233.t001g" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup span="1">
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subfamilies</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N° MNHN</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collection locality</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outgroups</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Filaria latala</italic> Chabaud and Mohammad, 1989</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Panthera leo</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Africa</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Protospirura muricola<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></italic> Gedoelst, 1916</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gorilla gorilla</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central African Republic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oswaldofilariinae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Oswaldofilaria chabaudi Pereira</italic>, <italic>Souza and Bain</italic>, <italic>2010</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tropidurus torquatus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brasil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Oswaldofilaria petersi Bain and Sulahian 1974</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Crocodilurus amazonicus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34PF</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peru</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waltonellinae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ochoterenella</italic> sp.1 Guerrero et <italic>al</italic>. work in progress</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rhinella granulosa</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venezuela</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ochoterenella sp</italic>.<italic>2 Guerrero et al</italic>. work in progress</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rhinella marina</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venezuela</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ochoterenella sp</italic>.<italic>3 Kuzmin et al</italic>. work in progress</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phyllomedusa bicolor</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194JW</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">French Guyana</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Icosiellinae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Icosiella neglecta</italic> (Diesing, 1851)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pelophylax ridibunda</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ukraine</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> </italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pelophylax kl</italic>. <italic>esculeta</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Setariinae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Setaria labiatopapillosa</italic> (Alessandrini, 1848)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bos taurus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">413YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Setaria tundra</italic> Bain, 1974</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rangifer tarandus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finlande</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dirofilariinae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dirofilaria</italic> (<italic>Dirofilaria</italic>) <italic>immitis</italic> (Leidy, 1856)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Canis familiaris</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bayer strain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dirofilaria (Nochtiella) repens Railliet and Henry</italic>, <italic>1911</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Canis familiaris</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Foleyella candezei</italic> (Fraipont, 1882)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Agama agama</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68CE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Togo</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Loa loa</italic> (Cobbold, 1864)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Homo sapiens</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pelecitus fulicaeatrae</italic> (Diesing, 1861)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Podiceps nigricollis</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Splendidofilariinae</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aproctella alessandroi Bain</italic>, <italic>Petit</italic>, <italic>Kosek and Chabaud</italic>, <italic>1981</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Saltator similis</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brasil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cardiofilaria pavlovskyi</italic> Storm, 1937</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Oriolus oriolus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bulgaria</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Madathamugadia hiepei</italic> Hering-Hagenbeck, Boomker, Petit, Killick-Kendrick and Bain, 2000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pachycactylus turneri</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Africa</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rumenfilaria andersoni Lankester and Snider</italic>, <italic>1982</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rangifer tarandus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finlande</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Onchocercinea</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acanthocheilonema odendhali</italic> (Perry, 1967)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Callorhinus ursinus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alaska</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acanthocheilonema viteae</italic> (Krepkogorskaya, 1933)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Meriones unguiculatus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FR3 strain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Breinlia</italic> (<italic>Breinlia</italic>) <italic>jittapalapongi</italic> Veciana, Bain, Morand, Chaisiri, Douanghoupha, Miquel and Ribas, 2015</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rattus tanezumi</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laos</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brugia malayi</italic> (Brug, 1927)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Meriones unguiculatus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FR3 strain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brugia pahangi (Buckley and Edeson</italic>, <italic>1956)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Meriones unguiculatus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FR3 strain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brugia timori</italic> Partono, 1977</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Homo sapiens</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indonesia</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cercopithifilaria bainae Almeida and Vicente</italic>, <italic>1984</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Canis familiaris</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">experimental</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cercopithifilaria rugosicauda (Böhm and Supperer</italic>, <italic>1953)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Capreolus capreolus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">350YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cruorifilaria tuberocauda Eberhard</italic>, <italic>Morales and Orihel</italic>, <italic>1976</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venezuela</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dipetalonema caudispina</italic> (Molin, 1858)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ateles paniscus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">362YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guyana</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ateles sp</italic>.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guyana</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dipetalonema gracile</italic> (Rudolphi, 1809)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cebus olivaceus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124CV</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venezuela</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> </italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cebus apella</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peru</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic> </italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ateles sp</italic>.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guyana</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dipetalonema graciliformis</italic> (Freitas, 1964)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Saimiri scuireus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peru</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dipetalonema robini Petit</italic>, <italic>Bain and Roussilhon</italic>, <italic>1985</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lagothrix poeppigii</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peru</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Litomosoides brasiliensis</italic> Lins de Almeida, 1936</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Carollia perspicillata</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35/37PF</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peru</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Litomosoides hamletti</italic> Sandground, 1934</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>glossophaga soricina</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36PF1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peru</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Litomosoides sigmodontis</italic> Chandler, 1931</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Meriones unguiculatus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186MS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNHN strain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Litomosoides solarii</italic> Guerrero, Martin, Gardner and Bain, 2002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Trachops cirrhosus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213YU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venezuela</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loxodontofilaria caprini Uni and Bain, 2006</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Naemorhedus crispus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YG2-58</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mansonella (Cutifilaria) perforata Uni, Bain and Takaoka, 2004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cervus nippon</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216JW</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mansonella</italic> (<italic>Mansonella</italic>) <italic>ozzardi</italic> (Manson, 1897)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Homo sapiens</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haiti</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monanema martini Bain, Bartlett and Petit, 1986</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31NC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Onchocerca armillata</italic> Railliet and Henry, 1909</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bos taurus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54FK</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Onchocerca dewittei japonica</italic> Uni, Bain and Takaoka, 2001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sus scrofa leucomystax</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OB9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Onchocerca eberhardi</italic> Uni and Bain, 2007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cervus nippon</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S63-5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Onchocerca gutturosa</italic> Neumann, 1910</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bos taurus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54FK</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Onchocerca ochengi</italic> Bwangamoi, 1969</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bos taurus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54FK</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Onchocerca skrjabini</italic> Ruklyadev, 1964</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cervus nippon</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S63-6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Yatesia hydrochoerus</italic> (Yates, 1980)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52YT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venezuela</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>*<italic>Protospirura muricola</italic> is typically a parasite of rodents, but has been reported from primates [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>].</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>From the following species, DNA had been extracted from adult worms for previous [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] and deposited in the MNHN collection (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>): <italic>Madathamugadia hiepei</italic>, <italic>Rumenfilaria andersoni</italic>, <italic>Cercopithifilaria rugosicauda</italic>, <italic>Aproctella alessandroi</italic>, <italic>Loxodontofilaria caprini</italic>, <italic>Mansonella</italic> (<italic>Cutifilaria</italic>) <italic>perforata</italic>, <italic>Onchocerca dewittei japonica</italic>, <italic>Onchocerca eberhardi</italic>, <italic>Onchocerca skrjabini</italic> and <italic>Ochoterenella</italic> sp. 1. DNA of adult <italic>Setaria labiatopapillosa</italic> (Dr Ben Makepeace, UK) was given to us. DNA of <italic>Cercopithifilaria bainae</italic> had been extracted from infective larvae from <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> (Prof Domenico Otranto, Italy). From the following species, DNA had been extracted from microfilaria: <italic>Brugia timori</italic> (Dr Tri Baskoro, Indonesia);. <italic>Mansonella (Mansonella) ozzardi</italic> (Prof. Christian Raccurt, Haiti); <italic>Dirofilaria</italic> (<italic>Dirofilaria</italic>) <italic>immitis</italic> (Bayer Animal Health GmbH, Germany).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Adults</title>
<p>From the following species, DNA had been extracted from adult females: <italic>Acanthocheilonema viteae</italic>, <italic>Brugia malayi</italic> and <italic>Brugia pahangi</italic> (NIAID/NIH Filariasis Research Reagent Resource Center (MTA University of Wisconsin Oshkosh—SJ 770–12); <italic>Loa loa</italic> (Prof Jean Dupouy Camet, Hopital Cochin, France); <italic>Litomosoides sigmodontis</italic> (experimentally infected jirds, <italic>Meriones unguiculatus;</italic> MNHN).</p>
<p>Additional specimens of adult filariae were recovered during dissections of their vertebrate hosts captured in the wild from different geographic areas (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). They were mainly recovered from body cavities and lymphatic vessels or extracted from the dermis, subcutaneous or connective tissue, or tendons of limbs. Identification were made by several experts (OB, KJ, RG, YM, YK, SL, and AR), based on morphological studies. A few species have not yet been named, as their description is still in progress. Samples were fixed and stored in 70% ethanol. The anterior and posterior parts of worms were used for morphological studies, whereas the median part was processed for molecular analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Ethical statement</title>
<p>Jirds are maintained in the animal facilities of UMR7245, MNHN, as hosts of L. sigmodontis; they are inoculated intraperitoneally with 70 infective larvae and sacrificed 60 days post infection, upon which adult worms are recovered from the peritoneal cavity. All experimental procedures were carried out in strict accordance with the EU Directive 2010/63/UE and the relevant national legislation, namely the French “Décret no 2013–118, 1er février 2013, Ministère de l’Agriculture, de l’Agroalimentaire et de la Forêt”,National licence number 75–1415 approved animal experiments: protocols were approved by the ethical committee of the Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle (Comité Cuvier, Licence: 68–002) and by the “Direction départementale de la cohésion sociale et de la protection des populations” (DDCSPP) (No. C75-05-15).</p>
<p>Some non-human vertebrates were captured for experimental procedures, subject to the ethics approval of the relevant national bodies (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>), while others were obtained at abattoirs or donated to the MNHN by hunters or veterinarians (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). The MNHN does neither solicit nor compensate for these donations.</p>
<p>Human samples were not collected specifically for this study. They were provided by third parties. Human blood samples were collected with the ethics approval of the relevant national bodies (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>).</p>
<p>The adult female of <italic>Loa loa</italic> had been surgically removed from a male patient in Hospital Cochin, France. The adult subject had given oral consent to Prof J. Dupouy Camet, head of parasitology department at Hospital Cochin, to donate the worm to the MNHN (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). The MNHN did not and will not compensate for the donation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Molecular screening</title>
<p>DNA was extracted using a commercial kit, following manufacturer’s instructions (QIAamp micro kit, Qiagen, Germany). A preliminary step of disruption for two cycles of 30 seconds at 30 Hz using a TissueLyser II (Qiagen, Germany) was added. PCR screening of filarial nematodes was based on seven partial sequences of seven different genes: two mitochondrial genes, 12S rDNA (approximately 450 base-pair (bp) sequence) and cytochrome oxidase subunit I (<italic>coxI</italic>; approximately 600 bp); five nuclear genes, 18S rDNA (approximately 740 bp), 28S rDNA (approximately 900 bp), the myosin heavy chain (<italic>MyoHC</italic>; approximately 785 bp), RNA polymerase II large subunit (<italic>rbp1</italic>; approximately 640 bp), 70 kilodalton heat shock proteins (<italic>hsp70</italic>; approximately 610 bp). Amplification of the 12S rDNA and <italic>coxI</italic> sequences was conducted according to Casiraghi et al. [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. For the remaining five genes, primer pairs were designed (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>) based on regions that had been found conserved among nine species for which drafts of or complete genome were accessible: from NCBI database <italic>Brugia malayi</italic> (PRJNA27801), <italic>Loa loa</italic> (PRJNA37757), <italic>Onchocerca flexuosa</italic> (Weld, 1856) (PRJEB512), <italic>Dirofilaria immitis</italic> (PRJEB1797) <italic>Onchocerca ochengi</italic> (PRJEB1809); from Nematode Genomes from the Blaxter lab, University of Edinburg (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nematode.org/" xlink:type="simple">www.nematode.org</ext-link>) <italic>Acanthocheilonema viteae</italic> (nAv.1.0), <italic>Litomosoides sigmodontis</italic> (nLs.2.1); and from Filarial worms Sequencing Project, Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.broadinstitute.org/</ext-link>) <italic>Onchocerca volvulus</italic> (Leuckart, 1893) and <italic>Wuchereria bancrofti</italic> (Cobbold, 1877). For each gene, primer pairs adapted to nested PCR were designed (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>). PCRs were processed in a final volume of 20 μl under the conditions summarised in <xref rid="pntd.0004233.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>. Obtained PCR products were purified using the SV Wizard PCR Purification Kit (Promega, USA) and sequenced directly. A total of 345 sequences were deposited in the GenBank Data Library: KP760116 to KP760460 (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Table</xref>)</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Phylogenetic analyses</title>
<p>Sequences generated during the current study and previously published sequences from draft/complete genomes were aligned using MAFFT [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. To check for the absence of stop codons, the alignment of coding genes was translated using EMBOSS Transeq [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], and a comparison with available transcript sequences made. Using the corrected version of the Akaike Information Criterion (AICc), JModelTest analysis [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] was performed to establish the evolution model best adapted to the sequences alignment for each individual gene and for the concatenation of all genes. The General time-reversible plus Invariant sites plus Gamma distributed model (GTR+I+Γ) offered the best fit for <italic>coxI</italic>, <italic>hsp70</italic>, 12S rRNA and 28S rRNA sequences as well as the concatenated alignment; the General Time-Reversible plus Gamma distributed model (GTR+Γ) for <italic>MyoHC</italic> and <italic>rbp1</italic> sequences alignment; and the Kimura 2-parameter Invariant sites plus Gamma distributed model (K80+I+Γ) for 18S rRNA sequences alignment. To root the trees, two species were included as outgroups: <italic>Filaria latala</italic> (Spirurida: Filariidae) and <italic>Protospirura muricola</italic> (Spirurida: Spiruridae). Phylogenetic relationships between onchocercid taxa, based on the concatenated dataset, were performed by Bayesian inference using MrBayes [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. A partitioned model was implemented to estimate evolution parameters separately for each gene. Two runs were performed using five millions steps with four chains, with tree sampling every 1,000 generations; the first 1,250 points were discarded as burn-in and Posterior Probabilities were calculated from these post-burning trees. In addition, Maximum Likelihood (ML) was used to infer a phylogenetic tree based on the partitioned concatenated dataset, and was executed with 1000 slow bootstrap replicates using RaxML [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]; presented in Supplementary data (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Accession numbers</title>
<p>All new sequences generated in this study were deposited in GenBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank</ext-link>) under the accession numbers: KP760168 to KP760211 for <italic>coxI</italic>, KP760314 to KP760357 for 12S rDNA, KP760116 to KP760167 for 18S rRNA, KP760212 to KP760262 for <italic>MyoHC</italic>, KP760410 to KP760460 for <italic>hsp70</italic>, KP760263 to KP760313 for <italic>rbp1</italic>, KP760358 to KP760409 for 28S rRNA.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Results/Discussion</title>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Choosing an outgroup</title>
<p>An important consideration when proposing a comprehensive phylogeny for any taxonomic group is the suitable rooting of the tree and, thus, the choice of appropriate outgroups. Previous studies of the Onchocercidae, based on <italic>coxI</italic> and 12S rRNA gene analyses, have used spirurid representatives of the Thelaziidae [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and Filariidae [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] as outgroups. Furthermore, some phylogenetic analyses of nematodes based on SSU rDNA [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] or complete mitochondrial genome sequences [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] suggested other spirurids as the Physalopteroidea or Diplotriaenoidea to be appropriate outgroups for the Onchocercidae. In the present study, <italic>P</italic>. <italic>muricola</italic> (Spiruridae) and <italic>F</italic>. <italic>latala</italic> (Filariidae) were investigated as potential outgroups. Our multi-gene analyses indicate that this choice is reasonable (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref> and <xref rid="pntd.0004233.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). To support this result, the average genetic divergence between the outgroup and ingroup taxa was about 20% (21% for <italic>P</italic>. <italic>muricola</italic>; 25% for <italic>F</italic>. <italic>latala</italic>), and only about 14% between onchocercid specimens themselves. It was, therefore, concluded that both <italic>P</italic>. <italic>muricola</italic> and <italic>F</italic>. <italic>latala</italic> are appropriate outgroups for the present multi-gene dataset. In congruence with previous systematic analyses [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], the chosen rooting clearly supported the monophyly of the Onchocercidae.</p>
<fig id="pntd.0004233.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Phylogeny of Onchocercidae based on partitioned concatenated datasets of 12S rDNA, <italic>coxI</italic>, <italic>rbp1</italic>, <italic>hsp70</italic>, <italic>myoHC</italic>, 18S rDNA, and 28S rDNA sequences using Bayesian Inference.</title>
<p>The total length of datasets is approximately 4950 bp. Sixty onchocercid specimens (representing 48 species) were analysed. <italic>Filaria latala</italic> and <italic>Protospirura muricola</italic> were used as outgroups. The topology was inferred using Bayesian (B) inference. Nodes are associated with Bayesian posterior probabilities based on one run of 5 million generations. The onchocercid subfamilies are indicated by colour: blue for Onchocercinae, dark green for Dirofilariinae, purple for Splendidofilariinae, pale green for Setariinae, yellow for Waltonellinae, orange for Icosiellinae and red for Oswaldofilariinae.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Monophyly of the Onchocercidae</title>
<p>All onchocercid taxa examined in the present study formed a monophyletic group and five strongly supported clades within the family were identified (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). Based on their monophyly and to facilitate the description of tree topology, these clades will be referred to as ONC1 to ONC5 (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pntd.0004233.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Onchocercid clades based on partitioned concatenated datasets of 12S rDNA, <italic>coxI</italic>, <italic>rbp1</italic>, <italic>hsp70</italic>, <italic>myoHC</italic>, 18S rDNA, and 28S rDNA sequences using Bayesian Inference.</title>
<p>The total length of datasets is approximately 4950 bp. Sixty onchocercid specimens (representing 48 species) were analysed. <italic>Filaria latala</italic> and <italic>Protospirura muricola</italic> were used as outgroups. Bayesian posterior probabilities support five clades named ONC1 to ONC5. Dotted areas represented species of the same genus. The topology was inferred using Bayesian (B) inference on one run of 5 million generations. The onchocercid subfamilies are indicated by colour: blue for Onchocercinae, dark green for Dirofilariinae, purple for Splendidofilariinae, pale green for Setariinae, yellow for Waltonellinae, orange for Icosiellinae and red for Oswaldofilariinae.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>The ancestrally derived subfamilies are comforted</title>
<p>In the present phylogenetic analysis, the Oswaldofilariinae, Icosiellinae and Waltonellinae occupied a commun position as a highly supported clade (ONC1) and sister group of all other taxa studied within the Onchocercidae (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>.). The three subfamilies appeared to be closely related, with ONC1 having evolved independently from the remaining onchocercid representatives (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>., <xref rid="pntd.0004233.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). Previous morphological studies revealed a number of ancestral characters in the Icosiellinae and Oswaldofilariinae, such as infective larvae possessing cephalic spines (Icosiellinae), and a vulva that is positioned posterior to the oesophagus (Oswaldofilariinae) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Therefore, these subfamilies have traditionally been considered “ancient” [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. In addition, it has been suggested that their Gondwanian distribution is an indication of an ancient evolution which occurred prior to the supercontinent’s break-up [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Interestingly, the Oswaldofilariinae appear to have evolved independently from the remaining two subfamilies of clade ONC1 and were placed as sister group to a clade that consists of <italic>Ochoterenella</italic> spp. (Waltonellinae) and <italic>Icosiella neglecta</italic> (Icosiellinae) (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). Indeed, previous studies emphasised the presence of numerous plesiomorphic characters (long oesophagus, large buccal capsule and the presence of deirids) within <italic>Oswaldofilaria</italic> spp. [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Moreover, the host spectrum of these subfamilies differs: oswaldofilariines are parasites of squamates, whereas members of Icosiellinae and Waltonellinae are exclusively parasites of anurans [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Setariinae are unusual Onchocercidae with an intermediate position</title>
<p>The systematic position of the Setariinae among the Filarioidea superfamily has long been questioned. Initially the Setariinae had been placed into Filariidae because they share certain morphological similarities with representatives of this family (spines on anterior end of first stage larva and adult cuticular elevation) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Nevertheless, based on other biological and morphological traits (<italic>e</italic>.<italic>g</italic>. viviparous, long microfilaria with pointed spineless tail), it would have been equally possible to consign them to the Onchocercidae. At a later stage, the Setariidae was proposed as a family with the purpose of removing the Setariinae from the Filariidae[<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], and current classifications list the Setariinae as a subfamily within the Onchocercidae [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Such an affiliation between the Setariinae and Onchocercidae has since been supported by many molecular phylogenies [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. The same was true for the present study, where the two <italic>Setaria</italic> species grouped in one clade (ONC2) with good support (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Excepting ONC1, the clade consisting of <italic>Setaria</italic> spp. was sister to all remaining onchocercid taxa sampled in this study. In the past, the Setariinae, Oswaldofilariinae and Waltonellinae were grouped together on the previous phylogenetic trees despite an unresolved topology [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. For some time, morphological studies of infective stages from <italic>Setaria</italic> spp. (long larvae, presence of deirids) have supported the hypothesis that Setariinae may have emerged early in the evolution of Onchocercidae [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. In contrast, the study of larval development of <italic>S</italic>. <italic>labiotopapillosa</italic> suggested that Setariinae, like the remaining Onchocercidae, could have been derived from habronematid ancestors, but that speciation leading to the Setariinae occurred later and independently from the remaining Onchocercidae [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. For example, the development of the glandular cells of the oesophagus in the Setariinae was shown to be closed to the development observed in some potential ancestors of the Onchocercidae, namely the Habronematidae [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The current phylogeny strongly supported the position of Setariinae as a group derived from an independent speciation to the examined Onchocercidae.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Subfamilies within the Onchocercidae: A need for systematic revision</title>
<p>The remaining taxa of the Onchocercidae analysed in this study grouped in three distinct and well supported clades (ONC3, ONC4 and ONC5) (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>), including representatives of the Dirofilariinae, Onchocercinae and Splendidofilariinae. It is noteworthy that the tree topology demonstrated here is not congruent with classic systematic delineations:</p>
<list list-type="roman-lower">
<list-item><p>The first clade, ONC3 (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>), contained representatives of the genera <italic>Dirofilaria</italic> (Dirofilariinae), <italic>Loxodontofilaria</italic> and <italic>Onchocerca</italic> (Onchocercinae) as suggested by several earlier molecular analyses [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Although these genera belong to two different subfamilies when looking at established classifications [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], a possible need to merge these subfamilies is reinforced by several biological traits [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Firstly, the infective stages of <italic>Dirofilaria</italic> spp. and <italic>Onchocerca</italic> spp. possess morphological similarities (normally developed buccal capsule; cylindrical tail with tiny caudal lappets) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Secondly, there are shared life history traits: an early first moult in the vertebrate host takes place early, <italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic> 2–3 days postinfection, in <italic>Dirofilaria</italic> spp. and <italic>Onchocerca</italic> spp. [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], as opposed to a late moult, <italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. 6–10 days postinfection, in all other onchocercid species studied thus far [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. No information is currently available on the infective larvae and development in the final host of representatives of <italic>Loxodontofilaria</italic>. This clade (ONC3) (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>) constitutes the most ancestrally derived group belonging to modern Onchocercidae. Clade ONC3 was sister group of both clades ONC4 and ONC5 (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>), suggesting an independent evolution.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The second clade, ONC4 (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>), was composed of the genera <italic>Dipetalonema</italic>, <italic>Acanthocheilonema</italic>, <italic>Monanema</italic>, <italic>Cruorifilaria</italic>, <italic>Cercopithifilaria</italic>, <italic>Yatesia</italic> and <italic>Litomosoides</italic>. For a long time, taxonomists used <italic>Dipetalonema</italic> as a “catch all” genus [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. In years to follow, numerous subgenera formerly included in this genus were elevated to generic rank, whereas other species were transferred in newly erected genera; together, they were referred to as the “<italic>Dipetalonema</italic> lineage” [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. This lineage combined those species of the Onchocercinae that present adults with a long tail, a buccal capsule divided into two segments (or three in <italic>Skrjabinofilaria</italic> spp.), and a caudal extremity with two subterminal lappets [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. These structures might, however, be more or less atrophied in the more specialised forms, such as seen in the buccal capsule of <italic>Monanema</italic> and <italic>Cercopithifilaria</italic> species [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. The present phylogenetic tree supports the accuracy of the <italic>Dipetalonema</italic> lineage, as all genera included in the clade ONC4, with the exception of <italic>Litomosoides</italic>, have been assigned to this lineage [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Prior to this study, molecular analyses had only supported the clustering of <italic>Dipetalonema</italic> with <italic>Acanthocheilonema</italic> [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. A closer look at clade ONC4 revealed its division into two groups (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>):
</p><p>i) <italic>Dipetalonema</italic> spp. were sister to all remaining taxa within clade ONC4 (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). This position agrees with earlier hypotheses that, based on ancestral morphological particularities (divided oesophagus, well developed and highly cuticularized buccal capsule) the genus <italic>Dipetalonema</italic> should be considered distinct from the remaining genera in the <italic>Dipetalonema</italic> lineage [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Moreover, it had been proposed that the genus may have been derived through geographic isolation in the Neotropical region after the Gondwana fragmentation and so would be a paleoendemic South American genus [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>].
</p><p>ii)The second subclade group comprised members of <italic>Acanthocheilonema</italic>, <italic>Monanema Cercopithifilaria</italic>, <italic>Yatesia</italic>, <italic>Cruorifilaria</italic> and <italic>Litomosoides</italic> seems more derived. However, species of <italic>Acanthocheilonema</italic> and <italic>Monanema</italic> seemed to be more closely related and were sister to the remaining taxa in this group. Earlier taxonomic studies described <italic>Acanthocheilonema</italic> as an ancestral genus due to several plesiomorph characters of its representatives (strongly divided oesophagus, highly cuticularized buccal capsule, shape of right spicule of male) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. In contrast, the morphology of <italic>Monanem</italic>a includes both ancestral (numerous caudal papillae distributed along length of tail) as well as derived characters (undivided oesophagus) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Bain <italic>et al</italic>. (70) considered <italic>Monanema</italic> as derived from Ethiopian <italic>Acanthocheilonema</italic> species [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The remaining genera formed two sister groups: the one uniting taxa of <italic>Cruorifilaria</italic>, <italic>Yatesia</italic> and <italic>Cercopithifilaria</italic>, the other containing species of <italic>Litomosoides</italic>. Earlier studies had suggested <italic>Cercopithifilaria</italic> to be derived from <italic>Acanthocheilonema</italic> and, as indicated by the derived morphological characters of its members (reduced buccal capsule, undivided oesophagus, shape of right spicule of male, number and repartition of caudal papillae), to represent the most evolved forms of the <italic>Dipetalonema</italic> lineage [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. <italic>Litomosoides</italic> had not been included in the <italic>Dipetalonema</italic> lineage in the 1976 classification by Chabaud and Bain [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. The latter authors did, however, point out that the reason for this omission was somewhat arbitrary. In fact, <italic>Litomosoides</italic> species do share morphological similarities with other representatives of the <italic>Dipetalonema</italic> lineage (long tail, long buccal capsule) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The third clade (ONC5) united genera belonging to the Dirofilariinae (<italic>Loa</italic>, <italic>Foleyella</italic>, <italic>Pelecitus</italic>), Onchocercinae (<italic>Wuchereria</italic>, <italic>Brugia</italic>, <italic>Breinlia</italic>, <italic>Mansonella</italic>) and Splendidofilariinae (<italic>Aproctella</italic>, <italic>Cardiofilaria</italic>, <italic>Madathamugadia</italic>, <italic>Rumenfilaria</italic>) (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Most human filariae were included in this clade, with the exception of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>volvulus</italic>, which groups in clade ONC3. Three groups could be pinpointed in clade ONC5:
</p><p>i) The first group, including <italic>Brugia</italic> and <italic>Wuchereria</italic>, was sister to all remaining representatives of clade ONC5. Previous molecular studies highlighted a close relation between these two genera [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], which is supported by shared morphological similarities (reduced buccal capsule, glandular part of oesophagus, vagina with bends and chamber in adults; infective larvae with a long tail and three lappets) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Moreover, their mode of transmission and development is similar (culicid vector, lymphatic location in the host) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
</p><p>ii) The second group comprised species exclusively assigned to the Dirofilariinae: <italic>L</italic>. <italic>loa</italic>, <italic>P</italic>. <italic>fulicaeatrae</italic> and <italic>F</italic>. <italic>candezei</italic>. These parasites did not group together in previous molecular analyses [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. However, they share morphological similarities, based on which this subfamily had originally been introduced (highly developed caudal alae of adult males) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Futhermore, <italic>L</italic>. <italic>loa</italic> and <italic>Pelecitus scapiceps</italic> Leidy, 1886 present similar biological traits, such as a late third moult (respectively on day 8 and day 6 postinfection) and a fourth moultprior to day 20 postinfection, both of which are close to the developmental pattern seen in many species of the Onchocercinae and Splendidofilariinae [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>].
</p><p>iii) The last group in clade ONC5 was composed of representatives of Splendidofilariinae and Onchocercinae. Up to now, Splendidofilariinae have rarely been studied [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In the present analysis, species of <italic>Madathamugadia</italic> and <italic>Rumenfilaria</italic> (Splendidofilariinae) appeared more closely related to the two species of <italic>Mansonella</italic> (Onchocercinae), of which they were a sister group, than they were to the remaining splendidofilariine genera, <italic>Cardiofilaria</italic> and <italic>Aproctella</italic> species. The close relationship between <italic>Cardiofilaria</italic> and <italic>Aproctella</italic> has been underlined by morphological similarities in infective larvae (body length exceeding 1300μm, thick and short tail, ending in two small lateral terminal papillae) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. <italic>Mansonella</italic> is a complex and taxonomically challenging genus and numerous attempts to reorganise its classification, including description of several subgenera, have been made throughout the years [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Its relationship with representatives of the Splendidofilariinae has not been resolved, but it does share similarities with some splendidofilariine genera such as the <italic>Madathamugadia</italic> (<italic>e</italic>.<italic>g</italic> short and thin infective larvae with long tail) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Species of <italic>Breinlia</italic> have been described as Australian representatives of the <italic>Dipetalonema</italic> lineage which have more recently migrated into Asia, and are morphologically distinct from the remaining species of this lineage [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Their somewhat isolated position was upheld by the current phylogeny. It is interesting to note that these various species (<italic>e</italic>.<italic>g</italic>. <italic>Madathamugadia</italic> or <italic>Foleyella</italic>) have been described as an evolved group [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>].</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>One of the main difficulties in comparing the results of the present study with those of earlier molecular analyses was either the lack of broad taxonomic sampling or incompletely resolved deeper phylogenetic relationships in preceding studies [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. However, an equivalent to clade ONC5 clade had been identified before,in the first phylogeny including <italic>L</italic>. <italic>loa</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>malayi</italic> and <italic>W</italic>. <italic>bancrofti</italic> and <italic>Mansonella</italic> (<italic>M</italic>.) <italic>perstans</italic> (Manson, 1891) [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. A similar clade, including <italic>B</italic>. <italic>malayi</italic>, <italic>W</italic>. <italic>bancrofti</italic>, <italic>L</italic>. <italic>loa</italic> and <italic>Chanderella quiscali</italic> Linstow, 1904, a Splendidofilariinae, was confirmed by a recent analysis of mitochondrial genomes [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p>
<p>To summarise, the present phylogeny did neither support the monophyly of the Dirofilariinae, Onchocercinae nor Splendidofilariinae (see ONC3 and ONC5, <xref rid="pntd.0004233.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Interestingly, however, the relationships exhibited between the various taxa in clades ONC3 and ONC5, although traditionally included in different subfamilies, are supported by morphological as well as biological features (see <xref rid="sec009" ref-type="sec">discussion</xref> above). Based on the combined analysis of molecular, structural and developmental characters, we, thus, conclude that a reassessment of the boundaries between these three subfamilies is called for.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Evolution of filariae, their vector and host: Is there a relationship?</title>
<p>The parasitic life style of the Onchocercidae has led to the reduction of certain morphological traits and promoted convergent evolution in others [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], reducing the usefulness of structural characters in developing a phylogenetic framework for this family. One might thus look at the role of vectors and hosts for further clues as to the speciation of the Onchocercidae. Three (ONC1, ONC2 and ONC3) of the five clades exhibited on the current phylogenetic tree use exclusively dipterans as vectors. In addition, dipterans are involved in the transmission of members of clades ONC4 and ONC5, supporting a hypothesis that old evolutionary bonds exist between this order and the Onchocercidae (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004233.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). The diversity of vectors used in clades ONC4 and ONC5 (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>), on the other hand, suggests that the evolution of filarial nematodes is not strictly constrained by their vector but does permit changes to other, more appropriate groups of vectors, to ensure parasite transmission, colonisation of new ecological niches and diversification. Clade ONC4 shows an adaptation to a new group of vectors–ticks and mites. It should, however, be emphasised that some <italic>Acanthocheilonema</italic> spp. (ONC4) are known to use fleas, hippoboscid flies or sucking lice as vectors [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and <italic>Dipetalonema</italic> spp. are transmitted by ceratopogonid biting midges (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). Considering relationships of the Onchocercidae with their definitive hosts, the present analysis revealed a group of parasites adapted exclusively to cold blooded tetrapods, namely squamates, crocodilians and amphibians (ONC1), while their sister group diversified in various groups of mammals (ONC2-5), as well as birds and squamates (ONC5) (<xref rid="pntd.0004233.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). It has been suggested that the parasite-host relationships of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>hiepei</italic> (parasite of the gecko <italic>Chondrodactylus turneri</italic>) and <italic>F</italic>. <italic>candezei</italic> (parasite of lizards) may be the result of secondary capture with the narrow geographical localisation of <italic>Foleyella</italic> and <italic>Madathamugadia</italic>, <italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. Africa and Madagascar, supporting the hypothesis of capture phenomena [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. The present phylogenetic analysis does not support a close relationship between parasites of birds, but representation of avian parasites was limited. All three parasites of birds formed part of clade ONC5, which presented the most heterogeneous host range within the Onchocercidae, comprising parasites of three classes of vertebrates, reptiles, birds and mammals. The diverse mammalian hosts represented in clades ONC3-5 indicate multiple events of host-switching and radiation within the evolutionary history of the group. In summary, the overall picture revealed by the current analysis does not suggest a broad pattern of onchocercid parasite-host/vector coevolution and is consistent with earlier studies suggesting that parasitic nematode speciation could be related to a variety of events of host switching and host acquisition and/or geographical and ecological drift [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>–<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].</p>
<fig id="pntd.0004233.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Phylogeny of Onchocercidae based on partitioned concatenated datasets of 12S rDNA, <italic>coxI</italic>, <italic>rbp1</italic>, <italic>hsp70</italic>, <italic>myoHC</italic>, 18S rDNA, and 28S rDNA sequences using Bayesian Inference with indication of vector range.</title>
<p>The total length of datasets is approximately 4950 bp. Sixty onchocercid specimens (representing 48 species) were analysed. <italic>Filaria latala</italic> and <italic>Protospirura muricola</italic> were used as outgroups. The topology was inferred using Bayesian (B) inference. Nodes are associated with Bayesian posterior probabilities based on one run of 5 million generations. The vector family for each filariae species is indicated to the right of the tree using the specified symbols.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<fig id="pntd.0004233.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Phylogeny of Onchocercidae based on partitioned concatenated datasets of 12S rDNA, <italic>coxI</italic>, <italic>rbp1</italic>, <italic>hsp70</italic>, <italic>myoHC</italic>, 18S rDNA, and 28S rDNA sequences using Bayesian Inference with indication of host vertebrate range.</title>
<p>The total length of datasets is approximately 4950 bp. Sixty onchocercid specimens (representing 48 species) were analysed. <italic>Filaria latala</italic> and <italic>Protospirura muricola</italic> were used as outgroups. The topology was inferred using Bayesian (B) inference. Nodes are associated with Bayesian posterior probabilities based on one run of 5 million generations. The host vertebrate order for each filariae species is indicated to the right of the tree using the specified symbols.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Concluding remarks</title>
<p>The present study casts doubt on the validity of of the currently eight traditional onchocercid subfamilies. Traditional classifications of the Onchocercidae have been established mainly on the basis of morphological characters of adult worms. However, as suggested by previous authors [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], biological features, such as larval biology or the morphology of the third-stage larva, may offer a better phylogenetic resolution. It is hoped that an approach combining broad molecular taxonomic sampling and traditional morphological as well as life history studies, will eventually lead to the development of more comprehensive phylogenetic hypotheses for this fascinating group of nematodes.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pntd.0004233.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Phylogeny of Onchocercidae based on partitioned concatenated datasets of 12S rDNA, <italic>coxI</italic>, <italic>rbp1</italic>, <italic>hsp70</italic>, <italic>myoHC</italic>, 18S rDNA, and 28S rDNA sequences using Maximum Likelihood Inference.</title>
<p>The total length of datasets is approximately 4950 bp. Sixty onchocercid specimens (representing 48 species) were analysed. <italic>Filaria latala</italic> and <italic>Protospirura muricola</italic> were used as outgroups. The topology was inferred using Maximum Likelihood (ML) inference. Nodes are associated with Bootstrap values based on 1000 replicates. The onchocercid subfamilies are indicated by colour: blue for Onchocercinae, dark green for Dirofilariinae, purple for Splendidofilariinae, pale green for Setariinae, yellow for Waltonellinae, orange for Icosiellinae and red for Oswaldofilariinae.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pntd.0004233.s002" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Supplementary information of filarial species used in phylogenetic analyses in this study.</title>
<p>The species were classified by subfamilies indicated in the first column. The name of the species as well as the author(s) and date are given in the second column. Columns 3 to 8 present species information, i.e. family host, order host, localisation in the host, genera vector, family vector and geographical distribution. The references of morphological studies on which species identifications were based are listed in the last column. For the most part of the sampling some supplementary information were based on Anderson et <italic>al</italic>. [<xref rid="pntd.0004233.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pntd.0004233.s003" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Ethical statement on vertebrate hosts and human samples.</title>
<p>Vertebrate host are indicated in the first column and their collection place is given in the second column. The name of the collected filarial species is given in the third column. Columns 4 and 5 present ethical information on the host collection, <italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. the capture permit number and the ethical committee or legal entity for scientific procedures; Columns 6 to 9 describe non-scientific procedures in which filariae are recovered from vertebrates after hunting, necropsies in slaughter houses, or post-veterinary or post-medical procedures. The number of MNHN collection registration is listed in the last column.</p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pntd.0004233.s004" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.s004" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S3 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Primers and PCR programs used in this study.</title>
<p>Abbreviations: Step 1: denaturation; Step 2: annealing; Step 3: elongation; T: temperature (°C); D: duration (sec); N: number of cycles. * Indicates the primers designed for nested PCR. References: PS means newly design for the present study.</p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pntd.0004233.s005" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.s005" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S4 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Accession number list of filarial species and outgroups used for phylogenetic analyses.</title>
<p>The name of the species are given in the first column. The identification number of samples are given in the second column. Columns 3 to 9 present accession number for each analysed genes, i.e. <italic>coxI</italic> (cytochrome oxidase subunit I), 12S rRNA, 18S rRNA, <italic>MyoHC</italic> (myosin heavy chain), <italic>hsp70</italic> (70 kilodalton heat shock proteins), <italic>rbp1</italic> (RNA polymerase II large subunit) and 28S rRNA. Abbreviations: ext. indicated external samples.</p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pntd.0004233.s006" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0004233.s006" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Appendix</label>
<caption>
<title>List of author(s) and date associated with name of the vertebrate hosts or vector species.</title>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors wish to thank the following collaborators for the material they provided: Dr. M. Casiraghi (DNA of <italic>Aproctella</italic> sp., <italic>R</italic>. <italic>andersoni</italic>, <italic>D</italic>. <italic>gracile</italic>, <italic>M</italic>. <italic>martini</italic>, <italic>F</italic>. <italic>candezei</italic>), Dr. S. Uni (DNA of <italic>O</italic>. <italic>eberhardi</italic>, <italic>O</italic>. <italic>d</italic>. <italic>japonica</italic>, <italic>O</italic>. <italic>skrjabini</italic>, <italic>L</italic>. <italic>caprini</italic>), Dr. S. Nikander (<italic>S</italic>. <italic>tundra</italic>), Dr. D. Otranto (<italic>C</italic>. <italic>bainae</italic>), Dr. M. Diagne (<italic>M</italic>. <italic>martini</italic>), Dr. S. Wanji (<italic>O</italic>. <italic>armillata</italic>, <italic>O</italic>. <italic>gutturosa</italic>, <italic>O</italic>. <italic>ochengi</italic>), Dr. B. Makepeace (<italic>S</italic>. <italic>labiatopapillosa</italic>), Dr. Alexis Ribas (<italic>B</italic>. (<italic>B</italic>.) <italic>jittapalapongi</italic>), Dr. J. Dupouy-Camet (<italic>Loa loa</italic>), Dr. S. Michalski from FR3 center (<italic>B</italic>. <italic>malayi</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>pahangi</italic>, <italic>A</italic>. <italic>viteae</italic>), S. Landi (<italic>B</italic>. <italic>Timori</italic>), Bayer Animal Health GmbH (<italic>Dirofilaria immitis</italic>).</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <chapter-title>Evolutionary relationships among filarial nematodes</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Rajan</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, editor. <source>World Class Parasites</source>: <publisher-name>Kluwer Acad</publisher-name>. pp. <fpage>181</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchery</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lefoulon</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karadjian</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieguitsila</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The symbiotic role of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> in Onchocercidae and its impact on filariasis</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/1469-0691.12069" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/1469-0691.12069</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23398406</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoerauf</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pfarr</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mand</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Debrah</surname> <given-names>AY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Specht</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Filariasis in Africa-treatment challenges and prospects</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>977</fpage>–<lpage>985</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-0691.2011.03586.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2011.03586.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21722251</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoerauf</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bockarie</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Lymphatic filariasis and onchocerciasis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>376</volume>: <fpage>1175</fpage>–<lpage>1185</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60586-7" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60586-7</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20739055</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mutafchiev</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Junker</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <chapter-title>Order Spirurida</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt-Rhaesa</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Handbook of Zoology Vol 2 Nematoda.</source> <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>De Gruyter</publisher-name>. pp. <fpage>661</fpage>–<lpage>732</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <chapter-title>Keys to genera of the order Spirurida. Part 3. Diplotriaenoidea, Aproctoidea and Filarioidea</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chabaud</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willmott</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, editors. <source>CIH Keys to the nematode parasites of vertebrates</source>. <publisher-loc>England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CAB International</publisher-name>. pp. <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibbons</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <chapter-title>Keys to the nematode parasites of vertebrates. Supplementary volume</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Wallingford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CAB International</publisher-name>. <fpage>i</fpage>–<lpage>viii</lpage>, pp 416.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mutafchiev</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Junker</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guerrero</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Review of the genus <italic>Mansonella</italic> Faust, 1929 sensu lato (Nematoda: Onchocercidae), with descriptions of a new subgenus and a new subspecies</article-title>. <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>3918</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3918.2.1" xlink:type="simple">10.11646/zootaxa.3918.2.1</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25781087</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Nematode Parasites of Vertebrates: Their Development and Transmission</source> <edition>2nd Edition</edition>. <publisher-loc>Wallingford, Oxon (UK)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>C.A.B. International</publisher-name>. pp <fpage>672</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chabaud</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The evolutionary expansion of the Spirurida</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1179</fpage>–<lpage>1201</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7729976</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wehr</surname> <given-names>EE</given-names></name> (<year>1935</year>) <article-title>A revised classification of the nematode superfamily Filarioidea</article-title>. <source>Proc Helminthol Soc Wash</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chabaud</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>1959</year>) <article-title>Nouvel essai de classification des filaires (superfamille des Filarioidea) II</article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chabaud</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choquet</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name> (<year>1953</year>) <article-title>Nouvel essai de classification des filaires (super-famille des Filarioidea)</article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">13092687</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Molecular phylogenetic studies on filarial parasites based on 5S ribosomal spacer sequences</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9140481</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casiraghi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bandi</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bazzocchi</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Genchi</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A phylogenetic analysis of filarial nematodes: comparison with the phylogeny of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> endosymbionts</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source> <volume>122</volume> <issue>Pt 1</issue>: <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11197770</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casiraghi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guerrero</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pocacqua</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mapping the presence of <italic>Wolbachia pipientis</italic> on the phylogeny of filarial nematodes: evidence for symbiont loss during evolution</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15037105</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferri</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barbuto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galimberti</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uni</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Integrated taxonomy: traditional approach and DNA barcoding for the identification of filarioid worms and related parasites (Nematoda)</article-title>. <source>Front Zool</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1742-9994-6-1" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1742-9994-6-1</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19128479</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferri</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barbuto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>New insights into the evolution of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infections in filarial nematodes inferred from a large range of screened species</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e20843</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0020843" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0020843</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21731626</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefoulon</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gavotte</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Junker</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barbuto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uni</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A new type F <italic>Wolbachia</italic> from Splendidofilariinae (Onchocercidae) supports the recent emergence of this supergroup</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1025</fpage>–<lpage>1036</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijpara.2012.09.004" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ijpara.2012.09.004</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23041355</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blaxter</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Ley</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garey</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>LX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheldeman</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>A molecular evolutionary framework for the phylum Nematoda</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>392</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9510248</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadler</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carreno</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mejia-Madrid</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ullberg</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pagan</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular phylogeny of clade III nematodes reveals multiple origins of tissue parasitism</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>1421</fpage>–<lpage>1442</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17506928</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sultana</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Monophyly of clade III nematodes is not supported by phylogenetic analysis of complete mitochondrial genome sequences</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>392</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-12-392" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2164-12-392</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21813000</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krueger</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morales-Hojas</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular phylogeny of the filaria genus <italic>Onchocerca</italic> with special emphasis on Afrotropical human and bovine parasites</article-title>. <source>Acta Trop</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17174932</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Molecular phylogenetic studies on <italic>Brugia</italic> filariae using Hha I repeat sequences</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>260</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9140492</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McNulty</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mullin</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaughan</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tkach</surname> <given-names>VV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weil</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Comparing the mitochondrial genomes of <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-dependent and independent filarial nematode species</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-13-145" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2164-13-145</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22530989</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title><italic>Oswaldofilaria chabaudi</italic> n. sp. (Nematoda: Onchocercidae) from a South American tropidurid lizard (Squamata: Iguania) with an update on Oswaldofilariinae</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21275236</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sulahian</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Trois nouvelles filaires du genre <italic>Oswaldofilaria</italic> chez des Lézards sud-américains; essai de classification des Oswaldofilariinae</article-title>. <source>Bull Mus Natl Hist Nat</source> <volume>156</volume>: <fpage>827</fpage>–<lpage>841</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chabaud</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Développement chez des moustiques de trois filaires de lézards Sud-Americains du genre <italic>Oswaldofilaria</italic></article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">240307</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Desportes</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1941</year>) <article-title>Nouvelles recherches sur la morphologie et sur l'évolution d'<italic>Icosiella neglecta</italic> (Diesing) filaire commune de la grenouille verte</article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikander</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laaksonen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saari</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oksanen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The morphology of the filaroid nematode <italic>Setaria tundra</italic>, the cause of peritonitis in reindeer <italic>Rangifer tarandus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Helminthol</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17381867</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlett</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greiner</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>A revision of <italic>Pelecitus Railliet</italic> and Henry, 1910 (Filarioidea, Dirofilariinae) and evidence for the ‘capture’ by mammals of filarioids from birds</article-title>. <source>Bull Mus Natl Hist Nat Ser. 4, Section A</source>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonin</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <chapter-title>Filariata of animals and man and disease caused by them</chapter-title>. <source>Onchocercidae</source>.; <name name-style="western"><surname>Skrjabin</surname> <given-names>KI</given-names></name>, editor. <publisher-loc>Moscow</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nauka Publisher</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petit</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kozek</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chabaud</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Sur les Filaires Splendidofilariinae du genre <italic>Aproctella</italic></article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7259001</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlett</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Filarioid nematodes (Filarioidae:Onchocercidae) of corvus <italic>Brachyrhynchos brachyrhynchos</italic> brehm in southern Ontario, Canada, and a consideration of epizootiology of avian Filariasis</article-title>. <source>Syst Parasitol</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hering-Hagenbeck</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boomker</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petit</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Killick-Kendrick</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Description of Madathamugadia hiepei n. sp. (nematoda: Splendidofilariinae), a parasite of a South African gecko, and its development in laboratory bred Phlebotomus dubosqi (Diptera: Psychodidae)</article-title>. <source>Syst Parasitol</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11071156</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laaksonen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saari</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikander</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oksanen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Lymphatic dwelling filarioid nematodes in reindeer <italic>Rangifer tarandus tarandus</italic>, (cervidae) in Finland, identified as <italic>Rumenfilaria andersoni</italic> Lankester &amp; Snider, 1982 (nematoda: Onchocercidae: Splendidofilariinae)</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20387735</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuzmina</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuzmin</surname> <given-names>YI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tkach</surname> <given-names>VV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spraker</surname> <given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyons</surname> <given-names>ET</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Ecological, morphological, and molecular studies of <italic>Acanthocheilonema odendhali</italic> (Nematoda: Filarioidea) in northern fur seals (<italic>Callorhinus ursinus</italic>) on St. Paul Island, Alaska</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source> <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>3091</fpage>–<lpage>3100</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00436-013-3483-3" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00436-013-3483-3</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23760875</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veciana</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morand</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaisiri</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Douangboupha</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2015</year>) <article-title><italic>Breinlia</italic> (<italic>Breinlia</italic>) <italic>jittapalapongi</italic> n. sp. (Nematoda: Filarioidea) from the Asian house rat <italic>Rattus tanezumi</italic> Temminck in Lao PDR</article-title>. <source>Syst Parasitol</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11230-014-9544-x" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s11230-014-9544-x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25693458</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Partono</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oemijati</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Purnomo</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Atmosoedjono</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>The Timor filaria on Flores and experimental transmission of the parasite</article-title>. <source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>354</fpage>–<lpage>355</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12599</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Otranto</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Varcasia</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Solinas</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scala</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brianti</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Redescription of <italic>Cercopithifilaria bainae</italic> Almeida &amp; Vicente, 1984 (Spirurida, Onchocercidae) from a dog in Sardinia, Italy</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>132</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1756-3305-6-132" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1756-3305-6-132</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23642161</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefoulon</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuzmin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plantard</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mutafchiev</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Otranto</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Redescription of <italic>Cercopithifilaria rugosicauda</italic> (Bohm &amp; Supperer, 1953) (Spirurida: Onchocercidae) of roe deer, with an emended diagnosis of the genus <italic>Cercopithifilaria</italic> and a genetic characterisation</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Int</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>808</fpage>–<lpage>816</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.parint.2014.07.011" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.parint.2014.07.011</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25108130</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eberhard</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morales</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orihel</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title><italic>Cruorifilaria tuberocauda</italic> gen. et sp. n. (Nematoda: Filarioidea) from the capybara, <italic>Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris</italic> in colombia</article-title>. <source>J Parasitol</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>604</fpage>–<lpage>607</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">957038</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eberhard</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowrie</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names> <suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orihel</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Development of <italic>Dipetalonema gracile</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>caudispina</italic> to the infective stage in <italic>Culicoides hollensis</italic></article-title>. <source>J Parasitol</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">571910</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petit</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosales-Loesener</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Filaires de Singes sud-américains</article-title>. <source>Bull Mus Natl Hist. Nat 4e ser.</source>, <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>542</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diagne</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Une cinquième filaire du genre <italic>Dipetalonema</italic>, parasite de singes Sud-Americains</article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>262</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3662331</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerrero</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>New and Known Species of <italic>Litomosoides</italic> (Nematoda: Filarioidae): Important Adult and Larval Characters and Taxonomic Changes</article-title>. <source>Comp Parasitol</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uni</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agatsuma</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katsumi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baba</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>New filarial nematode from Japanese serows (<italic>Naemorhedus crispus</italic>: Bovidae) close to parasites from elephants</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17007210</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uni</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takaoka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Affinities between <italic>Cutifilaria</italic> (Nematoda: Filarioidea), parasites of deer, and <italic>Mansonella</italic> as seen in a new onchocercid, <italic>M</italic>. (<italic>C</italic>.) <italic>perforata</italic> n. sp., from Japan</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15224573</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petit</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gueye</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Transmission experimentale de <italic>Monanema nilotica</italic> El Bihari et coll., 1977, filaire a microfilaires dermiques parasite de Murides africains</article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3985535</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuda</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takaoka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uni</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Infective larvae of five <italic>Onchocerca</italic> species from experimentally infected <italic>Simulium</italic> species in an area of zoonotic onchocerciasis in Japan</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18642503</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uni</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takaoka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miyashita</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title><italic>Onchocerca dewittei japonica</italic> n. subsp., a common parasite from wild boar in Kyushu Island, Japan</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11584751</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Redescription de cinq especes d'onchocerques</article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>763</fpage>–<lpage>788</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1227381</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uni</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agatsuma</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torii</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title><italic>Onchocerca eberhardi</italic> n. sp. (Nematoda: Filarioidea) from sika deer in Japan; relationships between species parasitic in cervids and bovids in the Holarctic region</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17933297</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz-Key</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Les onchocerques du cerf europeen: redescription d'<italic>O</italic>. <italic>flexuosa</italic> (Wedl, 1856) et description d'<italic>O</italic>. <italic>tubingensis</italic> n.sp. et <italic>O</italic>. <italic>tarsicola</italic> n.sp</article-title>. <source>Tropenmed Parasitol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>449</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">4446067</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Transmission de l'Onchocerque bovine, <italic>Onchocerca gutturosa</italic>, par <italic>Culicoides</italic></article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>488</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">533114</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yagi</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shoho</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title><italic>Onchocerca suzukii</italic> n. sp. and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>skrjabini</italic> (= <italic>O</italic>. <italic>tarsicola</italic>) from a relict bovid, <italic>Capricornis crispus</italic>, in Japan</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9140501</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voelker</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garms</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1972</year>) <article-title>Morphological studies of unknown filarial larvae from <italic>Simulium damnosum</italic>, the vector of onchocerciasis, and from <italic>S</italic>. <italic>kenyae</italic> in Liberia with reference to their possible final hosts</article-title>. <source>Z Tropenmed Parasitol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">4634262</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yates</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowrie</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Development of <italic>Yatesia hydrochoerus</italic> (Nematoda: Filarioidae) to the infective stage in ixodid ticks</article-title>. <source>Proceeding of Helminthological Society of Washington</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chabaud</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Atlas des larves infestantes de Filaires</article-title>. <source>Tropical Medicine and Parasitology</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katoh</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toh</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Recent developments in the MAFFT multiple sequence alignment program</article-title>. <source>Brief Bioinform</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bib/bbn013" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bib/bbn013</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18372315</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cowley</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uludag</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gur</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McWilliam</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The EMBL-EBI bioinformatics web and programmatic tools framework</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>W580</fpage>–<lpage>584</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkv279" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/nar/gkv279</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25845596</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>jModelTest: phylogenetic model averaging</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1253</fpage>–<lpage>1256</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msn083" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/molbev/msn083</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18397919</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>MrBayes 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference under mixed models</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1572</fpage>–<lpage>1574</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12912839</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stamatakis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and post-analysis of large phylogenies</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1312</fpage>–<lpage>1313</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btu033" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu033</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24451623</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casiraghi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uni</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The Nematode Filarioidea: critical analysis linking molecular and traditional approaches</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>342</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18814705</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Filariids and their evolution</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1970</year>) <article-title>Morphologie larvaire de <italic>Setaria labiatopapillosa</italic> (Nematoda, Filarioidea) chez <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">5511124</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wanji</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enyong</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petit</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noireau</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>New features on the moults and morphogenesis of the human filaria <italic>Loa loa</italic> by using rodent hosts consequences</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9754295</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chabaud</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>La lignée <italic>Dipetalonema</italic>. Nouvel essai de classification</article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">988773</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chabaud</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Nouvelles données sur la lignée <italic>Dipetalonema</italic> (Filarioidea, Nematoda)</article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>620</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">6891995</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Junker</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medger</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lutermann</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title><italic>Monanema joopi</italic> n. sp. (Nematoda, Onchocercidae) from <italic>Acomys</italic> (<italic>Acomys</italic>) <italic>spinosissimus</italic> Peters, 1852 (Muridae) in South Africa, with comments on the filarial genus</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23193517</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buckley</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edeson</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>1956</year>) <article-title>On the adult morphology of <italic>Wuchereria</italic> sp. (<italic>malayi</italic>?) from a monkey (<italic>Macaca irus</italic>) and from cats in Malaya, and on <italic>Wuchereria pahangi</italic> n.sp. from a dog and a cat</article-title>. <source>J Helminthol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">13319678</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eberhard</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orihel</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>The genus <italic>Mansonella</italic> (syn. <italic>Tetrapetalonema</italic>): a new classification</article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>496</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">6508144</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Description de nouvelles Filaires Oswaldofilariinae de Lézards sud-américains; hypothèse sur l'évolution des Filaires de Reptiles</article-title>. <source>Bull Mus Natl Hist Nat 3<sup>e</sup> ser n°208</source>, <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chilton</surname> <given-names>NB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jabbar</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huby-Chilton</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jex</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gasser</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Genetic variation within the <italic>Hypodontus macropi</italic> (Nematoda: Strongyloidea) complex from macropodid marsupial hosts in Australia</article-title>. <source>Electrophoresis</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>3544</fpage>–<lpage>3554</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/elps.201200364" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/elps.201200364</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23161349</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Susoy</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Preferential host switching and codivergence shaped radiation of bark beetle symbionts, nematodes of <italic>Micoletzkya</italic> (Nematoda: Diplogastridae)</article-title>. <source>J Evol Biol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>889</fpage>–<lpage>898</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/jeb.12367" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/jeb.12367</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24731122</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quentin</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>Sur les modalités d'évolution chez quelques lignées d'Helminthes de Rongeurs Muroidea</article-title>. <source>Cahiers ORSTOM (Série entomologie médicale et parasitologie)</source> <volume>IX</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0004233.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chauffour</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Todd</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guillot</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krief</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Seasonal Effects on Great Ape Health: A Case Study of Wild Chimpanzees and Western Gorillas</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>e49805</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0049805" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0049805</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23227152</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>