<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosntds</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1935-2735</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07-PNTD-RA-0002R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Population Genetics</subject><subject>Pharmacology/Drug Resistance</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genetic Selection of Low Fertile <italic>Onchocerca volvulus</italic>
                    by Ivermectin Treatment</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Ivermectin selection in <italic>O.
                    volvulus</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourguinat</surname><given-names>Catherine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pion</surname><given-names>Sébastien D. S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                        <sup>2</sup>
                    </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamgno</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardon</surname><given-names>Jacques</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                        <sup>4</sup>
                    </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" deceased="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duke</surname><given-names>Brian O. L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
                        <sup>5</sup>
                    </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boussinesq</surname><given-names>Michel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
                        <sup>6</sup>
                    </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>Roger K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
                        <sup>*</sup>
                    </xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
                <label>1</label>
                <addr-line>Institute of Parasitology, McGill University, Sainte Anne-de-Bellevue,
                    Quebec, Canada</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff2">
                <label>2</label>
                <addr-line>Laboratoire de Neuroparasitologie et
                    Neuroépidémiologie Tropicale, Faculté de
                    Médecine, Limoges Cedex, France</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff3">
                <label>3</label>
                <addr-line>National Onchocerciasis Task Force Cameroon, Yaoundé,
                Cameroon</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff4">
                <label>4</label>
                <addr-line>UR 24 Epidémiologie et Prévention, Institut de
                    Recherche pour le Développement, La Paz, Bolivia</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff5">
                <label>5</label>
                <addr-line>River Blindness Foundation, Lancaster, United Kingdom</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff6">
                <label>6</label>
                <addr-line>UR 24 Epidémiologie et Prévention,
                    Département Sociétés et Santé,
                    Institut de Recherche pour le Développement, Paris Cedex,
                France</addr-line>
            </aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lustigman</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">New York Blood Center, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">roger.prichard@mcgill.ca</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MB RP. Performed the experiments: CB.
                        Analyzed the data: MB RP CB SP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis
                        tools: MB JK JG BD. Wrote the paper: MB RP CB SP JK. Other: Conducted the
                        field trial and provided the Onchocerca material: JK JG BOLD ML.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>10</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e72</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date></history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bourguinat et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under
                the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted
                use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and
                source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article page="e76" related-article-type="commentary" vol="1" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000076" xlink:title="Expert Commentary" xlink:type="simple">
                <article-title>Ivermectin Resistance in <italic>Onchocerca volvulus:</italic> Toward
                    a Genetic Basis</article-title>
            </related-article><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p><italic>Onchocerca volvulus</italic> is the causative agent of
                        onchocerciasis, or “river blindness”. Ivermectin has
                        been used for mass treatment of onchocerciasis for up to 18 years, and
                        recently there have been reports of poor parasitological responses to the
                        drug. Should ivermectin resistance be developing, it would have a genetic
                        basis. We monitored genetic changes in parasites obtained from the same
                        patients before use of ivermectin and following different levels of
                        ivermectin exposure.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods and Findings</title><p><italic>O. volvulus</italic> adult worms were obtained from 73 patients
                        before exposure to ivermectin and in the same patients following three years
                        of annual or three-monthly treatment at 150 µg/kg or 800
                        µg/kg. Genotype frequencies were determined in
                            β-<italic>tubulin</italic>, a gene previously found to be linked
                        to ivermectin selection and resistance in parasitic nematodes. Such
                        frequencies were also determined in two other genes, <italic>heat shock
                            protein 60</italic> and <italic>acidic ribosomal protein</italic>, not
                        known to be linked to ivermectin effects. In addition, we investigated the
                        relationship between β-<italic>tubulin</italic> genotype and female
                        parasite fertility. We found a significant selection for
                            β-<italic>tubulin</italic> heterozygotes in female worms. There
                        was no significant selection for the two other genes. Quarterly ivermectin
                        treatment over three years reduced the frequency of the
                            β-<italic>tubulin</italic> “aa” homozygotes
                        from 68.6% to 25.6%, while the
                        “ab” heterozygotes increased from 20.9% to
                        69.2% in the female parasites. The female worms that were
                        homozygous at the β-<italic>tubulin</italic> locus were more fertile
                        than the heterozygous female worms before treatment (67% versus
                        37%; <italic>p</italic> = 0.003)
                        and twelve months after the last dose of ivermectin in the groups treated
                        annually (60% versus 17%;
                        <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001). Differences in fertility between
                        heterozygous and homozygous worms were less apparent three months after the
                        last treatment in the groups treated three-monthly.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The results indicate that ivermectin is causing genetic selection on
                            <italic>O. volvulus</italic>. This genetic selection is associated with
                        a lower reproductive rate in the female parasites. We hypothesize that this
                        genetic selection indicates that a population of <italic>O.
                        volvulus</italic>, which is more tolerant to ivermectin, is being selected.
                        This selection could have implications for the development of ivermectin
                        resistance in <italic>O. volvulus</italic> and for the ongoing
                        onchocerciasis control programmes.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><p><italic>Onchocerca volvulus</italic> is the causative agent of onchocerciasis, or
                    “river blindness”. Ivermectin has been used for mass
                    treatment of onchocerciasis for up to 18 years, and recently there have been
                    reports of poor parasitological responses to the drug and evidence of drug
                    resistance. Drug resistance has a genetic basis. In this study, genetic changes
                    in β-<italic>tubulin</italic>, a gene associated with ivermectin
                    resistance in nematodes, were seen in parasites obtained from the patients
                    exposed to repeated ivermectin treatment compared with parasites obtained from
                    the same patients before any exposure to ivermectin. Furthermore, the extent of
                    the genetic changes was dependent on the level of ivermectin treatment exposure.
                    This genetic selection was associated with a lower reproductive rate in the
                    female parasites. The data indicates that this genetic selection is for a
                    population of <italic>O. volvulus</italic> that is more tolerant to ivermectin.
                    This selection could have implications for the development of ivermectin
                    resistance in <italic>O. volvulus</italic> and for the ongoing onchocerciasis
                    control programmes. Monitoring for the possible development and spread of
                    ivermectin resistance, as part of the control programmes, should be implemented
                    so that any foci of resistant parasites can be treated by alternative control
                    measures.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by the River Blindness Foundation (to JK, JG, BOLD, MB),
                    the African Programme for Onchocerciasis Control (APOC), the Onchocerciasis
                    Control Programme in West Africa (OCP), the UNDP/World Bank/WHO Special
                    Programme for Research and Training in Tropical Diseases (TDR) and the Centre
                    for Host-Parasite Interactions (to RKP). SDSP was supported by the Fondation de
                    France, Fondation pour la Recherche Médicale and Fondation
                    Singer-Polignac. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and
                    analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic>Onchocerca volvulus</italic> is the filarial nematode, transmitted by
                    <italic>Simulium</italic> flies, that causes human onchocerciasis, or
                “river blindness”. It is estimated that 37 million people,
                mostly in Africa, are infected with this worm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Remme1">[1]</xref>. At present, ivermectin
                (IVM, Mectizan) is the only safe drug available for mass treatment of
                onchocerciasis. IVM, administered at the standard dose of 150 µg/kg, has a
                rapid effect on the embryonic stage of the parasite, the microfilariae (mf), which
                cause most of the ocular and cutaneous manifestations of the disease. As a result of
                this microfilaricidal effect, the skin microfilarial loads decrease by
                95–99% within one month after treatment. The drug also blocks
                the production of new mf by the adult female worms, who only resume mf release
                3–6 months after treatment. This “embryostatic effect”
                of IVM explains why the mf loads remain at very low levels for up to one year.
                Furthermore, IVM treatments repeated at 1- to 3-monthly intervals have some, though
                moderate, effect on the longevity of the adult worms (“macrofilaricidal
                effect”) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Duke1">[2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Gardon1">3]</xref>.</p><p>The drug, when given repeatedly, is therefore acting on at least three components of
                parasite fitness: reproduction, microfilarial survival and adult parasite lifespan,
                which together affect morbidity and the intensity of transmission. Due to the
                limited macrofilaricidal effect of the drug, treatments must be repeated and
                sustained. Endemic communities in Africa receive annual IVM treatment, while those
                of Latin America receive semi-annual treatments. To date, more than 400 million
                treatments have been distributed in Africa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Basanez1">[4]</xref>, with some individuals
                having received up to 18 annual treatments.</p><p>Due to this enormous drug pressure on the parasite, there is a risk of resistance of
                    <italic>O. volvulus</italic> to the drug <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Boussinesq1">[5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Prichard1">7]</xref>. This concern is
                justified by reports of suboptimal responses to IVM from Sudan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Ali1">[8]</xref> and Ghana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Awadzi1">[9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Awadzi2">10]</xref>, although in the
                former report reduced immune responsiveness in some of the treated people has been
                suggested as a possible explanation for the suboptimal responses to IVM. And in the
                study in Ghana the poor responses have been attributed to the parasites, with adult
                female worms resuming microfilarial production earlier after treatment than
                classically described. More recently, another report in Ghana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-OseiAtweneboana1">[11]</xref> shows the
                first unequivocal parasitological and epidemiological evidence of ivermectin
                resistance in <italic>O. volvulus</italic> populations.</p><p>In addition to this evidence of IVM resistance, changes in the genetic structure of
                    <italic>O. volvulus</italic> populations, associated with IVM treatments, have
                been observed in parasites from Ghana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Ardelli1">[12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng1">16]</xref>. These changes occurred particularly
                on the β-<italic>tubulin</italic> gene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng1">[16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng2">17]</xref>, which has been associated with IVM
                resistance in the sheep intestinal nematode <italic>Haemonchus contortus</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng2">[17]</xref>.
                However, in these previous studies, <italic>O. volvulus</italic> from
                IVM-naïve and -treated human populations were collected from different
                individuals in different communities.</p><p>It is important to assess whether the genetic changes reported in <italic>O.
                volvulus</italic> are associated with a reduced response to IVM in any of the three
                effects of IVM on parasite fitness, described above. Furthermore, to eliminate the
                possibility that differences in genotype frequencies between IVM-naïve and
                -treated populations could be due to geographical effects, due to separate
                individuals and communities being sampled, it is important to assess whether changes
                in genetic frequency could occur in parasites collected from the same individuals
                before and after exposure to IVM. Genetic changes clearly associated with treatment,
                which could not possibly be associated with other covariates, would provide
                unequivocal evidence of genetic selection by IVM on <italic>O. volvulus</italic>.
                Such treatment-induced selection would be heritable. Heritable genetic changes that
                could reduce the susceptibility of <italic>O. volvulus</italic> to any of the
                effects of IVM on the parasite could have long-term consequences for the control of
                onchocerciasis because there is currently no alternative drug available for mass
                treatment of this disease.</p><p>In a previous study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Bourguinat1">[18]</xref>, we reported that in an IVM-naïve
                    <italic>O. volvulus</italic> population from Cameroon, adult female worms
                presenting a homozygous genotype for β-tubulin were more fertile than adult
                worms that were heterozygous at this locus. In the present study, we have analyzed
                genetic characteristics (β-<italic>tubulin</italic> gene and two control
                genes, <italic>heat shock protein 60</italic> (hsp60) and <italic>acidic ribosomal
                    protein</italic> (ARP)) and phenotypic characteristics (female worm fertility)
                of parasites collected, in the same individuals, before and after 4 or 13 IVM
                treatments over a three-year period. These treatments were administered as part of a
                clinical trial conducted in Central Cameroon. The main objective of this trial was
                to assess the effects of different regimens of IVM treatment on the mortality of
                    <italic>O. volvulus</italic> adult worms, and the results of this phase have
                been published elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Gardon1">[3]</xref>. In the second phase, results of which are
                presented in this paper, we evaluated whether repeated treatment with IVM led to (a)
                genetic changes in the adult worm population and (b) any modification of the
                relationship between β-<italic>tubulin</italic> genotype of the female worms
                and their reproductive status.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Study Area, Study Design and Selection of Patients</title><p>The study was carried out in the Mbam Valley, a region hyper-endemic for
                    onchocerciasis, located in the Central province of Cameroon, where no IVM had
                    been distributed at the beginning of the study and where no vector control
                    activities have ever been performed. In this area, before the introduction of
                    IVM, the intensity of infection in the population, as expressed by the Community
                    Microfilarial Loads (CMFL) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Remme2">[19]</xref> ranged between 10 and 114 mf per skin snip
                    (mf/ss) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Gardon1">[3]</xref>. The full details of the clinical trial, which was
                    approved by the Cameroonian Ministry of Public Health and by Merck and Co., the
                    manufacturer of IVM (Mectizan), have been published elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Gardon1">[3]</xref>. The
                    study also subsequently received approval from the institutional review board of
                    McGill University. Briefly, 657 individuals were selected using the following
                    inclusion criteria: men between 18 and 60 years old, with at least two palpable
                    nodules during the preliminary examination but otherwise in good health, who had
                    not received any filaricidal treatment within the five previous years, and who
                    agreed to participate in the trial by signing an informed consent form. These
                    patients were randomly allocated to one of the four following IVM treatment
                    groups: 150 µg/kg body weight/year (standard group; group 1); 150
                    µg/kg/three-monthly (group 2); 800 µg/kg/year (group 3); and
                    800 µg/kg/three-monthly (group 4). Over the three-year study period,
                    patients received either 4 or 13 IVM treatments.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Collection of Nodules and Parasitological Examination</title><p>In order to assess the macrofilaricidal effect of IVM on <italic>O.
                    volvulus</italic>, adult worms were collected, by nodulectomy, at the outset of
                    the trial (before the first IVM dose was administered) and once again after
                    three years of treatment in the four different treatment groups described above.
                    The protocol used for parasite collection was identical for the two rounds of
                    nodulectomy. Just before each round of nodulectomy, each person was carefully
                    examined and all the sites on their body where a nodule or a group of nodules
                    was palpable were recorded on a body chart. Subsequently, one of the sites was
                    selected at random and all the nodules located at this site were removed from
                    each person. The site selected for the second nodulectomy was one of those
                    recorded at the outset of the study so that the worms collected at that time had
                    probably been subjected to the IVM treatments administered over the previous
                    three years. Just after the nodulectomy, all the nodules collected were immersed
                    in fixative (70% ethanol, 20% water, 10%
                    glycerol). One of the nodules was used for histological examination, as
                    previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Gardon1">[3]</xref>, to evaluate the status of the worms. Any
                    additional nodules (“extra nodule”) from the excision site
                    were stored in the fixative at room temperature and available for genotyping and
                    phenotyping.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Selection of Nodules for Genotyping and Phenotyping</title><p>Of the 657 individuals selected before treatment, 290 had more than one nodule at
                    the first nodulectomy site, and thus at least one “extra
                    nodule” available after the histological examination. Similarly, of
                    the 541 patients present at the second round of nodulectomy (following three
                    years of treatment), 156 had at least one extra nodule available. Patients
                    included in the present study were selected taking into account our objectives,
                    which were to assess the genotypes of three polymorphic genes, including
                        β-<italic>tubulin</italic>, in the adult worms, and any relationship
                    between the genotype of female parasites and their reproductive status, before
                    and after IVM treatment. To make the comparison more sensitive, we performed the
                    genotyping and the phenotyping only on parasites obtained from those people for
                    whom “extra nodules”, containing at least one adult worm,
                    had been collected at both nodulectomy rounds (pre-treatment and after three
                    years of repeated treatments). The total numbers of individuals who met these
                    inclusion criteria were 18 in group 1, 16 in group 2, 22 in group 3 and 17 in
                    group 4. Thus, the analyses were performed on the nodules collected from 73
                    individuals.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Procedure for Phenotyping the Female Reproductive Status</title><p>This procedure has been described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Bourguinat1">[18]</xref>. In 2002, the
                    nodules were washed with phosphate buffered saline (PBS) for 24 h with regular
                    changes of medium in order to remove all residues of fixative. The nodules were
                    then digested in collagenase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-SchulzKey1">[20]</xref>. Worms were collected and stored individually
                    in labelled Eppendorf tubes, which were frozen at −80°C. Each
                    female worm was phenotyped by microscopical examination of its reproductive
                    status in terms of the presence of mf and embryos. Three phenotypes were
                    defined: (a) non-fertile females, i.e. worms with empty reproductive organs, (b)
                    females with low fertility, in which the reproductive organs contained only a
                    few embryos, but no mf, and (c) fully fertile females, in which the reproductive
                    organs were full of mf and embryos.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Procedure for Genotyping</title><p>After the phenotyping, each worm was disrupted and its DNA was extracted using a
                    Dneasy kit (Qiagen Inc., Mississauga, Canada). <italic>Heat shock protein
                    60</italic> (<italic>hsp60</italic>) (GenBank, AF121264), which is a molecular
                    chaperone that participates in the folding of proteins, was chosen as a control
                    gene. It was known to be polymorphic and previously found not to be selected by
                    IVM treatment in <italic>O. volvulus</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng1">[16]</xref>. Two
                    polymorphs (“A” and “G”) were found in
                    the <italic>hsp60</italic> gene partial sequence analyzed. The region analyzed
                    started at position 214 on the cDNA and included 100 bp in the exon, followed by
                    276 bp in the intron. The A/G polymorphism was located in the intron region. The
                    fragment of 376 bp was amplified by PCR from individual adult worms with the
                    primers 5′CAA TCA TGG GGA AGT CCA AAG 3′ and 5′CTC
                    AAA ACC TTC CTT TGC AAT 3′ at
                    Tm = 53°C. PCR products were sequenced
                    with the <italic>hsp60</italic> anti-sense primer using the 3730XL DNA Analyzer
                    system (McGill University/Genome Quebec Innovation Centre). Platinum Taq DNA
                    polymerase High Fidelity (Invitrogen) was used in the PCR reaction to avoid
                    introduction of error during amplification. Each individual chromatogram was
                    analyzed with Sequencher 4.7 software (Gene Codes Corporation, Ann Arbor, MI,
                    USA), to detect the homozygotes AA and GG and the heterozygotes AG.</p><p>The <italic>acidic ribosomal protein</italic> (<italic>ARP</italic>) gene
                    (GenBank, AI130565), which is involved in protein synthesis, was chosen as a
                    second control because it was expected to be polymorphic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Klappenbach1">[21]</xref> and not known
                    to be sensitive to IVM treatment. Two polymorphs (“C” and
                    “T”) were found in the acidic ribosomal protein gene partial
                    sequence analyzed. The region of interest was from 1270 bp to 1488 bp of the
                    complete gene. It was amplified by PCR from individual adult worms with the
                    primers 5′ TGA AAA ACT GCT ACC GCA TA 3′ and 5′
                    AAA TTT TCG TTG GAA TTT GC 3′ at
                    Tm = 54°C. PCR products were analyzed
                    by restriction fragment length polymorphism, based on C/T polymorphism apparent
                    in the EST database, using the restriction enzyme Mnl 1 for 2 hours, and
                    subjected to electrophoresis on a 12% polyacrylamide gel
                    (39∶1) for 2 hours at 130 V, stained with ethidium bromide and
                    visualized using an ABI Imager (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA).</p><p>Two alleles (“a” and “b”) have been
                    described for β-<italic>tubulin</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng1">[16]</xref>.
                    These two alleles have three single nucleotide polymorphisms in an exon region.
                    These differences lead to changes in three amino acids in the putative protein
                    sequence. The worms were genotyped individually for
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic> (GenBank, F019886) by PCR amplification
                    followed by amplicon length analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng2">[17]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The aim of the analysis was to assess whether a variety of covariates related to
                    the worm, nodule or patient characteristics were associated with three different
                    dependent variables: (a) the inability to genotype some of the worms from the
                    preserved nodules; (b) the frequency of the various polymorphs analyzed; and (c)
                    the degree of fertility of the worm. We considered the five following
                    covariates: the age of the patient at the outset of the trial (continuous
                    variable); the CMFL in the village of residence of the patient, defined in four
                    categories: 10–40, 41–60, 61–70, and
                    71–114 mf/ss; the treatment group (for analysis of the worms collected
                    post-treatment: 150 µg/kg/year, 150 µg/kg/three-monthly, 800
                    µg/kg/year, and 800 µg/kg/three-monthly); the total number
                    of females in the nodule; and the total number of palpable nodules on the
                    patient at the outset of the trial. In addition, we also assessed the degree of
                    fertility in relation to the genotype of the worms and to the total number of
                    males in the nodule.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Study of Possible Bias in Female Worms That Could Not Be Genotyped</title><p>The procedure for genotyping the worms failed with a significant number of worms
                    obtained from the nodules that had been preserved at room temperature for 5 to 8
                    years. To test whether this inability to genotype some worms could be explained
                    by sampling biases, we assessed, using multivariate logistic regression, whether
                    the success in genotyping the worm (genotyped vs. non-genotyped status) was
                    associated with one or the other of the possible covariates quoted above. All
                    regressions analyses were performed using Stata v9.0 (Stata Corporation, TX,
                    USA), where parameters were estimated using the cluster option <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Williams1">[22]</xref>
                    accounting for intra-nodular correlation.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Changes in Genotypic Frequencies</title><p>Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium was tested using the χ<sup>2</sup> test,
                    unless the sample size was small. In this case, Fisher's exact test was
                    used. The genotypic frequencies before and after treatment were compared using
                    Fisher's exact test. To evaluate whether some host covariates or
                    village characteristics may have influenced the heterozygosity of the worms, the
                    association between heterozygous status and the five main possible covariates
                    quoted above was assessed separately on pre- and post-treatment data, by
                    multivariate logistic regressions. Potential intra-nodule clustering was
                    accounted in the regression models.</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Relationship between Genotype and Fertility of Female Worms Before and After
                    Treatment</title><p>Logistic regression models were used to analyze the independent variables
                    associated with the fertility of the female worms before and after treatment.
                    The dependent variable “fertility” was defined, for this
                    analysis, using two categories: no or low fertility versus high fertility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Bourguinat1">[18]</xref>. This choice is based on the fact that only worms
                    with mf have the possibility of having their progeny transmitted, at the time of
                    sampling, and this may be relevant to the possible transmission of any
                    “resistant” genotypes. However, any treatment group effect
                    on fertility status could be due to either treatment frequency or to the fact
                    that the worms were collected three months after the last treatment in the
                    three-monthly treated groups (groups 2 and 4) and twelve months post-treatment
                    in the annual groups (groups 1 and 3). The possible covariates in the model
                    included the five host-related independent variables defined above, and two
                    other independent variables: the genotype of the worm at the
                        β-<italic>tubulin</italic> locus (homozygous versus heterozygous),
                    and the total number of males present in the nodule. Here again, the
                    intra-nodule clustering was considered in the logistic regressions. The
                        χ<sup>2</sup> and Fisher's exact test analyses were
                    performed using VassarStats (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://faculty.vassar.edu/lowry/VassarStats.html" xlink:type="simple">http://faculty.vassar.edu/lowry/VassarStats.html</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 73 patients provided one nodule at the outset of the trial and one nodule
                after treatment. A total of 367 worms (248 females, 119 males) were isolated from
                the 73 nodules collected before treatment, and 224 worms (153 females, 71 males)
                were extracted from the 73 nodules provided by the same hosts after three years of
                repeated treatment. Details on the numbers of worms analyzed in the different
                treatment groups are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000072-t001">Tables
                    1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000072-t002">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pntd-0000072-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Number of Nodules and Worms Collected and Genotyped Before Ivermectin
                        Treatment in 73 Patients Who Provided Pre- and Post-Treatment
                    Nodules.</title></caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0000072-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rx group</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. Nod.</td><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Female worms</td><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Male worms</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.worms (No./Nod.)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">β-tubulin (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsp60 (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ARP (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. Phen.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. worms (No./Nod.)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">β-tubulin (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsp60 (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ARP (%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150*1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (3.72)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (77.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (68.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57 (85.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (1.89)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (35.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (47.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (97.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150*4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (3.06)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (71.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (67.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (75.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (1.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (42.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (39.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (92.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">800*1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (3.05)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 (67.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53 (79.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (83.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (1.27)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (60.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (50.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">800*4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65 (3.82)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (78.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55 (84.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (90.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (1.71)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (51.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (51.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (93.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">248 (3.40)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">183(73.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">187 (75.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">209 (84.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">247</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119 (1.63)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (47.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (47.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114 (95.8)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>Rx group = treatment group (dose
                            μg/kg * frequency per year); No.
                            Nod. = number of nodules; No.
                            worms = number of worms;
                            No./Nod. = number of worms per nodule;
                            β-tubulin = number of worms
                            genotyped for β-tubulin;
                            hsp60 = number of worms genotyped for
                            hsp60; ARP = number of worms genotyped
                            for acidic ribosomal protein; No.
                            Phen. = number of worms phenotyped for
                            fecundity.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pntd-0000072-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Number of Nodules and Worms Collected and Genotyped After Ivermectin
                        Treatment in 73 Patients Who Provided Pre- and Post-Treatment
                    Nodules.</title></caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0000072-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rx group</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. Nod</td><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Female worms</td><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Male worms</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. worms (No./Nod.)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">β-tubulin (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsp60 (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ARP (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. Phen.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. worms (No./Nod.)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">β-tubulin (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsp60 (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ARP (%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150*1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (2.28)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (78.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (58.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (75.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (1.22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (22.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (45.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150*4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (2.19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (60.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (48.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (80.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (0.94)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (26.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (33.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (80.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">800*1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (2.14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (57.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (59.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39 (83.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (1.05)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (56.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (43.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (95.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">800*4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (1.76)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (60.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (66.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (86.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (0.65)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (36.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (36.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">153 (2.10)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98 (64.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89 (58.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">124 (81.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71 (0.97)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (36.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (40.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (94.4)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><p>Rx group = treatment group (dose
                            μg/kg * frequency per year); No.
                            Nod. = number of nodules; No.
                            worms = number of worms;
                            No./Nod. = number of worms per nodule;
                            β-tubulin = number of worms
                            genotyped for β-tubulin;
                            hsp60 = number of worms genotyped for
                            hsp60; ARP = number of worms genotyped
                            for acidic ribosomal protein; No.
                            Phen. = number of worms phenotyped for
                            fecundity.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="s3a"><title>Study of the Independent Variables That Could Be Associated with the
                    Inability to Genotype the Worms for the β-<italic>tubulin</italic> Gene</title><p>We previously showed, in a sample of 320 female worms collected before treatment
                    as part of the same trial, that the 90 worms that could not be genotyped for
                        β-<italic>tubulin</italic> did not differ significantly, with regard
                    to several host independent variables, from the 230 worms that could be
                    genotyped <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Bourguinat1">[18]</xref>. Similar results were obtained when comparing
                    the 65 non-genotyped females to the 183 genotyped ones, and the 63 non-genotyped
                    males to the 56 genotyped males, collected before treatment, from the 73 people
                    from whom nodules could be analyzed both before and after treatment.</p><p>The proportion of female worms that could not be genotyped for
                        β-<italic>tubulin</italic> was significantly higher after treatment
                    (respectively 26.2% and 35.9% before and after treatment;
                        <italic>p</italic> = 0.043). Among the 153
                    female worms collected after treatment, 55 could not be genotyped. According to
                    multivariate logistic regression, the “genotyped” status was
                    not associated with any of the five covariates included in the analysis. The
                    proportion of non-genotyped male worms did not differ significantly before and
                    after treatment (respectively 52.9% and 63.4%;
                    <italic>p</italic> = 0.17). After treatment, we
                    observed that a significantly higher proportion of male worms could be genotyped
                    in the 800 µg/kg/year treatment group
                    (OR = 3.97 (95% CI,
                    1.05–15.08);
                    <italic>p</italic> = 0.043) compared to the
                    standard group. None of the other independent variables differed significantly
                    between the genotyped and the non-genotyped male worms. Taken together, these
                    results do not provide evidence of bias between the 45 non-genotyped and 26
                    genotyped male worms according to the tested covariates.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Genotypic Frequencies for the <italic>Heat Shock Protein 60</italic> Gene</title><sec id="s3b1"><title>Male worms</title><p>Amongst the 56 pre-treatment male worms that could be genotyped for this
                        gene, the proportions of worms showing AA, AG and GG genotypes were
                        8.9%, 32.1% and 59.0%, respectively. This
                        gene was in Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium before treatment. After treatment,
                        among the 29 genotyped males, the corresponding proportions were
                        6.9%, 34.5% and 58.6%. Fisher's
                        exact test did not demonstrate any significant difference in genotypic
                        frequencies between pre- and post-treatment male worms
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.99). It was not
                        possible to determine whether treatment frequency affected male worm hsp60
                        genotype after treatment because the sample size was too small.</p></sec><sec id="s3b2"><title>Female worms</title><p>Amongst the 187 pre-treatment female worms that could be genotyped, the
                        proportions of AA, AG and GG were, respectively, 9.1%,
                        35.3% and 55.6%. This gene was in Hardy-Weinberg
                        equilibrium before treatment. After treatment, among the 89 genotyped
                        females, the corresponding proportions were 6.8%,
                        43.8% and 49.4%. Fisher's exact test did not
                        demonstrate any significant difference in genotypic frequencies between pre-
                        and post-treatment female worms
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.37). It was
                        possible to pool the female worms based on frequency of treatment because
                        there were no significant differences between groups 1 and 3 before
                        treatment (<italic>p</italic> = 0.96) and
                        after treatment
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.12), and between
                        the groups 2 and 4 before treatment
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.055) and after
                        treatment (<italic>p</italic> = 0.40).
                        There were no significant differences in the hsp60 genotype frequencies
                        between the pooled annual treatment groups before and after treatment
                            (<italic>p</italic> = 0.11) and between
                        the three-monthly treatment groups before and after treatment
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.23).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Genotypic Frequencies for the Acidic Ribosomal Protein Gene</title><sec id="s3c1"><title>Male worms</title><p>Amongst the 114 pre-treatment male worms that could be genotyped for this
                        gene, the proportions of worms showing CC, CT and TT genotypes were
                        4.4%, 27.2% and 68.4%, respectively. After
                        treatment, among the 67 genotyped males, the corresponding proportions were
                        0%, 28.4% and 71.6%. Fisher's
                        exact test did not demonstrate any significant difference in genotypic
                        frequencies between pre- and post-treatment male worms
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.27). Hardy-Weinberg
                        analysis was not conducted on the acidic ribosomal protein gene because it
                        has multiple copies in eukaryotes with copies occurring at different loci
                            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Klappenbach1">[21]</xref>. It was possible to pool the male worms,
                        in frequency of treatment groups, because there were no significant
                        differences between groups 1 and 3 before treatment
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.47) and after
                        treatment (<italic>p</italic> = 0.09), and
                        between groups 2 and 4 before treatment
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 1) and after
                        treatment (<italic>p</italic> = 0.59).
                        There were no significant differences in ARP genotypes frequencies between
                        the pooled annual treatment groups before and after treatment
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.51) and between the
                        three-monthly treatment groups before and after treatment
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.19).</p></sec><sec id="s3c2"><title>Female worms</title><p>Amongst the 209 pre-treatment female worms that could be genotyped, the
                        proportions of CC, CT and TT were, respectively, 0%,
                        89.0% and 11.0%. After treatment, among the 124
                        genotyped females, the corresponding proportions were 0.8%,
                        90.3% and 8.9%. Fisher's exact test did not
                        demonstrate any change in genotype frequencies between pre- and
                        post-treatment female worms
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.38). It was
                        possible to pool the female worms in frequency of treatment groups because
                        there were no significant differences between groups 1 and 3 before
                        treatment (<italic>p</italic> = 0.39) and
                        after treatment
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.08), and between
                        groups 2 and 4 before treatment
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.50) and after
                        treatment (<italic>p</italic> = 0.61).
                        There were no significant differences in ARP genotype frequencies between
                        the pooled annual treatment groups before and after treatment
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.59) and between the
                        three-monthly treatment groups before and after treatment
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.77).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Genotypic Frequencies for the β-<italic>tubulin</italic> Gene</title><sec id="s3d1"><title>Male worms</title><p>Amongst the 56 pre-treatment male worms that could be genotyped, the
                        proportions of homozygous allele a (aa), heterozygotes (ab) and homozygous
                        allele b (bb) were, respectively, 92.9%, 5.4% and
                        1.8%. After treatment, among the 26 genotyped males, the
                        corresponding proportions were 96.2%, 3.8% and
                        0%. No change in genotypic frequencies between pre- and
                        post-treatment male worms was found, using Fisher's exact test.
                        Before treatment, the 56 males were in Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium
                        (Fisher's exact test,
                        <italic>p</italic> = 0.99).</p></sec><sec id="s3d2"><title>Female worms</title><p>Before treatment, there was no difference in genotype frequency
                            (χ<sup>2</sup> = 0.036;
                            <italic>p</italic> = 0.98) between any
                        of the groups. The 183 females analyzed before treatment were not in
                        Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium
                        (χ<sup>2</sup> = 26.5;
                        <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001), with an excess of homozygotes. Amongst
                        the female worms, the treatment led to an increase in the proportion of
                        β-tubulin heterozygous worms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0000072-g001">Figure 1</xref>). The reduction in the
                        proportion of homozygous aa worms for β-tubulin was most marked in
                        the 150 µg/kg three-monthly group (reduction rate in the
                        proportion of aa worms: 73.6%). We also observed the same pattern
                        of reduction in aa worms, though less dramatic, in the other treated groups
                        (21.9%, 49.3% and 50.0%, respectively, in
                        groups 1, 3 and 4). Conversely, the frequency of heterozygotes increased
                        dramatically among the female worms collected in the group treated at 150
                        µg/kg three-monthly and also markedly in the other groups
                            (χ<sup>2</sup> test,
                            <italic>p</italic>&lt;10<sup>−11</sup>). It was possible
                        to pool the female worms in frequency of treatment groups because there were
                        no significant differences between groups 1 and 3 before treatment
                            (<italic>p</italic> = 0.60) and after
                        treatment (<italic>p</italic> = 0.43), and
                        between groups 2 and 4 before treatment
                        (<italic>p</italic> = 0.78) and after
                        treatment (<italic>p</italic> = 0.72).
                        After treatment, dose rate (150 or 800 µg/kg) per se did not have
                        an effect on β-<italic>tubulin</italic> genotype frequency. However,
                        there was a significant difference (Fisher's exact test,
                        <italic>p</italic> = 0.047) between the
                        pooled annual treatment groups with respectively 44.1%,
                        55.9% and 0% of aa, ab and bb and the three-monthly
                        treatment groups with respectively 25.6%, 69.2% and
                        5.1% of aa, ab and bb. Hence treatment frequency, or the total
                        number of treatments given within the three years, did have a significant
                        effect on the β-<italic>tubulin</italic> genotype frequencies in the
                        female worms, recorded after treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0000072-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig id="pntd-0000072-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>β-<italic>tubulin</italic> Genotype of Female Worms.</title><p>β-tubulin genotype of female worms, that could be genotyped,
                                before and after different doses of ivermectin.
                                IVM = ivermectin treatment.
                                † Pooled by treatment frequency.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.g001" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Covariates Associated with Heterozygosity in
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic> among Female Worms</title><p>Before treatment, β-<italic>tubulin</italic> heterozygous status was not
                    influenced by age of host, total number of females in the nodule, total number
                    of palpable nodules or CMFL in the village of residence (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000072-t003">Table 3</xref>). After treatment, none of the tested
                    covariates was significantly associated with the
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic> heterozygous status, except the fact of
                    living in a village with a CMFL between 41 and 60 mf/ss. This weak association
                    (OR = 6.24 (95% CI,
                    1.09–35.59);
                    <italic>p</italic> = 0.039) might indicate that
                    the probability of being heterozygous was higher in the villages where infection
                    rates were rather high (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000072-t004">Table
                    4</xref>). The probability of being heterozygous tended to be higher in the
                    groups treated three-monthly. Even if this was not significant in the analysis
                    taking into account the various groups separately, this trend is consistent with
                    the results presented above comparing the pooled annual treatment groups and the
                    pooled three-monthly treatment groups.</p><table-wrap id="pntd-0000072-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Analysis of the Relationship of β-<italic>tubulin</italic>
                            Genotype with Patient and Parasitological Independent Variables Before
                            Treatment.</title></caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0000072-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>N</italic> = 183
                                    female worms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <italic>p</italic>
                                </td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age of patient</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93–1.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.081</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. females/nod.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73–1.21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.629</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMFL 41–60 mf/ss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13–5.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.819</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMFL 61–70 mf/ss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.93</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44–8.49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.385</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMFL 71–114 mf/ss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06–3.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.413</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. nod. 1994</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.81–1.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.976</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><p>Odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals
                                (95% CI) for logistic regression of heterozygote status
                                (vs. homozygote) of worms collected before ivermectin treatment on
                                four independent variables. No.
                                females/nod. = total number of
                                females in the nodule; No. nod.
                                1994 = total number of palpable
                                nodules in 1994; CMFL = Community
                                Microfilarial Load (reference category: 10–40
                                microfilariae per skin snip (mf/ss)).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pntd-0000072-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Analysis of the Relationship of β-<italic>tubulin</italic>
                            Genotype with Patient and Parasitological Independent Variables After
                            Treatment.</title></caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0000072-t004-4" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.t004" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>N</italic> = 98 female
                                    worms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <italic>p</italic>
                                </td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150 µg/kg three-monthly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.39–12.65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.370</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">800 µg/kg yearly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22–3.94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.923</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">800 µg/kg three-monthly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23–12.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.609</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age of patient</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94–1.04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.691</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. females/nod</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.57–1.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.356</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMFL 41–60 mf/ss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09–35.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.039</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMFL 61–70 mf/ss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91–21.54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.065</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMFL 71–114 mf/ss<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. nod. 1994</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68–1.13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.305</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><p>Odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals
                                (95% CI.) for logistic regression of heterozygote status
                                (vs. homozygote) of worms collected after ivermectin treatment on
                                five independent variables. No.
                                females/nod. = total number of
                                females in the nodule; No. nod.
                                1994 = total number of palpable
                                nodules in 1994; CMFL = Community
                                Microfilarial Load (reference category: 10–40
                                microfilariae per skin snip (mf/ss)). Reference category for
                                treatment group: 150 µg/kg yearly.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>*</label><p>All worms from villages with CMFL 71–114 mf/ss were
                                heterozygotes; consequently, the highest CMFL category was not used
                                for the estimation of other independent variables.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>Relationship between β-<italic>tubulin</italic> Genotype and
                    Fertility of Female Worms Before and After Treatment</title><p>Before treatment, the homozygote genotype was the only independent variable
                    associated with a high fertility phenotype (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.002)
                        (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000072-t005">Table 5</xref>). After
                    treatment, high fertility of the worms was still associated with the homozygous
                    genotype (<italic>p</italic> = 0.035). In
                    addition, high fertility of the worms was more likely to be observed amongst
                    younger patients (<italic>p</italic> = 0.018).
                    Finally, high fertility in the worms was more apparent in nodules containing
                    higher numbers of male worms
                    (<italic>p</italic> = 0.030) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000072-t006">Table 6</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pntd-0000072-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Analysis of the Relationship of Parasite Fertility with
                                β-<italic>tubulin</italic> Genotype, Patient and
                            Parasitological Independent Variables Before Treatment.</title></caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0000072-t005-5" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.t005" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>N</italic> = 183
                                    female worms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <italic>p</italic>
                                </td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Genotype = homozygote</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.71</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.59–8.70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age of patient</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97–1.04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.940</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. females/nod.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.70–1.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.085</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMFL 41–60 mf/ss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15–3.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.635</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMFL 61–70 mf/ss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25–5.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.879</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMFL 71–114 mf/ss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.93</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.40–9.37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.415</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. nod. 1994</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86–1.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.633</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. males</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76–1.60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.599</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt106"><p>Odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals
                                (95% CI) for logistic regression of full fertility (vs.
                                low- or non-fertility) of worms collected before ivermectin
                                treatment on six independent variables. Reference category for
                                genotype: heterozygosity for β-<italic>tubulin</italic>
                                gene. No. females/nod. = total
                                number of females in the nodule. No. nod.
                                1994 = total number of palpable
                                nodules in 1994. No. males = number
                                of males in the nodule.
                                CMFL = Community Microfilarial Load
                                (reference category: 10–40 microfilariae per skin snip
                                (mf/ss)).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pntd-0000072-t006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>Analysis of the Relationship of Parasite Fertility with
                                β-<italic>tubulin</italic> Genotype, Patient and
                            Parasitological Independent Variables After Treatment.</title></caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pntd-0000072-t006-6" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.t006" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>N</italic> = 98 female
                                    worms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <italic>p</italic>
                                </td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Genotype = homozygote</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10–13.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.035</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150 µg/kg three-monthly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.71</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.27–10.60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.566</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">800 µg/kg yearly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20–3.14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.731</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">800 µg/kg three-monthly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.42–14.58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.320</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age of patient</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89–0.99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. females/nod.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76–1.76</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.506</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMFL 41–60 mf/ss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04–3.21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.342</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMFL 61–70 mf/ss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20–12.47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.657</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMFL 71–114 mf/ss</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06–5.18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.619</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. nod. 1994</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84–1.40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.522</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. males</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09–5.21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.030</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt107"><p>Odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals
                                (95% CI) for logistic regression of full fertility (vs.
                                low- or non-fertility) of worms collected after ivermectin treatment
                                on seven independent variables. Reference category for genotype:
                                heterozygosity for β-<italic>tubulin</italic> gene.
                                Reference category for treatment group: 150 µg/kg yearly.
                                No. females/nod. = total number of
                                females in the nodule; No. nod.
                                1994 = total number of palpable
                                nodules in 1994; No. males = number
                                of males in the nodule;
                                CMFL = Community Microfilarial Load
                                (reference category: 10-40 microfilariae per skin snip (mf/ss)).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>As the intervals between the last IVM treatment and nodulectomy in the
                    three-monthly groups and the annual treatment groups were different, they have
                    also been considered separately (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0000072-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Twelve months after the last IVM treatment, analysis of
                    the fertility (non- and low fertility versus full fertility) in relation to
                    genotype showed that the β-<italic>tubulin</italic> homozygous worms
                    remained more fertile than the heterozygous worms
                    (χ<sup>2</sup> = 11.06,
                    <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0000072-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Because the sample size was small, we did not perform an
                    analysis on the data collected on the three-monthly groups (samples collected
                    three months after the last IVM treatment; groups 2 and 4). However, the figure
                    shows that the proportion of fully fertile worms was higher in the homozygous
                    worms (42% compared with 24%), but both genotype groups
                    showed a similar proportion of non-fertile worms (50% and
                    48%, respectively, for the homozygous and heterozygous parasites).</p><fig id="pntd-0000072-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Relationship between Female Worm Fertility and
                                β-<italic>tubulin</italic> Genotype in Relation to Treatment
                            Group.</title><p>Relationship between female worm fertility and β-tubulin genotype
                            (homozygous or heterozygous) in relation to treatment group (annual
                            versus three-monthly treatments, corresponding also to 4 versus 13
                            treatment rounds within three years).
                            IVM = ivermectin treatment;
                            FF = fully fertile;
                            F = low fertility;
                            NF = not fertile.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000072.g002" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>With the implementation of the onchocerciasis control programmes, an increasing
                proportion of people in endemic areas have received community-directed treatment
                with IVM on a regular basis. Even though children under 5 years of age and pregnant
                women are excluded from mass treatment, a high proportion of the parasite
                population, in control areas, is under treatment. As a consequence, and because most
                of the parasite population is in the human hosts rather than in the vector, only a
                relatively small proportion of the <italic>O. volvulus</italic> population is likely
                to be <italic>in refugia</italic> (not exposed to the drug) at the time of
                treatment. Thus, selection pressure for any IVM resistance alleles is expected to be
                high in <italic>O. volvulus</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Prichard1">[7]</xref>.</p><p>Parasitological and epidemiological evidence of ivermectin resistance in <italic>O.
                    volvulus</italic> populations has been reported in Ghana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-OseiAtweneboana1">[11]</xref>. Selection on
                the β-<italic>tubulin</italic> gene following repeated IVM treatment of
                people infected with <italic>O. volvulus</italic>, compared with parasites from
                IVM-naïve people has been found in Ghana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng1">[16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng2">17]</xref>. Because gene selection is the first
                step in the development of drug resistance, it is important to assess genetic change
                in a population of parasites exposed to selection pressure.</p><p>Our study of the possible effects of IVM on the genetic structure of an <italic>O.
                    volvulus</italic> population is unique in several respects. We analyzed nodules
                from the same patients before and after three years of IVM treatment at different
                treatment frequencies, dose rates, and with complete knowledge of the number of IVM
                treatments. To our knowledge, this has never been done in past investigations of the
                effect of IVM on genetic selection in human parasitic nematodes. In the study area,
                because there was no vector control and only a small proportion of the population
                living in the area was treated during the trial, the force of infection probably did
                not decrease during the trial <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Gardon1">[3]</xref>.</p><p>The main finding, that IVM treatment selected for heterozygotes at the
                β-tubulin locus and that this selection was dependent on the number of
                doses, raises interesting questions in view of the fact that this gene has been
                linked with IVM resistance in another parasitic nematode <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng2">[17]</xref> and the recent evidence
                that IVM resistance is occurring in <italic>O. volvulus</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-OseiAtweneboana1">[11]</xref>. The period over which the IVM treatment-associated
                genetic change in β-<italic>tubulin</italic> occurred was short (1994 to
                1997). It takes about 1 year from microfilarial birth until an adult worm commences
                production of the next generation of microfilaria. The observed genetic changes are
                dramatic, given the time period and the generation interval, and could result from
                differential mortality of existing adult worms and possibly a differential
                establishment of new worms, dependent on the worm genotype and tolerance to the drug
                pressure. These possible selective events will require further investigation. IVM
                might be more toxic to the more fertile female worms, which were previously found to
                be homozygous at the β-<italic>tubulin</italic> locus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Bourguinat1">[18]</xref>, as a result of the
                effect of IVM in preventing the release of microfilariae from the uterus and the
                subsequent degeneration of these trapped microfilariae.</p><p>The main limitation of the present study was that some samples could not be
                genotyped. As suggested in the previous paper <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Bourguinat1">[18]</xref> with samples from
                the same trial <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Gardon1">[3]</xref>, there are several explanations for the difficulty
                in genotyping some of the adult worms. The nodules had been stored in a dessicating
                fixative, at room temperature, for several years before they were digested and the
                DNA extracted. It is likely that some of the worms that could not be genotyped were
                dead or moribund at the time that the nodules were harvested. The DNA of dead or
                moribund parasites may have been degraded or fragmented, and difficult to amplify.
                Dead <italic>O. volvulus</italic> are not rapidly resorbed and can be readily found
                in nodules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-SchulzKey1">[20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Klager1">23]</xref>. In the study area before treatment, 15.2% of
                adult female worms found in nodules were moribund or dead <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Boussinesq2">[24]</xref>. After treatment,
                the proportion of non-genotyped parasites was higher
                (<italic>p</italic> = 0.024), which could be due to
                the macrofilaricidal effect of IVM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Gardon1">[3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Duke2">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Duke3">26]</xref>.</p><p>Very similar numbers of worms were genotyped for β-<italic>tubulin</italic>
                and for <italic>hsp60</italic> before and after treatment. Most of the worms that
                could not be genotyped for the acidic ribosomal protein gene could also not be
                genotyped for β-<italic>tubulin</italic>. However, a higher proportion of
                the <italic>acidic ribosomal protein</italic> gene was genotyped compared with the
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic> and the <italic>hsp60</italic> genes. The
                fact that <italic>acidic ribosomal protein</italic> has many gene copies in
                eukaryotic genomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Klappenbach1">[21]</xref>, whereas β-<italic>tubulin</italic> and
                    <italic>hsp60</italic> typically do not occur with multiple gene copies, could
                explain the difference in the ease of genotyping the <italic>acidic ribosomal
                    protein</italic> gene compared with the β-<italic>tubulin</italic> and
                    <italic>hsp60</italic> genes.</p><p>Notwithstanding these likely reasons why some worms could not be genotyped, we have
                performed several analyses to evaluate whether the population of those worms that
                could not be genotyped was similar to the population of worms that were genotyped.
                We showed that the two populations did not differ according to various external
                covariates (host age, CMFL level, etc.).</p><p>The female worms were not dissected into different tissues, but each worm was
                analyzed as a single entity. Any microfilarial DNA present within the female worm
                would be included in the DNA analysis of the female worm, and so the
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic> genotype frequencies of the female worms
                could have resulted from microfilarial/embryo DNA contamination within the female
                worm. Such daughter microfilariae/embryos would have half of their DNA derived from
                that mother worm and thus reflect the genome of the mother worm. Any contribution
                from male worms to the assessed genotype of a female worm via the daughter
                microfilaria/embryos contained within the female worm, would, if a significant
                effect, tend to increase the probability that female worm genotypes would be seen as
                heterozygotes. In fact, in the female worms before treatment there was an excess of
                homozygotes, indicating that any contribution from male worms to the genotype
                assessed in the female worms was not significant. Given the low frequency of the
                “b” allele in the male worms before and after treatment, the
                increase in the frequency of “ab” heterozygotes in the female
                worms, following treatment, could not be accounted for by male worm contamination
                via microfilaria/embryos contained within the female worm.</p><p>Finally, the frequency of “ab” heterozygotes was greater in the
                three-monthly treatment groups (69%) than in the annual treatment groups
                (56%) and the pre-treatment sample (21%). IVM treatment
                reduces fertility so that if microfilarial/embryonic DNA were contributing to the
                assessment of DNA of the female worms, treatment should have decreased, rather than
                increased, the proportion of female worms that appeared as heterozygotes. For these
                reasons we do not believe that microfilarial/embryonic DNA within the female worms
                had any significant influence on the observed genotype frequencies for
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic> observed in the female worms.</p><p>One possible explanation for the apparent IVM selection on
                β-<italic>tubulin</italic> in the female worms is the existence of a null
                allele (an allele that is not being detected by the method used) that could be
                distorting the genotype frequencies determined. Previously, we have found that
                freshly frozen <italic>O. volvulus</italic> samples always amplified readily with
                the same β-<italic>tubulin</italic> primers as have been used in this study
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng2">[17]</xref>
                suggesting that no null allele exists, using the procedures followed, for
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic> in <italic>O. volvulus</italic>. We do not
                believe that a null allele exists to affect the genotype frequencies. Furthermore,
                even if it did exist, it could not account for the change in genotype frequencies
                resulting from IVM treatment. We can conclude that the observed change in
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic> genotype frequency with treatment is genetic
                selection as has been seen previously in <italic>O. volvulus</italic> that have been
                obtained from people who have been repeatedly treated with IVM and also observed in
                IVM-resistant <italic>H. contortus</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng1">[16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng2">17]</xref>.</p><p>One of the main findings of the study is that female worms, homozygous for
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic>, were more fertile than heterozygote female
                worms. A similar difference in fertility before treatment was reported previously
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Bourguinat1">[18]</xref>. Homozygous worms, in the patients treated annually
                and collected twelve months after the last IVM treatment, also had higher fertility
                than heterozygotes. However, this difference decreased if the worms were collected
                three months after 13 three-monthly IVM treatments, at a time when the embryostatic
                effect of IVM is normally still apparent. The results observed three months after
                IVM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0000072-g002">Figure 2</xref>) could be due to a
                combination of innate differences in fertility between homozygous and heterozygous
                worms and the relative effects of IVM on embryostasis in the different genotypes. If
                the fertility disadvantage of heterozygotes tends to disappear when the parasite is
                under strong IVM pressure, this could have implications for parasite transmission
                and possible resistance selection. It would be interesting to study, perhaps in
                    <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>, how polymorphism in
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic> may affect the fertility of nematodes.</p><p>Before treatment, <italic>hsp60</italic> gene was in Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium in
                the female and male worm populations as well as for the
                β-<italic>tubulin</italic> gene in the male worm population. The
                    <italic>acidic ribosomal protein</italic> gene normally has multiple gene copies
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Klappenbach1">[21]</xref>, which means that there are multiple loci in the
                genome. For this reason, it is inappropriate to apply a Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium
                test, as used on a single locus. The β-<italic>tubulin</italic> gene was not
                in Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium in the female worms, as there was an excess of
                homozygotes in this population. Various assumptions are required for Hardy-Weinberg
                equilibrium including random mating. Non-random mating could occur in the <italic>O.
                    volvulus</italic> population and be due to inbreeding, positive assortative
                mating or a subpopulation structure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Hartl1">[27]</xref>. The inbreeding coefficient <italic>F</italic>,
                which represents the proportional loss of heterozygosity due to inbreeding, was
                calculated for the population of 73 patients, based on the β-tubulin data,
                to be 0.41. This index of inbreeding is moderately high and has implications not
                only for Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium, but also for the possible rate of selection of
                a resistant population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Schwab1">[28]</xref>. Inbreeding could be explained by the fact that
                vectors transmitting to the study population were living in the local area and tend
                to bite people from the same community.</p><p>It is of interest that the <italic>F<sub>IT</sub></italic> (inbreeding coefficient
                within a subpopulation) for <italic>Wuchereria bancrofti</italic> microfilariae, a
                closely related human filarial nematode, was calculated on the basis of
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic> genotype frequencies to be 0.44 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Schwab2">[29]</xref>.
                However, other processes may be involved. An assortative mating coefficient R (which
                could include inbreeding) was calculated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Hartl1">[27]</xref> to be 0.54. The higher
                fertility of the female β-<italic>tubulin</italic> homozygote
                “aa” worms, when compared with the female heterozygote
                “ab” worms, could be consistent with positive assortative mating
                if the likelihood that a worm will mate is associated with the female
                worm's fecundity. It is known that male <italic>O. volvulus</italic>
                migrate between nodules and may be attracted by the fully fertile females
                (predominantly homozygous). Subpopulation structure could also explain the
                Hardy-Weinberg disequilibrium. Because the samples were collected in a
                forest/savannah transition zone, the worms could belong either to a savannah, or to
                forest or mixed forest/savannah strains. Subpopulations can result from
                environmental segregation, inbreeding and/or positive assortative mating. Finally,
                it is possible that in the absence of IVM treatment, the
                β-<italic>tubulin</italic> heterozygote female worms die faster than the
                homozygote female worms. Differential mortality between the genotypes could also
                affect Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium.</p><p>The selection for the β-<italic>tubulin</italic> heterozygote
                “ab”, found in female worms after IVM treatment, was more
                important in the worms exposed to IVM every three months compared with the worms
                exposed to IVM annually. This difference could be due to either the total number of
                treatments or to the interval between treatments. These are important points for the
                onchocerciasis control programmes because semi-annual or more frequent treatments
                are ongoing in some areas and under consideration in other areas. An increase in
                treatment frequency might increase the selection pressure.</p><p>No selection was demonstrated in the male worm population after treatment, during the
                three-year study period. This result suggests that the female worms are more
                susceptible to IVM pressure than the males and could reflect an increased
                IVM-induced mortality in female worms that are homozygous at the
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic> locus. From the Gardon et al. trial in
                Cameroon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Gardon1">[3]</xref>, it is possible to estimate the relative proportional
                decrease in male and female parasites due to IVM treatment over the study period.
                This amounts to 13.5% and 27.5%, respectively. If the male
                parasites are less affected by the treatment, the genotype frequencies in the male
                population would only change significantly following transmission and subsequent
                infection by progeny of the parasites under selection. Given that it takes about one
                year to complete the life cycle of <italic>O. volvulus</italic>, in this situation
                it would take longer for IVM selection to influence male worm genotype frequencies.
                It is interesting in this regard that in <italic>Brugia malayi</italic>,
                sex-dependent expression in a possible IVM receptor has been demonstrated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Li1">[30]</xref>. The
                putative glutamate-gated chloride (GluCl) channel gene, <italic>AF118554,</italic>
                was estimated to be expressed at a 24.3-fold higher level in female worms compared
                with male worms. As GluCl is thought to be the main target of IVM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Dent1">[31]</xref>, one
                could speculate that the effect of IVM might be greater in female than male worms.
                This might explain why <italic>O. volvulus</italic> male worms seem to be less
                susceptible to IVM and thus less rapidly selected than female worms, so that in the
                short three-year time interval of this study no significant change in
                    β-<italic>tubulin</italic> genome frequency was seen in the male worms.
                However, selection on β-<italic>tubulin</italic> in male <italic>O.
                volvulus</italic> has been found when parasite populations were exposed over 6 or
                more years to IVM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng1">[16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Eng2">17]</xref>.</p><p>There may also be an IVM-induced mortality of the incoming larvae or pre-adult stages
                of the parasites, with the homozygous worms being more sensitive to repeated
                treatment than the heterozygote parasites. An effect of IVM on the pre-adult stages
                of <italic>O. volvulus</italic> has been suggested <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Klager2">[32]</xref> and demonstrated in
                results obtained on the bovine parasite <italic>Onchocerca ochengi</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Tchakoute1">[33]</xref>.</p><p>Today, intestinal trichostrongylid nematodes of livestock are commonly strongly
                resistant to IVM, and the development of IVM resistance can occur rapidly in these
                nematode parasites, sometimes in less than three years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Shoop1">[34]</xref>. However,
                trichostrongylid nematodes and filarial nematodes have different biology. As the
                generation time is shorter in trichostrongylid nematodes than in filarial nematodes,
                resistance selection would be expected to take longer to be manifested in filarial
                worms. In contrast to soil transmitted nematodes, filariae have no free-living
                stages and most of the population of the nematode occurs in the human host, so that
                    <italic>refugia</italic> is likely to be low in a community under treatment. As
                a result, selection pressure for resistance to develop could be high in human
                filarial nematodes under intensive drug treatment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Prichard1">[7]</xref>.</p><sec id="s4a"><title>Conclusion</title><p>IVM has been used since the late 1980s, and more than 400 million doses have been
                    distributed in Africa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0000072-Basanez1">[4]</xref>. It remains the only safe drug for community
                    treatment of onchocerciasis. Our results clearly show a genetic selection in
                        <italic>O. volvulus</italic> caused by repeated IVM treatment. Since the
                    parasites were collected before and after treatment from the same patients,
                    these results cannot be explained as differences arising from different host
                    populations being sampled. These results, together with other evidence of
                    genetic selection and reports of sub-optimal responses to IVM, provide a warning
                    that selection for IVM resistance could be occurring in some populations of
                        <italic>O. volvulus</italic>.</p><p>In view of these results, it is imperative that field studies be undertaken to
                    characterize all treatment responses to IVM in <italic>O. volvulus</italic>,
                    coupled to further genetic analysis, in order to confirm or not the possible
                    emergence of IVM resistance. Such longitudinal studies, which would look at the
                    repopulation of the skin of treated people by mf, should be undertaken without
                    delay if the benefits that have been achieved by the onchocerciasis control
                    programmes are not to be lost as a result of the spread of IVM resistance in
                        <italic>O. volvulus</italic>.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pntd.0000072-Remme1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Remme</surname><given-names>JHF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feenstra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lever</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Médici</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <source>Tropical Diseases Targeted for Elimination: Chagas Disease, Lymphatic
                        Filariasis, Onchocerciasis, and Leprosy. Disease Control Priorities in
                        Developing Countries</source>
                    <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>433</fpage>
                    <lpage>450</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Duke1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duke</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zea-Flores</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cupp</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1990</year>
                    <article-title>Effects of multiple monthly doses of ivermectin on adult
                        Onchocerca volvulus.</article-title>
                    <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
                    <volume>43</volume>
                    <fpage>657</fpage>
                    <lpage>664</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Gardon1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boussinesq</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamgno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardon-Wendel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demanga</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Effects of standard and high doses of ivermectin on adult worms
                        of Onchocerca volvulus: a randomised controlled trial.</article-title>
                    <source>Lancet</source>
                    <volume>360</volume>
                    <fpage>203</fpage>
                    <lpage>210</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Basanez1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basanez</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pion</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breitling</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>River blindness: a success story under threat?</article-title>
                    <source>PLoS Med</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>e371</fpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Boussinesq1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boussinesq</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>la résistance d' Onchocerca volvulus
                        à l'ivermectine: une éventualité
                        à considérer.</article-title>
                    <source>Ann Inst Pasteur</source>
                    <volume>10</volume>
                    <fpage>81</fpage>
                    <lpage>91</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Grant1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>What is the real target for ivermectin resistance selection in
                        Onchocerca volvulus?</article-title>
                    <source>Parasitol Today</source>
                    <volume>16</volume>
                    <fpage>458</fpage>
                    <lpage>459</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Prichard1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Is anthelmintic resistance a concern for heartworm control? What
                        can we learn from the human filariasis control programs?</article-title>
                    <source>Vet Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>133</volume>
                    <fpage>243</fpage>
                    <lpage>253</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Ali1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukhtar</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baraka</surname><given-names>OZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Homeida</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kheir</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Immunocompetence may be important in the effectiveness of
                        Mectizan (ivermectin) in the treatment of human onchocerciasis.</article-title>
                    <source>Acta Trop</source>
                    <volume>84</volume>
                    <fpage>49</fpage>
                    <lpage>53</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Awadzi1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Awadzi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attah</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Addy</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Opoku</surname><given-names>NO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quartey</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Thirty-month follow-up of sub-optimal responders to multiple
                        treatments with ivermectin, in two onchocerciasis-endemic foci in Ghana.</article-title>
                    <source>Ann Trop Med Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>98</volume>
                    <fpage>359</fpage>
                    <lpage>370</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Awadzi2"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Awadzi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boakye</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Opoku</surname><given-names>NO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attah</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>An investigation of persistent microfilaridermias despite
                        multiple treatments with ivermectin, in two onchocerciasis-endemic foci in
                        Ghana.</article-title>
                    <source>Ann Trop Med Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>98</volume>
                    <fpage>231</fpage>
                    <lpage>249</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-OseiAtweneboana1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osei-Atweneboana</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boakye</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyapong</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Prevalence and intensity of Onchocerca volvulus infection and
                        efficacy of ivermectin in endemic communities in Ghana: a two-phase
                        epidemiological study.</article-title>
                    <source>Lancet</source>
                    <volume>369</volume>
                    <fpage>2021</fpage>
                    <lpage>2029</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Ardelli1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ardelli</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Identification of variant ABC-transporter genes among Onchocerca
                        volvulus collected from ivermectin-treated and untreated patients in Ghana,
                        West Africa.</article-title>
                    <source>Ann Trop Med Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>98</volume>
                    <fpage>371</fpage>
                    <lpage>384</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Ardelli2"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ardelli</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerriero</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Genomic organization and effects of ivermectin selection on
                        Onchocerca volvulus P-glycoprotein.</article-title>
                    <source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>143</volume>
                    <fpage>58</fpage>
                    <lpage>66</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Ardelli3"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ardelli</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerriero</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Ivermectin imposes selection pressure on P-glycoprotein from
                        Onchocerca volvulus: linkage disequilibrium and genotype diversity.</article-title>
                    <source>Parasitology</source>
                    <volume>132</volume>
                    <fpage>375</fpage>
                    <lpage>386</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Ardelli4"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ardelli</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerriero</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Characterization of a half-size ATP-binding cassette transporter
                        gene which may be a useful marker for ivermectin selection in Onchocerca
                        volvulus.</article-title>
                    <source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>145</volume>
                    <fpage>94</fpage>
                    <lpage>100</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Eng1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>A comparison of genetic polymorphism in populations of Onchocerca
                        volvulus from untreated- and ivermectin-treated patients.</article-title>
                    <source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>142</volume>
                    <fpage>193</fpage>
                    <lpage>202</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Eng2"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackhall</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osei-Atweneboana</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourguinat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galazzo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Ivermectin selection on beta-tubulin: evidence in Onchocerca
                        volvulus and Haemonchus contortus.</article-title>
                    <source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>150</volume>
                    <fpage>229</fpage>
                    <lpage>235</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Bourguinat1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourguinat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pion</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamgno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardon-Wendel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Genetic polymorphism of the beta-tubulin gene of Onchocerca
                        volvulus in ivermectin naive patients from Cameroon, and its relationship
                        with fertility of the worms.</article-title>
                    <source>Parasitology</source>
                    <volume>132</volume>
                    <fpage>255</fpage>
                    <lpage>262</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Remme2"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Remme</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ba</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dadzie</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1986</year>
                    <article-title>A force-of-infection model for onchocerciasis and its
                        applications in the epidemiological evaluation of the Onchocerciasis Control
                        Programme in the Volta River basin area.</article-title>
                    <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>
                    <volume>64</volume>
                    <fpage>667</fpage>
                    <lpage>681</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-SchulzKey1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz-Key</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1988</year>
                    <article-title>The collagenase technique: how to isolate and examine adult
                        Onchocerca volvulus for the evaluation of drug effects.</article-title>
                    <source>Trop Med Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>39</volume>
                    <supplement>Suppl 4</supplement>
                    <fpage>423</fpage>
                    <lpage>440</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Klappenbach1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klappenbach</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saxman</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>rrndb: the Ribosomal RNA Operon Copy Number Database.</article-title>
                    <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
                    <volume>29</volume>
                    <fpage>181</fpage>
                    <lpage>184</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Williams1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>A note on robust variance estimation for cluster-correlated data.</article-title>
                    <source>Biometrics</source>
                    <volume>56</volume>
                    <fpage>645</fpage>
                    <lpage>646</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Klager1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klager</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1988</year>
                    <article-title>Investigations of enzymatically isolated male Onchocerca
                        volvulus: qualitative and quantitative aspects of spermatogenesis.</article-title>
                    <source>Trop Med Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>39</volume>
                    <supplement>Suppl 4</supplement>
                    <fpage>441</fpage>
                    <lpage>445</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Boussinesq2"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boussinesq</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamgno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demanga</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pion</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Studies on the macrofilarial population of Onchocerca volvulus in
                        hyper-endemic villages of the Central province of Cameroon.</article-title>
                    <source>Ann Trop Med Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>95</volume>
                    <fpage>379</fpage>
                    <lpage>388</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Duke2"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duke</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1990</year>
                    <article-title>An improved method of examining adult Onchocerca volvulus worms.</article-title>
                    <source>Trop Med Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>41</volume>
                    <fpage>25</fpage>
                    <lpage>28</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Duke3"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duke</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Evidence for macrofilaricidal activity of ivermectin against
                        female Onchocerca volvulus: further analysis of a clinical trial in the
                        Republic of Cameroon indicating two distinct killing mechanisms.</article-title>
                    <source>Parasitology</source>
                    <volume>130</volume>
                    <fpage>447</fpage>
                    <lpage>453</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Hartl1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1989</year>
                    <source>Principles of Population Genetics</source>
                    <publisher-name>Sinauer Associates, Inc.</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>682</fpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Schwab1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basáñez</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>An Analysis of the Population Genetics of Potential Multi-drug
                        Resistance in Lymphatic Filariasis due to Combination Chemotherapy.</article-title>
                    <source>Parasitology</source>
                    <volume>134</volume>
                    <fpage>1025</fpage>
                    <lpage>1040</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Schwab2"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basáñez</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Population genetics of concurrent selection with albendazole and
                        ivermectin or diethylcarbamazine on the possible spread of albendazole
                        resistance in Wuchereria bancrofti.</article-title>
                    <source>Parasitology</source>
                    <volume>133</volume>
                    <fpage>589</fpage>
                    <lpage>601</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Li1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rush</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weil</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Quantitative analysis of gender-regulated transcripts in the
                        filarial nematode Brugia malayi by real-time RT-PCR.</article-title>
                    <source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>137</volume>
                    <fpage>329</fpage>
                    <lpage>337</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Dent1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dent</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vassilatis</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>The genetics of ivermectin resistance in Caenorhabditis elegans.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>97</volume>
                    <fpage>2674</fpage>
                    <lpage>2679</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Klager2"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klager</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitworth</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chavasse</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Downham</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1993</year>
                    <article-title>How long do the effects of ivermectin on adult Onchocerca
                        volvulus persist?</article-title>
                    <source>Trop Med Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>44</volume>
                    <fpage>305</fpage>
                    <lpage>310</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Tchakoute1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tchakoute</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronsvoort</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanya</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Renz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trees</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Chemoprophylaxis of Onchocerca infections: in a controlled,
                        prospective study ivermectin prevents calves becoming infected with O.
                        ochengi.</article-title>
                    <source>Parasitology</source>
                    <volume>118</volume>
                    <issue>Pt 2</issue>
                    <fpage>195</fpage>
                    <lpage>199</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0000072-Shoop1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoop</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1993</year>
                    <article-title>Ivermectin resistance.</article-title>
                    <source>Parasitol Today</source>
                    <volume>9</volume>
                    <fpage>154</fpage>
                    <lpage>159</lpage>
                </element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>