<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosntds</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1935-2735</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PNTD-D-16-01023</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>From Innovation to Application</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Disease vectors</subject><subj-group><subject>Insect vectors</subject><subj-group><subject>Mosquitoes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Species interactions</subject><subj-group><subject>Disease vectors</subject><subj-group><subject>Insect vectors</subject><subj-group><subject>Mosquitoes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animals</subject><subj-group><subject>Invertebrates</subject><subj-group><subject>Arthropoda</subject><subj-group><subject>Insects</subject><subj-group><subject>Mosquitoes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Parasitic diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Malaria</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Tropical diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Malaria</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Entomology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographical locations</subject><subj-group><subject>South America</subject><subj-group><subject>Brazil</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Polymer chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Macromolecules</subject><subj-group><subject>Polymers</subject><subj-group><subject>Nylons</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Materials science</subject><subj-group><subject>Materials by structure</subject><subj-group><subject>Polymers</subject><subj-group><subject>Nylons</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Disease vectors</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Species interactions</subject><subj-group><subject>Disease vectors</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathology and laboratory medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathogenesis</subject><subj-group><subject>Host-pathogen interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Body fluids</subject><subj-group><subject>Blood</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Body fluids</subject><subj-group><subject>Blood</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Body fluids</subject><subj-group><subject>Blood</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Body fluids</subject><subj-group><subject>Blood</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>MosqTent: An individual portable protective double-chamber mosquito trap for anthropophilic mosquitoes</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lima</surname>
<given-names>José Bento Pereira</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Galardo</surname>
<given-names>Allan Kardec Ribeiro</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bastos</surname>
<given-names>Leonardo Soares</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lima</surname>
<given-names>Arthur Weiss da Silva</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9512-6567</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Rosa-Freitas</surname>
<given-names>Maria Goreti</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Laboratório de Fisiologia e Controle de Artrópodes Vetores, Instituto Oswaldo Cruz, Fiocruz, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Laboratório de Entomologia, Instituto de Biologia do Exército, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Instituto de Pesquisas Científicas e Tecnológicas do Estado do Amapá, Macapá, Brazil</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>Programa de Computação Científica, Fiocruz, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff005"><label>5</label> <addr-line>Laboratório de Mosquitos Transmissores de Hematozoários, Instituto Oswaldo Cruz, Fiocruz, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Kittayapong</surname>
<given-names>Pattamaporn</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Mahidol University, THAILAND</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">goreti@ioc.fiocruz.br</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>9</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<elocation-id>e0005245</elocation-id>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Lima et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245"/>
<abstract abstract-type="summary">
<title>Author summary</title>
<p>Here, we describe the development of the MosqTent, an innovative double-chamber mosquito trap in which a human being attracts mosquitoes while is protected from being bitten within the inner chamber of the trap, while mosquitoes are lured to enter an outer chamber where they are trapped. The MosqTent previously collected an average of 3,000 anophelines/man-hour compared to 240 anophelines/man-hour for the human landing catch (HLC), thereby providing high numbers of human host–seeking mosquitoes while protecting the collector from mosquito bites. The MosqTent performed well by collecting a high number of specimens of <italic>Anopheles</italic> <italic>marajoara</italic>, a local vector and anthropophilic mosquito species present in high density, but not so well in collecting <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>, an anthropophilic mosquito species considered the main vector in Brazil but is present in low-density conditions in the area. The HLC showed a higher efficiency in collecting <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> in these low-density conditions. The MosqTent is light (&lt;1 kg), portable (comes as a bag with two handles), flexible (can be used with other attractants), adaptable (can be deployed in a variety of environmental settings and weather conditions), and it can be used in the intra-, peri-, and in the extradomicile. Also, the MosqTent collected similar portions of parous females and anthropophilic mosquito species and collects specimens suitable for downstream analysis. Further developments may include testing for other fabric colors, different mesh sizes and dimensions for other hematophagous insects and conditions, additional chemical mosquito attractants, and even the replacement of the human attractant in favor of other attractants. MosqTent modifications that would allow the trap to be applied as a vector control tool with killing action could also be explored.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>Although the authors received no specific funding for this work, financial resources of the Conselho Nacional de Pesquisas e Desenvolvimento Tecnológico-CNPq and Instituto Oswaldo Cruz-FIOCRUZ to JBPL benefited the final outcome. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="8"/>
<table-count count="5"/>
<page-count count="18"/>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Overview</title>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Given the preference of vector-borne human parasites to feed on human blood, most adult mosquito traps currently in use are far less efficient than human landing catches (HLCs) for collecting host-seeking mosquitoes. A clear picture of the dynamics and transmission risks posed by anthropophilic mosquitoes in disease-endemic areas is provided by the use of HLC. HLC is logistically complex, and ethical dilemmas arise when fieldworkers may be exposed to the risk of infective biting and acquiring deadly or unknown pathogens. To address the problem of how to attract and assess anthropophilic mosquitoes while protecting the human bait from being bitten, we have designed and tested a novel, portable, double-chamber mosquito trap, the MosqTent.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>The MosqTent consists of an isolated inner chamber and an outer chamber to collect mosquitoes that are attracted by human cues (visual, temperature, and odor, among other cues—hereafter referred to as "human-attractant"), which is protected within the inner chamber. Two versions of the MosqTent (black versus white) were tested in the Brazilian Amazon against the Biogents (BG)-sentinel trap + CO<sub>2</sub>, the protected HLC (human attractant wearing a protective sock), and the HLC. The HLC was considered the gold standard for data analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The MosqTent collected all anopheline species caught by the HLC. The MosqTent collected more mosquitoes than the HLC in high mosquito–density conditions (3,000 anophelines/man-hour compared to only 240 anophelines for the HLC). The MosqTent performed well by collecting a high number of <italic>Anopheles marajoara</italic> specimens, a local anthropophilic vector present in high density, but not so well in collecting <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>, an anthropophilic species that is considered the main Brazilian vector but is present in low-density conditions in the area. The HLC showed higher efficiency in collecting <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> in these low-density conditions. For <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>, the MosqTent white and black collected nearly twice as many specimens as the HLC (25.7% and 28.9%, respectively; HLC: 15.1%). For <italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic>, the BG compared to the HLC and tent traps were much lower (BG: 33.4%; MosqTent white and black: 10.1% and 6.4%, respectively). For <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>, both tent traps caught half as many as the HLC (MosqTent white and black: 12.5% and 14.9%, respectively; HLC: 35.5%). For <italic>An</italic>. <italic>braziliensis</italic>, there was no significant difference between the MosqTent white (20.2%) and the HLC (17.6%). For <italic>An</italic>. <italic>nuneztovari</italic>, the MosqTent white collected twice as much as the HLC (MosqTent white: 34.7%; HLC: 15.5%), while the MosqTent black collected the same amount as the HLC (15.5%). The MosqTent collected <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> and <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic> with the same parity proportions as the HLC (<italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>—HLC: 58.3%, MosqTent white: 59.6%, <italic>X</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = 3.55, df = 4, <italic>p</italic> = 0.47; <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>—HLC: 50.4%, MosqTent white: 50.8%, <italic>X</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = 3.03, df = 4, <italic>p</italic> = 0.5).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The high efficiency of the MosqTent is probably due to the high mosquito density presented by <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>. In these conditions, many mosquitoes bite and escape the HLC collector, who is heavily attacked and cannot collect efficiently. Possibly, this is one of the best qualities of the MosqTent. In high mosquito–density conditions, field workers are more prone to get infected in malarigenous areas.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The MosqTent produces high data output by collecting large numbers of human host–seeking mosquitoes in high-density conditions while protecting the human attractant/mosquito collector from being bitten. Besides anthropophily and population density, other dynamic biological and ecological factors might influence the collection efficiency of the MosqTent.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007" sec-type="intro">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Although malaria has decreased dramatically over the last decade, particularly in sub-Saharan Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref001">1</xref>], in Brazil there were approximately 140,000 cases in 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref002">2</xref>], and the highly endemic situation persists in other countries of the Americas and Africa and in the Southeastern Asia, Western Pacific, and Eastern Mediterranean regions, with millions of cases yearly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref003">3</xref>].</p>
<p>Monitoring mosquito vector populations is among the key elements of vector management strategies and assessment of mosquito-borne disease risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref004">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref009">9</xref>].</p>
<p>Adult mosquitoes can usually be sampled by traps, such as the CDC light-trap, the BG-sentinel, and many other models that make use of light, CO<sub>2</sub>, and chemical attractants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref010">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref013">13</xref>] to lure mosquitoes. To transmit parasites and pathogens to humans, mosquitoes must be anthropophilic to some degree. Nonetheless, for highly anthropophilic mosquitoes, none of the existing traps are as effective as the Human Landing Catch (HLC), which uses the human catcher as an attractant. Therefore, HLCs continue to be the gold standard in some areas for vector surveillance of anthropophilic mosquito populations. Because of the importance of the HLC as a surveillance tool, even when using established guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref014">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref015">15</xref>], researchers and fieldwork professionals continue exposing themselves to infective bites of known and unknown pathogens.</p>
<p>In order to attract anthropophilic mosquitoes, while still protecting the human bait from being bitten, we present an innovative mosquito trap, the MosqTent. This trap is a double-chamber portable model for use in entomological research and by entomology surveillance teams. We present results from experiments with Neotropical malaria vectors, comparing trap data from the MosqTent against three alternative sampling tools.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Test site description</title>
<p>The MosqTent, in its final design, was tested in field conditions for anthropophilic anopheline mosquitoes in a malaria-endemic area. The area chosen was in the Northern Brazilian Amazon inside a farm located at the edge of the Ramal da Viúva road, 14 km from Cariobal, Macapá, Amapá Sate, Brazil (00° 08. 023'N, 051° 11. 131 W).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Mosquito trap testing</title>
<p>The new mosquito trap was tested against: a BG-sentinel trap using only CO<sub>2</sub> as an attractant (CO<sub>2</sub> cylinder, BioGents GmbH, Regensburg, Germany), a protected HLC where a human individual used a thick sock on one leg to increase protection from biting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref010">10</xref>], and the traditional HLC as the gold standard. Because black is reported to increase attraction with other traps [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref016">16</xref>], and black also allows better visualization and easier collection of mosquitoes, particularly anophelines at night, we also tested a MosqTent constructed in black nylon and another in white nylon. Five distinct sites, 50 m apart from each other, were chosen for the field trials on a farm in the city of Cariobal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g001">Fig 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pntd.0005245.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Distribution of collection points, 50 m from each other.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Comparisons were carried out in a 5 x 5 Latin square design, testing each of the five sampling methods at five sites, on five consecutive nights, rotating treatments. The Latin square was repeated four times; two collections were performed in August and October 2009, which corresponds to summer, and two more collections were performed in winter, in January and April 2010.</p>
<p>The initial distribution of the collection methods at the five collection sites was random and was rotated clockwise during the five-night consecutive collections so that each trap was tested in each of the five collection sites (at each site only once) at a distance of 50 m from each other distributed around the farm house, where five individuals lived (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pntd.0005245.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Latin square rotation scheme adopted for testing a new mosquito trap design against other collection methods for anthropophilic anophelines in Cariobal, Amapá State, Brazil.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pntd.0005245.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="6"><bold>August 2009 Rotation scheme</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Days</td>
<td align="center">point 1</td>
<td align="center">point 2</td>
<td align="center">point 3</td>
<td align="center">point 4</td>
<td align="center">point 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO<sub>2</sub></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="6"><bold>October 2009 Rotation scheme</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Days</td>
<td align="center">point 1</td>
<td align="center">point 2</td>
<td align="center">point 3</td>
<td align="center">point 4</td>
<td align="center">point 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="6"><bold>January 2010 Rotation scheme</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Days</td>
<td align="center">point 1</td>
<td align="center">point 2</td>
<td align="center">point 3</td>
<td align="center">point 4</td>
<td align="center">point 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="6"><bold>April 2010 Rotation scheme</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Days</td>
<td align="center">point 1</td>
<td align="center">point 2</td>
<td align="center">point 3</td>
<td align="center">point 4</td>
<td align="center">point 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">New trap white</td>
<td align="center">protected HLC</td>
<td align="center">HLC</td>
<td align="center">BGs + CO2</td>
<td align="center">New trap black</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p>Anopheline collections started half an hour before dusk and lasted for 4 h, approximately from 1800h to 2200h. For the MosqTent, the same human individual sitting as attractant inside the inner chamber in the new mosquito trap acted as the collector. After a period of 40 min sitting in the inner chamber of the trap as the attractant, the collector would leave the inner chamber fully dressed (No-see-um mesh bug jackets, pants, and hat [Bioquip, California, USA] and latex gloves) to avoid mosquito biting and captured anophelines from the outer chamber using a tube collector and transferred them to cardboard canisters in the remaining 20 min each hour. This protocol was followed by all five collectors so that yields could be compared.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Mosquito processing</title>
<p>Mosquitoes captured by each collection method were separated into cardboard canisters with nylon covers, identified by type of collection method and time of collection. During identification, mosquitoes collected by the MosqTent were verified if engorged with blood. The canisters were packed in styrofoam boxes containing a moistened cloth or paper towel to maintain humidity and transported to the laboratory for identification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref017">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref018">18</xref>]. A solution of 10% sucrose embedded in a piece of cotton was placed on the canister´s nylon cover. In the laboratory, mosquitoes were identified to species, and the ovaries of at least 10% of the females were dissected and examined for parity (presence of coiled tracheolar skeins) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref019">19</xref>].</p>
<p>Parity was checked for the malaria vectors <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> Root, 1926 and <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic> (Galvão and Damasceno 1942). Parity is an important entomological parameter for the life span of an anopheline species, as the older females indicate a population that has lived long enough to complete the malaria parasite cycle.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>Differences in the number of specimens collected for each mosquito species among the collection methods were modeled using a multilevel Poisson regression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref020">20</xref>], controlled by collection point, month, day, and exposure hour. Collection site and month were treated as independent random effects, whereas we have included time-dependence in the random effects for day and hour, using first-order random walk. The Bayesian approach was used with vague priors, and the posterior marginals were obtained by the integrated nested Laplace approximations approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref021">21</xref>]. Statistical analyses were done in R 3.1.2, using the integrated nested Laplace approximations (INLA) package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref022">22</xref>]. The posterior median and the 95% credible intervals of the capture rates for each trap were estimated and reported. Random effects for precision for the models were adjusted by mosquito species.</p>
<p>Differences in the number of parous females were checked by chi-square tests, adjusting the expected values by the total number of mosquitoes dissected for each collection method. All statistical analyses were carried out for <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>, <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>, and <italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic> (Neiva and Pinto 1922), the three most abundant species in the area, and for the total number of anophelines captured. Statistical analyses were done in R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref022">22</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Mosquito trap design</title>
<p>We have developed a mosquito trap named the MosqTent (patent deposited BR 10 2016 010859 4). MosqTent is a portable, double-chamber individual trap measuring 2m x 2m x 2m (height, length, and width), made in 2mm mesh white nylon, weighing &lt;1 kg. MosqTent can be attached by strings into a gazebo-like tent (weighing &lt;5.5 kg; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005245.s001">S1 Supporting Information</xref>, Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g002">2A, 2B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g003">3A and 3B</xref>) or in tree branches when it is mounted to form a cube.</p>
<fig id="pntd.0005245.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>The MosqTent, a portable, double-chamber individual trap, designed to avoid mosquito biting while collecting anthropophilic mosquitoes for research and surveillance; A-outer chamber closed, B-outer and inner chamber open.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<fig id="pntd.0005245.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Gazebo-like tent that allows the MosqTent to be used in light rainy conditions.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The basic MosqTent design consists of an inner chamber, in which the human attractant sits throughout the sampling period (as traditionally performed for the HLCs), surrounded by an outer chamber, where the mosquitoes are trapped. The gazebo-like tent acts as an impermeable roof for protection from light rain.</p>
<p>Mosquitoes enter the trap through spaces at the bottom of the outer chamber, where the tent material is lifted 10 cm from the ground. They are trapped when they enter the outer chamber. It was observed during the development of the trap that once the mosquitoes entered the outer chamber at ground level, they tended to fly to the top of the walls inside the outer chamber. Because of this observation, a surrounding wing, consisting of a trapezoid cut and a longitudinal row of holes was created in the wall of the outer chamber to increase collection efficiency. This design also makes it difficult for mosquitoes to escape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g004">Fig 4</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pntd.0005245.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>MosqTent parts; A in perspective; B side view: 1: Inner chamber, 2: Outer chamber, 3: Zippers, 4: Floor of the inner chamber, 5: Wing, 6: Holes in the wall of the outer chamber, 7: Space between the wing and the outer wall, 8: Corners, 9: Roof common to the inner and outer chambers, red dotted-lines: Alternative ways for mosquito trapping.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Inside the inner chamber of the MosqTent, a human individual remains seated acting as an attractant. This inner chamber is a cube formed by a floor, a roof, and four walls completely closed by a vertical zipper. The inner chamber is surrounded by the outer chamber, formed by a roof, wings, trapezoid-cut walls, a longitudinal row of holes, and four walls also closed by a vertical zipper. This design avoids the direct biting of anthropophilic mosquitoes on the human individual that sits in the inner chamber. The four corners may have sticks passing inside sheaths built in the material (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g002">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g004">4</xref>) or strings that attach the trap to the gazebo-like tent. Mosquitoes are allowed to enter the trap through spaces located at the bottom of the outer chamber, lifted 10 cm from the ground.</p>
<p>The addition of a commercially available gazebo-like tent (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g003">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g005">5</xref>) allows the MosqTent to be used in low to moderate rain conditions.</p>
<fig id="pntd.0005245.g005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g005</object-id>
<label>Fig 5</label>
<caption>
<title>The MosqTent fully deployed using aluminium sticks inserted into sheaths sewn in the walls´ corners used with a commercially available gazebo-like tent (in blue).</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Ethical considerations</title>
<p>Mosquito collections were carried out under permit #1922008 of the Brazilian Institute for the Environment and Renewable Resources (Instituto Brasileiro do Meio Ambiente e dos Recursos Naturais Renováveis—IBAMA) and verbal authorization of the farm owner. The mosquito collections did not involve endangered or protected species and were not made in environmental-protected areas. The use of the HLC was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of the Institute of Scientific and Technological Research of the State of Amapá—IEPA (Official Letter 007/2008-CEP/IEPA). Anophelines were collected by experienced entomology technicians from IEPA or by the authors themselves. All technicians involved in the anthropophilic anopheline collections provided their written informed consent to participate in this study, were approved by the Research Ethics Committee of the Institute of Scientific and Technological Research of the State of Amapá, Brazil, and are registered in the IBAMA Federal Technical Register (Cadastro Técnico Federal—IBAMA).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Comparison of results for black and white MosqTents, BG Sentinel, and HLC catches</title>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Mosquito yields</title>
<p>During anopheline identification that occurred within 24 h after collection, it was visually verified that none of the mosquitoes collected by the MosqTent were engorged with blood. A total of 22,151 anophelines belonging to five species (including species complexes) that are all malaria vectors were caught over 20 nights for 4 h/night, repeating a 5 x 5 Latin square four times in different months to compare the MosqTent catch with a range of catching methods for sampling the five main species of anthropophilic anopheline species in Amapá, Brazil (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pntd.0005245.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Number of anopheline vectors collected by the MosqTent tested against other anopheline collection methods in Cariobal, Amapá State, Brazil.</title> <p>Highest values are shaded.</p></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pntd.0005245.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Anopheline species/ Collection method</th>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Month and year</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">Species subtotal (%)</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">(Total %)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic></th>
<th align="left">Aug 2009</th>
<th align="left">Oct 2009</th>
<th align="left">Jan 2010</th>
<th align="left">Apr 2010</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">HLC</td>
<td align="left">532</td>
<td align="left">836</td>
<td align="left">313</td>
<td align="left">426</td>
<td align="left">2,107 (15.1)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">protected HLC</td>
<td align="left">501</td>
<td align="left">1318</td>
<td align="left">266</td>
<td align="left">469</td>
<td align="left">2,554 (18.3)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">BG using CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left">569</td>
<td align="left">459</td>
<td align="left">318</td>
<td align="left">340</td>
<td align="left">1,686 (12.1)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">MosqTent white</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">875</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">1,271</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">839</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">1,048</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">4,033 (28.9)</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MosqTent black</td>
<td align="left">858</td>
<td align="left">1093</td>
<td align="left">762</td>
<td align="left">877</td>
<td align="left">3,590 (25.7)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Subtotal (%)</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>3,335</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>4,977</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>2,498</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>3,160</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>13,970</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>(63.1)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">HLC</td>
<td align="left">689</td>
<td align="left">325</td>
<td align="left">120</td>
<td align="left">126</td>
<td align="left">1,260 (25.8)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">protected HLC</td>
<td align="left">495</td>
<td align="left">365</td>
<td align="left">118</td>
<td align="left">205</td>
<td align="left">1,183 (24.3)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">BG using CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">550</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">149</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">398</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">529</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">1,626 (33.4)</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MosqTent white</td>
<td align="left">186</td>
<td align="left">68</td>
<td align="left">97</td>
<td align="left">143</td>
<td align="left">494 (10.1)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MosqTent black</td>
<td align="left">117</td>
<td align="left">43</td>
<td align="left">66</td>
<td align="left">86</td>
<td align="left">312 (6.4)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Subtotal (%)</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>2,037</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>950</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>799</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>1,089</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>4,875</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>(22)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">HLC</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">627</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">64</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">72</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">143</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">906 (35.5)</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">protected HLC</td>
<td align="left">484</td>
<td align="left">125</td>
<td align="left">65</td>
<td align="left">110</td>
<td align="left">784 (30.7)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">BG using CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left">119</td>
<td align="left">12</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
<td align="left">31</td>
<td align="left">162 (6.3)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MosqTent white</td>
<td align="left">199</td>
<td align="left">46</td>
<td align="left">34</td>
<td align="left">41</td>
<td align="left">320 (12.5)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MosqTent black</td>
<td align="left">233</td>
<td align="left">47</td>
<td align="left">22</td>
<td align="left">78</td>
<td align="left">380 (14.9)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Subtotal (%)</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>1,662</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>294</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>193</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>403</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>2,552</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>(11.5)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>braziliensis</italic></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">HLC</td>
<td align="left">34</td>
<td align="left">46</td>
<td align="left">4</td>
<td align="left">2</td>
<td align="left">86 (17.6)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">protected HLC</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">37</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">90</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">6</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">0</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">133 (27.2)</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">BG using CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left">37</td>
<td align="left">2</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
<td align="left">39 (8)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MosqTent white</td>
<td align="left">45</td>
<td align="left">29</td>
<td align="left">13</td>
<td align="left">12</td>
<td align="left">99 (20.2)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">MosqTent black</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">39</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">68</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">12</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">13</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">132 (27.0)</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Subtotal (%)</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>192</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>235</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>35</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>27</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>489</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>(2.2)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>nuneztovari</italic></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">HLC</td>
<td align="left">9</td>
<td align="left">10</td>
<td align="left">20</td>
<td align="left">2</td>
<td align="left">41 (15.5)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">protected HLC</td>
<td align="left">15</td>
<td align="left">15</td>
<td align="left">8</td>
<td align="left">9</td>
<td align="left">47 (17.7)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">BG using CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left">5</td>
<td align="left">1</td>
<td align="left">28</td>
<td align="left">10</td>
<td align="left">44 (16.6)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">MosqTent white</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">19</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">7</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">55</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">11</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">92 (34.7)</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MosqTent black</td>
<td align="left">15</td>
<td align="left">7</td>
<td align="left">14</td>
<td align="left">5</td>
<td align="left">41 (15.5)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Subtotal (%)</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>63</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>40</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>125</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>37</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>265</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>(1.2)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>TOTAL (%)</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>14,578</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>12,992</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>7,300</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>9,432</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>22,151</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>(100)</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p>Cariobal is a malaria-endemic area where the most prevalent anopheline species is the highly anthropophilic <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>, with 63.1% of the total mosquitoes collected (or 13,970 specimens, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<p>In absolute numbers, the MosqTent collected <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>, <italic>An</italic>. <italic>braziliensis</italic> Chagas, 1907, and <italic>An</italic>. <italic>nuneztovari</italic> Gabaldón, 1940, catching approximately 30% of the specimens for these three species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). For the anthropophilic <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>, considered the main malaria vector in Brazil, the collection methods with highest yields were the HLC and the protected HLC (36% and 30%, respectively, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). As expected from previous studies, BG-sentinel traps using CO<sub>2</sub> as an attractant performed poorly for <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>. The white and black MosqTents yielded half of the HLC and protected HLC yields for <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<p>Nonetheless, estimates of the posterior median and the 95% credible intervals of the collection rates for each collection method, controlling per collection point, month, day, and collection period showed that the HLC most efficiently collected <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> and that the MosqTents (white and black) were the most efficient in collecting <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic> compared to the other trapping methods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g006">Fig 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t003">Table 3</xref>). On the other hand, the BG Sentinel was more efficient in collecting <italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic> than the other methods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g006">Fig 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pntd.0005245.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Posterior median (95% credible interval) of the expected number of mosquitoes per hour by collection method and anopheline species (<italic>An darlingi</italic>, <italic>An marajoara</italic>, <italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic>, and total anophelines) in Cariobal, Macapá, Amapá State, Brazilian Amazon.</title> <p>Highest values are shaded.</p></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pntd.0005245.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Collection method</th>
<th align="left"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic></th>
<th align="left"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic></th>
<th align="left"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic></th>
<th align="left">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">HLC</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">7.1 (6.6, 7.7)</td>
<td align="left">24.3 (23.2, 25.4)</td>
<td align="left">12.9 (12.2, 13.7)</td>
<td align="left">51.0 (49.5, 52.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">BG</td>
<td align="left">1.2 (1.0, 1.4)</td>
<td align="left">19.5 (18.6, 20.5)</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">16.3 (15.4, 17.2)</td>
<td align="left">40.9 (39.6, 42.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MosqTent black</td>
<td align="left">2.8 (2.5, 3.1)</td>
<td align="left">41.2 (39.8, 42.6)</td>
<td align="left">3.1 (2.8, 3.5)</td>
<td align="left">50.5 (49.0, 52.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MosqTent white</td>
<td align="left">2.3 (2.0, 2.6)</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">46.5 (45.1, 48.0)</td>
<td align="left">5.1 (4.7, 5.6)</td>
<td align="left" style="background-color:#EEECE1">57.7 (56.1, 59.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Protected HLC</td>
<td align="left">5.8 (5.3, 6.3)</td>
<td align="left">29.3 (28.2, 30.5)</td>
<td align="left">12.5 (11.8, 13.3)</td>
<td align="left">53.9 (52.3, 55.5)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="pntd.0005245.g006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g006</object-id>
<label>Fig 6</label>
<caption>
<title>Posterior median (95% credible interval) of the expected number of mosquitoes per hour (<italic>x</italic>-axis) for <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>, <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>, <italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic>, and total anophelines per collection method (protected HLC, MosqTent white and black, HLC, and BG-sentinel traps).</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>For all mosquito species, the collection method is the most important effect in order to explain the variability of mosquito capture rates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t004">Table 4</xref>). Data suggests that for <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>, the month of collection also played an important role (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t004">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g007">Fig 7</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pntd.0005245.g007" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g007</object-id>
<label>Fig 7</label>
<caption>
<title>Random effects for the multilevel poisson model for the number of <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>, <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>, <italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic>, and total anophelines collected by method, controlled by month, collection point, day, and time.</title>
<p>Each random effect is the contribution to the logarithm of the expected number of mosquitoes. The further from zero (<italic>y</italic>-axis), the greater the effect of the variable in the mosquito yield.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="pntd.0005245.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>Posterior mean of the precision parameter for the random effects of collection method, month, collection point, day, and time (hour of the day) for <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>, <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>, <italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic>, and total anophelines in Cariobal, Macapá, Amapá State, Brazilian Amazon.</title> <p>The lower the precision the more important is the effect to explain data variability (shaded).</p></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pntd.0005245.t004g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center">Precision</th>
<th align="center"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic></th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Collection method</td>
<td align="char" char="." style="background-color:#EEECE1">0.80</td>
<td align="char" char="." style="background-color:#EEECE1">0.12</td>
<td align="char" char="." style="background-color:#EEECE1">0.28</td>
<td align="char" char="." style="background-color:#EEECE1">0.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Month</td>
<td align="char" char=".">1.88</td>
<td align="char" char=".">21.41</td>
<td align="char" char=".">10.00</td>
<td align="char" char=".">17.88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Collection point</td>
<td align="char" char=".">5.22</td>
<td align="char" char=".">54.22</td>
<td align="char" char=".">34.59</td>
<td align="char" char=".">65.83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Day</td>
<td align="char" char=".">11.29</td>
<td align="char" char=".">12.53</td>
<td align="char" char=".">5.21</td>
<td align="char" char=".">11.89</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Time</td>
<td align="char" char=".">17.14</td>
<td align="char" char=".">17.63</td>
<td align="char" char=".">5.92</td>
<td align="char" char=".">16.72</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p>Estimated controlled random effects show that month and hour of collection seem more relevant for the three species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g007">Fig 7</xref>). <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> and <italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic> were likely to be observed mostly in August, while <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic> was likely to be observed in October. All the species were observed mainly at dusk, starting from 1800h until 2000h, while <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> was seen later, at 2100h–2200h.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Parity</title>
<p>A total of 1,385 <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> and 5,618 <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic> females had their ovaries dissected to determine parity status. No differences in the abundance of parous mosquitoes among traps was observed between <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> (<italic>X</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = 3.55, df = 4, <italic>p</italic> = 0.47, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t005">Table 5</xref>) and <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic> (<italic>X</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = 3.03, df = 4, <italic>p</italic> = 0.55, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t005">Table 5</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pntd.0005245.t005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.t005</object-id>
<label>Table 5</label> <caption><title>Number of parous <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> and <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic> females collected in the MosqTent against other collection methods in Cariobal, Macapá, Amapá State, the Brazilian Amazon.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pntd.0005245.t005g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Type of Trap/Anopheline</th>
<th align="center">Human landing catch</th>
<th align="center">Protected human landing catch</th>
<th align="center">BG-sentinel + CO2</th>
<th align="center">MosqTent white</th>
<th align="center">MosqTent black</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> Parous</td>
<td align="center">263</td>
<td align="center">248</td>
<td align="center">44</td>
<td align="center">112</td>
<td align="center">151</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> (%)</td>
<td align="center" style="background-color:#F2F2F2">(58.3)</td>
<td align="center">(58.4)</td>
<td align="center">(48.4)</td>
<td align="center" style="background-color:#F2F2F2">(59.6)</td>
<td align="center">(65.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>Total</bold></td>
<td align="center"><bold>451</bold></td>
<td align="center"><bold>425</bold></td>
<td align="center"><bold>91</bold></td>
<td align="center"><bold>188</bold></td>
<td align="center"><bold>230</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> Parous</td>
<td align="center">488</td>
<td align="center">544</td>
<td align="center">416</td>
<td align="center">694</td>
<td align="center">706</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> (%)</td>
<td align="center" style="background-color:#F2F2F2">(50.4)</td>
<td align="center">(53.9)</td>
<td align="center">(49.3)</td>
<td align="center" style="background-color:#F2F2F2">(50.8)</td>
<td align="center">(49.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>Total</bold></td>
<td align="center"><bold>969</bold></td>
<td align="center"><bold>1,008</bold></td>
<td align="center"><bold>844</bold></td>
<td align="center"><bold>1,365</bold></td>
<td align="center"><bold>1,432</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In an ever-changing environment in which mosquito vector species distributions vary continuously, due not only to distinct regional differences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref023">23</xref>] but also due to ecological changes and adaptation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref024">24</xref>], mosquito vector collections are routinely needed. All traps from the least-demanding anthropophilic mosquito collection methods, such as, CDC light traps, BG Sentinel, and Mosquito Magnet traps, to more labor-intensive methods, such as Shannon-type tents, use human-produced molecules, from simple to complex, to mimic human attraction and, hence, mosquito yields [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref004">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref005">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref006">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref007">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref010">10</xref>].</p>
<p>For anthropophilic mosquitoes, there has been no better and more productive way of collection than the use of a human individual as an attractant as in the HLC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref025">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref028">28</xref>]. The use of the HLC as a gold standard for the assessment of anthropophilic mosquitoes will continue to be used until a trap that can lure and collect as many mosquitoes as efficiently as the HLC is available.</p>
<p>The MosqTent was field tested in an area with highly anthropophilic malaria vectors in the Brazilian Amazon against other collection methods that were previously tested as yielding high numbers of Brazilian malaria vectors, (BG-sentinel + CO<sub>2</sub> and protected HLC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref010">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref016">16</xref>]. During MosqTent testing, the clockwise rotation may have led to neighboring effect since this rotation did not follow a complete randomized collection point change. Nevertheless, this effect might have been reduced by the 50 m distance guarded among collection methods. The HLC and the protected HLC had statistically similar yields.</p>
<p>Parity is a proxy to mosquito age and gonotrophic cycle and, therefore, a major entomological parameter in the epidemiology of mosquito vector–borne diseases. A suitable mosquito sampling method should provide an accurate figure of this parameter. The MosqTent collected the two most important malaria vectors in the area, <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> and <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>, with the same parity proportions as the HLC (58.3% for HLC and 59.6% for MosqTent white for <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>, and 50.4% for HLC and 50.8% for MosqTent white for <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t005">Table 5</xref>). The same species caught by HLC were also collected by the MosqTent (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). Regarding yield, for <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>, nearly twice as many specimens were caught by both tent traps than the HLC (25.7% MosqTent white and 28.9% MosqTent black compared to 15.1% for HLC, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic> is an anthropophilic species belonging to the Albitarsis complex. In Cariobal, <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic> was present in high density (63% or 13,970 specimens out of the total of 22,151 specimens, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). The high efficiency of the MosqTent is probably due to the high number of <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic> specimens. In high mosquito–density conditions, during the HLC collection, many mosquitoes bite and escape since the collector is heavily attacked and cannot collect efficiently. On a previous occasion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref029">29</xref>], the MosqTent was able to collect an average of 3,000 anophelines/man-hour compared to only 240 anophelines/man-hour for the HLC (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). In these high mosquito–density conditions, field workers are more prone to get infected in endemic malaria areas. Possibly, this is one of the best qualities of the MosqTent, i.e., the collection of a high number of specimens of anthropophilic mosquito species in high-density conditions. For <italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic>, BG was as good as HLC, and tent traps were much lower (33.4% BG when compared to 10.1% MosqTent white and 6.4% MosqTent black, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). All <italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic> species members of the Triannulatus complex are considered zoophilic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref030">30</xref>]. Thus, the low efficiency in collecting <italic>An</italic>. <italic>triannulatus</italic> might be due to the human collector present in the inner chamber of the MosqTent, which better attracts anthropophilic mosquito species. For <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> in Cariobal, both tent traps caught half the amount of the HLC (14.9% for MosqTent black and 12.5% for MosqTent white while HLC collected 35.5%, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). Conceivably, the MosqTent may have a minimum threshold to efficiently collect. <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> in Cariobal was present in low density (2,552 specimens or 11.5% out of the 22,151 total specimens, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). In this condition, when an anthropophilic mosquito species is present in low density, the MosqTent might not be able to determine which species are present as accurately as the HLC. For <italic>An</italic>. <italic>braziliensis</italic>, there was no significant difference between the MosqTent white (20.2%) and the HLC (17.6%, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). <italic>An</italic>. <italic>braziliensis</italic> was present in very low density in Cariobal, even less than <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> (489 specimens or 2.2% out of the 22,151 total specimens, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). Nonetheless, contrary to the anthropophilic <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>, also present in low density, the zoophilic <italic>An</italic>. <italic>braziliensis</italic> could be efficiently collected by the MosqTent white for reasons that cannot be explored by the current experiment design. Interestingly, <italic>An</italic>. <italic>braziliensis</italic> was caught in significantly high numbers in the protected HLC (27.2%) when the collector uses a thick black sock (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g001">Fig 1</xref>) and in the MosqTent black (27%, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). Maybe for <italic>An</italic>. <italic>braziliensis</italic> the black color acts as an additional attractant. For <italic>An</italic>. <italic>nuneztovari</italic>, the MosqTent white collected twice as much as the HLC (34.7% MosqTent white and 15.5% for HLC, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>), while the MosqTent black collected the same proportions as the HLC (15.5%, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). <italic>An</italic>. <italic>nuneztovari</italic> is a complex of cryptic species and was the species with the lowest density in Cariobal (265 specimens or 1.2% out of the 22,151 total specimens, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005245.t002">Table 2</xref>). The efficiency in <italic>An</italic>. <italic>nuneztovari</italic> collection by the MosqTent white might indicate that an anthropophilic member of the complex is present in Cariobal. Besides anthropophily and population density, other dynamic biological and ecological factors might influence the collection efficiency of the MosqTent.</p>
<p>The main innovation characteristics of the MosqTent are its design (side wings that increase the collection efficiency) and portability (~1 kg bag that opens up in a full trap in less than 2 min, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005245.s001">S1 Supporting information</xref>) when compared to other double-chamber mosquito traps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g008">Fig 8</xref>). The side wings were added after the observation that when mosquitoes come avid to feed, they encounter the outer net wall. The mosquitoes then start hopping towards the upper side of the wall and are conducted by the wings to the outer chamber from where they try to pass through the second net wall, but, failing to bite, they also cannot leave the outer chamber (red dotted lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005245.g004">Fig 4B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pntd.0005245.g008" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g008</object-id>
<label>Fig 8</label>
<caption>
<title>Simplified schemes of traps aiming to collect anthropophilic mosquitoes to show differences in their designs: Shannon (single chamber) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref031">31</xref>], Mbita [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref032">32</xref>], Ifakara [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref033">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref034">34</xref>], Tent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref035">35</xref>], Malaise (Townes style) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref035">35</xref>], Infoscitex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref036">36</xref>], Human Double Net-HDN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0005245.ref037">37</xref>], and MosqTent (this paper).</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.g008" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Given the promising data that has resulted from our studies, the MosqTent’s efficiency should be tested in a range of other contexts in which medically important mosquitoes are not easily captured using the prevailing trapping techniques, and for a variety of other important mosquito vector species, whenever adult collection is required.</p>
<p>Further developments may include testing for other fabric colors, different mesh sizes and dimensions for other hematophagous insects and conditions, additional chemical mosquito attractants, and even the replacement of the human attractant for other attractants. MosqTent modifications that would allow the trap to be applied as a vector control tool with killing action could also be explored.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The MosqTent is a newly developed, protective, double-chamber, portable, individual mosquito trap for anthropophilic mosquitoes that protects the collector from mosquito biting since the collector sits inside an inner chamber netted compartment. The same individual can serve as an attractant (in the inner chamber) and leave the inner chamber well dressed and protected to collect the mosquitoes trapped in the outer chamber after the luring period. The MosqTent aims to be used for research and entomological surveillance by field personnel. The MosqTent collected more mosquitoes than the HLC in high mosquito–density conditions. The MosqTent performed well by collecting a high number of specimens of <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajoara</italic>, a local vector and anthropophilic mosquito species present in high density, but not so well in collecting <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic>, an anthropophilic mosquito species considered the main vector in Brazil but present in low-density conditions in the area. The HLC showed a higher efficiency in collecting <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> in these low-density conditions. The MosqTent was able to catch comparable portions of parous females for both <italic>An</italic>. <italic>darlingi</italic> and <italic>An</italic>. <italic>marajora</italic> as the HLC. The results encourage further development and the use of this mosquito trap for anthropophilic vectors elsewhere.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec021">
<title>Supporting information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pntd.0005245.s001" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005245.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Supporting Information</label>
<caption>
<title>Setting up of a MosqTent.</title>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We extend our thanks to Cynara de Melo Rodovalho and Ademir de Jesus Martins for help with the text, to Hooman Momen for invaluable comments, to Celeste Emerick, Adriana Britto, Christoph Milewski, and the innovation management team at Coordenação de Gestão Tecnológica-GESTEC-FIOCRUZ for their assistance with the patent deposit. Thanks also to the technical group of Instituto de Pesquisas Científicas e Tecnológicas do Estado do Amapá-IEPA for help in collecting material in the field.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Word Health Organization 2016. Malaria Fact Sheet: World Malaria Report 2015. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/malaria/media/world-malaria-report-2015/en/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.who.int/malaria/media/world-malaria-report-2015/en/</ext-link> Accessed 12 December 2016</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Brazil Ministry of Health 2016. Secretaria de Vigilância em Saúde. Sistema de Informação de Vigilância Epidemiológica-SIVEP-Malária. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dw.saude.gov.br/gsid/servlet/mstrWeb?evt=2048001&amp;hiddensections=header%2Cpath%2CdockTop%2CdockLeft%2Cfooter&amp;documentID=AC2B0F5041CEEC8C671FA39D5337A697&amp;Server=srvbipdf03&amp;Project=DMMalaria&amp;" xlink:type="simple">http://dw.saude.gov.br/gsid/servlet/mstrWeb?evt=2048001&amp;hiddensections=header%2Cpath%2CdockTop%2CdockLeft%2Cfooter&amp;documentID=AC2B0F5041CEEC8C671FA39D5337A697&amp;Server=srvbipdf03&amp;Project=DMMalaria&amp;</ext-link> Accessed 30 May 2016</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization 2016. World Malaria Report 2015 Summary. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/205224/1/WHO_HTM_GMP_2016.2_eng.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/205224/1/WHO_HTM_GMP_2016.2_eng.pdf</ext-link> Accessed 30 May 2016</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beier</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keating</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Githure</surname> <given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macdonald</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Impoinvil</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name> <etal>et al</etal>.: <article-title>Integrated vector management for malaria control</article-title>. <source>Malar J</source> <year>2008</year>, <volume>7</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>S4</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubio-Palis</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guzman</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magris</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>: <article-title>Evaluación de trampas de luz vs cebo humano para capturer Anopheles darlingi</article-title>. <source>Root Bol Dir Malariol San Amb</source> <year>1999</year>, <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubio-Palis</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Estrada</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anaya</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bevilacqua</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cárdenas</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medina</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>: <article-title>Can Mosquito Magnet<sup>®</sup> substitute for human-landing catches to sample anopheline populations?</article-title> <source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source> <year>2012</year>, <volume>107</volume>:<fpage>546</fpage>–<lpage>549</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22666868</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">WHO: Development of a global action plan for integrated vector management (IVM). Report of a WHO Consultation (WHO/HTM/NTD/VEM/2009.1) Geneva; 2009.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>WHO</collab>: <source>Global strategic framework for integrated vector management</source>. (WHO/CDS/CPE/PVC /2004.10) <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>; <year>2004</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>WHO</collab>: <source>Guidance on policy-making for integrated vector management</source>. (WHO/HTM/NTD/VEM /2012.2) <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>; <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname> <given-names>JBP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosa-Freitas</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name>,<name name-style="western"><surname>Rodovalho</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lourenço-de-Oliveira</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> <year>2014</year>. <article-title>Is there an efficient trap or collection method for sampling Anopheles darlingi and other malaria vectors that can describe the essential parameters affecting transmission dynamics as effectively as human landing catches?—A Review</article-title>. <source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source>, <volume>109</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>705</lpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/0074-0276140134" xlink:type="simple">10.1590/0074-0276140134</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25185008</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiwat</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andriessen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Rijk</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koenraadt</surname> <given-names>CJM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takken</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>: <article-title>Carbon dioxide baited trap catches do not correlate with human landing collections of Anopheles aquasalis in Suriname</article-title>. <source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source> <year>2011</year>, <volume>106</volume>:<fpage>360</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21655826</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubio-Palis</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname> <given-names>CF</given-names></name>: <article-title>Evaluation of different methods of catching anopheline mosquitoes in western Venezuela</article-title>. <source>J Amer Mosq Control Assoc</source> <year>1992</year>, <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>WHO</collab>: <chapter-title>Manual de entomologia prática aplicada à malaria, Pt. II, 1975</chapter-title>. <collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <source>International Ethical Guidelines for Epidemiological Studies. Biomedical Research</source> <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>; <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Achee</surname> <given-names>N. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Youngblood</surname> <given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bangs</surname> <given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lavery</surname> <given-names>J. V.</given-names></name>, &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname> <given-names>S.</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Considerations for the Use of Human Participants in Vector Biology Research: A Tool for Investigators and Regulators</article-title>. <source>Vector Borne and Zoonotic Diseases</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1089/vbz.2014.1628" xlink:type="simple">http://doi.org/10.1089/vbz.2014.1628</ext-link> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/vbz.2014.1628" xlink:type="simple">10.1089/vbz.2014.1628</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25700039</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gama</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname> <given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geier</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eiras</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name>. <year>2013</year>. <article-title>Development of the BG-Malaria trap as an alternative to human-landing catches for the capture of Anopheles darlingi</article-title>. <source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source>. 2013 <month>Sep</month>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>763</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/0074-0276108062013013" xlink:type="simple">10.1590/0074-0276108062013013</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24037199</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faran</surname> <given-names>M E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linthicum</surname> <given-names>K J</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>A handbook of the Amazonian species of Anopheles (Nyssorhynchus) (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title>. <source>Mosquito Sys</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Consoli</surname> <given-names>RAG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lourenço-de-Oliveira</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>. <year>1994</year>. <source>Principais mosquitos de importância sanitária no Brasil</source>. <publisher-name>Editora Fiocruz</publisher-name>. <fpage>225</fpage> pp</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Detinova</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Age-grouping methods in Diptera of medical importance with special reference to some vectors of malaria</chapter-title>. <source>Mon Ser</source> <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name> <year>1962</year>;<fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelman</surname> <given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname> <given-names>J.</given-names></name>. <source>Data analysis using regression and multilevel/hierarchical models</source>, <publisher-name>Cambridge University press</publisher-name>. <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rue</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martino</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chopin</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Approximate bayesian inference for latent gaussian models by using integrated nested laplace approximations</article-title>. <source>J Royal Stat Soc: Series B (Statistical Methodology)</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>R Core Team</collab> (<year>2014</year>). <source>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</source>. <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>. URL <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmerman</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lounibos</surname> <given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishimura</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galardo</surname> <given-names>AKR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galardo</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mercia Arruda</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>: <article-title>Nightly biting cycles of malaria vectors in a heterogeneous transmission area of eastern Amazonian Brazil</article-title>. <source>Malar J</source> <year>2013</year>, <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>262</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1475-2875-12-262" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1475-2875-12-262</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23890413</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiwat</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bretas</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>: <article-title>Ecology of Anopheles darlingi with respect to vector importance: a review</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source> <year>2011</year>, <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1756-3305-4-177" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1756-3305-4-177</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21923902</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Service</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name>: <article-title>A critical review of procedures for sampling populations of adult mosquitoes</article-title>. <source>Bull Entomol Res</source> <year>1977</year>, <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Goff</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carnevale</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fondjo</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparison of three sampling methods of man-biting anophelines in order to estimate the malaria transmission in a village of south Cameroon</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source>. <year>1997</year>; <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1051/parasite/1997041075" xlink:type="simple">10.1051/parasite/1997041075</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9208033</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seng</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matusop</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sen</surname> <given-names>FK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Differences in Anopheles composition and malaria transmission in the village settlements and cultivated farming zone in Sarawak, Malaysia</article-title>. <source>SE Asian J Trop Med</source> <year>1999</year> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>454</fpage>–<lpage>459</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Govella</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaki</surname> <given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mpangile</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Killeen</surname> <given-names>GF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Monitoring mosquitoes in urban Dares Salaam: evaluation of resting boxes, window exit traps, CDC light traps, Ifakara tent traps and human landing catches</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1756-3305-4-40" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1756-3305-4-40</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21418622</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname> <given-names>JBP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosa-Freitas</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name>,<name name-style="western"><surname>Rodovalho</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lourenço-de-Oliveira</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> <year>2014</year>. <article-title>Is there an efficient trap or collection method for sampling Anopheles darlingi and other malaria vectors that can describe the essential parameters affecting transmission dynamics as effectively as human landing catches?—A Review</article-title>. <source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source>, <volume>109</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>705</lpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/0074-0276140134" xlink:type="simple">10.1590/0074-0276140134</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25185008</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva-do-Nascimento</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pitaluga</surname> <given-names>LDR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peixoto</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Lourenço-de-Oliveira</surname> <given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Molecular divergence in the timeless and cpr genes among three sympatric cryptic species of the Anopheles triannulatus complex</article-title>. <source>Memórias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz</source>, <volume>106</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>), <fpage>218</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S0074-02762011000900027" xlink:type="simple">https://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S0074-02762011000900027</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shannon</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> <year>1939</year>. <article-title>Methods for collecting and feeding mosquitoes in jungle yellow fever</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mathenge EM, Killeen GF, Oulo DO, Irungu LW, Ndegwa PN, Knols BG. 2002.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><article-title>Development of an exposure-free bednet trap for sampling Afrotropical malaria vectors</article-title>. <source>Med Vet Entomol</source>. <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11963983</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Govella</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaki</surname> <given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geissbuhler</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kannady</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okumu</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charlwood</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Killeen</surname> <given-names>GF</given-names></name>. <article-title>A new tent trap for sampling exophagic and endophagic members of the Anopheles gambiae complex</article-title>. <source>Malar J</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1475-2875-8-157" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1475-2875-8-157</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19602253</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Govella</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Killeen</surname> <given-names>GF</given-names></name>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>An exposure-free tool for monitoring adult malaria mosquito populations</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source> <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>596</fpage>–<lpage>600</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4269/ajtmh.2010.09-0682" xlink:type="simple">10.4269/ajtmh.2010.09-0682</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20810826</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoops</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gionar</surname> <given-names>YR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rusmiarto</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Susapto</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andris</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elyazar</surname> <given-names>IR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barbara</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Munif</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <year>2010</year>.<article-title>Laboratory and field testing of bednet traps for mosquito (Diptera: Culicidae) sampling in West Java, Indonesia</article-title>. <source>Vector Ecol</source>. <volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krajacich</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slade</surname> <given-names>Jeremiah R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulligan</surname> <given-names>Robert T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labrecque</surname> <given-names>Brendan</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kobylinski</surname> <given-names>Kevin C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname> <given-names>Meg</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuklinski</surname> <given-names>Wojtek S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burton</surname> <given-names>Timothy A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seaman</surname> <given-names>Jonathan A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sylla</surname> <given-names>Massamba</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Foy</surname> <given-names>Brian D.</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Design and Testing of a Novel, Protective Human-Baited Tent Trap for the Collection of Anthropophilic Disease Vectors</article-title>. <source>J Med Entomol</source>, <volume>51</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24605476</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pntd.0005245.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tangena</surname> <given-names>J-AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thammavong</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiscox</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindsay</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brey</surname> <given-names>PT</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The Human-Baited Double Net Trap: An Alternative to Human Landing Catches for Collecting Outdoor Biting Mosquitoes in Lao PDR</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>e0138735</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0138735" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0138735</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26381896</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>