<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PLoS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Med</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosmed</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1549-1676</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PMEDICINE-D-14-02305</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001711</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Observational Studies: Getting Clear about Transparency</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">The <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> Editors</collab><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">medicine_editors@plos.org</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors' individual competing interests are at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plosmedicine.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.plosmedicine.org/</ext-link>static/editorsInterests.action. PLOS is funded partly through manuscript publication charges, but the <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> Editors are paid a fixed salary (their salaries are not linked to the number of papers published in the journal).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Wrote the first draft of the manuscript: LP. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: LP LC RM AR PS MW TM. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icmje.org/" xlink:type="simple">ICMJE</ext-link> criteria for authorship read and met: LP LC RM AR PS MW TM. Agree with manuscript results and conclusions: LP LC RM AR PS MW TM.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e1001711</elocation-id><permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The PLOS Medicine Editors</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="toc"><sec>
<title/>
<p>The <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> Editors endorse four measures to ensure transparency in the analysis and reporting of observational studies.</p>
<p><italic>Please see later in the article for the Editors' Summary</italic></p>
</sec></abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>The authors are each paid a salary by the Public Library of Science, and they wrote this editorial during their salaried time.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="3"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Extending the Standard</title>
<p>When publishing observational research, what information should journals make available to the medical community before a result can be considered sufficiently reliable to inform patient care or health policy?</p>
<p>For clinical trials, editors and researchers share the context of a reporting standard (CONSORT and its modifications <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-Equator1">[1]</xref>), a requirement for prospective, public registration of clinical trials <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-International1">[2]</xref>, and a number of laws (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-ClinicalTrialsgov1">[3]</xref>) and policies requiring data sharing. This combination supports transparency in the design, conduct, and reporting of clinical trials, and has proven sufficiently flexible to allow editors to define appropriate exceptions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-Virginia1">[4]</xref>). Systematic reviews and meta-analyses, which often present a basis for clinical decisions, are also subject to strict reporting guidelines <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-PRISMA1">[5]</xref>. Public registration is available for such studies, and <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> has long encouraged publication of the review protocol alongside the study report <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-The1">[6]</xref>.</p>
<p>Should a similar framework apply to observational studies? In a Guidance and Guidelines article published recently in <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic>, Peat and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-Peat1">[7]</xref> identify study registration, protocol publication, better study reporting, and data sharing as key to improving the transparency of prognosis research, which encompasses both observational and interventional studies. Case-control, cohort, and cross-sectional studies, even when given ethics review, are not subject to all of the regulations that facilitate standardized reporting of clinical trials. Nonetheless, when observational studies provide the best evidence available, they influence clinical practice. Selective presentation of analyses or non-publication of results can therefore misinform patient care. As the authors of the STROBE guidelines for reporting observational studies have noted, “Research should be reported transparently so that readers can follow what was planned, what was done, what was found, and what conclusions were drawn” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-vonElm1">[8]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>New Guidelines for Observational Studies in <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic></title>
<p>The <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> editors, in recent consultation with our editorial board, endorse measures in four areas to advance transparency in the analysis and reporting of observational studies.</p>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Quality of Study Reporting</title>
<p><italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> already requires CONSORT checklists for the clinical trials that we consider, and our current author guidelines encourage authors to report observational studies according to the STROBE statement or its more specialized derivatives <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-vonElm1">[8]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-Vandenbroucke1">[9]</xref>. Additionally, we endorse the following measure:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p><bold>(1) Going forward </bold><bold><italic>PLOS Medicine</italic></bold><bold> will require that the STROBE checklist for cohort, case-control or cross-sectional studies </bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-STROBE1">[<bold>10</bold>]</xref><bold>, and the STARD checklist for studies of diagnostic accuracy </bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-Equator2">[<bold>11</bold>]</xref><bold> are included with manuscript submissions and published alongside reports of observational studies to which they apply. Authors must complete the appropriate reporting checklist not only with page references, but also with sufficient text excerpted from the manuscript to explain how they accomplished all applicable items.</bold></p>
</disp-quote>
<p>(Note: The EQUATOR Network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org" xlink:type="simple">www.equator-network.org</ext-link>) provides access to reporting guidelines for additional specific study types, and authors within the particular research communities to which they apply are encouraged to use these guidelines when appropriate.)</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Data Sharing</title>
<p>The PLOS data policy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-PLOS1">[12]</xref> lays out requirements for data sharing in research manuscripts submitted after March 1, 2014. Therefore,</p>
<disp-quote>
<p><bold>(2) The PLOS Data Policy applies to all research submitted to </bold><bold><italic>PLOS Medicine</italic></bold><bold>, including observational studies.</bold></p>
</disp-quote></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Transparency Regarding What Was Planned and What Was Done</title>
<p>Research reports should make clear the distinction between hypothesis testing and exploratory evaluation of research questions, each of which may have validity, and both of which may occur in the same manuscript. Consequently,</p>
<disp-quote>
<p><bold>(3) Going forward, </bold><bold><italic>PLOS Medicine</italic></bold><bold> will require that reports of observational studies clearly specify the following items:</bold><list list-type="simple"><list-item>
<p><bold>(a) What specific hypotheses the researchers intended to test, and the analytical methods by which they planned to test them;</bold></p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>(b)  What analyses they actually performed; and</bold></p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>(c) When reported analyses differ from those that were planned, authors must provide transparent explanations for differences that affect the reliability of the study's results.</bold></p>
</list-item></list>             </p>
</disp-quote>
<p>For example, if a reported analysis was performed based on an interesting but unanticipated pattern in the data, authors must be clear that the analysis was data-driven. If hypotheses that were not included in the original study design later became important to test because new evidence became available from other studies, the authors should explain the situation, so that reviewers and readers need not wonder if the additional analyses were driven post-hoc by the authors' own data.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Protocol Publication</title>
<p><italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> already requires that study protocols be submitted with reports of clinical trials, and publishes these alongside the accepted paper. Accordingly, for observational studies,</p>
<disp-quote>
<p><bold>(4) Going forward, if a prospective analysis plan (from the study's funding proposal, IRB or other ethics committee submission, study protocol, or other planning document written before analyzing the data) was used in designing an observational study, authors must include the relevant prospectively written document with the manuscript submission for access by editors and reviewers and eventual publication alongside the accepted paper.</bold></p>
</disp-quote>
<p>As with studies of any design, in some cases the final analysis of an observational study will necessarily differ from the analysis plan (as a result of unforeseen practical circumstances, changes requested by peer reviewers, etc.). Under such conditions, authors should explain why analyses could not be completed as planned, or why they had to be revised, and thereby address potential concerns over selective non-publication. If no prospectively written document exists, authors should explain how and when they determined the analyses being reported.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Looking Forward: Registration?</title>
<p>Editors cannot anticipate, nor would we desire to create rules for, every possible situation. Ultimately readers must judge the reliability of a study relative to their own needs and criteria.</p>
<p>We believe that promoting transparency by publishing prospective analysis plans and accounting clearly for substantial changes will help readers (including editors and peer reviewers) to assess the reliability of published observational research. Our goal is not only to establish these practices for <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> but to advocate for such transparency as a standard within the research community.</p>
<p>We also recognize that no practice that applies only to published reports can guard against bias due to selective non-publication of observational studies, an issue that the open question of prospective protocol registration could potentially address <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-Sox1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-Williams1">[16]</xref>. ClinicalTrials.gov, among other registries, already allows registration of observational studies, and, as technologies allowing the “flexibility to update date-stamped protocols” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-vonElm1">[8]</xref> become more widely available, it seems likely that community standards for registration will move toward the greater transparency that such tools facilitate. At the same time, new evidence published by Dwan and colleagues in a recent issue of <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> indicate that, in the case of clinical trials, substantial discrepancies exist between registered and reported analyses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-Dwan1">[17]</xref>. This result suggests that prospective registration alone, should it become the standard for observational clinical research, will still be no substitute for a conscientious explanation of differences between registered and actual analyses.</p>
<p>Peat and colleagues have contributed to this debate by calling for public registration of prognostic research, arguing that “routine registration of all prognostic studies, linked to an accessible study protocol using agreed reporting guidelines, would improve transparency and promote data sharing” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-Peat1">[7]</xref>. They further point out that protocol sharing and registration are not equivalent: “Protocols describe the rationale, objectives, design, methodology, statistical considerations, and organization of a study and they present a research plan made before the conduct of the study. Compared to study registers, protocols contain more detail, particularly about study design and analysis plans.” Interestingly, while registration of clinical trials is mandatory under International Committee of Medical Journal Editors (ICMJE) requirements, posting of trial protocols in registries is optional <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001711-International1">[2]</xref>.</p>
<p>The <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> editors welcome opportunities to collaborate with the research community on issues of transparency and publication quality. We hope authors will find our requirements constructive and will let us know of suggested improvements. <bold>We encourage members of the research community to share your insights by commenting on this editorial, either on the </bold><bold><italic>PLOS Medicine</italic></bold><bold> site or in Pub Med Commons, with thoughts on whether or how medical journals should establish requirements for prospective, public registration of observational studies that are intended to inform patient care or health policy.</bold> We plan to revisit this issue in due course, and your views will help us determine our future direction.</p>
</sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors thank Dr. Virginia Barbour for her comments on an earlier draft of this editorial, and members of the <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> Editorial Board for thoughtful discussion of these issues.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-Equator1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Equator Network (2014) CONSORT 2010 Statement: updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trials. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/consort/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/consort/</ext-link>. Accessed 17 July 2014.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-International1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">International Committee of Medical Journal Editors (2014) Clinical Trial Registration. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icmje.org/recommendations/browse/publishing-and-editorial-issues/clinical-trial-registration.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.icmje.org/recommendations/browse/publishing-and-editorial-issues/clinical-trial-registration.html</ext-link>. Accessed 17 July 2014.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-ClinicalTrialsgov1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">ClinicalTrials.gov (2014) FDAAA 801 Requirements. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/manage-recs/fdaaa" xlink:type="simple">http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/manage-recs/fdaaa</ext-link>. Accessed 17 July 2014.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-Virginia1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Virginia Barbour (2013) Full registration and reporting of all trials at PLOS Medicine. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blogs.plos.org/speakingofmedicine/2013/08/13/full-registration-and-reporting-of-all-trials-at-plos-medicine/" xlink:type="simple">http://blogs.plos.org/speakingofmedicine/2013/08/13/full-registration-and-reporting-of-all-trials-at-plos-medicine/</ext-link>. Accessed 17 July 2014.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-PRISMA1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">PRISMA. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.prisma-statement.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.prisma-statement.org</ext-link>. Accessed 17 July 2014.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-The1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">The <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> Editors</collab> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Many Reviews Are Systematic but Some Are More Transparent and Completely Reported than Others</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>4</volume><supplement>(3)</supplement>: <fpage>e147</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0040147" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0040147</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-Peat1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peat</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kyzas</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Improving the Transparency of Prognosis Research: The Role of Reporting, Data Sharing, Registration, and Protocols</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>11</volume><supplement>(7)</supplement>: <fpage>e1001671</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1001671" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001671</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-vonElm1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Elm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gøtzsche</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) Statement: Guidelines for Reporting Observational Studies</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>4</volume><supplement>(10)</supplement>: <fpage>e296</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0040296" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0040296</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-Vandenbroucke1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenbroucke</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Elm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gøtzsche</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulrow</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE): Explanation and Elaboration</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>4</volume><supplement>(10)</supplement>: <fpage>e297</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0040297" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0040297</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-STROBE1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">STROBE (2007) STROBE checklists, Version 4 as published in Oct/Nov 2007. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.strobe-statement.org/index.php?id=available-checklists" xlink:type="simple">http://www.strobe-statement.org/index.php?id=available-checklists</ext-link>. Accessed 3 June 2014.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-Equator2"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Equator Network (2014) Towards complete and accurate reporting of studies of diagnostic accuracy: the STARD initiative. Standards for Reporting of Diagnostic Accuracy. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/stard/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/stard/</ext-link>. Accessed 17 July 2014.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-PLOS1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">PLOS Medicine (2014) Sharing of Data, Materials, and Software. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plosmedicine.org/static/policies#sharing" xlink:type="simple">http://www.plosmedicine.org/static/policies#sharing</ext-link>. Accessed 17 July 2014.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-Sox1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sox</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helfand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grimshaw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dickersin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <collab xlink:type="simple">the <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> Editors</collab>, (<year>2010</year>) <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Comparative Effectiveness Research: Challenges for Medical Journals</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>7</volume><supplement>(4)</supplement>: <fpage>e1000269</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000269" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000269</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-The2"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">The Lancet</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Should protocols for observational research be registered?</article-title> <source>Lancet</source> <volume>375</volume>: <fpage>348</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-Loder1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loder</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Groves</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>MacAuley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Registration of observational studies</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>340</volume>: <fpage>c950</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-Williams1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harlan</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zarin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Registration of observational studies: Is it time?</article-title> <source>CMAJ</source> <volume>182</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001711-Dwan1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dwan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gamble</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JPT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Evidence for the Selective Reporting of Analyses and Discrepancies in Clinical Trials: A Systematic Review of Cohort Studies of Clinical Trials</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>11</volume><supplement>(6)</supplement>: <fpage>e1001666</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1001666" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001666</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance:</bold> Written by editorial staff; not externally peer reviewed</p></fn>
</fn-group></back>
</article>