<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">pmed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="flc">plme</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosmed</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1549-1277</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1549-1676</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">06-PLME-RA-0214R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="sici">plme-03-12-30</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Immunology</subject>
          <subject>Microbiology</subject>
          <subject>Molecular Biology</subject>
          <subject>Pathology</subject>
          <subject>Virology</subject>
          <subject>Virology</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy">
          <subject>Infectious Diseases</subject>
          <subject>Microbiology</subject>
          <subject>Geriatric Medicine</subject>
          <subject>Respiratory Medicine</subject>
          <subject>Immunology and allergy</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Vaccine Efficacy in Senescent Mice Challenged with Recombinant SARS-CoV
          Bearing Epidemic and Zoonotic Spike Variants </article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">SARS-CoV Vaccine Development</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Deming</surname>
            <given-names>Damon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sheahan</surname>
            <given-names>Timothy</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Heise</surname>
            <given-names>Mark</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Yount</surname>
            <given-names>Boyd</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Davis</surname>
            <given-names>Nancy</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sims</surname>
            <given-names>Amy</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Suthar</surname>
            <given-names>Mehul</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Harkema</surname>
            <given-names>Jack</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Whitmore</surname>
            <given-names>Alan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Pickles</surname>
            <given-names>Raymond</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>West</surname>
            <given-names>Ande</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Donaldson</surname>
            <given-names>Eric</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Curtis</surname>
            <given-names>Kristopher</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Johnston</surname>
            <given-names>Robert</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Baric</surname>
            <given-names>Ralph</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line> Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of North Carolina at
          Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, North Carolina, United States of America </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line> Carolina Vaccine Institute, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel
          Hill, North Carolina, United States of America </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line> Department of Genetics, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel
          Hill, North Carolina, United States of America </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line> Department of Epidemiology, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel
          Hill, North Carolina, United States of America </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff5">
        <label>5</label>
        <addr-line> Department of Pathobiology and Diagnostic Investigation, College of Veterinary
          Medicine, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, United States of America
        </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff6">
        <label>6</label>
        <addr-line> United States Army Medical Research Institute of Infectious Diseases, Fort
          Detrick, Frederick, Maryland, United States of America </addr-line>
      </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Peiris</surname>
            <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Academic Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">The University of Hong Kong, People's Republic of China</aff><author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="ack1">
          <p>D. Deming, M. Heise, R. Johnston, and R. Baric designed the study. D. Deming, M. Heise,
            J. Harkema, A. Whitmore, R. Pickles, R. Johnston, and R. Baric analyzed the data. D.
            Deming, M. Heise, N. Davis, A. Sims, J. Harkema, R. Pickles, E. Donaldson, K. Curtis, R.
            Johnston, and R. Baric contributed to writing the paper. D. Deming, T. Sheahan, and B.
            Yount performed the SARS-CoV mice challenge experiments, the neutralization assays, and
            prepared tissue for titer and histopathology. T. Sheahan and B. Yount prepared virus
            using the SARS-CoV infectious cDNA system. K. Curtis, B. Yount, A. Whitmore, N. Davis,
            and A. West constructed and prepared the VRP vectors and to vaccinate and monitor mice.
            A. Sims and M. Suthar performed and analyzed the Western blot and in situ experiments,
            respectively. E. Donaldson generated the phylogenetic trees comparing SARS-CoV spike
            glycoprotein sequences and contributed to the design of the chimeric GDO3-S
          construct.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor1">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">rbaric@email.unc.edu</email></corresp>
      <fn fn-type="conflict" id="n102">
        <p> Experiments described in this manuscript use technology that ND helped develop at the
          University of North Carolina, and that has been licensed to AlphaVax, Inc., for commercial
          use. ND is a shareholder in AlphaVax, Inc.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e525</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><copyright-holder> Deming, et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the
        terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
        distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are
        credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article issue="2" page="e80" related-article-type="correction-forward" vol="4" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0040080" xlink:title="Correction" xlink:type="simple">
        <article-title>Correction: Vaccine Efficacy in Senescent Mice Challenged with Recombinant
          SARS-CoV Bearing Epidemic and Zoonotic Spike Variants</article-title>
      </related-article><abstract>
        <sec id="st1">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>In 2003, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) was identified as the
            etiological agent of severe acute respiratory syndrome, a disease characterized by
            severe pneumonia that sometimes results in death. SARS-CoV is a zoonotic virus that
            crossed the species barrier, most likely originating from bats or from other species
            including civets, raccoon dogs, domestic cats, swine, and rodents. A SARS-CoV vaccine
            should confer long-term protection, especially in vulnerable senescent populations,
            against both the 2003 epidemic strains and zoonotic strains that may yet emerge from
            animal reservoirs. We report the comprehensive investigation of SARS vaccine efficacy in
            young and senescent mice following homologous and heterologous challenge.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="st2">
          <title>Methods and Findings</title>
          <p>Using Venezuelan equine encephalitis virus replicon particles (VRP) expressing the 2003
            epidemic Urbani SARS-CoV strain spike (S) glycoprotein (VRP-S) or the nucleocapsid (N)
            protein from the same strain (VRP-N), we demonstrate that VRP-S, but not VRP-N vaccines
            provide complete short- and long-term protection against homologous strain challenge in
            young and senescent mice. To test VRP vaccine efficacy against a heterologous SARS-CoV,
            we used phylogenetic analyses, synthetic biology, and reverse genetics to construct a
            chimeric virus (icGDO3-S) encoding a synthetic S glycoprotein gene of the most
            genetically divergent human strain, GDO3, which clusters among the zoonotic SARS-CoV.
            icGD03-S replicated efficiently in human airway epithelial cells and in the lungs of
            young and senescent mice, and was highly resistant to neutralization with antisera
            directed against the Urbani strain. Although VRP-S vaccines provided complete short-term
            protection against heterologous icGD03-S challenge in young mice, only limited
            protection was seen in vaccinated senescent animals. VRP-N vaccines not only failed to
            protect from homologous or heterologous challenge, but resulted in enhanced
            immunopathology with eosinophilic infiltrates within the lungs of
            SARS-CoV–challenged mice. VRP-N–induced pathology presented at day
            4, peaked around day 7, and persisted through day 14, and was likely mediated by
            cellular immune responses.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="st3">
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>This study identifies gaps and challenges in vaccine design for controlling future
            SARS-CoV zoonosis, especially in vulnerable elderly populations. The availability of a
            SARS-CoV virus bearing heterologous S glycoproteins provides a robust challenge inoculum
            for evaluating vaccine efficacy against zoonotic strains, the most likely source of
            future outbreaks.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc">
        <p>Experiments in mice suggest challenges in vaccine design for controlling future SARS-CoV
          zoonosis, especially in vulnerable elderly populations.</p>
      </abstract><abstract abstract-type="editor">
        <title>Editors' Summary</title>
        <sec id="sb1">
          <title/>
          <sec id="sb1a">
            <title>Background.</title>
            <p>Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) is a flu-like illness and was first
              recognized in China in 2002, after which the disease rapidly spread around the world.
              SARS was associated with high death rates, much higher than those for flu. Around
              10% of people recognized as being infected with SARS died, and the death
              rate approached 50% among elderly people. The virus causing SARS was
              identified as a member of the coronavirus family; it is generally thought that this
              virus “jumped” to humans from bats, which harbor related viruses.
              Although SARS was declared eradicated by the World Health Organization in May 2005,
              there is still the possibility that similar viruses will again cross the species
              barrier and infect humans, with potentially serious consequences. As a result, many
              groups are working to develop vaccines that will protect against SARS infection.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="sb1b">
            <title>Why Was This Study Done?</title>
            <p>A SARS vaccine should be effective in people of all ages, including the elderly who
              are more likely to get seriously ill or die if they become infected. In addition,
              potential vaccines should protect against different variants of the virus, because
              there are different types of the virus that could potentially cross the species
              barrier from animals to humans. Of the different proteins that make up the SARS
              coronavirus, the spike glycoprotein is thought to elicit an immune response in humans
              that can protect against future infection. The researchers therefore examined vaccine
              candidates based on this particular protein (termed SARS-CoV S), as well as a second
              one called SARS-CoV N, in mice. Specifically, they tested whether the vaccines would
              protect against SARS infection in both young and older mice, and whether they would
              protect against infection by different strains of the SARS virus.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="sb1c">
            <title>What Did the Researchers Do and Find?</title>
            <p>The researchers created vaccines based on SARS-CoV S and SARS-CoV N by taking the
              genes coding for those proteins and inserting them into another type of virus particle
              that acted as a delivery vehicle. They injected mice with these vaccines and then
              tested whether the mice generated an immune response against the specific SARS
              proteins, which they did. The next step was to work out whether mice injected with the
              vaccines would be protected against later infection with SARS-CoV. The researchers
              found that mice injected with vaccine based on SARS-CoV S were protected against later
              infection with a standard SARS-CoV strain, both in the short term (eight weeks after
              vaccination) and the long term (54 weeks after vaccination). However, the vaccine
              based on SARS-CoV N did not seem to result in protection, and, worryingly, caused
              pathological changes in the lungs of mice following virus challenge. To find out if
              their candidate vaccines would protect against different strains of SARS, the
              researchers made a synthetic test virus that contained a mixture of genetic material
              from different natural variants of the virus. This test virus was used to
              “challenge” mice that had been immunized with the two different
              vaccines. The researchers found that the vaccine based on SARS-CoV S protected against
              infection by the test virus when mice were vaccinated young, but it failed to
              efficiently protect when administered to older mice.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="sb1d">
            <title>What Do These Findings Mean?</title>
            <p>The findings confirm others suggesting that vaccines based on the SARS-CoV S protein
              are more effective than those based on SARS-CoV N. They also suggest that the former
              can provide long-term protection in animals vaccinated young against closely related
              viruses. However, protection against more distantly related viruses remains a
              challenge, especially when vaccinating older animals. The differences seen between
              young and older mice suggest that older mice might provide a useful model for animal
              testing of candidate vaccines for diseases like SARS, flu, and West Nile virus that
              pose a particular threat to elderly people. Overall, these results provide useful
              lessons toward future SARS vaccine development in animals. The synthetic virus strain
              generated here, and others like it, are likely to be useful tools for such future
              studies.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="sb1e">
            <title>Additional Information.</title>
            <p>Please access these Web sites via the online version of this summary at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525</ext-link>.</p>
            <p>• The World Health Organization provides <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/csr/sars/en/" xlink:type="simple">guidance, archives,
                and other information resources</ext-link> on SARS.</p>
            <p>• Information from the US Centers for Disease Control on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/NCIDOD/SARS/" xlink:type="simple">SARS</ext-link>.</p>
            <p>• Wikipedia (an internet encyclopedia anyone can edit) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SARS" xlink:type="simple">has an entry on
                SARS</ext-link>.</p>
            <p>• Collected resources from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/severeacuterespiratorysyndrome.html" xlink:type="simple">MedLinePlus</ext-link> about SARS.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases of the
          National Institutes of Health (NIH/NIAID) grant AI05944302 and AI059136 to RSB. The
          funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or
          preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="17"/>
      </counts><!--===== Restructure custom-meta-wrap to custom-meta-group =====--><custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>citation</meta-name>
          <meta-value>Deming D, Sheahan T, Heise M, Yount B, Davis N, et al. (2006) Vaccine efficacy
            in senescent mice challenged with recombinant SARS-CoV bearing epidemic and zoonotic
            spike variants. PLoS Med 3(12): e525. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525</ext-link></meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) infection results in severe acute
        respiratory disease, pneumonia, and sometimes death[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b001">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b002">2</xref>]. The disease was reported in Guangdong Province, China, in 2002 and
        spread to more than 30 nations within a few months. Disease severity was linked to age and
        other comorbidities, with mortality rates increasing with age and exceeding 50%
        in individuals over 65 y [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b003">3</xref>]. SARS-CoV is a zoonotic virus that crossed the species barrier, most
        likely originating from bats[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b004">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b006">6</xref>] or
        from other species including civets, raccoon dogs, domestic cats, swine, and
          rodents[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b007">7</xref>]. New
        zoonotic variants may emerge as evidenced by sporadic cases of human disease in late 2003
        and early 2004, which arose from strains distinct from that of the epidemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b008">8</xref>]. In 2004, several
        laboratory-acquired infections were reported, including secondary spread resulting in fatal
          disease[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b009">9</xref>]. Given
        the significant health and economic impact, the development of an effective vaccine strategy
        that is protective against both epidemic and zoonotic SARS-CoV strains is highly desirable.</p>
      <p>Attenuated and killed SARS-CoV, DNA, and viral vectored vaccines are being evaluated in a
        number of animal models including mouse, ferret, hamster, and primate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b010">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b023">23</xref>], and have demonstrated that the SARS-CoV spike
        (S) glycoprotein is the principal component of protective immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b015">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b024">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b025">25</xref>]. Although strong immune responses are elicited against both S
        glycoprotein and nucleocapsid (N) protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b010">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b015">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b027">27</xref>], passive transfer studies have illustrated
        that only anti-S antibody confers protection from SARS-CoV replication in the mouse model
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b016">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b017">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b028">28</xref>]. Vaccine development faces a series of potential concerns including
        reversion or recombination repair of attenuated vaccine strains, induction of
        immune-mediated enhancement of pathology, waning immune protection, lack of cross-protection
        for heterologous strains, and limited vaccine efficacy within senescent populations.
        Furthermore, immune enhancement has been demonstrated with another coronavirus, feline
        infectious peritonitis coronavirus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b029">29</xref>], and more recently with a modified vaccinia vector expressing SARS-S
        that exacerbated hepatitis in ferrets while failing to protect from infection
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b030">30</xref>]. Notably, some
        antibodies against the epidemic Urbani strain increased the infectivity of lentiviruses
        pseudotyped with an animal SARS-S glycoprotein in an in vitro model, raising the specter of
        vaccine-mediated immune enhancement of disease following heterotypic challenge
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b031">31</xref>]. Another
        potential problem is that SARS vaccines might fail to induce antibodies that protect from
        infection with divergent strains of SARS-CoV. The S glycoprotein of SARS-CoV contains about
        2%–20% amino acid variation between zoonotic and the 2003
        epidemic strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b031">31</xref>], possibly limiting the
        effectiveness of monotypic SARS-S vaccines. Finally, studies measuring the duration of
        protective immunity or vaccine efficacy in animals greater than 4 mo post-boost have not yet
        been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b017">17</xref>].</p>
      <p>In this report, the efficacy of Venezuelan equine encephalitis virus replicon particle
        (VRP) vaccines expressing the Urbani SARS-CoV S glycoprotein (VRP-S) and N protein (VRP-N),
        either individually or in combination (VRP-S+N), are determined in young and
        senescent mouse models. We tested whether the senescent mouse model, which exhibits an
        age-related susceptibility to SARS-CoV similar to that seen in the human disease
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b032">32</xref>], will provide
        a sensitive measure of vaccine efficacy and reveal potential complications in SARS-CoV
        vaccine development for vulnerable elderly populations. We evaluated the duration of
        protective immunity following homologous and heterologous SARS virus challenge, examining
        the impact of waning immunity on long-term protection. Through the use of publicly available
        SARS-CoV sequence databases, bioinformatics approaches, synthetic biology, and reverse
        genetics, we constructed a viable heterologous challenge virus to test the ability of
        current vaccine regimens to protect against zoonotic strains; the likely source of future
        epidemics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b008">8</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Viruses and Cells</title>
        <p>The Urbani, Tor-2, recombinant Urbani (icSARS), and a recombinant chimeric virus encoding
          the S gene of GDO3 SARS-CoV (icGD03-S), strains were propagated on VeroE6 cells in Eagle's
          MEM supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum, kanamycin (0.25 μg/ml), and
          gentamycin (0.05 μg/ml) at 37 °C in a humidified CO<sub>2</sub> incubator.
          For virus growth, cultures of VeroE6 cells were infected at a multiplicity of infection
          (MOI) of 1 for 1 h, the monolayer washed twice with 2 ml of PBS and overlaid with complete
          MEM. Virus samples were harvested at different times post-infection and titered by plaque
          assay. Plaques were visualized by neutral red staining and then counted.</p>
        <p>Human nasal and tracheobronchial epithelial cells were obtained from airway specimens
          rejected from patients undergoing elective surgery under University of North Carolina
          (UNC) Institutional Review Board–approved protocols by the UNC Cystic Fibrosis
          (CF) Center Tissue Culture Core. Briefly, primary cells were expanded on plastic to
          generate passage 1 cells and plated at a density of 250,000 cells per well on permeable
          Transwell-Col (T-Col, 12-mm diameter; Corning [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.corning.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.corning.com</ext-link>])
          supports. Human airway epithelium (HAE) cultures were generated by provision of an
          air–liquid interface for 4–6 wk to form well-differentiated, polarized
          cultures that resemble in vivo pseudo-stratified mucosciliary epithelium, and infected
          with wild-type or recombinant SARS-CoV as previously described by our laboratory
            [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b033">33</xref>]. All virus
          work was performed in a biological safety cabinet (BSC cabinet) in a biosafety level three
          (BSL3) laboratory containing redundant HEPA-filtered exhaust fans. Personnel were double
          gloved and wore Tyvek suits with hoods supplied with HEPA-filtered air by a powered
          air-purifying respirator (PAPR).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Construction and Isolation of the icGDO3-CoV Variant Virus</title>
        <p>The GD03-S glycoprotein sequence has been reported. A synthetic DNA containing the
          5′-most GD03 mutations was purchased (Blue Heron Biotechnology
            [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.blueheronbio.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.blueheronbio.com</ext-link>]) and inserted into the SARS-E
          fragment. The plasmid clone (SARS-E GD03) was fully sequenced and shown to contain all of
          the appropriate mutations. The remaining GDO3 mutation was incorporated by PCR mutagenesis
          (5′ amplicon A: 5′-CTGTTTTCCCTGGGATCGC-3′; 3′
          amplicon A: 5′-NNNNNNCACCTGCTTTTGGGCAACTCCAATGCC-3′; 5′
          amplicon B: 5′-NNNNNNCACCTGCAGTTGCCCAAAATGTTCTCTATGAGAAC-3′;
          3′ amplicon B: 5′-CATAAATTGGATCCATTGCTGG), followed by seamless
          ligation of the amplicons as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b034">34</xref>] into the SARS-F subclone. The final
          construct (SARS-F GD03) was fully sequenced and found to contain the appropriate set of
          GD03-S glycoprotein alleles.</p>
        <p>The icGDO3-S was generated as previously described. Infectious clone fragment plasmid DNA
          was prepared in <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Escherichia
          coli</named-content> (TOP-10, Invitrogen [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.invitrogen.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.invitrogen.com</ext-link>]),
          isolated, and purified (Qiagen [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.qiagen.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.qiagen.com</ext-link>]).
          Infectious clone fragments B, C, D, and E were digested with BglI. Infectious clone
          fragments A and F were digested with EcoRI and NotI, respectively. Infectious clone
          fragments A and F were then dephosphorylated and then digested with BglI. Individual cDNA
          fragments were gel purified (Qiagen) and ligated (Roche [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.roche.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.roche.com</ext-link>]) to form a full-length genomic cDNA and then
          chloroform extracted and EtOH precipitated. N cDNA and full-length viral genomic cDNA were
          then used as templates for in vitro transcription reactions (Ambion [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ambion.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ambion.com</ext-link>]). N and full-length viral genomic transcripts
          were then electroporated into Vero cells. Cell culture media containing virus was
          harvested 48 h post-electroporation. Virus was plaque purified and then passaged twice in
          Vero cells. The resultant stock was plaque titered and cyropreserved at −80
          °C.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Western Blot Analysis</title>
        <p>Twelve hours post-infection, Urbani–, icSARS-CoV–,
          SARS-CoV–, Tor-2–, and icGD03-S–infected cells were washed
          in 1X PBS, lysed in buffer containing 20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.6), 150 mM NaCl,
          0.5% deoxycholine, 1% Nonidet-p-40, 0.1% SDS, and
          post-nuclear supernatants added to an equal volume of 5 mM EDTA/0.9% SDS,
          resulting in a final SDS concentration of 0.5%. Samples were then heat
          inactivated for 30 min at 90 °C in the BL3 prior to removal. At BL2, samples were
          again heat inactivated for 30 min at 90 °C before use. Equivalent sample volumes
          were loaded onto 4% to 20% Criterion gradient gels (BioRad
            [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bio-rad.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.bio-rad.com</ext-link>]) and then transferred to PVDF membrane
          (BioRad). Blots were probed with polyclonal mouse antisera directed against the Urbani-S
          glycoprotein diluted 1:200 or convalescent human sera 1128 diluted 1:400 and developed
          using electrogenerated chemiluminescence (ECL) reagents (Amersham Biosciences
            [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www5.amershambiosciences.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www5.amershambiosciences.com</ext-link>]). Patient #1128 was
          infected during the second disease outbreak in Toronto, Canada.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Plaque Reduction Neutralization Titer Assays</title>
        <p>One hundred plaque-forming units (pfu) of either icSARS-CoV or icGDO3-S were treated with
          heat-inactivated serum diluted to final concentrations of 1:100, 1:200, 1:400, 1:800, or
          1:1,600 and incubated at 37 °C for 30 min, and the resulting titer determined by
          plaque assay. Plaque numbers formed by virus treated with each dilution of sera from
          individual mice vaccinated with VRP-S or VRP-S+N were compared to the average
          number of plaques formed after treatment with a given dilution of sera from VRP expressing
          the influenza A HA protein (VRP-HA)- or PBS-vaccinated mice and expressed as the relative
          percentage. The dilution at which 80% of plaques were neutralized was
          determined for each VRP-S– or VRP-S+N–vaccinated animal.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Mice</title>
        <p>Female BALB/c mice (Charles River Laboratories [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.criver.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.criver.com</ext-link>]) were
          anesthetized with a ketamine (1.3 mg/mouse) and xylazine (0.38 mg/mouse) mixture
          administered intraperitoneally with a 50-μl volume. Each mouse was intranasally
          (i.n.) inoculated with 50 μl of virus at a concentration of 2 ×
          10<sup>6</sup> pfu/ml of virus. Four days post-infection, the right lung was removed and
          frozen at −70 °C for later plaque assay determination of viral titers.
          Half of the left lung was placed into Trizol Reagent (Invitrogen) for RNA extraction. The
          second half of the left lung was fixed in 4% PFA in PBS (pH 7.4) for at least 7
          d prior to paraffin imbedding and sectioning for histopathological analysis. All mice were
          housed under sterile conditions, and sentinel mice were used to verify that the colony was
          mouse hepatitis virus (MHV) negative. Experimental protocols were reviewed and approved by
          the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at UNC Chapel Hill. Young mice refer to
          those challenged with SARS-CoV at ages equal or less than 5 mo old, whereas old or
          senescent mice are those animals with ages greater than 1 y at the time of challenge.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Plaque Assay Titration of Virus from Lungs</title>
        <p>Lungs were weighed and homogenized in four equivalent volumes of PBS to generate a
          20% solution. The solution was centrifuged at 13,000 rpm on a tabletop
          centrifuge for 5 min, the clarified supernatant serially diluted in PBS, and 200-μl
          volumes of the dilutions placed onto monolayers of Vero cells in 60-mm dishes. Following a
          1-h incubation at 37 °C, cells were overlaid with 1% agarose-containing
          medium. Two days later, plates were stained with neutral red and then plaques counted.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>VRP-S and VRP-N</title>
        <p>The VRP constructs were made in two rounds of PCR, the first to generate two amplicons,
          and a second round of overlapping PCR to fuse them together. The fused DNA was digested
          with ApaI and AscI, and ligated into the similarly digested pVR21 plasmid. PCR reactions
          were performed with Expand Long Taq (Roche Molecular Biochemicals <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.roche-applied-science.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.roche-applied-science.com</ext-link>) in 30 cycles of 94 °C for 30
          s, 55 °C for 30 s, and extensions at 68 °C for 1 min. The first amplicon,
          which was used in the construction of both VRP-S and VRP-N, was generated with primers
          5′nsp4Sw (5′-GATTGAGGCGGCTTTCGGCG) and 3′26S
          (5′-TTAATTAAGTCAATCGGCGCGCCCTTGGCGGACTAGACTATGTC) using pVR21 as template. The
          N-gene–specific amplicon was produced using primers V5′SARNg
          (5′-AGTCTAGTCCGCCAAGATGTCTGATAATGGACCCCAATC) and 3′SARSNg
          (5′-NNNNTTAATTAATTATGCCTGAGTTGAATCAGC) with SARS-F plasmid for template. The
          S-gene–containing amplicon was made with V5′SARSg
          (5′-AGTCTAGTCCGCCAAGATGTTTATTTTCTTATTATTTCTTACTCTCAC) and SARS3′Sg
          (5′-NNNNTTAATTAATTATGTGTAATGTAATTTGACACCC) using ligated SARS-E and -F
          fragments. The VRP-S and VRP-N cDNA templates were sequenced for verification and replicon
          particles produced as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b035">35</xref>]. Mice were vaccinated with 10<sup>6</sup>
          infectious units (IU) of VRP in a 10-μl volume in the left rear footpad.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Lung Histopathology</title>
        <p>Lungs were fixed in 4% PFA in PBS for 7 d before being submitted to the
          Histopathology Core Facility (UNC, Chapel Hill) for paraffin imbedding, sectioning at
          5-μm thickness, and hematoxylin and eosin staining. Approximately one-quarter of
          the total lungs were sectioned, with four to six sections mounted from cuts taken at five
          different depths within the paraffin-imbedded tissue. Lung pathology was scored in a
          blinded manner, in which six to ten sections per animal were evaluated and scored using
          the following scale. 1.0 to 2.0 = no to mild inflammation, 2.0 to 3.0
          = mild to moderate inflammation, 3.0 to 4.0 = moderate to severe
          inflammation in less than half of the tissue section, and 4.0 to 5.0 = severe
          inflammation in more than half of the tissue section. The same sets of tissues were also
          evaluated qualitatively by a respiratory pathologist (author JH).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2i">
        <title>In Situ Hybridization</title>
        <p>The 5 μm–thick paraffin-embedded sections were probed with<sup>35</sup>S UTP-labeled riboprobes complementary to the N gene of SARS-CoV (Urbani) or
          the HA gene of the A/PR8 strain of influenza as a negative control using previously
          described methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b036">36</xref>]. In brief, following treatment to prevent nonspecific probe binding,
          the tissues were incubated overnight with either probe at 5 × 10<sup>4</sup>
          cpm/μl in hybridization buffer at 42 °C. The slides were then washed,
          dehydrated, and coated with NBT emulsion (Kodak [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kodak.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.kodak.com</ext-link>]), and
          incubated at −80 °C. for 1 wk prior to development. Positive signal, as
          determined by silver grain deposition, was then evaluated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2j">
        <title>Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay</title>
        <p>Antibody titers were determined by standard indirect enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay
          (ELISA). High-binding 96-well round-bottom plates (Corning [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.corning.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.corning.com</ext-link>]) were coated with 10 μg/ml of SARS-S,
          SARS-N, or inactivated influenza A diluted in carbonate buffer containing 32 mM sodium
          carbonate, 68 mM sodium bicarbonate (pH 9.6) at 4 °C overnight. Mouse sera,
          diluted 1:100 in casein blocking buffer (Sigma [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sigmaaldrich.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.sigmaaldrich.com</ext-link>]), were added to wells in duplicate, and
          2-fold serial dilutions were performed, followed by incubation for 2 h at 37 °C.
          Plates were then incubated for 1 h with goat anti-mouse IgG with alkaline phosphatase (AP)
          conjugate (Sigma), developed with <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenyl phosphate
          (<italic>p</italic>NPP; Sigma), and the optical density (OD) at 405 nm was measured
          (Bio-Rad Model 680 microplate reader). Log<sub>10</sub> half-maximum ELISA titers were
          calculated with Sigmaplot (Systat [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.systat.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.systat.com</ext-link>]) using the
          solution of the sigmoidal line of the plot of the log of the reciprocal dilutions of mouse
          sera and the resulting absorbances to determine the log of the reciprocal dilution at
          which an absorbance of 2.1 was achieved. Since very low amounts of antibody were being
          measured in the passive transfer experiment, log<sub>10</sub> OD = 0.2 ELISA
          titers were calculated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2k">
        <title>Passive Sera Transfer</title>
        <p>Mice were inoculated with 10<sup>6</sup> IU of VRP-HA, VRP-S, or VRP-N at 7 wk of age,
          boosted 4 wk later, and terminally bled via cardiac puncture 3 wk post-boost. The sera of
          each group were pooled and 150 μl transferred by tail vein injection into mice at 7
          or 43 wk of age. Mice receiving sera were bled and i.n. challenged with 10<sup>5</sup> pfu
          of icSARS.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2l">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Unless otherwise noted, two-tailed Mann-Whitney tests were used for statistical
          comparisons. The Fisher exact tests were completed by comparing the number of animals
          positive for viral replication within the lungs of a group of animals vaccinated with
          VRP-S or VRP-S+N to that of the negative control group, VRP-HA or PBS. Values
          outside the limit of detection were assigned a value equal to the limit of detection for
          any analysis. The plus or minus (±) symbol is used to refer to standard
          deviation.</p>
        <p>An amino acid multiple alignment was generated for the entire S gene of viral sequences
          representing early, middle, and late phases of the SARS epidemic in humans, as well as
          animal strains of SARS-CoV isolated from civets and racoon dogs found in Chinese live
          animal markets or housed on farms in China that supplied the markets. The sequences were
          aligned using ClustalX 1.83 with default settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b037">37</xref>]. A phylogenetic tree was generated using
          Bayesian inference as implemented in the program MrBayes v3.0b4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b038">38</xref>]. Briefly, the alignment was
          exported in the nexus format, the amino acid substitution model was set to JTT
            [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b039">39</xref>] using the
          lset command, and Markov chain Monte Carlo simulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b038">38</xref>] was used to approximate the posterior
          probabilities of trees with sampling conducted on four chains over 500,000 generations
            [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b040">40</xref>]. Trees were
          sampled every 100 generations, and the 5,001 trees collected were summarized with the sumt
          command set to a burnin of 1,000, which generated a consensus tree using the
          50% majority rule [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b040">40</xref>]. The burnin value was determined using the sump command with an
          arbitrary burnin of 250, which demonstrated that stationarity occurred prior to the
          100,000th generation, indicating that a burnin of 1,000 was appropriate for the sumt
          command [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b040">40</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Venezuelan Equine Encephalitis Virus Replicon Particles Expressing SARS-CoV S and N</title>
        <p>The SARS-CoV S glycoprotein gene and N protein gene were PCR cloned, sequence verified,
          and inserted into Venezuelan equine encephalitis VRPs. VRP-S and VRP-N constructs were
          packaged to give titers greater than 10<sup>9</sup> IU per ml and shown to express
          antigenically relevant recombinant proteins. VRP-infected cell lysates were probed with
          antiserum 1128, derived from a convalescent human SARS patient. Western blot analysis of
          VRP-S–infected lysates revealed the expected S glycoprotein doublet of
          approximately 180–210 kDa, whereas that of VRP-N–infected lysates
          revealed a major product of less than 50 kDa, the expected sizes for SARS-S and -N,
          respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g001">Figure 1</xref>A). VRP-S was
          inoculated into BALB/c mice and tested for its ability to induce antigen-specific
          antibody. Western blots were performed with Vero cell lysates infected with Urbani,
          SARS-CoV Tor-2, icSARS-CoV (the Urbani recombinant virus), and icGD03-S, a chimeric
          SARS-CoV expressing the S glycoprotein of the heterologous GDO3 strain. Blots were probed
          with anti–VRP-S mouse serum, 1128 human convalescent serum, or with
          anti–VRP-N mouse serum. The Western blots demonstrated that probing with human
          serum resolved bands corresponding to the major SARS antigens S (a doublet at
          ~180–210 kDa) and N (triplet at &lt;50 kDa), as well as other unidentified
          SARS-CoV proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g001">Figure 1</xref>B). Serum
          from mice vaccinated with VRP-S only identified SARS-S (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g001">Figure 1</xref>C), whereas serum from mice vaccinated with VRP-N
          recognized SARS-N in addition to another SARS-CoV protein that is probably a dimer of N
            (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g001">Figure 1</xref>D).</p>
        <fig id="pmed-0030525-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>VRP Expression of SARS S and N and VRP-S Induction of Anti-SARS S Antibody</title>
            <p>(A) Western blot of cell lysates infected with VRP-S or VRP-N and probed with human
              serum collected from a convalescent SARS patient, 1128.</p>
            <p>(B–D) Western blot of lysates from cells infected with the SARS-CoV strains
              Urbani, Tor2, icSARS, or icGDO3-S and probed with human convalescent serum, 1128 (B),
              mouse anti–SARS-S serum from VRP-S–vaccinated animals (C), or
              mouse serum from a mouse vaccinated with VRP-N (D).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>VRP Vaccine Efficacy against icSARS-CoV Replication in the Mouse Model</title>
        <p>As a general measure of vaccine efficacy (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, experiment 1), six 4-wk-old BALB/c mice were vaccinated with either
            10<sup>5</sup> IU of VRP-S or VRP-HA, boosted 4 wk later with an equal amount of VRP,
          and then i.n. challenged with 10<sup>5</sup> pfu of icSARS-CoV 8 wk post-boost. Consistent
          with other studies that made use of vectored SARS-S–expressing vaccines to
          induce protective responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b016">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b041">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b042">42</xref>], vaccination with VRP-S also prevented the replication of icSARS-CoV
          following challenge. No virus was detected by plaque assay (250 pfu/g limit of detection)
          in the lungs of VRP-S–vaccinated animals at 2 d post-infection, whereas the
          VRP-HA–vaccinated mouse lung had a mean titer of 6.7 ± 0.5
          log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g002">Figure 2</xref>A).
          Vaccination with VRP-S demonstrated significant protection at the time of peak lung titer
          relative to VRP-HA–vaccinated control animals (<italic>p</italic> =
          0.007, Fisher exact test).</p>
        <table-wrap content-type="2col" id="pmed-0030525-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <p> Summary of Vaccine Groups and Select Results for Mouse Experiments</p>
          </caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup><col id="tb01col1" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb01col2" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb01col3" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb01col4" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb01col5" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb01col6" align="char" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb01col7" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb01col8" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb01col9" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb01col10" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left"><hr/>Experiment</td><td><hr/><italic>n</italic></td><td><hr/>Vaccine</td><td><hr/>Age Vaccinated (wk)</td><td><hr/>Age Boosted (wk)</td><td><hr/>Challenge Virus</td><td><hr/>Age Challenged (wk)</td><td><hr/>Lungs Harvested (days Post Challenge)</td><td><hr/>Lung Titer (log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g)</td><td><hr/>Positive for Viral Replication</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>6</td><td>VRP-S</td><td>4</td><td>8</td><td>icSARS</td><td>16</td><td>2</td><td align="center">0</td><td>0/6</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>6</td><td>VRP-HA</td><td>4</td><td>8</td><td>icSARS</td><td>16</td><td>2</td><td>6.7 &plusmn; 0.5</td><td>6/6</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>8</td><td>VRP-S</td><td>5</td><td>10</td><td>icSARS</td><td>64</td><td>4</td><td align="center">0</td><td>0/8</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>VRP-N</td><td>5</td><td>10</td><td>icSARS</td><td>64</td><td>4</td><td>5.3 &plusmn; 0.6</td><td>7/7</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>VRP-S&plus;N</td><td>5</td><td>10</td><td>icSARS</td><td>64</td><td>4</td><td align="center">0</td><td>0/8</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>7</td><td>VRP-HA</td><td>5</td><td>10</td><td>icSARS</td><td>64</td><td>4</td><td>5.8 &plusmn; 0.6</td><td>8/8</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>8</td><td>VRP-S</td><td>7</td><td>10</td><td>icGDO3-S</td><td>17</td><td>2</td><td align="center">0</td><td>0/8</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>VRP-N</td><td>7</td><td>10</td><td>icGDO3-S</td><td>17</td><td>2</td><td>6.3 &plusmn; 0.1</td><td>8/8</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>VRP-S&plus;N</td><td>7</td><td>10</td><td>icGDO3-S</td><td>17</td><td>2</td><td align="center">0</td><td>0/8</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>VRP-HA</td><td>7</td><td>10</td><td>icGDO3-S</td><td>17</td><td>2</td><td>7.0 &plusmn; 0.1</td><td>8/8</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>8</td><td>VRP-S</td><td>&gt;26</td><td>&gt;30</td><td>icGDO3-S</td><td>&gt;62</td><td>4</td><td>5.0 &plusmn; 0.9</td><td>3/8</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>7</td><td>VRP-N</td><td>&gt;26</td><td>&gt;30</td><td>icGDO3-S</td><td>&gt;62</td><td>4</td><td>4.4 &plusmn; 0.5</td><td>8/8</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>VRP-S&plus;N</td><td>&gt;26</td><td>&gt;30</td><td>icGDO3-S</td><td>&gt;62</td><td>4</td><td>3.7 &plusmn; 1.2</td><td>8/8</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>PBS</td><td>&gt;26</td><td>&gt;30</td><td>icGDO3-S</td><td>&gt;62</td><td>4</td><td>4.9 &plusmn; 0.6</td><td>8/8</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>3</td><td>VRP-N</td><td>8</td><td>15</td><td>icSARS</td><td>19</td><td>2</td><td>7.5 &plusmn; 0.2</td><td>3/3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>VRP-HA</td><td>8</td><td>15</td><td>icSARS</td><td>19</td><td>2</td><td>8.1 &plusmn; 0.1</td><td>3/3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>VRP-N</td><td>8</td><td>15</td><td>icSARS</td><td>19</td><td>4</td><td>5.5 &plusmn; 0.3</td><td>3/3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>VRP-HA</td><td>8</td><td>15</td><td>icSARS</td><td>19</td><td>4</td><td>5.7 &plusmn; 0.1</td><td>3/3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>VRP-N</td><td>8</td><td>15</td><td>icSARS</td><td>19</td><td>7</td><td align="center">0</td><td>0/3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>VRP-HA</td><td>8</td><td>15</td><td>icSARS</td><td>19</td><td>7</td><td>3.2 &plusmn; 0.5</td><td>2/3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>VRP-N</td><td>8</td><td>15</td><td>icSARS</td><td>19</td><td>14</td><td align="center">0</td><td>0/3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>2</td><td>VRP-HA</td><td>8</td><td>15</td><td>icSARS</td><td>19</td><td>14</td><td align="center">0</td><td>0/2</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>3</td><td>VRP-N</td><td>53</td><td>60</td><td>icSARS</td><td>64</td><td>2</td><td>8.2 &plusmn; 0.2</td><td>3/3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>2</td><td>VRP-HA</td><td>53</td><td>60</td><td>icSARS</td><td>64</td><td>2</td><td>8.5 &plusmn; 0.1</td><td>2/2</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>VRP-N</td><td>53</td><td>60</td><td>icSARS</td><td>64</td><td>4</td><td>5.4 &plusmn; 0.6</td><td>3/3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>VRP-HA</td><td>53</td><td>60</td><td>icSARS</td><td>64</td><td>4</td><td>5.7 &plusmn; 0.5</td><td>3/3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>2</td><td>VRP-N</td><td>53</td><td>60</td><td>icSARS</td><td>64</td><td>7</td><td align="center">3.7</td><td>1/2</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>2</td><td>VRP-HA</td><td>53</td><td>60</td><td>icSARS</td><td>64</td><td>7</td><td>3.7 &plusmn; 0.5</td><td>2/2</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>VRP-N</td><td>53</td><td>60</td><td>icSARS</td><td>64</td><td>14</td><td align="center">0</td><td>0/3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>2</td><td>VRP-HA</td><td>53</td><td>60</td><td>icSARS</td><td>64</td><td>14</td><td align="center">0</td><td>0/2</td></tr></tbody></table> --><!-- --></table-wrap>
        <fig id="pmed-0030525-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>VRP-S Induces Short- and Long-Term Protection against icSARS-CoV Challenge</title>
            <p>icSARS titers are expressed as the log<sub>10</sub> plaque-forming units per gram
              (pfu/g) of lung. Tissues were homogenized in PBS to form a 20% suspension
              and titered on Vero monolayers. The titers for individual mice are shown as a filled
              circle, and the mean titer for the group is represented by a solid bar. Limit of
              detection (lod) is 2.4 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g.</p>
            <p>(A) Lung titers of16-wk-old BALB/c mice harvested 2 d after being i.n. infected with
                10<sup>5</sup> PFU of icSARS-CoV (<italic>n</italic> = 6).</p>
            <p>(B) Lung titers of BALB/c mice vaccinated and boosted with 10<sup>6</sup> infectious
              units (IU) of VRP expressing the influenza HA (VRP-HA), SARS-S glycoprotein (VRP-S),
              SARS-N protein (VRP-N), or a combination of VRP-S and VRP-N (VRP-S+N). Mice
                (<italic>n</italic> = 7 VRP-HA, <italic>n</italic> = 8 for
              other groups) were vaccinated at 5 wk of age, boosted 5 wk later, then i.n. challenged
              with 10<sup>5</sup> pfu of icSARS-CoV 54-wk post-boost. Lungs were harvested 4 d later
              and titered.</p>
            <p>(C) Plaque assay results were confirmed by in situ hybridization to sectioned lungs
              of five mice from each vaccinated group with a radiolabeled riboprobe complementary to
              the SARS CoV N gene. In senescent mice challenged with the icSARS-CoV, representative
              lung sections from VRP-HA– (unpublished data) and VRP-N–vaccinated
              (a) animals exhibited extensive in situ signal (black arrows), whereas only one of
              five sections from VRP-S–vaccinated (b) and zero of five sections from
              VRP-S+N–vaccinated (c) mice exhibited SARS-CoV–specific
              signal above background levels.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>A second vaccine experiment was completed to evaluate long-term VRP protection.
          Five-week-old BALB/c mice were vaccinated with 10<sup>5</sup> IU of VRP-HA, VRP-S, VRP-N,
          or a combination of VRP-S and VRP-N (VRP-S+N), and boosted 5 wk later. Fifty-four
          weeks post-boost, mice were i.n. challenged with 10<sup>5</sup> pfu of icSARS-CoV and
          lungs removed 4 d post-infection (summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, experiment 2). Although day 2 post-challenge
          demonstrates peak viral titers, day 4 was chosen to harvest lungs because it is the time
          at which the highest level of pathology is evident in senescent mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b032">32</xref>]. Titers in the lungs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g002">Figure 2</xref>B) of animals vaccinated with
          VRP-S or the combination of VRP-S+N were below the limit of detection (250
          pfu/g). In contrast, the lung titers of VRP-HA–vaccinated animals were 5.8
          ± 0.6 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g, comparable to the VRP-N–vaccinated
          animal titers of 5.3 ± 0.6 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g (<italic>p</italic>
          = 0.2). These plaque assay results were confirmed by
          SARS-CoV–specific in situ hybridization on lung tissues from the infected mice
            (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g002">Figure 2</xref>C). Radiolabeled riboprobes
          complementary to the SARS-CoV N gene were hybridized to sectioned lungs of five mice from
          VRP-HA, VRP-N, VRP-S, or VRP-S+N vaccinated groups. Lung sections from VRP-HA
          (unpublished data) and VRP-N (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g002">Figure
          2</xref>C, image a) vaccinated animals exhibited extensive in situ signal (arrows),
          whereas only one of five sections from VRP-S–vaccinated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g002">Figure 2</xref>C, image b) and zero of five sections from
          VRP-S+N–vaccinated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g002">Figure
            2</xref>C, image c) mice exhibited SARS-CoV N-specific signal. Both VRP-S and the
          combination of VRP-S+N provided complete long-term protection against challenge
          with the homologous vaccine strain of SARS-CoV at 4 d post-infection (<italic>p</italic>
          &lt; 0.001, Fisher exact test for both VRP-S- and
          VRP-S+N–vaccinated groups relative to VRP-HA).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Protection against Heterologous Challenge</title>
        <p>To perform cross-protection efficacy studies, it was necessary to construct a
          heterologous SARS-CoV. Selection of a likely candidate strain was made after Bayesian
          analysis of the SARS-CoV S glycoprotein, which demonstrated three main phylogenetic
          branches. Two of the branches include viruses isolated from animals, such as the palm
          civet and raccoon dog, and low pathogenic viruses sporadically isolated from humans, such
          as GDO3 and GZ0401.Viruses representing the 2003 early, middle, and late phases of the
          epidemic strains form the third branch in the SARS-S phylogenetic tree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g003">Figure 3</xref>A). We resurrected the S
          glycoprotein of GDO3, a virus reported from a sporadic SARS case on December 22, 2003.
          Although GDO3 was not successfully isolated, its S glycoprotein was sequenced and
          reported. Compared to epidemic strains, GDO3 likely represented an independent
          introduction, was reported to be less pathogenic, and its S glycoprotein sequence is among
          the most divergent of all human strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b008">8</xref>]. The GDO3-S glycoprotein contains 17 amino
          acid changes relative to Urbani-S (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g003">Figure
          3</xref>B), many of which map within neutralizing epitopes between amino acids
          130–150 and 318–510, part of the receptor binding domain (RBD)
            [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b041">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b043">43</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b050">50</xref>]. Importantly, polyclonal antibody directed
          against the late-phase Urbani strain was less effective at neutralizing pseudotyped
          viruses bearing GDO3-S glycoproteins than those bearing Urbani-S [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b031">31</xref>]. The Urbani-S glycoprotein
          was removed from the SARS-CoV molecular clone, replaced with a synthetic cDNA encoding the
          GD03-S sequence, and used to generate recombinant virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b034">34</xref>]. Sequence analysis of plaque-purified
          icGDO3-S recombinant virus confirmed the presence of the GDO3-S glycoprotein and two
          additional changes in the S gene relative to Urbani-S (F7L and D613G), which likely arose
          as tissue-culture adaptations. The chimeric icGDO3-S, which only differs from Urbani
          SARS-CoV in its S glycoprotein, and wild-type icSARS-CoV recombinant viruses replicated in
          Vero cells to comparable titers that approached 10<sup>7</sup> PFU/ml within 24 h
          (unpublished data) and their proteins were both detected in Western blots with human
          antiserum from convalescent patients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g001">Figure
            1</xref>B). Given the reduced amount of N present in the lysate of
          icGDO3-S–infected cells, the reduced intensity of the GDO3-S band probed with
          either anti–VRP-S mouse sera or the convalescent human serum is most likely due
          to the presence of lower GDO3-S protein rather than a marked difference in antibody
          specificity between GDO3-S and Urbani-S. icGD03-S replicated efficiently in HAE cells,
          although its maximum titer was approximately 1 log lower than that of icSARS or Urbani
            (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g003">Figure 3</xref>C). To compare the growth
          of icSARS and icGDO3-S in animals, 6-wk-old BALB/c mice were i.n. infected with
          10<sup>5</sup> pfu of either icSARS or icGDO3-S. At 2 d post-infection, icSARS-CoV mean
          lung titer was 6.8 ± 0.5 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g, whereas icGDO3-S titers were
          lower at 6.3 ± 0.2 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g (<italic>p</italic> =
          0.04). The mean lung titer of icSARS-CoV–infected mice on day 4 was 4.5
          ± 0.5 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g compared to icGDO3-S titers of 3.7 ±
          0.3 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.04). By the seventh day, virus replication in the
          lungs of three of five mice infected with icSARS-CoV and four of five mice infected with
          icGDO3-S fell below the limit of detection (50 pfu/g). Average icSARS-CoV and icGDO3-S
          titers were similar on day 7 with 1.7 ± 0.1 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g and 1.8
          ± 0.1 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g (<italic>p</italic> = 0.9),
          respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g003">Figure 3</xref>D).</p>
        <fig id="pmed-0030525-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Synthetic Reconstruction of icGD03-S</title>
            <p>(A) Unrooted phylogenetic gene tree of 35 SARS isolates ranging from early, middle,
              and late phases of the 2002–2003 epidemic to 2003–2004 animal
              isolates. Branch confidence values are shown as posterior probabilities. The three
              human isolates that fall within the cluster otherwise isolated from animals (shown in
              boxes), GZ0402, GD03, and GZ0401, may represent infections in which a human acquired
              the virus from a Himalayan palm civet.</p>
            <p>(B) The GDO3-S glycoprotein. Amino acid changes unique to the GDO3-S with the GDO3-S
              amino acid listed on the left and the corresponding Urbani to the right. The GDO3-S
              amino acid changes are shown in relation to the S1 and S2 subunits, the receptor
              binding domain (RBD), heptad repeats one (HR1) and two (HR2), the transmembrane domain
              (TM), and known neutralizing epitopes. Two mutations that arose during tissue culture
              passage of the chimeric icGDO3-S are shown in red.</p>
            <p>(C) Growth curves of the Urbani strain of SARS-CoV (diamond, solid line), the
              recombinant Urbani icSARS (squares, dashed line), and the recombinant chimeric virus
              icGDO3-S (triangles, dotted line) in human airway epithelial cells.</p>
            <p>(D) Comparing growth of icSARS-CoV to icGDO3-S in the lungs of mice. Six-week-old
              female BALB/C mice were infected with icSARS-CoV or icGDO3-S (<italic>n</italic>
              = 5 per group). The individual titer of each mouse is represented by a
              filled circle, and the mean titer of the group is represented as a solid bar.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To evaluate VRP protection against short-term heterologous challenge, groups of eight
          animals were primed at 7 wk of age with 10<sup>6</sup> IU of VRP-S, VRP-N,
          VRP-S+N, or VRP-HA, boosted 3 wk later, and then challenged 7 wk post-boost with
            10<sup>5</sup> pfu of icGD03-S (summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, experiment 3). Lungs were harvested 2 d after
          challenge. VRP-S and VRP-S+N protected (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Fisher
          exact test for both VRP-S and VRP-S+N groups relative to VRP-HA) against
          heterologous icGD03-S recombinant virus replication (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g004">Figure 4</xref>A). Although high titers of virus were detected
          in VRP-N– and mock-vaccinated animals with mean titers of 6.3 ± 0.1
          and 7.0 ± 0.1 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g, respectively, the
          VRP-N–vaccinated animals had a lower mean titer (<italic>p</italic> &lt;
          0.001).</p>
        <fig id="pmed-0030525-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>VRP-S Induces Short-Term Protection against icGDO3-S in Young and Partial
              Protection in Old Mice</title>
            <p>(A) Lung titers of BALB/c mice vaccinated and boosted with 10<sup>6</sup> IU of
              VRP-S, VRP-N, a combination of VRP-S plus VRP-N (VRP-S+N), or mock vaccinated
              with PBS, then challenged with 10<sup>5</sup> pfu of icGDO3-S challenge
              (<italic>n</italic> = 8 per group). Lungs were harvested 2 d
              post-challenge.</p>
            <p>(B) Lung titers of aged BALB/c mice vaccinated at greater than 26 wk of age, boosted
              4 wk later, then challenged 12 wk post-boost with icGDO3-S (<italic>n</italic>
              = 7 VRP-N, <italic>n</italic> = 8 for other groups). Tissue was
              harvested 4 d post-challenge.</p>
            <p>(C) SARS CoV specific in situ signal (black arrows) was observed in the lungs of
              senescent mice that were vaccinated with PBS (unpublished data) or VRP-N (a) and
              challenged with icGDO3-S, although overall, the signal appeared to be less intense
              than that observed in the icSARS challenge animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g002">Figure 2</xref>C). Vaccination with VRP-S (b) or
              VRP-S+N (c) failed to induce complete protection from icGD03-S challenge, as
              sections from two of five S- and three of four S+N-vaccinated animals
              exhibited signal above that of uninfected controls.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>SARS-CoV vaccines should confer protection to elderly subjects who face infection with a
          new variant of the virus. To model this scenario, we vaccinated 6-mo-old to 1-y-old BALB/c
          retired breeders with 10<sup>6</sup> IU of VRP-S, VRP-N, VRP-S+N, or PBS, boosted
          them 4 wk later, and then challenged them 32 wk post-boost with 10<sup>5</sup> pfu of
          icGDO3-S (summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>,
          experiment 4). At 4 d post-infection, mean titers in the lungs of animals vaccinated with
          VRP-N and PBS were similar at 4.4 ± 0.5 and 4.7 ± 0.6
          log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g (<italic>p</italic> = 0.2), respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g004">Figure 4</xref>B). VRP-S vaccination provided
          partial protection when compared to the PBS control group (<italic>p</italic> =
          0.026, Fisher exact test), with the lungs of three of eight animals positive for viral
          replication at a mean titer of 2.9 ± 1.8 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g. All eight of
          the lungs harvested from the VRP-S+N–vaccinated animals were positive
          for viral replication, although a mean titer of 3.5 ± 1.2 log<sub>10</sub>
          pfu/g was comparable to the mean titer for VRP-S–vaccinated mice
          (<italic>p</italic> = 0.4) and reduced relative to the PBS control
          (<italic>p</italic> = 0.02). The presence of SARS-CoV replication in the lungs
          of control and vaccinated animals was confirmed by in situ hybridization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g004">Figure 4</xref>C). SARS-CoV N-specific riboprobe
          was hybridized to lung sections of mice from PBS-, VRP-N–, VRP-S–, and
          VRP-S+N–vaccinated groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g004">Figure 4</xref>C). All tested lung sections from PBS mocks (unpublished data) and
          VRP-N–vaccinated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g004">Figure 4</xref>C,
          image a) animals exhibited in situ signal (arrows), although the signal did not appear to
          be as intense as that of the icSARS-CoV–infected animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g002">Figure 2</xref>C). Lungs of the VRP-S–vaccinated
          animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g004">Figure 4</xref>C, image b) had two
          of five slides exhibiting SARS-CoV–specific signal above background levels,
          whereas VRP-S+N (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g004">Figure 4</xref>C,
          image c) had three of four slides.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Senescence and VRP-S Immune Responses</title>
        <p>Because neutralizing antibody has been reported to confer protection from SARS-CoV
          replication within the lungs of mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b013">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b016">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b028">28</xref>], it was of
          interest to determine whether the VRP-S vaccine established high neutralizing antibody
          levels that persisted until challenge. Plaque reduction neutralization titer (PRNT) of
          serum samples harvested prior to vaccination showed no neutralization of icSARS-CoV;
          similar results were noted from serum collected from mice vaccinated with the negative
          controls, VRP-HA or PBS (unpublished data). The 80% PRNT values
          (PRNT<sub>80</sub>), the dilution of serum at which plaque numbers are reduced by
          80% relative to virus treated with control sera, for VRP-S– and
          VRP-S+N–vaccinated animals at 5 and 53 wk post-boost against both
          icSARS-CoV and icGDO3-S were compared (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g005">Figure
            5</xref>A; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed-0030525-st001">Table
          S1</xref>). The mean reciprocal dilutions for the PRNT<sub>80</sub> of VRP-S and
          VRP-S+N against icSARS were measured at 796 ± 307 at 5 wk post-boost
          and 628 ± 363 at 53 wk. Sera from mice vaccinated with the combination of
          VRP-S+N had mean reciprocal PRNT<sub>80</sub> of 1,091 ± 361 and 370
          ± 179 at 5 and 53 wk, respectively. The initial neutralizing response in
          animals vaccinated with VRP-S and VRP-S+N was similar (<italic>p</italic>
          = 0.2 at 5 wk post-boost), and although there was not significant waning of the
          icSARS-neutralizing activity over the 48-wk period in the VRP-S–vaccinated
          animals (<italic>p</italic> = 0.3 Wilcoxin matched pairs signed-rank test),
          VRP-S+N serum was diminished by about 3-fold (<italic>p</italic> =
          0.03 Wilcoxin matched pairs signed-rank test). All tested sera remained above the lower
          limit of detection (1:100) and were sufficient to prevent icSARS replication within the
          lungs of challenged animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g002">Figure
          2</xref>B). The neutralizing activity of sera from the vaccinated animals was more
          effective against the vaccine strain than against heterologous icGDO3-S virus for both
          sera harvests and vaccine combinations. The reciprocal dilutions for the PRNT<sub>80</sub>
          of the VRP-S samples at 5 wk post-boost were below the limit of detection, whereas two
          samples of the week 53 bleed were measured above the limit of detection with a mean value
          of 112 ± 28. The icGDO3-S PRNT<sub>80</sub> measurements for VRP-S+N
          at weeks 5 and 53 post-boost were below the limit of detection with one exception for each
          time point: one mouse was measured to have a PRNT<sub>80</sub> of 124 at 5 wk, for an
          average titer of 103 ± 8, and another a PRNT<sub>80</sub> of 107 at 53 wk
          post-boost, an average of 101 ± 3.</p>
        <fig id="pmed-0030525-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>An 80% Plaque Reduction Neutralization Titers (PRNT<sub>80</sub>) for
              VRP-S and VRP-S+N Hyperimmune Serum</title>
            <p>(A) Mice vaccinated young: icSARS-CoV (left) and icGDO3-S (right) PRNT<sub>80</sub>
              for VRP-S immune serum (experiment 2) collected at 5 wk post-boost (<italic>n</italic>
              = 5) and 53 wk post-boost (<italic>n</italic> = 8).</p>
            <p>(B) Mice vaccinated old: icSARS (left) and icGDO3-S (right) PRNT<sub>80</sub> values
              for VRP-S and VRP-S+N immune serum (experiment 4) at 12 and 29 wk post-boost
                (<italic>n</italic> = 6 for icSARS; <italic>n</italic> = 5 for
              icGDO3-S). The PRNT<sub>80</sub> values for individual animals are show as black
              circles, and the mean value is shown as a solid bar. The limits of detection (1:1,600
              upper and 1:100 lower) are represented by horizontal dotted lines.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Given that the VRP-S vaccine's ability to provide long-term protection was likely due to
          the strong SARS-CoV–neutralizing response induced in vaccinated mice, we
          measured the PRNT<sub>80</sub> of the VRP-S immune sera from mice vaccinated when old
            (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, experiment 4) to
          determine if the incomplete protection seen in that study could be linked to a reduced
          neutralizing antibody response in the senescent animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g005">Figure 5</xref>B; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed-0030525-st001">Table S1</xref>). Against the vaccine strain, the reciprocal
          dilutions of the mean PRNT<sub>80</sub> were 170 ± 82 with two of six samples
          falling below the limit of detection for VRP-S mice at 12 wk and 142 ± 65 at 29
          wk post-boost with four of six falling below the limit of detection. Sera from the
          VRP-S+N–inoculated mice had PRNT<sub>80</sub> values falling near or
          below the limit of detection with only one measurable sample at 114, for an average of 103
          ± 6 and no icSARS-neutralizing ability detected at week 29. Against icGDO3-S,
          the VRP-S PRNT<sub>80</sub> values were below the limit of detection with the exception of
          a single VRP-S–vaccinated animal showing a neutralizing titer of 179 at 12 wk
          post-boost, for an average dilution of 116 ± 35 for the group. Sera harvested
          from these animals exhibited a marked reduction in neutralizing ability when compared to
          the response in animals vaccinated when young, even against the vaccine strain
          (<italic>p</italic> = 0.008 for VRP-S week 5 versus VPP-S week 12 post-boost;
            <italic>p</italic> = 0.006 VRP-S+N week 5 versus VRP-S+N
          week 12 post-boost). A strong anti–SARS-CoV neutralizing response was not
          induced by the VRP vaccines when administered to senescent mice.</p>
        <p>ELISAs for total IgG specific for SARS-S and influenza-HA were performed to compare the
          VRP vaccines' ability to induce antibody to those antigens in mice vaccinated when young
          or senescent. ELISA for SARS-S was performed on sera collected prechallenge from the
          VRP-S– and VRP-S+N–vaccinated mice of experiments 2 and 4
            (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g006">Figure 6</xref>A). Mice vaccinated young
          with VRP-S (experiment 2) had an average log<sub>10</sub> half-maximum ELISA titer of 2.6
          ± 0.6 at 53 wk post-boost, whereas that of the senescent animals was
          approximately a log lower at 1.5 ± 0.9 at 29 weeks post-boost
          (<italic>p</italic> = 0.007). The difference between animals of the two age
          groups was even more striking when anti-S IgG levels were compared in the VRP-S+N
          mice. The animals vaccinated young with VRP-S+N had an average titer of 2.6
          ± 0.3, whereas the average for senescent animals was at the limit of detection
          of 0.02 log<sub>10</sub> half-maximum ELISA titer. To verify that the reduced ability of
          the senescent animals to mount specific antibody responses was not limited to the SARS-S
          antigen; anti-HA IgG titers were compared in mice vaccinated with VRP-HA. The average
          anti-HA titer of animals vaccinated when young was 4.7 ± 0.2, whereas the titer
          of the vaccinated senescent mice was approximately one-tenth the size with a mean titer of
          3.7 ± 0.8 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). The reduced ability of sera
          harvested from senescent animals to neutralize virus correlates to a general reduction in
          antigen-specific antibody production.</p>
        <fig id="pmed-0030525-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>ELISA Titers for Anti-S and Anti-HA igG in Vaccinated Animals</title>
            <p>(A) Log<sub>10</sub> half-maximum ELISA titers for anti-S IgG antibody in aged mice
              vaccinated with VRP-S or VRP-S+N when young (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, experiment 2) or senescent (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, experiment 4). Values
              represent mean values, and error bars indicate standard deviation.</p>
            <p>(B) Log<sub>10</sub> half-maximum ELISA titers for anti-HA IgG antibody in aged mice
              vaccinated when young (experiment 2) or senescent (experiment 4).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>Pathologic Findings in Mice</title>
        <p>Lungs from the vaccinated senescent mice challenge studies (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, experiments 2 and 4) were sectioned, hematoxylin
          and eosin stained, and analyzed for pathology. Though there was some animal-to-animal
          variation, in general only minor inflammatory changes were observed in the senescent
          control mice challenged with either icSARS or icGDO3-S (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g007">Figures 7</xref>C, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g008">8</xref>A, and 8B). However, following SARS-CoV challenge in senescent mice, the
          N-vaccinated groups exhibited more marked bronchiolitis and alveolitis, as well as a
          conspicuous perivascular and peribronchiolar interstitial accumulation of numerous
          mononuclear leukocytes (mainly lymphocytes and plasma cells; i.e., lymphoplasmacytic
          cuffing) and increased numbers of widely scattered eosinophils (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g007">Figures 7</xref>B, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g007">7</xref>C, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g008">8</xref>C, and 8D). Upon
          SARS-CoV challenge, the animals vaccinated with S+N also exhibited a similar, but
          less severe, lymphoplasmacytic infiltration around pulmonary vessels and bronchiolar
          airways, although alveolitis and eosinophil infiltration were not a prominent feature in
          these animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g007">Figures 7</xref>F, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g008">8</xref>G, and 8H). The lungs of animals
          vaccinated with VRP-S were similar to VRP-HA– or PBS mock-vaccinated animals
          with minimal lymphoplasmacytic cell accumulations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g007">Figures 7</xref>E, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g008">8</xref>E, and 8F). Therefore, not only did N vaccination fail to control SARS-CoV
          replication within the lungs, but N vaccination also resulted in an enhanced
          immunopathology in the lungs of the senescent animals upon viral challenge.</p>
        <fig id="pmed-0030525-g007" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Pathogenic Findings Following Homologous Challenge</title>
            <p>Light photomicrographs of representative histologic lung sections (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, experiment 2) taken from an
              untreated control mouse (A), a VRP-N–vaccinated mouse (B) and (D), a
              VRP-HA–vaccinated mouse (C), a VRP-S–vaccinated mouse (E), and a
              VRP-S– and VRP-N–treated mouse (F). No histopathology was evident
              in (A). A marked mixed inflammatory infiltrate composed mainly of mononuclear
              leukocytes (lymphocytes and plasma cells) and widely scattered eosinophils are evident
              in the perivascular and peribronchiolar interstitium (asterisk) in (B). Similar
              inflammatory cells are also present in bronchiolar (br) airways and alveolar airspaces
              along with enlarged and vacuolated alveolar macrophages (arrows). The box in (B)
              denotes the site of the light photomicrograph (D) that was taken at a higher
              magnification to better illustrate the lymphoplasmacytic inflammatory cell infiltrate
              with lesser numbers of eosinophils (arrows). Similar, but slightly less severe,
              perivascular inflammatory infiltrates (asterisk) are also present in (F), but without
              accompanying alveolitis. Minimal lymphoplasmacytic cell accumulations around the
              pulmonary arteriole (a) are evident in (C) and (E). All tissues were stained with
              hematoxylin and eosin. Bars denote the scale of the magnification. a, pulmonary
              arteriole; ap, alveolar parenchyma; br, bronchiolar lumen; e, surface epithelium of
              the bronchiole.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pmed-0030525-g008" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g008</object-id>
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Pathogenic Findings Following Heterologous Challenge</title>
            <p>Light photomicrographs of representative histologic lung sections (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, experiment 4) taken from a
              mock PBS–vaccinated mouse (A) and (B), a VRP-N–vaccinated mouse
              (C) and (D), a VRP-S–vaccinated mouse (E) and (F), or a
              VRP-S+N–vaccinated mouse (G) and (H). The boxes in (A), (C), (E),
              and (G) (200× magnification) denote the site of the light photomicrograph
              that was taken at a higher magnification (400×) to better illustrate the
              lymphoplasmacytic inflammatory cell infiltrates including eosinophils (yellow arrows).
              All tissues were stained with hematoxylin and eosin.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g008" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3f">
        <title>Duration of N-Induced Pathology</title>
        <p>In order to determine the kinetics of the VRP-N–associated immunopathology and
          whether this effect was age dependent, young and old VRP-N– or
          VRP-HA–vaccinated mice were challenged with icSARS and sacrificed on days 2, 4,
          7, and 14 post-challenge. Young (8 wk of age) or senescent (53 wk of age) female BALB/c
          mice were vaccinated with 10<sup>6</sup> IU of VRP-N or VRP-HA, boosted 7 wk later, then
          i.n. challenged with 10<sup>5</sup> pfu of icSARS-CoV 4 wk post-boost. Lungs were
          harvested on days 2, 4, 7, and 14, titered, and processed for histology (Summarized in
            <xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, experiments 5 and 6). In
          young mice, day 2 average lung titers were 7.5 ± 0.2 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g and
          8.1 ± 0.1 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g for the VRP-N– and
          VRP-HA–vaccinated animals, respectively. Day 4 average titers were 5.5
          ± 0.3 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g for VRP-N–vaccinated and 5.7
          ± 0.1 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g for VRP-HA–vaccinated mice. SARS titers
          in the VRP-N–vaccinated mice lungs had dropped to the limit of detection by day
          7, with two of the three lungs from VRP-HA–vaccinated mice showing measurable
          titers at a mean of 3.2 ± 0.3 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g. By day 14, virus was
          undetectable in either group. In senescent animals, the day 2 average lung titers were 8.2
          ± 0.2 and 8.5 ± 0.1 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g for the VRP-N–
          and VRP-HA–vaccinated animals, respectively. By day 4, the mean titers had
          dropped to 5.4 ± 0.6 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g for VRP-N–vaccinated
          animals and 5.7 ± 0.5 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g for the VRP-HA controls. On day 7,
          one VRP-N–vaccinated mouse had a detectable titer of 3.7 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g,
          whereas the lungs of two VRP-HA–vaccinated mice were positive for replication
          with a titer of 3.7 ± 0.5 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g. No virus was detected in
          either group on day 14 post–challenge.</p>
        <p>Though enhanced inflammation was observed in a subset of the VRP-N–vaccinated
          animals at day 2 post–infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g009">Figure 9</xref>B), the inflammatory infiltrates were readily apparent in both young and
          senescent animals at day 4 post-infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g009">Figure 9</xref>D and unpublished data) and were maintained at days 7 and 14
          post-infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g009">Figure 9</xref>F and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g009">9</xref>H). As had been noted previously,
          VRP-HA– and VRP-N–vaccinated animals also differed by the presence of
          eosinophils (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g010">Figure 10</xref>). At day 2
          post-infection, eosinophils were rarely seen in either VRP-HA– or
          VRP-N–vaccinated mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g010">Figure
          10</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g010">10</xref>B, respectively). In
          VRP-N–vaccinated animals, but not HA–vaccinated animals, eosinophils
          were widespread on days 4 and 7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g010">Figure
          10</xref>D and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g010">10</xref>F), but had largely
          cleared from the lungs by day 14 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0030525-g010">Figure
          10</xref>H). There was no apparent difference in severity between the young and senescent
          animals, suggesting that the immune pathology was specific to pre-existing N immunity, but
          was not age dependent (unpublished data).</p>
        <fig id="pmed-0030525-g009" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g009</object-id>
          <label>Figure 9</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Kinetics of VRP-N–Associated Inflammation</title>
            <p>Light photomicrographs of lung sections taken from VRP-HA– and
              VRP-N–vaccinated mice harvested at days 2, 4, 7, and 14
              post–icSARS-CoV challenge (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, experiment 5). Representative lung sections (200×
              magnification) comparing pulmonary inflammation between VRP-HA–vaccinated
              (A), (C), (E), and (G) and VRP-N–vaccinated (B), (D), (F), and (H) mice.
              Enhanced inflammation was evident by day 2 (A) and (B) in some
              VRP-N–vaccinated animals relative to lung sections of
              VRP-HA–inoculated mice. By day 4 post-infection (C) and (D), increased
              inflammation in VRP-N–vaccinated animals was widely apparent and was
              maintained through days 7 (E) and (F) and 14 (G) and (H).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g009" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pmed-0030525-g010" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g010</object-id>
          <label>Figure 10</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Identifying Eosinophils among Inflammatory Infiltrates</title>
            <p>The 400× magnification comparing eosinophil infiltration within the lung
              sections of VRP-HA–vaccinated (A), (C), (E), and (G) and
              VRP-N–vaccinated (B), (D), (F), and (H) mice (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, Experiment 5). At day 2 post-infection (A)
              and (B), eosinophils are rarely evident in the lungs of either VRP-HA (A) or VRP-N (B)
              mice. Day 4 post-infection (C) and (D), extensive eosinophils (yellow arrows) are
              present within the lungs of VRP-N–vaccinated mice. Widespread eosinophils
              are seen at day 7 post-challenge in VRP-N–vaccinated (F), but not
              VRP-HA–vaccinated (E) mice. By day 14 (G) and (H), eosinophils are rarely
              found among inflammatory cells of VRP-N–vaccinated mice. An identical
              experiment in old animals was performed simultaneously (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0030525-t001">Table 1</xref>, experiment 6), showed results
              indistinguishable from those of young mice (unpublished data). All tissues were
              stained with hematoxylin and eosin.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.g010" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3g">
        <title>Anti–SARS-N Antibody and Inflammation</title>
        <p>A passive transfer of anti-N, anti-HA, or anti-S sera into naive mice was performed to
          determine if the increased inflammatory response could be attributed to N-specific
          antibody, and to confirm that protection in S-vaccinated animals was mediated by
          S-specific antibody. Hyperimmune sera against VRP-HA (5.26 log<sub>10</sub> OD
          = 0.2 ELISA titer), VRP-N (5.6 log<sub>10</sub> OD = 0.2 ELISA
          titer), or VRP-S (5.5 OD = 0.2 ELISA titer) were intravenously transferred in
          150-μl volumes to groups of 8-wk-old or 43-wk-old naive BALB/c mice prior to
          challenge with 10<sup>5</sup> pfu of icSARS. Prior to challenge, serum was collected from
          mice and antigen-specific IgG titered to verify successful transfer. Young mice receiving
          anti–VRP-HA (<italic>n</italic> = 4) had a mean ELISA serum titer of
          2.8 ± 2.4 log<sub>10</sub> OD = 0.2, whereas senescent mice
            (<italic>n</italic> = 4) had a 2.9 ± 1.8 log<sub>10</sub> OD
          = 0.2 ELISA titer. The average serum titers for mice injected with
          anti–VRP-N were 2.7 ± 2.4 log<sub>10</sub> OD = 0.2 ELISA
          titer in young (<italic>n</italic> = 4) and 2.3 ± 1.9
          log<sub>10</sub> OD = 0.2 ELISA titer in senescent animals (<italic>n</italic>
          = 4). The anti–VRP-S log<sub>10</sub> OD = 0.2 ELISA
          titers were 3.1 ± 3.1 in young animals (<italic>n</italic> = 3) and
          2.9 ± 2.3 in senescent mice (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Lungs were
          harvested 4 d post-challenge, virus titers determined, and processed for histological
          analysis. Virus titers in the young mice were 5.0 ± 0.1 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g
          in the anti–VRP-HA group, 5.2 ± 0.1 in the anti VRP-N group, and
          below the limit of detection (2.4 log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g) in animals injected with the
          anti–VRP-S. Titers in the senescent mice were 5.3 ± 0.3
          log<sub>10</sub> pfu/g in the anti–VRP-HA group, 5.6 ± 0.6 in animals
          receiving the anti–VRP-N, and below the limit of detection in mice inoculated
          with anti–VRP-S. None of the mice displayed the enhanced inflammation noted in
          VRP-N–vaccinated animals (unpublished data), indicating that the observed
          immunopathology was not the result of antibody-dependent enhancement.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>VRP vaccine vectors induce robust mucosal and cellular immune responses against a large
        number of foreign antigens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b035">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b051">51</xref>] and were
        evaluated as candidate vaccines against homologous and zoonotic SARS-CoV challenge in young
        and senescent animals. Inoculation of mice with VRP-S induced antibody that recognized the
        epidemic SARS-CoV S glycoprotein as well as the S of a highly divergent strain, GDO3. The
        VRP-S vaccine induced long-term protection against challenge with the vaccine strain,
        complete short-term protection against icGDO3-S challenge, and partial protection against
        the divergent virus in the senescent mouse model. In contrast, vaccination with VRP-N failed
        to inhibit viral replication within the lungs of either young or senescent animals, resulted
        in enhanced immunopathology following viral challenge, and did not provide any measurable
        benefit when combined with VRP-S. The data suggest that vaccine regimens eliciting complete
        protection against antigenically heterologous forms of SARS-CoV in healthy individuals may
        not be sufficient for higher risk groups, including vulnerable elderly populations, and that
        there is a need for further testing of candidate vaccines that induce an anti-N response.</p>
      <p>VRP-S vaccination generated a strong neutralizing antibody response (PRNT<sub>80</sub>
        &gt; 1:600) that persisted for over a year and provided complete protection against
        challenge with the vaccine strain. In humans, neutralization titers have been measured from
        1:12 to 1:512 with a geometric mean titer of 1:61 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b052">52</xref>]. In a study evaluating an inactivated virus
        vaccine, neutralizing antibody titers greater than 1:114 resulted in complete protection
        against challenge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b021">21</xref>]. Mice inoculated with vesicular stomatitis virus vectors expressing
        SARS-S developed lower average neutralizing titers of 1:32, which were nevertheless
        protective against SARS-CoV infection for up to 4 mo after vaccination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b017">17</xref>]. We followed animals for over
        1 y after boost. To our knowledge, these are the first assays illustrating waning immune
        responses to a SARS-CoV candidate vaccine. On average, mice vaccinated when young with VRP-S
        did not show a significant reduction in neutralizing titers up to 53 wk post-boost, whereas
        mice vaccinated with the combination of VRP-S+N experienced about a 3-fold
        reduction over the same period of time. Although it is problematic to compare our
        neutralizing antibody titers to those induced by other SARS vaccines due to the use of
        different assays, we demonstrate protection from challenge with either vaccine or
        heterologous challenge virus strains in animals with an icSARS PRNT<sub>80</sub> greater
        than 1:114, near the assay's limit of detection. Vaccines that induce robust neutralizing
        titers against the homologous strain will likely confer protection against zoonotic
        reintroductions, especially in younger populations.</p>
      <p>As reported with other SARS-N–expressing DNA and vectored vaccines
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b015">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b024">24</xref>], VRP-N did not protect mice from SARS-CoV
        replication, and no benefit to vaccination with a cocktail of both VRP-S and VRP-N was
        observed, although an approximately half-log reduction in viral titers within the lungs of
        some VRP-N–vaccinated mice was occasionally observed. Although any reduction in
        SARS-CoV titer can be interpreted as a positive aspect of a potential vaccine, given the
        relationship between viral titer and SARS disease severity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b053">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b054">54</xref>], the increased number of lymphocytic and eosinophilic inflammatory
        infiltrates, which are also characteristic of the immune pathology observed with respiratory
        syncytial virus (RSV) infection following vaccination with formalin-inactivated RSV
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b055">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b056">56</xref>], raises concerns that vaccination with N alone
        will not only fail to effectively protect against SARS-CoV replication, but may result in
        vaccine-enhanced pulmonary disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b057">57</xref>]. N-induced pathology has not been previously reported, probably
        because most studies examined young mice at 2–3 d post-infection, prior to the
        infiltration of inflammatory cells into the lung. VRP-N–induced pathology was
        clearly evident by day 4 and persisted for 1–2 wk following wild-type virus
        challenge, suggesting the potential for serious complications in lung physiology and
        function. This finding has particular significance for SARS-N and inactivated SARS-CoV
        vaccines currently under development that also induce anti-N antibody and T cell responses
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b019">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b021">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b058">58</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b061">61</xref>], because they may lead to adverse effects. Therefore, caution is
        merited with respect to the inclusion of SARS-CoV N protein in any vaccine formulation. The
        passive transfer of anti-N antibody did not contribute to inflammation and leads us to
        hypothesize that it is the activity of SARS-N–specific T cells in the absence of
        effective neutralizing anti–SARS-CoV antibody that mediates the adverse response.
        It is interesting that a T<sub>h</sub>2–skewed cytokine profile is a hallmark of
        the RSV vaccine-enhanced disease, which raises the possibility that the N-specific immune
        response is skewed in a similar manner [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b062">62</xref>].</p>
      <p>SARS-CoV strain diversity was mostly confined to China where many human and animal isolates
        were not successfully cultured in vitro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b008">8</xref>]. Consequently, most available experimental
        strains, like Urbani, are nearly identical and do not reflect natural diversity
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b063">63</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b064">64</xref>]. Recent advances in synthetic biology used to
        reconstruct extinct viruses, or specific genes of those viruses, de novo from their
        nucleotide sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b065">65</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b067">67</xref>]
        provide the means for expanding the number of available SARS-CoV test strains. Using a
        comprehensive SARS-CoV genetic database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b031">31</xref>], we resurrected the divergent GDO3-S glycoprotein in the Urbani genetic
        backbone. The icGD03-S recombinant virus was identical to the molecular clone except for the
        presence of two mutations in S that likely evolved after transfection of full-length RNA and
        virus passage in Vero cells, similar to the cell culture adaptations reported in S for other
        SARS-CoV strains isolated from human clinical specimens and passaged in vitro
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b068">68</xref>]. The icGDO3-S
        CoV's sequence divergence from Urbani, efficient in vitro replication in HAE and Vero
        cultures, and robust in vivo replication in the mouse model, make it an excellent
        heterologous challenge inoculum for vaccine studies. The GD03 RBD is also present in many
        zoonotic isolates described in civets and raccoon dogs, supporting its use as a zoonotic
        model strain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b008">8</xref>].
        Furthermore, the reduced replication in HAE cultures of icGDO3-S compared to Urbani-CoV is
        consistent with the reduced pathogenesis noted in the GDO3 human case [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b053">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b054">54</xref>].</p>
      <p>Consistent with previous work comparing the susceptibility of pseudotyped lentiviruses
        bearing the S glycoproteins of various SARS strains to neutralization by anti-S (Urbani) IgG
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b031">31</xref>]<bold>,</bold>
        anti–VRP-S antibody demonstrated reduced neutralization of icGDO3-S relative to
        the vaccine strain. In spite of this, the VRP-S vaccine successfully provided short-term
        protection against the divergent virus. Vaccination of senescent animals produced
        significantly reduced antibody responses compared with younger mice, and when challenged
        with the heterologous icGDO3-S virus, protection was incomplete. However, any animal with a
          PRNT<sub>80</sub> value above 1:114 against icSARS showed reduced viral replication within
        the lungs following challenge with either the vaccine or icGDO3-S strains. As noted for the
        homologous challenge studies, the combination of VRP-S+N did not enhance protection
        from heterologous challenge, but may actually have weakened it, with senescent animals
        showing even lower anti-S antibody responses and an even higher rate of viral replication,
        albeit with reduced titers, and increased lung pathology. One possible cause for vaccine
        failure is the emergence of an escape mutant in an environment of suboptimal neutralization.
        However, initial data comparing the neutralization susceptibility of viruses isolated from
        these mice to the challenge stock refute this conjecture (unpublished data). Incomplete
        protection by a vaccine in immunosenescent animals and humans is well documented and is more
        likely the result of an age-related compromise in one or more stages of the immune response
        to the vaccine. For instance, antibody responses in the immunosenescent tend to offer less
        protection with limited switching to secondary isotypes, lower antibody levels in general,
        and production of antibody with lower affinities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b069">69</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b074">74</xref>]. Although we have not tested single-vaccine dose regimens, previous
        studies have demonstrated that these are efficacious against SARS-CoV challenge in young
        animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b017">17</xref>]. Given
        the low antibody titers following boost in senescent populations, single-vaccine dose
        formulations will likely prove ineffective. Rather, improving the VRP-S efficacy in older
        vaccinees may require additional vaccine boosts, the use of adjuvants, or other additional
        therapies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b075">75</xref>].
        Another likely contributing factor to vaccine failure in older animals was the resistance of
        icGDO3-S to neutralization relative to the vaccine strain, icSARS-CoV. At least three
        neutralizing sites have been identified in the SARS-CoV S glycoprotein, two of which map at
        the N-terminus and in the RBD of the S glycoprotein, and one to a weak third site near the
        carboxy-terminus of S. Given that most of the GD03 mutations map in and around the
        N-terminus and RBD in S1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b031">31</xref>], it is possible that either one or both of these critical epitopes are
        significantly different in icGD03-S, and likely explains the resistance to neutralization
        with antisera against Urbani-S. These data suggest that robust neutralizing titers should be
        induced by candidate vaccines to provide long-term protection from SARS-CoV infection,
        especially in the vulnerable senescent population and against heterologous strains.</p>
      <p>Earlier work had indicated that antibodies to the Urbani strain of SARS-CoV enhanced the in
        vitro infectivity of pseudotyped viruses bearing the S glycoprotein of zoonotic strains,
        primarily with strains SZ16 and SZ3, and raised the specter of S-vaccine–induced
        complications with newly emergent strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b031">31</xref>]. In contrast, it was shown that monoclonal,
        but not polyclonal, antibodies that neutralized the epidemic strain may enhance the
        infectivity of pseudotyped viruses bearing GD03-S glycoproteins, although the enhanced
        infection was marginal at best [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b031">31</xref>]. Our research with antibody directed against Urbani-S indicated that
        the polyclonal antibody neutralized icGD03-S on Vero cells, although less efficiently than
        the vaccine strain, which is consistent with the previous report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b031">31</xref>]. Moreover, in the young and
        senescent mouse models, VRP-S–vaccinated animals challenged with homologous or
        heterologous icGD03-S recombinant viruses did not display vaccine-mediated enhancement of
        virus replication or enhanced pathology. Because VRP-S vaccines induce broad neutralizing
        antibody responses that likely target multiple epitopes across the S glycoprotein, it is
        possible that the noted enhancement of infectivity with monoclonal antibodies is nullified.
        Indeed, recent work showed that antibody specific for the RBD of Tor-2–S,
        GDO3–S, and SZ3–S glycoproteins did not reproduce enhanced infectivity
        in pseudotyped viruses bearing SZ3-S and identified conserved epitopes that allowed all
        three strains to be effectively neutralized, raising hope that a single vaccine could be
        effective against widely divergent strains of SARS-CoV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b076">76</xref>]. Clearly, additional studies are needed with
        more heterologous strains in alternative animal models before the possibility of
        vaccine-induced enhancement of infection and pathology can be discounted.</p>
      <p>To our knowledge, this study is the first to demonstrate that a SARS-CoV vaccine conferred
        long-term protection into the period in which a host is most susceptible to SARS-CoV
        pathology: senescence. Furthermore, the VRP-S vaccination of young animals protected against
        challenge with a divergent strain of SARS-CoV, indicating that current vaccines may also
        provide protection from many zoonotic strains that might emerge in the future. Such cross
        protection has been observed among other vaccines, such as HA formulations for influenza
        virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b077">77</xref>] and VRP
        vaccines against norovirus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b078">78</xref>]. Inducing robust immune responses in older animals is more challenging,
        but VRP-S vectors provided some protection from icGDO3-S challenge, and did so without the
        enhanced pathology induced by the VRP-N vaccine.</p>
      <p>Because human infections have not been reported since 2004, animal models are essential for
        the development of SARS-CoV vaccines. The young mouse model provides readily available
        animals on a homogenous genetic background and efficient replication within the respiratory
        tract. The senescent mouse model adds the benefit of enhanced pathogenesis and mimicks the
        age-related susceptibility seen in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b032">32</xref>]. Although aging decreases B and T cell
        immunity and innate immune function in humans and mice, characterization of these immune
        deficiencies is incomplete in both species. SARS-CoV infection in senescent mice provides a
        key model to evaluate the mechanisms by which aging deters immune responsiveness to highly
        pathogenic emerging viruses like SARS-CoV and influenza virus, and develop key intervention
        approaches to enhance vaccine efficacy in the elderly. The expense and limited availability
        of other senescent species makes the mouse model invaluable.</p>
      <p>Important caveats must be considered while evaluating this work. Murine models of SARS
        disease have limitations. The disease progression in mice is faster than in humans, rodents
        and humans do not share the same symptoms, and virus infection is less severe; limitations
        that are also evident in the hamster, primate, and ferret models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b079">79</xref>]. These shortcomings
        necessitate that vaccine candidates be tested in other animal systems and underscore the
        critical need for the development of highly pathogenic challenge models for vaccine and
        therapeutic testing. This report does not provide a mechanism for the
        VRP-N–induced pathology nor provide solutions for minimizing potential risks
        associated with it. Although the passive transfer of anti–SARS-N serum did not
        reproduce the inflammation seen in VRP-N–vaccinated animals, these results must be
        interpreted with caution because the anti-N antibody levels in the recipient mice were lower
        than those of mice directly immunized by VRP-N.</p>
      <p>The data presented in this manuscript do reveal critical needs and potential complications
        in vaccine design, laying the foundation for continuing and future studies to improve the
        quality, safety, and efficacy of SARS-CoV vaccines. Our model systems provide a means for
        identifying the host factors that contribute to immune senescence and will allow us to
        evaluate whether changes in vaccine design or regimen will improve vaccine efficacy in
        senescent animals. The models provide clear rational to test candidate SARS vaccines in the
        hamster, ferret, and primate models in which pathology and clinical disease are more
        prominent following wild-type virus challenge. Our research provides a model for future
        experiments designed to characterize the components and inducers of the
        VRP-N–enhanced pulmonary inflammation, and suggests that vaccine regimens that
        contain N protein should be used with caution in human populations until further testing.
        The successful resurrection of a novel recombinant SARS challenge virus bearing zoonotic S
        glycoproteins suggests that it might be feasible to reconstruct other rare zoonotic
        SARS-CoVs that have never been successfully cultured, providing novel challenge viruses for
        vaccine and therapeutic drug testing against potential future zoonotic SARS introductions
        into human populations. Finally, these studies should encourage the development of senescent
        animal models of human disease and encourage vaccine testing and design against influenza,
        West Nile virus, and other pathogens that produce disproportionate disease burdens in the
        elderly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b080">80</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0030525-b081">81</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pmed-0030525-st001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0030525.st001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Titers and PRNT<sub>80</sub> Dilutions for Individual Senescent Mice</title>
          <p>(146 KB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <sec id="s5a">
        <title>Accession Numbers</title>
        <p>The GenBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Genbank" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Genbank</ext-link>) accession number for the GD03-S
          glycoprotein sequence is AY525636.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Marth Collier for VRP packaging, safety testing, and titering; Wrennie Edwards for
        the in situ hybridizations; and Susan Burkett for preparation of the HAE cultures.</p>
    </ack>
    
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>ELISA</term>
          <def>
            <p>enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>HAE</term>
          <def>
            <p>human airway epithelium</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>icGD03-S</term>
          <def>
            <p>recombinant chimeric virus encoding a synthetic S gene from the SARS-CoV strain,
            GD03</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>icSARS</term>
          <def>
            <p>recombinant Urbani strain of SARS-CoV</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>i.n.</term>
          <def>
            <p>intranasally</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>IU</term>
          <def>
            <p>infectious unit</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>N</term>
          <def>
            <p>nucleocapsid</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>OD</term>
          <def>
            <p>optical density</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>pfu</term>
          <def>
            <p>plaque-forming unit</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>PRNT</term>
          <def>
            <p>plaque reduction neutralization titer</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>RBD</term>
          <def>
            <p>receptor binding domain</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>S</term>
          <def>
            <p>spike</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>SARS-CoV</term>
          <def>
            <p>severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>UNC</term>
          <def>
            <p>University of North Carolina</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>VRP</term>
          <def>
            <p>Venezuelan equine encephalitis virus replicon particle</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>VRP-HA</term>
          <def>
            <p>Venezuelan equine encephalitis virus replicon particle expressing the influenza A HA
              protein</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>VRP-N</term>
          <def>
            <p>Venezuelan equine encephalitis virus replicon particle expressing the Urbani SARS-CoV
              nucleocapsid</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>VRP-S</term>
          <def>
            <p>Venezuelan equine encephalitis virus replicon particle expressing the Urbani SARS-CoV
              spike</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b001">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drosten</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunther</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Preiser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Werf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodt</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Identification of a novel coronavirus in patients with severe acute
            respiratory syndrome.</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <volume>348</volume>
          <fpage>1967</fpage>
          <lpage>1976</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b002">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ksiazek</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaki</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peret</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>A novel coronavirus associated with severe acute respiratory syndrome.</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <volume>348</volume>
          <fpage>1953</fpage>
          <lpage>1966</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b003">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>A follow-up study of 69 discharged SARS patients.</article-title>
          <source>J Tradit Chin Med</source>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>214</fpage>
          <lpage>217</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b004">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsoi</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-like virus in Chinese
            horseshoe bats.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>14040</fpage>
          <lpage>14045</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b005">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Identification of a novel coronavirus in bats.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>2001</fpage>
          <lpage>2009</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b006">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Bats are natural reservoirs of SARS-like coronaviruses.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>310</volume>
          <fpage>676</fpage>
          <lpage>679</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b007">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Isolation and characterization of viruses related to the SARS coronavirus
            from animals in southern China.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>302</volume>
          <fpage>276</fpage>
          <lpage>278</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b008">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <collab xlink:type="simple">The Chinese SARS Molecular Epidemiology Consortium</collab>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Molecular evolution of the SARS coronavirus during the course of the SARS
            epidemic in China.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>303</volume>
          <fpage>1666</fpage>
          <lpage>1669</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b009">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Normile</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Infectious diseases. Mounting lab accidents raise SARS fears.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>304</volume>
          <fpage>659</fpage>
          <lpage>661</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b010">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hengge</surname><given-names>UR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Immune responses with DNA vaccines encoded different gene fragments of
            severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus in BALB/c mice.</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
          <volume>327</volume>
          <fpage>130</fpage>
          <lpage>135</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b011">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Inactivated SARS-CoV vaccine elicits high titers of spike protein-specific
            antibodies that block receptor binding and virus entry.</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
          <volume>325</volume>
          <fpage>445</fpage>
          <lpage>452</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b012">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takasuka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>A subcutaneously injected UV-inactivated SARS coronavirus vaccine elicits
            systemic humoral immunity in mice.</article-title>
          <source>Int Immunol</source>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1423</fpage>
          <lpage>1430</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b013">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>A DNA vaccine induces SARS coronavirus neutralization and protective
            immunity in mice.</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>428</volume>
          <fpage>561</fpage>
          <lpage>564</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b014">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>DNA vaccine of SARS-Cov S gene induces antibody response in mice.</article-title>
          <source>Acta Biochim Biophys Sin (Shanghai)</source>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>41</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b015">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchholz</surname><given-names>UJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bukreyev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamirande</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Contributions of the structural proteins of severe acute respiratory
            syndrome coronavirus to protective immunity.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>9804</fpage>
          <lpage>9809</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b016">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bisht</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bukreyev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus spike protein expressed by
            attenuated vaccinia virus protectively immunizes mice.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>6641</fpage>
          <lpage>6646</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b017">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapadia</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamirande</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subbarao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Long-term protection from SARS coronavirus infection conferred by a single
            immunization with an attenuated VSV-based vaccine.</article-title>
          <source>Virology</source>
          <volume>340</volume>
          <fpage>174</fpage>
          <lpage>182</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b018">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bukreyev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamirande</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchholz</surname><given-names>UJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkins</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Mucosal immunisation of African green monkeys <italic>(Cercopithecus
              aethiops)</italic> with an attenuated parainfluenza virus expressing the SARS
            coronavirus spike protein for the prevention of SARS.</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <volume>363</volume>
          <fpage>2122</fpage>
          <lpage>2127</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b019">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>See</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zakhartchouk</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petric</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mok</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Comparative evaluation of two severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS)
            vaccine candidates in mice challenged with SARS coronavirus.</article-title>
          <source>J Gen Virol</source>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>641</fpage>
          <lpage>650</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b020">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eickmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>SARS vaccine protective in mice.</article-title>
          <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>1312</fpage>
          <lpage>1314</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b021">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spruth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savidis-Dacho</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hitter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>A double-inactivated whole virus candidate SARS coronavirus vaccine
            stimulates neutralising and protective antibody responses.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>652</fpage>
          <lpage>661</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b022">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizutani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Induction of protective immunity against severe acute respiratory syndrome
            coronavirus (SARS-CoV) infection using highly attenuated recombinant vaccinia virus DIs.</article-title>
          <source>Virology</source>
          <volume>351</volume>
          <fpage>368</fpage>
          <lpage>380</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b023">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yount</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindesmith</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baric</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Rewiring the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV)
            transcription circuit: Engineering a recombination-resistant genome.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>12546</fpage>
          <lpage>12551</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b024">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Antibody responses to individual proteins of SARS coronavirus and their
            neutralization activities.</article-title>
          <source>Microbes Infect</source>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>882</fpage>
          <lpage>889</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b025">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saif</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Animal coronavirus vaccines: Lessons for SARS.</article-title>
          <source>Dev Biol (Basel)</source>
          <volume>119</volume>
          <fpage>129</fpage>
          <lpage>140</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b026">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Induction of SARS-nucleoprotein-specific immune response by use of DNA
            vaccine.</article-title>
          <source>Immunol Lett</source>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>237</fpage>
          <lpage>243</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b027">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>She</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marasco</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>An animal model of SARS produced by infection of <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Macaca mulatta</named-content> with SARS coronavirus.</article-title>
          <source>J Pathol</source>
          <volume>206</volume>
          <fpage>251</fpage>
          <lpage>259</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b028">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subbarao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAuliffe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fahle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Prior infection and passive transfer of neutralizing antibody prevent
            replication of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus in the respiratory tract of
            mice.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>3572</fpage>
          <lpage>3577</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b029">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corapi</surname><given-names>WV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngichabe</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baines</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>1992</year>
          <article-title>Monoclonal antibodies to the spike protein of feline infectious peritonitis
            virus mediate antibody-dependent enhancement of infection of feline macrophages.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>956</fpage>
          <lpage>965</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b030">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weingartl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czub</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czub</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marszal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Immunization with modified vaccinia virus Ankara-based recombinant vaccine
            against severe acute respiratory syndrome is associated with enhanced hepatitis in
            ferrets.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>12672</fpage>
          <lpage>12676</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b031">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Traggiai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Evasion of antibody neutralization in emerging severe acute respiratory
            syndrome coronaviruses.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>797</fpage>
          <lpage>801</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b032">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paddock</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Aged BALB/c mice as a model for increased severity of severe acute
            respiratory syndrome in elderly humans.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>5833</fpage>
          <lpage>5838</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b033">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baric</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yount</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burkett</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection of human ciliated
            airway epithelia: Role of ciliated cells in viral spread in the conducting airways of
            the lungs.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>15511</fpage>
          <lpage>15524</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b034">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caley</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irlbeck</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>Vaccination of macaques against pathogenic simian immunodeficiency virus
            with Venezuelan equine encephalitis virus replicon particles.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>371</fpage>
          <lpage>378</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b035">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heise</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>A single amino acid change in nsP1 attenuates neurovirulence of the
            Sindbis-group alphavirus S.A.AR86.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>4207</fpage>
          <lpage>4213</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b036">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chenna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugawara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Multiple sequence alignment with the Clustal series of programs.</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>3497</fpage>
          <lpage>3500</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b037">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees.</article-title>
          <source>Bioinformatics</source>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>754</fpage>
          <lpage>755</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b038">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>1992</year>
          <article-title>The rapid generation of mutation data matrices from protein sequences.</article-title>
          <source>Comput Appl Biosci</source>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>275</fpage>
          <lpage>282</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b039">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>MrBayes 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference under mixed models.</article-title>
          <source>Bioinformatics</source>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>1572</fpage>
          <lpage>1574</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b040">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ba</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Recombinant modified vaccinia virus Ankara expressing the spike
            glycoprotein of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus induces protective
            neutralizing antibodies primarily targeting the receptor binding region.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>2678</fpage>
          <lpage>2688</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b041">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamirande</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koprowski</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>A single immunization with a rhabdovirus-based vector expressing severe
            acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) S protein results in the production of
            high levels of SARS-CoV-neutralizing antibodies.</article-title>
          <source>J Gen Virol</source>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <fpage>1435</fpage>
          <lpage>1440</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b042">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakhatskyy</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mboudoudjeck</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Epitope mapping and biological function analysis of antibodies produced by
            immunization of mice with an inactivated Chinese isolate of severe acute respiratory
            syndrome-associated coronavirus (SARS-CoV).</article-title>
          <source>Virology</source>
          <volume>334</volume>
          <fpage>134</fpage>
          <lpage>143</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b043">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Identification of a critical neutralization determinant of severe acute
            respiratory syndrome (SARS)-associated coronavirus: importance for designing SARS
            vaccines.</article-title>
          <source>Virology</source>
          <volume>334</volume>
          <fpage>74</fpage>
          <lpage>82</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b044">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keng</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fielding</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Amino acids 1055 to 1192 in the S2 region of severe acute respiratory
            syndrome coronavirus S protein induce neutralizing antibodies: implications for the
            development of vaccines and antiviral agents.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>3289</fpage>
          <lpage>3296</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b045">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakhatskyy</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Identification of two neutralizing regions on the severe acute respiratory
            syndrome coronavirus spike glycoprotein produced from the mammalian expression system.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>1906</fpage>
          <lpage>1910</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b046">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Potent neutralization of severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS)
            coronavirus by a human mAb to S1 protein that blocks receptor association.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>2536</fpage>
          <lpage>2541</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b047">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenough</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babcock</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>WD</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Development and characterization of a severe acute respiratory
            syndrome-associated coronavirus-neutralizing human monoclonal antibody that provides
            effective immunoprophylaxis in mice.</article-title>
          <source>J Infect Dis</source>
          <volume>191</volume>
          <fpage>507</fpage>
          <lpage>514</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b048">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>A human SARS-CoV neutralizing antibody against epitope on S2 protein.</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
          <volume>333</volume>
          <fpage>186</fpage>
          <lpage>193</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b049">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tripp</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Monoclonal antibodies to SARS-associated coronavirus (SARS-CoV):
            Identification of neutralizing and antibodies reactive to S, N, M and E viral proteins.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol Methods</source>
          <volume>128</volume>
          <fpage>21</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b050">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yount</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahrling</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Reverse genetics with a full-length infectious cDNA of severe acute
            respiratory syndrome coronavirus.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>12995</fpage>
          <lpage>13000</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b051">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reap</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Alphavirus replicon particles as candidate HIV vaccines.</article-title>
          <source>IUBMB Life</source>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>209</fpage>
          <lpage>211</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b052">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>A serological survey on neutralizing antibody titer of SARS convalescent
            sera.</article-title>
          <source>J Med Virol</source>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <fpage>147</fpage>
          <lpage>150</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b053">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Initial viral load and the outcomes of SARS.</article-title>
          <source>CMAJ</source>
          <volume>171</volume>
          <fpage>1349</fpage>
          <lpage>1352</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b054">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Viral loads in clinical specimens and SARS manifestations.</article-title>
          <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>1550</fpage>
          <lpage>1557</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b055">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Speelman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bortell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>1996</year>
          <article-title>Generation of atypical pulmonary inflammatory responses in BALB/c mice
            after immunization with the native attachment (G) glycoprotein of respiratory syncytial
            virus.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <fpage>7783</fpage>
          <lpage>7791</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b056">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Swart</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuiken</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Timmerman</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Amerongen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Den Hoogen</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Immunization of macaques with formalin-inactivated respiratory syncytial
            virus (RSV) induces interleukin-13-associated hypersensitivity to subsequent RSV
            infection.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>11561</fpage>
          <lpage>11569</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b057">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canchola</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyles</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chanock</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>1969</year>
          <article-title>Respiratory syncytial virus disease in infants despite prior administration
            of antigenic inactivated vaccine.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>422</fpage>
          <lpage>434</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b058">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lien</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Immunological characterizations of the nucleocapsid protein based SARS
            vaccine candidates.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>3100</fpage>
          <lpage>3108</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b059">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Generation and characterization of DNA vaccines targeting the nucleocapsid
            protein of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>4638</fpage>
          <lpage>4645</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b060">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Immunogenicity of SARS inactivated vaccine in BALB/c mice.</article-title>
          <source>Immunol Lett</source>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          <lpage>143</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b061">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zakhartchouk</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petric</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babiuk</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Augmentation of immune responses to SARS coronavirus by a combination of
            DNA and whole killed virus vaccines.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>4385</fpage>
          <lpage>4391</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b062">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varga</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braciale</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Vbeta14(+) T cells mediate the vaccine-enhanced disease induced by
            immunization with respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) G glycoprotein but not with
            formalin-inactivated RSV.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>8753</fpage>
          <lpage>8760</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b063">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Radun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niedrig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ammon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>SARS: Retrospective cohort study among German guests of the Hotel
            ‘M', Hong Kong.</article-title>
          <source>Euro Surveill</source>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>228</fpage>
          <lpage>230</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b064">
        <label>64</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skowronski</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Astell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunham</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Low</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petric</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS): A year in review.</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Med</source>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>357</fpage>
          <lpage>381</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b065">
        <label>65</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cello</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wimmer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Chemical synthesis of poliovirus cDNA: Generation of infectious virus in
            the absence of natural template.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>297</volume>
          <fpage>1016</fpage>
          <lpage>1018</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b066">
        <label>66</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchison</surname><given-names>CA</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfannkoch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venter</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Generating a synthetic genome by whole genome assembly: phiX174
            bacteriophage from synthetic oligonucleotides.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>15440</fpage>
          <lpage>15445</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b067">
        <label>67</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobasa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halfmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Enhanced virulence of influenza A viruses with the haemagglutinin of the
            1918 pandemic virus.</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>431</volume>
          <fpage>703</fpage>
          <lpage>707</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b068">
        <label>68</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srikantiah</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reagan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pletz</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>SARS clinical features, United States, 2003.</article-title>
          <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>138</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b069">
        <label>69</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murasko</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Role of humoral and cell-mediated immunity in protection from influenza
            disease after immunization of healthy elderly.</article-title>
          <source>Exp Gerontol</source>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>427</fpage>
          <lpage>439</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b070">
        <label>70</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blasco</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>Impaired germinal center reaction in mice with short telomeres.</article-title>
          <source>Embo J</source>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>472</fpage>
          <lpage>481</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b071">
        <label>71</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelsoe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>1997</year>
          <article-title>Immunosenescence and germinal center reaction.</article-title>
          <source>Immunol Rev</source>
          <volume>160</volume>
          <fpage>63</fpage>
          <lpage>77</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b072">
        <label>72</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frasca</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blomberg</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Humoral immune response and B-cell functions including immunoglobulin class
            switch are downregulated in aged mice and humans.</article-title>
          <source>Semin Immunol</source>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>378</fpage>
          <lpage>384</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b073">
        <label>73</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cerny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>1997</year>
          <article-title>Age-related changes in antibody repertoire: Contribution from T cells.</article-title>
          <source>Immunol Rev</source>
          <volume>160</volume>
          <fpage>55</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b074">
        <label>74</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McElhaney</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>The unmet need in the elderly: Designing new influenza vaccines for older
            adults.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>S10</fpage>
          <lpage>S25</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b075">
        <label>75</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frech</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenney</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spyr</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viret</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Improved immune responses to influenza vaccination in the elderly using an
            immunostimulant patch.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>946</fpage>
          <lpage>950</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b076">
        <label>76</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lustigman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farzan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Cross-neutralization of human and palm civet severe acute respiratory
            syndrome coronaviruses by antibodies targeting the receptor-binding domain of spike
            protein.</article-title>
          <source>J Immunol</source>
          <volume>176</volume>
          <fpage>6085</fpage>
          <lpage>6092</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b077">
        <label>77</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Couch</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>An overview of serum antibody responses to influenza virus antigens.</article-title>
          <source>Dev Biol (Basel)</source>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>25</fpage>
          <lpage>30</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b078">
        <label>78</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>LoBue</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindesmith</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yount</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Multivalent norovirus vaccines induce strong mucosal and systemic blocking
            antibodies against multiple strains.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>5220</fpage>
          <lpage>5234</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b079">
        <label>79</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subbarao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Is there an ideal animal model for SARS?</article-title>
          <source>Trends Microbiol</source>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>299</fpage>
          <lpage>303</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b080">
        <label>80</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <year>1995</year>
          <article-title>From the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Pneumonia and
            influenza death rates—United States, 1979–1994.</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <volume>274</volume>
          <fpage>532</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0030525-b081">
        <label>81</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baraniuk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Resnick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arafat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilborn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Risk factors for encephalitis and death from West Nile virus infection.</article-title>
          <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>