<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PLoS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Med</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosmed</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1549-1676</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PMEDICINE-D-13-02214</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001598</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Essay</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious disease epidemiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Global health</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Infectious diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Sexually transmitted diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Gonorrhea</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Infectious disease control</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Public health</subject><subj-group><subject>Preventive medicine</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Molecular Diagnostics for Gonorrhoea: Implications for Antimicrobial Resistance and the Threat of Untreatable Gonorrhoea</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Molecular Diagnostics and Gonococcal Resistance</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Low</surname><given-names>Nicola</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Unemo</surname><given-names>Magnus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skov Jensen</surname><given-names>Jørgen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>Judith</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>Judith M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Institute of Social and Preventive Medicine, University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>World Health Organization Collaborating Centre for Gonorrhoea and other Sexually Transmitted Infections, Örebro University Hospital, Örebro, Sweden</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Microbiology and Infection Control, Statens Serum Institut, Copenhagen, Denmark</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>MRC-UCL Centre for Medical Molecular Virology, Division of Infection and Immunity, University College London, London, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Institute for Women's Health, University College London, London, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">low@ispm.unibe.ch</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>NL is a member of the Editorial Board of <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic>. The other authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Wrote the first draft of the manuscript: NL. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: MU JSJ JB JMS. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icmje.org/" xlink:type="simple">ICMJE</ext-link> criteria for authorship read and met: NL MU JSJ JB JMS. Agree with manuscript results and conclusions: NL MU JSJ JB JMS.</p></fn>
<fn><p>The Essay section contains opinion pieces on topics of broad interest to a general medical audience.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<elocation-id>e1001598</elocation-id><permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Low et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract abstract-type="toc"><sec>
<title/>
<p>This Essay from Nicola Low and colleagues discusses the importance of the nucleic acid amplification tests for rapid detection of N. gonorrhoeae and its resistance determinants, as well as the importance of ensuring their rational use, as priorities for controlling both gonorrhoea and antimicrobial resistance.</p>
<p><italic>Please see later in the article for the Editors' Summary</italic></p>
</sec></abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>No funding was received.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="5"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><boxed-text id="pmed-1001598-box001" position="float"><sec id="s1a">
<title>Summary Points</title>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item>
<p>Antimicrobial resistance and overuse of antimicrobials are serious threats to the treatment of gonorrhoea.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p><italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> susceptibility to extended spectrum cephalosporins is decreasing and treatment failures are spreading, but no new drug class is licensed to replace them for immediate treatment.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>Nucleic acid amplification tests are increasingly used to diagnose gonorrhoea but current commercially available tests do not detect antimicrobial resistance.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>Tests for gonorrhoea that allow individually tailored antimicrobial therapy at the first contact with health services will need to be point-of-care tests that can be integrated into the diagnostic process to give accurate results in around an hour.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>Development of nucleic acid amplification tests that incorporate rapid detection of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> and its resistance determinants and ensuring the rational use of antimicrobials are priorities for controlling both gonorrhoea and antimicrobial resistance.</p>
</list-item></list>
</sec></boxed-text><sec id="s2">
<title/>
<p>Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is making the clinical management of infections such as gonorrhoea increasingly difficult worldwide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Davies1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ison1">[3]</xref>. In between the discovery of penicillin and the emergence of multidrug resistant (MDR-NG) and extensively drug resistant (XDR-NG) strains <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ohnishi1">[4]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Tapsall1">[5]</xref>, gonorrhoea was considered unpleasant, but not particularly serious, because it was easily treated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ohnishi1">[4]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Unemo1">[7]</xref>. Experts increasingly describe <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> as becoming an untreatable superbug <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ohnishi1">[4]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Unemo1">[7]</xref> because of reports of MDR-NG and XDR-NG strains resulting in treatment failures with extended spectrum cephalosporins (ESCs), such as cefixime and ceftriaxone, from Europe, North America, Asia, and Africa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Unemo1">[7]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Lewis1">[9]</xref>. The World Health Organization (WHO) estimated that there were 106 million new uncomplicated gonococcal infections worldwide in 2008, the majority of cases in places with limited diagnostic and treatment options. If these infections become untreatable then complications, including pelvic inflammatory disease, ectopic pregnancy, tubal infertility, neonatal eye infections, and consequences such as facilitation of HIV co-transmission, will become more common <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Tapsall1">[5]</xref>.</p>
<p>The emergence of ESC resistance has coincided with the rapid expansion of molecular diagnostic testing for gonorrhoea (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-1001598-g001">Figure 1</xref>). PCR is an invention that revolutionised diagnostic testing in infectious diseases, as in many other fields of medicine. Diagnostic tests that amplify specific DNA or RNA sequences are known collectively as nucleic acid amplification tests (NAATs) and include PCR. The benefits of NAATs for pathogen detection are widely recognised <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Davies1">[1]</xref>. There are now commercially available NAATs for rapid detection of tuberculosis, including rifampicin resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Lawn1">[10]</xref>, and for methicillin resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) and its main resistance gene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Diekema1">[11]</xref>. Experience with rapid molecular diagnostics shows that the potential health gains are determined not by the technology but by its successful implementation in a diagnostic process <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Diekema1">[11]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Pai1">[12]</xref>. For tuberculosis, the time to diagnosis could be shortened from weeks to hours if the rapid test can be placed at the point of care. At present, culture-based antimicrobial susceptibility testing is still needed because the specificity of the rapid NAATs is too low to allow definitive decisions about treatment of either tuberculosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Lawn1">[10]</xref> or MRSA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Diekema1">[11]</xref>. Mathematical modelling suggests that the impact of rapid molecular diagnosis of tuberculosis in high HIV prevalence areas might be less than anticipated because the major gain is in early detection of less infectious smear-negative tuberculosis and the large reservoir of latent infection remains undetected <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Menzies1">[13]</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pmed-1001598-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001598.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Trend in number of cases of gonorrhoea diagnosed, NAAT testing for gonorrhoea, and selected antimicrobial resistance in genitourinary medicine clinics in England and Wales.</title>
<p>Cases of gonorrhoea are from Public Health England; percentages of tests done using NAATs are from UK audits of asymptomatic patients in genitourinary medicine clinics (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bashh.org/BASHH/BASHH_Groups/National_Audit_Group/BASHH/BASHH_Groups/National_Audit_Group.aspx?hkey=c17918b8-5c72-40bd-981f-632f89e45708" xlink:type="simple">http://www.bashh.org/BASHH/BASHH_Groups/National_Audit_Group/BASHH/BASHH_Groups/National_Audit_Group.aspx?hkey=c17918b8-5c72-40bd-981f-632f89e45708</ext-link>). Percentage of isolates resistant to ciprofloxacin and cefixime are from reference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Davies1">[1]</xref> and the 2012 report of the UK Gonococcal Resistance to Antimicrobials Surveillance Programme (GRASP, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hpa.org.uk/Topics/InfectiousDiseases/InfectionsAZ/Gonorrhoea/AntimicrobialResistance/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.hpa.org.uk/Topics/InfectiousDiseases/InfectionsAZ/Gonorrhoea/AntimicrobialResistance/</ext-link>), with values obtained using PlotDigitizer software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plotdigitizer.sourceforge.net/" xlink:type="simple">http://plotdigitizer.sourceforge.net/</ext-link>).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1001598.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The limitations of molecular diagnostic tests for sexually transmitted infections are less widely publicised and tend to focus on diagnostic test performance issues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Katz1">[14]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Zenilman1">[17]</xref>. In this Essay we discuss the benefits and disadvantages of molecular diagnosis of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> in the context of AMR and the implications of AMR for gonorrhoea treatment recommendations.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Current Management of Gonorrhoea</title>
<p>Prompt and appropriate treatment for patients with gonorrhoea and their sexual partners at the first contact with health services is the priority, endorsed by international guidelines <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World2">[18]</xref>. Delaying treatment to wait for diagnostic and antimicrobial susceptibility results is unacceptable for three reasons. First, urethritis, the most common clinical presentation in men, can cause purulent urethral discharge and severe pain, typically described as “pissing glass” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Pitts1">[19]</xref>. Second, sexual partners of people with diagnosed gonorrhoea have a very high risk of being infected <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Bignell1">[20]</xref>; rapid treatment is especially important for preventing re-infection and reducing onward transmission in groups with the highest rates of sexual partner change and AMR gonorrhoea, such as men who have sex with men and sex workers. Third, most gonococcal infections are diagnosed in settings with no, or limited, diagnostic facilities. WHO syndromic management flow charts recommend empirical antimicrobial treatment that should cure 95% or more cases of the most common causes of the syndrome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World2">[18]</xref>. The syndromic approach is reasonably accurate for the management of gonococcal urethritis in men but does not work well for cervical gonorrhoea in women or rectal gonorrhoea in men who have sex with men and women because most of these infections are asymptomatic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Clark1">[21]</xref>. Immediate treatment for symptomatic infections is a useful strategy when antimicrobials can be replaced once the cure rate falls below the threshold. But overuse of antimicrobials is now a serious problem for gonorrhoea because ESCs are “last-line” antimicrobials and no new drug classes are licensed to replace them <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Unemo1">[7]</xref>.</p>
<p>Where laboratory facilities are available, culture is a sensitive method for the diagnosis of genital <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> infections and is completely specific if adequate confirmatory tests are done <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Bignell1">[20]</xref>. <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> has fastidious growth requirements so highly nutritious selective culture media are needed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-1001598-t001">Table 1</xref>). Antimicrobial susceptibility can then be tested on cultured isolates but is, unfortunately, not always done. The laboratory tests for culture and susceptibility take 48 hours in total. Strengthening culture-based surveillance of local AMR patterns is an increasingly important tool for the detection of resistant strains and monitoring their spread <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref>, even if routine culture facilities are not available.</p>
<table-wrap id="pmed-1001598-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001598.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Advantages and disadvantages of molecular diagnostic testing for gonorrhoea in relation to culture and antimicrobial susceptibility testing.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pmed-1001598-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1001598.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Advantage of NAATs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disadvantage of NAATs</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ease of testing</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Can be done on non-invasive and self-collected specimens.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">More testing in low risk populations; low positive predictive value results in unnecessary treatment and potential harm to personal relationships.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case detection</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">More cases diagnosed. More accessible testing for hard to reach groups at high risk of infection, e.g., sex workers, men who have sex with men.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gains in increased case detection over culture could be offset if treating more cases results in more people who are susceptible to re-infection.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test performance</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">More sensitive than culture, especially in pharyngeal, rectal, and asymptomatic infections.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity decreased by cross-reactions and other sequence-related issues.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laboratory requirements</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Automation allows high throughput, reduces contamination.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expensive equipment and specialised training required.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In-house assays detect some AMR mutations and resistant strains.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No current antimicrobial susceptibility testing in commercial tests; Complete AMR testing cannot be performed.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment failure</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detection relies on clinical treatment failure or a late test of cure.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Licensing approval</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Approved for endocervical, vaginal, urethral, urine specimens</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not approved for pharyngeal or rectal specimens but can be used if laboratory evaluation satisfactory.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Advantages of Molecular Diagnostics for Gonorrhoea</title>
<p>There is no commercially available test for gonorrhoea that gives both same-day diagnosis and an antimicrobial susceptibility profile for <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic>. But the ability of NAATs to detect tiny amounts of nucleic acid has several advantages over culture for the diagnosis of an <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> infection. First, specimens for NAATs are easier to transport and store because they do not need the organism to be viable for detection. Second, NAATs can be automated and multiplexed detecting both <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> and <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic>, which is useful because both organisms cause similar clinical syndromes. Third, analysis can be done on non-invasive self-collected specimens like urine and vaginal swabs. These qualities mean that testing is easier in remote areas and can be extended to groups who were previously hard to reach but at high risk of both infection and AMR, such as men who have sex with men <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ison1">[3]</xref>. Fourth, NAATs are more sensitive than culture methods in general and particularly for asymptomatic infections in the pharynx and rectum (although no internationally available commercial NAAT has licensing approval for use on extra-genital samples) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Whiley1">[22]</xref>.</p>
<p>NAATs for <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> diagnosis became available in the early 1990s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Whiley1">[22]</xref> and are now the most common method used for gonorrhoea diagnosis in many countries, including the UK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-1001598-g001">Figure 1</xref>) and US <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Dicker1">[23]</xref>. The sharp increase in the number of diagnosed gonorrhoea cases since 2010 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-1001598-g001">Figure 1</xref>) is likely to be associated, in part, with both higher numbers of tests and the higher sensitivity of NAAT. In the US, the absolute number of gonorrhoea tests, estimated from data from manufacturers, increased from 2000 to 2004 but the percentage of tests that were done by culture fell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Dicker1">[23]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Disadvantages of Molecular Diagnostics for Gonorrhoea</title>
<sec id="s5a">
<title>NAATs do not routinely provide information about antimicrobial susceptibility of N. gonorrhoeae</title>
<p>Many of the limitations of NAATs for gonorrhoea diagnosis are the flip-side of their advantages. The main limitation for clinical management is that there is no viable organism so NAATs cannot provide data about minimum inhibitory concentrations for antimicrobials, which guide therapy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ison1">[3]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Unemo1">[7]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Katz1">[14]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ison2">[24]</xref>. If the health care professional takes a culture specimen and requests antimicrobial susceptibility testing that shows that the organism is resistant to the antibiotic prescribed, they can recall the patient within 2 to 3 days and prescribe individually tailored antibiotics. Or, if the culture-based test on an asymptomatic patient is positive, antimicrobial susceptibility testing allows specific antimicrobial therapy to be prescribed. All results from NAAT-diagnosed gonococcal infections have to be treated “blind” and commercially available NAATs do not currently detect any AMR determinants, so more NAAT-diagnosed than culture-diagnosed infections will be unnecessarily treated with ESC-based regimens.</p>
<p>Molecular methods for AMR <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> could give results faster (2–3 hours) than culture-based testing (48 hours). But the actual turnaround time, from ordering the test to changing patient care, is not much faster if the molecular test is run on batched samples once a day or every other day <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Diekema1">[11]</xref>. Tests for gonorrhoea that allow individually tailored antimicrobial therapy at the first contact with health services will need to be point-of-care tests with an actual turnaround time of around an hour <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Sadiq1">[25]</xref>. The weak correlation between <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> genetic resistance determinants, minimum inhibitory concentrations of ESC, and treatment outcome currently makes it difficult to use genetic markers to guide therapy for gonorrhoea <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Unemo1">[7]</xref>.</p>
<p>The first documented case of XDR-NG was diagnosed in a Japanese female sex worker who had a pharyngeal infection diagnosed initially by NAAT. A culture specimen was obtained two weeks later when she returned for treatment but there was no post-treatment culture specimen and she was lost to follow-up for three months, after receiving a second dose of ceftriaxone for presumed treatment failure diagnosed by NAAT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ohnishi1">[4]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ohnishi2">[26]</xref>. This case report shows how detection of AMR and treatment failure in NAAT-diagnosed gonorrhoea infections can be delayed. AMR will only be detected if the patient returns for a follow-up visit and a culture specimen is taken or if the patient returns with persistent symptoms. But antimicrobial resistant infections can persist asymptomatically. Pharyngeal gonorrhoea is often asymptomatic, might require higher doses of antibiotics to cure it <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Tapsall1">[5]</xref>, and is the location that is most difficult to diagnose by culture because of growth of other bacterial species and low bacterial load <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Young1">[27]</xref>. Many patients with gonorrhoea do not attend for a follow-up visit at all <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Price1">[28]</xref>. Resistant strains of gonorrhoea can therefore spread undetected if patients have not had a culture specimen taken at initial presentation and do not attend for follow-up.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5b">
<title>NAATs encourage over-testing and overtreatment of gonorrhoea</title>
<p>Simplified specimen collection and multiplex testing have disadvantages. Over-testing is facilitated by simultaneous testing for <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> on specimens taken for chlamydia screening in populations at low risk of gonorrhoea such as asymptomatic heterosexual adults tested in primary care <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Klausner1">[15]</xref>. In such settings, the predictive value of a positive test for gonorrhoea can be unacceptably low <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Katz1">[14]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Zenilman1">[17]</xref>, meaning that most people with a positive test are not infected. Overtreatment will occur if clinicians interpret initial positive gonorrhoea NAAT results as diagnosed infections without supporting information from a sexual history and/or a confirmatory test, as recommended <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Katz1">[14]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Bignell1">[20]</xref>. The negative consequences of false-positive diagnosis of gonorrhoea in a low risk population include breakdown of previously stable monogamous relationships <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Katz1">[14]</xref>. Whilst some NAATs for <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> show very high specificity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Golden1">[29]</xref>, their performance is inherently limited by genetic sequence variation between subtypes and cross-reactions with related <italic>Neisseria</italic> species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Whiley1">[22]</xref>. Overtreatment also has consequences for AMR. Unnecessary use of extended spectrum antimicrobials, such as ceftriaxone, increases the chances that commensal <italic>Neisseria spp.</italic> develop resistance and that resistance determinants will be transferred horizontally to <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Whiley1">[22]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Furuya1">[30]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5c">
<title>The cost of NAAT for gonorrhoea diagnosis</title>
<p>The high cost of NAATs can result in over-testing or under-testing, depending on who has to pay for the test and who makes the profit. Over-testing with NAATs occurs if health care systems reimburse laboratories for the number of analytic targets. Laboratories can charge twice for a NAAT to detect <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> and <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> even if the tests are done simultaneously in the same automated procedure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Klausner1">[15]</xref>. Under-testing can occur if the patient has to pay an out of pocket contribution, e.g., in primary care in the Netherlands (J van Bergen, 02.07.2013, personal communication) and in the Swiss health system (D. Oertle, 03.07.2013, personal communication). Patients at high risk of sexually transmitted infections might be unwilling to have check-ups if they are asymptomatic. Patients with symptoms might decline laboratory testing and opt for syndromic treatment with antimicrobials to cover the most common causative organisms. In the latter situation, blind antibiotic treatment and loss to follow-up could exacerbate the spread of AMR, which will, however, be undetected.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5d">
<title>Antimicrobial prescribing for gonorrhoea and AMR</title>
<p>Antimicrobial prescribing policies can also contribute to the emergence of AMR gonorrhoea <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Unemo1">[7]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ison2">[24]</xref>. Single dose oral treatment with a single class of antimicrobials is a goal of selecting drugs for sexually transmitted infections, including gonorrhoea <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref> to aid adherence to recommended regimens by both patients and health care professionals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ison2">[24]</xref>. Monotherapy, however, exerts selection pressure for resistance to emerge <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ison2">[24]</xref>. The WHO criterion for selecting regimens for which microbial resistance is “unlikely to develop or can be delayed” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref> is probably incompatible with the desire for single dose oral monotherapy. Efficacy of at least 95% is required for a first line antimicrobial that will be used for empiric treatment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref>. Cefixime was the last available single dose oral treatment and AMR surveillance data show that this no longer has the required level of efficacy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-1001598-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Clinical guidelines in Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Bignell1">[20]</xref> and the US <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Centers1">[31]</xref> now recommend combination treatment with intramuscular ceftriaxone and oral azithromycin. The addition of azithromycin is to delay the emergence of resistance to ESC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Bignell1">[20]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ison2">[24]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Centers1">[31]</xref>. High level resistance to azithromycin monotherapy has already emerged in the treatment of gonorrhoea, syphilis, chancroid, and <italic>Mycoplasma genitalium</italic> and experts have called for its use to treat all bacterial sexually transmitted infections to be limited <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ison2">[24]</xref>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s6">
<title>The Role of Molecular Diagnosis in the Spread and Control of Drug Resistant Gonorrhoea</title>
<p>Could the expansion of NAAT diagnosis for gonorrhoea exacerbate the continuing spread of AMR gonorrhoea? There is no definitive answer to this question yet but there are issues that should be investigated further, given the global increase in AMR, the lack of new first line antimicrobials for gonorrhoea treatment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Davies1">[1]</xref>, and the continued expansion of NAAT at the expense of culture-based testing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Unemo1">[7]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Dicker1">[23]</xref>. Countries with strong gonococcal antimicrobial surveillance systems and antimicrobial stewardship policies can mitigate the potentially negative impacts of a diagnostic shift to NAATs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ison1">[3]</xref>. But misuse and abuse of antimicrobials are widespread in many countries, and there is no strong surveillance of AMR, even in Japan where AMR is often detected first <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Tapsall1">[5]</xref>.</p>
<p>Another reasonable question is whether diagnostic test manufacturers, regulators, and researchers should have considered the implications that NAATs for gonorrhoea diagnosis might have on AMR before promoting and expanding their use so widely. The benefits of NAAT diagnosis for sexually transmitted infections often consider gonorrhoea and chlamydia together. The gains in sensitivity and technical complexity of NAATs compared to culture are smaller for <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> diagnosis than for <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Katz1">[14]</xref>, and AMR in chlamydia remains largely unexplored <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ison2">[24]</xref>. Early descriptions of commercial NAAT development for <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> do not appear to mention the inability to give AMR data as a potential problem <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Birkenmeyer1">[32]</xref>. This is surprising as gonococcal resistance was already a global public health issue at the time of development.</p>
<p>Academic research groups have developed in-house molecular tests for one or more genetic determinants of AMR <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Goire1">[33]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Magooa1">[35]</xref>. But very few of these tests detect mutations associated with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Balashov1">[36]</xref>, or strains exhibiting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Goire2">[37]</xref>, ESC resistance, which is the imminent threat. The ongoing evolution of ESC resistance, involving combinations of mutations in several genes, is a major challenge for test development. Tests that need continual updating with new target sequences are unlikely to be profitable for diagnostics companies in the short term. Supranational initiatives to invest in non-profit research might therefore be needed to overcome some of the challenges of feasibility and commercial viability.</p>
</sec><sec id="s7">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Current knowledge and practice about the use of NAAT for gonorrhoea diagnosis could be improved in several ways. First, all national and international guidelines about the use of NAAT for gonorrhoea diagnosis should specify situations in which culture-based testing and tests of cure are needed; transport media that can be used for both NAAT and culture will facilitate this. The cost of additional testing should be borne by the health system because the information about AMR would be used for the public health good. Second, in the absence of empirical diagnostic trials, mathematical modelling will be needed to explore the impact of NAAT-based rapid tests for the detection of AMR gonorrhoea on the spread of resistance and on clinical outcomes. Dynamic transmission models can capture the net effects of competing factors such as increased detection and treatment of gonorrhoea, increased re-infection risk, and reduced or delayed detection of AMR on the transmission of gonorrhoea and of resistant strains. Third, clinicians should follow international guidelines for the early detection of ESC resistant gonorrhoea and clinical treatment failure, which take into account the role of NAAT diagnosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref>. Fourth, the development of molecular tests to detect gonococcal resistance mutations should become part of the solution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Davies1">[1]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Unemo1">[7]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Sadiq1">[25]</xref>. Commercial diagnostics companies should invest more to develop and evaluate NAATs that detect both <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> and AMR determinants reliably, particularly in resource poor settings. The true cost of ignoring gonococcal AMR will include the costs of treating the infection and its complications as experienced in the pre-antibiotic era <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Smith1">[38]</xref>. AMR gonorrhoea needs to be conceptualised and tackled as part of the global problem of resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Davies1">[1]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-World1">[2]</xref> with strong proactive programs for phenotypic AMR surveillance to monitor and even pre-empt the emergence of critical levels of AMR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001598-Ison1">[3]</xref>. Improving the capabilities of NAAT diagnosis for gonorrhoea and ensuring their rational use is a priority for controlling both gonorrhoea and AMR.</p>
</sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Davies1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Livermore</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Annual Report of the Chief Medical Officer: infection and the rise of antimicrobial resistance</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>381</volume>: <fpage>1606</fpage>–<lpage>1609</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-World1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization (2012) Global action plan to control the spread and impact of antimicrobial resistance in <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic>. Geneva: World Health Organization.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Ison1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ison</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Town</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Obi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chisholm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Decreased susceptibility to cephalosporins among gonococci: data from the Gonococcal Resistance to Antimicrobials Surveillance Programme (GRASP) in England and Wales, 2007–2011</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>762</fpage>–<lpage>768</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Ohnishi1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Golparian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimuta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saika</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoshina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Is <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> initiating a future era of untreatable gonorrhea?: detailed characterization of the first strain with high-level resistance to ceftriaxone</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>3538</fpage>–<lpage>3545</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Tapsall1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tapsall</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ndowa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Unemo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Meeting the public health challenge of multidrug- and extensively drug-resistant <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic></article-title>. <source>Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>821</fpage>–<lpage>834</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Zappa1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zappa F (1979) Why does it hurt when I pee? Joe's Garage: Zappa Records.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Unemo1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Unemo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Emergence of multidrug-resistant, extensively drug-resistant and untreatable gonorrhea</article-title>. <source>Future Microbiol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1401</fpage>–<lpage>1422</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Allen1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rebbapragada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tijet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Molecular analysis of antimicrobial resistance mechanisms in <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> isolates from Ontario, Canada</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>703</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Lewis1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sriruttan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Golparian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gumede</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Phenotypic and genetic characterization of the first two cases of extended-spectrum-cephalosporin-resistant <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> infection in South Africa and association with cefixime treatment failure</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>1267</fpage>–<lpage>1270</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Lawn1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawn</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kranzer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicol</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whitelaw</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Screening for HIV-associated tuberculosis and rifampicin resistance before antiretroviral therapy using the Xpert MTB/RIF assay: a prospective study</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1001067</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Diekema1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diekema</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pfaller</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Rapid Detection of Antibiotic Resistant Organism Carriage for Infection Prevention</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>1614</fpage>–<lpage>1620</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Pai1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vadnais</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denkinger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Point-of-care testing for infectious diseases: diversity, complexity, and barriers in low- and middle-income countries</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e1001306</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Menzies1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menzies</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salomon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Population health impact and cost-effectiveness of tuberculosis diagnosis with Xpert MTB/RIF: a dynamic simulation and economic evaluation</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e1001347</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Katz1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Effler</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohye</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brouillet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>False-positive gonorrhea test results with a nucleic acid amplification test: the impact of low prevalence on positive predictive value</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>814</fpage>–<lpage>819</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Klausner1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klausner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The NAAT is out of the bag</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>820</fpage>–<lpage>821</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Herrmann1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Low</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klint</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A new genetic variant of Chlamydia trachomatis in Sweden: National study of impact on detection rates</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1462</fpage>–<lpage>1465</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Zenilman1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zenilman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaydos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>LCR testing for gonorrhoea and chlamydia in population surveys and other screenings of low prevalence populations: coping with decreased positive predictive value</article-title>. <source>Sex Transm Infect</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-World2"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization (2003) Guidelines for the Management of Sexually Transmitted Infections; Revised version 2003. Geneva: World Health Organization.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Pitts1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AMA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mischewski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fairley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Men, bodily change and urethritis: a qualitative study</article-title>. <source>Sex Health</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Bignell1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bignell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Unemo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>2012 European Guideline on the diagnosis and treatment of gonorrhoea</article-title>. <source>Int J STD AIDS</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Clark1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lescano</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Konda</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Syndromic management and STI control in urban Peru</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e7201</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Whiley1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whiley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tapsall</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sloots</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Nucleic acid amplification testing for <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic>: an ongoing challenge</article-title>. <source>J Mol Diagn</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Dicker1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dicker</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mosure</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steece</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Laboratory tests used in US public health laboratories for sexually transmitted diseases, 2004</article-title>. <source>Sex Transm Dis</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Ison2"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ison</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Antimicrobial resistance in sexually transmitted infections in the developed world: implications for rational treatment</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Infect Dis</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Sadiq1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadiq</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dave</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butcher</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Point-of-care antibiotic susceptibility testing for gonorrhoea: improving therapeutic options and sparing the use of cephalosporins</article-title>. <source>Sex Transm Infect</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>446</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Ohnishi2"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saika</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoshina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasaku</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Ceftriaxone-resistant <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic>, Japan</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Young1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moyes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Non-cultural detection of rectal and pharyngeal gonorrhoea by the Gen-Probe PACE 2 assay</article-title>. <source>Genitourin Med</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Price1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Menon-Johansson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <collab xlink:type="simple">National Audit Group of the British Association for Sexual Health and HIV</collab> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A national audit of gonorrhoea management</article-title>. <source>Int J STD AIDS</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Golden1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cles</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crouse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gudgel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Positive predictive value of Gen-Probe APTIMA Combo 2 testing for <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> in a population of women with low prevalence of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1387</fpage>–<lpage>1390</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Furuya1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Furuya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Onoye</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanayama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saika</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iyoda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Antimicrobial resistance in clinical isolates of <italic>Neisseria subflava</italic> from the oral cavities of a Japanese population</article-title>. <source>J Infect Chemother</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>302</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Centers1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Update to CDC's <italic>Sexually Transmitted Diseases Treatment Guidelines, 2010</italic>: Oral Cephalosporins No Longer a Recommended Treatment for Gonococcal Infections MMWR</article-title>. <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>590</fpage>–<lpage>593</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Birkenmeyer1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Birkenmeyer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Preliminary evaluation of the ligase chain reaction for specific detection of <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic></article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>3089</fpage>–<lpage>3094</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Goire1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goire</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tapsall</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Enhancing gonococcal antimicrobial resistance surveillance: a real-time PCR assay for detection of penicillinase-producing <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> by use of noncultured clinical samples</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>518</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Li1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ezaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Rapid detection of quinolone resistance-associated gyrA mutations in <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> with a LightCycler</article-title>. <source>J Infect Chemother</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Magooa1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magooa</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gumede</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Determination of <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> susceptibility to ciprofloxacin in clinical specimens from men using a real-time PCR assay</article-title>. <source>Int J Antimicrob Agents</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Balashov1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balashov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mordechai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adelson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gygax</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Multiplex bead suspension array for screening <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> antibiotic resistance genetic determinants in noncultured clinical samples</article-title>. <source>J Mol Diagn</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Goire2"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goire</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Limnios</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lahra</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Enhanced gonococcal antimicrobial surveillance in the era of ceftriaxone resistance: a real-time PCR assay for direct detection of the <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> H041 strain</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>902</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pmed.1001598-Smith1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coast</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The true cost of antimicrobial resistance</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <volume>346</volume>: <fpage>f1493</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance:</bold> Commissioned; not externally peer-reviewed.</p></fn>
</fn-group></back>
</article>