<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PLoS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosmed</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1549-1676</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PMEDICINE-D-12-03513</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001370</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Perspective</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Global health</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Public health</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Public Health and Epidemiology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Preventing Antiretroviral Treatment Interruptions among HIV/AIDS Patients in Africa</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mills</surname>
            <given-names>Edward J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Nabiryo</surname>
            <given-names>Christine</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Ottawa, Ottawa, Canada</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Stanford Prevention Research Center, Department of Medicine, Stanford University School of Humanities and Sciences, Stanford, California, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>The AIDS Support Organization (TASO), Kampala, Uganda</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">edward.mills@uottawa.ca</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Wrote the first draft of the manuscript: EJM. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: EJM CN. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icmje.org/" xlink:type="simple">ICMJE</ext-link> criteria for authorship read and met: EJM CN. Agree with manuscript results and conclusions: EJM CN.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other">
          <p><bold>Provenance:</bold> Commissioned; not externally peer reviewed.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>8</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <elocation-id>e1001370</elocation-id>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Mills, Nabiryo</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <related-article id="RA1" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="uri" vol="" page="1001369" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1001369"> <article-title>Toward an Understanding of Disengagement from HIV Treatment and Care in sub-Saharan Africa: A Qualitative Study</article-title></related-article>
      <abstract abstract-type="toc">
        <p>Edward Mills and Christine Nabiryo discuss a new qualitative study in <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> that offers insight into disengagement from HIV treatment care in sub-Saharan Africa.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>No specific funding was received to write this article.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="2"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <boxed-text id="pmed-1001370-box001" position="float">
      <sec id="s1a">
        <title>Linked Research Article</title>
        <p>This Perspective discusses the following new study published in <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic>:</p>
        <p>Ware NC, Wyatt MA, Geng EH, Kaaya SF, Agbaji OO, et al. (2013) Toward an Understanding of Disengagement from HIV Treatment and Care in Sub-Saharan Africa: A Qualitative Study. PLoS Med 10(1): e1001369. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plosmedicine.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1001369" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1371/journal.pmed.10001369</ext-link></p>
        <p>Norma Ware and colleagues conducted a large qualitative study among patients in HIV treatment programs in sub-Saharan Africa to investigate reasons for missed visits and provide an explanation for disengagement from care.</p>
      </sec>
    </boxed-text>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title/>
      <p>The roll-out of antiretroviral therapy (ART) in the poorest parts of the world is one of the greatest public health achievements in history. During the 1990s in Africa and elsewhere, thousands died every day for lack of access to treatment. Back then, courageous flight attendants at Lufthansa airlines, couriers at DHL company, and family members from the African diaspora found clever, albeit not always legal, ways to smuggle antiretrovirals into Africa and keep small numbers of patients alive. Visionary thinkers in organizations such as Médecins Sans Frontières (MSF) in South Africa and the Joint Clinical Research Centre (JCRC) in Uganda began treating patients while donors prevaricated over concerns about drug resistance, adherence challenges, and human resources logistics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Mugyenyi1">[1]</xref>. Then, in 2003, thanks in large part to US President George W. Bush, the President's Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief (PEPFAR) and The Global Fund began providing widespread antiretrovirals to those qualifying as most in need of treatment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Goosby1">[2]</xref>. This signaled a massive turning point in the pandemic. The challenge now would be getting people onto treatment and keeping them on treatment. A new study in this week's <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Ware1">[3]</xref> offers more insight into this challenge.</p>
      <p>Historically, one issue that was not foreseen was that despite the best efforts of providers and donors, a proportion of patients would withdraw from treatment. Sydney Rosen and colleagues published their important systematic review on the prevalence of loss to follow up among early treatment cohorts in 2007 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Rosen1">[4]</xref>. Their study reported average attrition from early treatment programs at about 40%, and spirited the development of a field of research examining rates and risk factors for retention in programs. This was a wake-up call to those working on issues of adherence that pillboxes and fixed-dose combinations do nothing to help a patient who is no longer in care.</p>
      <p>Even now, our understanding of why people drop out of care, and how to intervene, remains limited <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Kranzer1">[5]</xref>. Initially, there was widespread concern that most patients who leave care have died. However, studies that tracked patients lost from care have since provided important insights <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Brinkhof1">[6]</xref>, including the fact that mortality among patients lost to follow up in Africa varies widely. Early tracing studies, for example, found that 12%–87% of patients died, indicating large heterogeneity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Brinkhof1">[6]</xref>. Mortality associated with attrition from care is inversely associated with the proportion of patients lost <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Egger1">[7]</xref>. So, if patients have disengaged from care and are not dead, then why have they chosen to interrupt life-saving treatment?</p>
      <p>Structured supervised treatment interruptions were once explored as a way to ration therapy and minimize adverse events but were found to result in higher mortality, and this strategy was abandoned <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-ElSadr1">[8]</xref>. A systematic review found that about 23% of patients take an unstructured treatment interruption that lasts an average of 150 days <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Kranzer2">[9]</xref>. Interruptions from clinical care can be dichotomized between short-term and long-term. Short-term interruptions can be characterized as patients who miss clinical appointments due to a logistic or health barrier and will re-enter care when they can. These patients will likely miss both clinical assessment and take a short-term break from their pill-taking, increasing the risk of developing drug resistance, but ultimately returning to care. Longer-term interruptions may have more grave consequences. In an assessment of longer-term retention in care in Cameroon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Meresse1">[10]</xref>, Mégane Meresse and colleagues found that, among patients on treatment in the longer term, 20% had experienced treatment interruptions and these were uniquely predictive of virological failure, whereas adherence assessments did not predict failure.</p>
      <p>For many reasons, the study in this week's <italic>PLOS Medicine</italic> by Norma Ware and colleagues will be important for those engaged in supporting patient care in resource-limited settings. This study helps us understand that patient interactions with clinics are not simply about receiving pills or seeing a doctor. Some patients interrupt care due to costs or logistical reasons and likely re-enter care when their situation improves, while others discontinue care because of a lack of connection with their fellow patients or caregivers. These are different problems requiring different solutions. Even when field officers traced patients in this study, some patients felt that they were viewed as being bad patients. This should be a learning opportunity for those of us working in the HIV/AIDS field. An HIV+ diagnosis is often associated with a sense of shame and judgment that the person has engaged in some act that is socially unacceptable, whether that person has a partner who is unfaithful or themselves engage in casual sex. Ware and colleagues importantly highlight that, for patients who feel disconnected from a sense of community with the clinic, the shame and judgment are compounded at the clinic level and result in discontinuation of care.</p>
      <p>Several organizations have endeavored to create a sense of community at the clinic level. Efforts to build a sense of connection include drama and music groups, income-generating activities, and community-based delivery of care <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Meresse1">[10]</xref>. While these may sound like unscientific methods to provide medical care, they recognize that patients who feel disconnected from a community will ultimately have poor clinical outcomes that affect them, their families, and the local community. One of the most important evaluations of a community-based strategy comes from a rural MSF program in Mozambique <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Decroo1">[11]</xref>. Tom Decroo and colleagues referred patients to self-forming groups of patients in rural communities whose responsibility was to look after each other through assessing each other's health, ensuring adherence, and retaining each other in care. After more than 1 year, among 1,384 patients initiated on ART, 2% had died, and only two individual patients (0.2%) were absent from care, compared with 20% in other local programs. These remarkable findings display the importance of patients caring for other patients through shared experiences, lessons about coping, and friendship. Could “expert patients” be the next specialized health worker in the pandemic? <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1001370-Decroo2">[12]</xref></p>
      <p>ART roll-out has been a highly innovative endeavor, and there have been many lessons learned since 2003, but there is still a long way to go. The next challenge is to find the best models for delivering effective ART care over the long-term. Understanding the reasons is a necessary first step, but this work should now move to interventional studies to define the most appropriate service delivery and patient support models for the next decade and beyond.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pmed.1001370-Mugyenyi1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mugyenyi P (2008) Genocide by denial: how profiteering from HIV/AIDS killed millions. Kampala: Fountain Publishers. SBN-10: 9970027530. Full text: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fountainpublishers.co.ug/download.php?bkid=804" xlink:type="simple">http://www.fountainpublishers.co.ug/download.php?bkid=804</ext-link>. Accessed 6 December 2012.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed.1001370-Goosby1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goosby</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dybul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fauci</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The United States President's Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief: a story of partnerships and smart investments to turn the tide of the global AIDS pandemic</article-title>. <source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>S51</fpage>–<lpage>S56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed.1001370-Ware1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wyatt</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaaya</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agbaji</surname><given-names>OO</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Toward an understanding of disengagement from HIV treatment and care in sub-Saharan Africa: a qualitative study</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>1</issue>)  <fpage>e1001369</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1001369" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001369</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed.1001370-Rosen1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Patient retention in antiretroviral therapy programs in sub-Saharan Africa: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e298</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0040298" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0040298</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed.1001370-Kranzer1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kranzer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Govindasamy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lawn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Quantifying and addressing losses along the continuum of care for people living with HIV infection in sub-Saharan Africa: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Int AIDS Soc</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>17383</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed.1001370-Brinkhof1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brinkhof</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pujades-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mortality of patients lost to follow-up in antiretroviral treatment programmes in resource-limited settings: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e5790</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0005790" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0005790</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed.1001370-Egger1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spycher</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sidle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Correcting mortality for loss to follow-up: a nomogram applied to antiretroviral treatment programmes in sub-Saharan Africa</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1000390</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000390" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000390</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed.1001370-ElSadr1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sadr</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neaton</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>CD4+ count-guided interruption of antiretroviral treatment</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>355</volume>: <fpage>2283</fpage>–<lpage>2296</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed.1001370-Kranzer2">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kranzer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Unstructured treatment interruption of antiretroviral therapy in clinical practice: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Trop Med Int Health</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>3131</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed.1001370-Meresse1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meresse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carrieri</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kouanfack</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanche</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Time patterns of adherence and long term virological response to NNRTI regimens in the Stratall ANRS 12110/ESTHER trial in Cameroon</article-title>. <source>Antiviral Therapies</source> In press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed.1001370-Decroo1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Decroo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Telfer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maikere</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dezembro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Distribution of antiretroviral treatment through self-forming groups of patients in Tete province, Mozambique</article-title>. <source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>e39</fpage>–<lpage>e44</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed.1001370-Decroo2">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Decroo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kegels</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Remartinez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rasschaert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Are expert patients an untapped resource for ART provision in Sub-Saharan Africa?</article-title> <source>AIDS Res Treat</source> <volume>2012</volume>: <fpage>749718</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>ART</term>
          <def>
            <p>antiretroviral therapy</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>MSF</term>
          <def>
            <p>Médecins Sans Frontières</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
  </back>
</article>