<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">pmed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="allenpress-id">plme</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosmed</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1549-1277</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1549-1676</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-PLME-RA-0341R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="sici">plme-05-10-10</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Infectious Diseases</subject>
          <subject>Public Health and Epidemiology</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy">
          <subject>Public Health</subject>
          <subject>Infectious Diseases</subject>
          <subject>Respiratory Medicine</subject>
          <subject>Health Policy</subject>
          <subject>Health services research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Effect of Universal Influenza Immunization on Mortality and Health Care
          Use</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Universal Influenza Immunization</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kwong</surname>
            <given-names>Jeffrey C</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Stukel</surname>
            <given-names>Thérèse A</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Lim</surname>
            <given-names>Jenny</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>McGeer</surname>
            <given-names>Allison J</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Upshur</surname>
            <given-names>Ross E. G</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Johansen</surname>
            <given-names>Helen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">
            <sup>8</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sambell</surname>
            <given-names>Christie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">
            <sup>9</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Thompson</surname>
            <given-names>William W</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">
            <sup>10</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Thiruchelvam</surname>
            <given-names>Deva</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Marra</surname>
            <given-names>Fawziah</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11">
            <sup>11</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Svenson</surname>
            <given-names>Lawrence W</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff12">
            <sup>12</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff13">
            <sup>13</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff14">
            <sup>14</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Manuel</surname>
            <given-names>Douglas G</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line> Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences, Toronto, Ontario, Canada
        </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line> Dalla Lana School of Public Health, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario,
          Canada </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line> Department of Family and Community Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto,
          Ontario, Canada </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line> Department of Health Policy, Management and Evaluation, University of Toronto,
          Toronto, Ontario, Canada </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff5">
        <label>5</label>
        <addr-line> Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathobiology, University of Toronto,
          Toronto, Ontario, Canada </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff6">
        <label>6</label>
        <addr-line> Mount Sinai Hospital, Department of Microbiology, Toronto, Ontario, Canada
        </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff7">
        <label>7</label>
        <addr-line> Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre Primary Care Research Unit, Toronto, Ontario,
          Canada </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff8">
        <label>8</label>
        <addr-line> Health Information and Research Division, Statistics Canada, Ottawa, Ontario,
          Canada </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff9">
        <label>9</label>
        <addr-line> Health Statistics Division, Statistics Canada, Ottawa, Ontario, Canada
        </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff10">
        <label>10</label>
        <addr-line> Influenza Division<bold>,</bold> National Center for Immunization and
          Respiratory Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia, United
          States of America </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff11">
        <label>11</label>
        <addr-line> British Columbia Centre for Disease Control, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada
        </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff12">
        <label>12</label>
        <addr-line> Alberta Health and Wellness, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff13">
        <label>13</label>
        <addr-line> Department of Public Health Sciences, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta,
          Canada </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff14">
        <label>14</label>
        <addr-line> Department of Community Health Sciences, University of Calgary, Calgary,
          Alberta, Canada </addr-line>
      </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Peiris</surname>
            <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Academic Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">jeff.kwong@utoronto.ca</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="ack1">
          <p> JCK was involved in all aspects of the study. TAS, JL, AJM, REGU, HJ, WWT, FM, LWS,
            and DGM provided input on study design and interpretation of results. TAS provided
            statistical expertise. CS, FM, and LWS assisted with data collection. DT assisted with
            data analyses. DGM provided overall supervision and guidance. JCK, TAS, JL, AJM, REGU,
            HJ, CS, WWT, DT, FM, LWS, and DGM critically reviewed and approved the manuscript for
            publication.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict" id="n102">
        <p> AJM reports receiving travel grants from Sanofi Pasteur and Solvay Pharmaceuticals for
          speaking at meetings, and payment from Sanofi Pasteur for chairing a safety committee for
          a clinical trial.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e211</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
        Creative Commons Public Domain declaration, which stipulates that, once placed in the public
        domain, this work may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon,
        or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article ext-link-type="doi" id="RA1" page="e200" related-article-type="companion" vol="5" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050200" xlink:title="Research Article" xlink:type="simple">
        <article-title>The Effects of Influenza Vaccination of Health Care Workers in Nursing Homes:
          Insights from a Mathematical Model</article-title>
      </related-article><related-article ext-link-type="doi" id="RA2" page="e216" related-article-type="companion" vol="5" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050216" xlink:title="Perspectives" xlink:type="simple">
        <article-title>Health Benefits of Universal Influenza Vaccination Strategy</article-title>
      </related-article><abstract>
        <sec id="st1">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>In 2000, Ontario, Canada, initiated a universal influenza immunization program (UIIP)
            to provide free influenza vaccines for the entire population aged 6 mo or older.
            Influenza immunization increased more rapidly in younger age groups in Ontario compared
            to other Canadian provinces, which all maintained targeted immunization programs. We
            evaluated the effect of Ontario's UIIP on influenza-associated mortality,
            hospitalizations, emergency department (ED) use, and visits to doctors' offices.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="st2">
          <title>Methods and Findings</title>
          <p>Mortality and hospitalization data from 1997 to 2004 for all ten Canadian provinces
            were obtained from national datasets. Physician billing claims for visits to EDs and
            doctors' offices were obtained from provincial administrative datasets for four
            provinces with comprehensive data. Since outcomes coded as influenza are known to
            underestimate the true burden of influenza, we studied more broadly defined conditions.
            Hospitalizations, ED use, doctors' office visits for pneumonia and influenza, and
            all-cause mortality from 1997 to 2004 were modelled using Poisson regression,
            controlling for age, sex, province, influenza surveillance data, and temporal trends,
            and used to estimate the expected baseline outcome rates in the absence of influenza
            activity. The primary outcome was then defined as influenza-associated events, or the
            difference between the observed events and the expected baseline events. Changes in
            influenza-associated outcome rates before and after UIIP introduction in Ontario were
            compared to the corresponding changes in other provinces. After UIIP introduction,
            influenza-associated mortality decreased more in Ontario (relative rate
            [RR] = 0.26) than in other provinces (RR = 0.43)
            (ratio of RRs = 0.61, <italic>p</italic> = 0.002). Similar
            differences between Ontario and other provinces were observed for influenza-associated
            hospitalizations (RR = 0.25 versus 0.44, ratio of RRs = 0.58,
              <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), ED use (RR = 0.31 versus 0.69, ratio of
            RRs = 0.45, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and doctors' office visits
            (RR = 0.21 versus 0.52, ratio of RRs = 0.41, <italic>p</italic>
            &lt; 0.001). Sensitivity analyses were carried out to assess consistency,
            specificity, and the presence of a dose-response relationship. Limitations of this study
            include the ecological study design, the nonspecific outcomes, difficulty in modeling
            baseline events, data quality and availability, and the inability to control for
            potentially important confounders.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="st3">
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>Compared to targeted programs in other provinces, introduction of universal vaccination
            in Ontario in 2000 was associated with relative reductions in influenza-associated
            mortality and health care use. The results of this large-scale natural experiment
            suggest that universal vaccination may be an effective public health measure for
            reducing the annual burden of influenza.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc">
        <p>Comparing influenza-related mortality and health care use between Ontario and other
          Canadian provinces, Jeffrey Kwong and colleagues find evidence that Ontario's universal
          vaccination program has reduced the burden of influenza.</p>
      </abstract><abstract abstract-type="editor">
        <title>Editors' Summary</title>
        <sec id="sb1a">
          <title>Background.</title>
          <p>Seasonal outbreaks (epidemics) of influenza—a viral disease of the nose,
            throat, and airways—affect millions of people and kill about 500,000
            individuals every year. These epidemics occur because of “antigenic
            drift”: small but frequent changes in the viral proteins to which the human
            immune system responds mean that an immune response produced one year by exposure to an
            influenza virus provides only partial protection against influenza the next year.
            Immunization can boost this natural immunity and reduce a person's chances of catching
            influenza. That is, an injection of killed influenza viruses can be used to prime the
            immune system so that it responds quickly and efficiently when exposed to live virus.
            However, because of antigenic drift, for influenza immunization to be effective, it has
            to be repeated annually with a vaccine that contains the major circulating strains of
            the influenza virus.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sb1b">
          <title>Why Was This Study Done?</title>
          <p>Public-health organizations recommend targeted vaccination programs, so that elderly
            people, infants, and chronically ill individuals—the people most likely to die
            from pneumonia and other complications of influenza—receive annual influenza
            vaccination. Some experts argue, however, that universal vaccination might provide
            populations with better protection from influenza, both directly by increasing the
            number of vaccinated people and indirectly through “herd immunity,”
            which occurs when a high proportion of the population is immune to an infectious
            disease, so that even unvaccinated people are unlikely to become infected (because
            infected people rarely come into contact with susceptible people). In this study, the
            researchers compare the effects of the world's first free universal influenza
            immunization program (UIIP), which started in 2000 in the Canadian province of Ontario,
            on influenza-associated deaths and health care use with the effects of targeted vaccine
            programs on the same outcomes elsewhere in Canada.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sb1c">
          <title>What Did the Researchers Do and Find?</title>
          <p>Using national records, the researchers collected data on influenza vaccination, on all
            deaths, and on hospitalizations for pneumonia and influenza in all Canadian provinces
            between 1997 and 2004. They also collected data on emergency department and doctors'
            office visits for pneumonia and influenza for Ontario, Quebec, Alberta, and Manitoba.
            They then used a mathematical model to estimate the baseline rates for these outcomes in
            the absence of influenza activity, and from these calculated weekly rates for deaths and
            health care use specifically resulting from influenza. In 1996–1997,
            18% of the population was vaccinated against influenza in Ontario whereas in
            the other provinces combined the vaccination rate was 13%. On average, since
            2000—the year in which UIIP was introduced in Ontario—vaccination
            rates have risen to 38% and 24% in Ontario and the other
            provinces, respectively. Since the introduction of UIIP, the researchers report,
            influenza-associated deaths have decreased by 74% in Ontario but by only
            57% in the other provinces combined. Influenza-associated use of health care
            facilities has also decreased more in Ontario than in the other provinces over the same
            period.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sb1d">
          <title>What Do These Findings Mean?</title>
          <p>These findings are limited by some aspects of the study design. For example, they
            depend on the accuracy of the assumptions made when calculating events due specifically
            to influenza, and on the availability and accuracy of vaccination and clinical outcome
            data. In addition, it is possible that influenza-associated deaths and health care use
            may have decreased more in Ontario than in the other Canadian provinces because of some
            unrecognized health care changes specific to Ontario but unrelated to the introduction
            of universal influenza vaccination. Nevertheless, these findings indicate that, compared
            to the targeted vaccination programs in the other Canadian provinces, the Ontarian UIIP
            is associated with reductions in influenza-associated deaths and health care use,
            particularly in people younger than 65 years old. This effect is seen at a level of
            vaccination unlikely to produce herd immunity so might be more marked if the uptake of
            vaccination could be further increased. Thus, although it is possible that Canada is a
            special case, these findings suggest that universal influenza vaccination might be an
            effective way to reduce the global burden of influenza.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sb1e">
          <title>Additional Information.</title>
          <p>Please access these Web sites via the online version of this summary at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211</ext-link>.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Read the related <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://medicine.plosjournals.org/perlserv/?request=get-document&amp;doi=10.1371/journal.pmed.0050216" xlink:type="simple"><italic>PLoS</italic>
                  <italic>Medicine</italic> Perspective by Cécile Viboud and Mark
                  Miller</ext-link></p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A related <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://medicine.plosjournals.org/perlserv/?request=get-document&amp;doi=10.1371/journal.pmed.0050200" xlink:type="simple"><italic>PLoS</italic>
                  <italic>Medicine</italic> Research Article by Carline van den Dool and
                  colleagues</ext-link> is also available</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The Ontario Ministry of Health provides information on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.health.gov.on.ca/english/public/program/pubhealth/flu/flu_mn.html" xlink:type="simple">its universal influenza immunization program</ext-link> (in English and
                French)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The World Health Organization provides information on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs211" xlink:type="simple">influenza</ext-link>
                and on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/csr/disease/influenza/vaccinerecommendations" xlink:type="simple">influenza vaccines</ext-link> (in several languages)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention provide information for patients
                and professionals on all aspects of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/flu" xlink:type="simple">influenza</ext-link> (in English and
                Spanish)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>MedlinePlus provides a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/flu.html" xlink:type="simple">list of links to other
                  information about influenza</ext-link> (in English and Spanish)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The UK National Health Service provides information about <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.immunisation.nhs.uk/About_Immunisation/Science/What_is_a_vaccine" xlink:type="simple">the science of immunization</ext-link>, including a simple explanatory animation
                of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.immunisation.nhs.uk/About_Immunisation/Science/Herd_immunity_-_animation" xlink:type="simple">immunity</ext-link></p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement> This study was supported by an operating grant from the Public Health Agency of Canada,
          a Fellowship Award (to JCK), a Canada Research Chair Award in Primary Care Research (to
          REGU), and a Chair in Applied Public Health (to DGM) from the Canadian Institutes of
          Health Research, and a Career Scientist Award from the Ontario Ministry of Health and
          Long-Term Care (to DGM). The Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences (ICES) is
          supported in part by a grant from the Ontario Ministry of Health and Long-Term Care.
          Funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or
          preparation of the manuscript. The findings and conclusions in this study are those of the
          authors and do not necessarily represent the views of the Centers for Disease Control and
          Prevention, the Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences, the Ontario Ministry of Health
          and Long-Term Care, or Manitoba Health and Healthy Living.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="13"/>
      </counts><!--===== Restructure custom-meta-wrap to custom-meta-group =====--><custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>citation</meta-name>
          <meta-value>Kwong JC, Stukel TA, Lim J, McGeer AJ, Upshur REG, et al. (2008) The effect of
            universal influenza immunization on mortality and health care use. PLoS Med 5(10): e211.
              doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211</ext-link></meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Annual epidemics of influenza continue to cause worldwide morbidity, mortality, and
        societal disruption. When there is good match to circulating strains, influenza vaccines are
        generally efficacious and cost-effective for most age groups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b001">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b005">5</xref>]. However, some recent studies have questioned the validity of the
        nonexperimental evidence for influenza vaccine effectiveness in the elderly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b006">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b009">9</xref>]. Efforts to reduce the impact of influenza have
        mainly involved targeted influenza immunization programs, which aim to vaccinate those at
        high risk of complications from influenza infection and their contacts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b010">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b011">11</xref>].</p>
      <p>In October 2000, the Canadian province of Ontario initiated the world's first large-scale
        universal influenza immunization program (UIIP) to provide free influenza vaccinations for
        the entire population ≥6 mo of age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b012">12</xref>]. Supporters have argued that universal
        programs have several benefits: increased numbers of people directly protected from
        influenza by vaccination; possible indirect protection (i.e., protection extending to
        nonvaccinated individuals) arising from vaccinating greater proportions of the population;
        and having vaccine procurement and delivery systems in place for an influenza pandemic
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b013">13</xref>]. Critics have
        argued that uncertainties surrounding both the effectiveness and the cost-effectiveness of
        vaccinating healthy adults and children may not justify the costs of implementing such
        programs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b014">14</xref>].</p>
      <p>Ontario was the lone Canadian province to implement UIIP; other provinces maintained
        targeted programs. Canadian vaccination programs traditionally involve centralized vaccine
        procurement by provincial governments with publicly insured local delivery to high risk
        individuals and their close contacts/care providers. Vaccine is delivered in health care
        settings by nurses or physicians, or in community settings through public health
        departments. High risk individuals include seniors aged ≥65 y, individuals with
        chronic medical conditions, children aged 6–23 mo (since 2004), and pregnant women
        (since 2007) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b011">11</xref>].
        UIIP introduction in Ontario entailed expansion of prior vaccination activities, with local
        variations in delivery. Vaccine delivery settings include physician offices, hospitals,
        schools, workplaces, pharmacies, community centres, and shopping malls. The program also
        includes extensive media campaigns promoting the availability and benefits of free influenza
        vaccinations.</p>
      <p>Our earlier work found that universal vaccination was associated with an overall
        incremental increase in vaccine uptake in the household population aged ≥12 y of 9
        percentage points (24- versus 15-percentage-point increase in Ontario versus other
        provinces) between 1996–1997 and 2005 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b015">15</xref>]. For those &lt;65 y, greater increases
        over time were observed in Ontario compared to other provinces, whereas lesser increases
        were observed in Ontario compared to other provinces for those ≥85 y. All age groups
        in Ontario maintained higher uptake rates compared to corresponding age groups in other
        provinces throughout the study period.</p>
      <p>In this study, we evaluated the effect of Ontario's UIIP on mortality, hospitalizations,
        emergency department (ED) use, and doctors' office visits compared to targeted programs in
        other Canadian provinces.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Study Population and Setting</title>
        <p>This study included the population of the ten Canadian provinces from 1997 to 2004 who
          were eligible for universal, publicly insured health care services. Ethics approval was
          obtained from the Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre Research Ethics Board, Toronto,
          Ontario.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Study Design</title>
        <p>We used a pre-/post-intervention study design with concurrent controls to assess the
          effect of Ontario's UIIP on influenza-associated mortality and health care use. Although
          ecological studies do not permit inference to individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b016">16</xref>], this design was appropriate to evaluate the
          impact of a population-level vaccination program on population outcomes rather than the
          effect of vaccination on individual outcomes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Data Sources</title>
        <p>Mortality data were obtained from Statistics Canada's Mortality Database, a national
          vital statistics dataset.</p>
        <p>Hospitalization data were obtained from Statistics Canada's Hospital Morbidity Database,
          a national discharge abstract dataset.</p>
        <p>Physician services data were obtained from the following provinces: Ontario, Quebec,
          Alberta, and Manitoba. These provinces account for approximately 76% of the
          Canadian population and were selected because of availability of comprehensive data on
          physician services.</p>
        <p>Annual population estimates were obtained from Statistics Canada.</p>
        <p>Vaccination rate data were obtained from the 1996–1997 cycle of the National
          Population Health Survey (NPHS) and the 2000–2001, 2003, and 2005 cycles of the
          Canadian Community Health Survey (CCHS). Conducted by Statistics Canada using telephone
          and in-person interviews, these surveys covered the household population aged ≥12 y
          but excluded members of the Canadian Forces, Indian reserves, and some remote areas, and
          those living in institutions. The surveys had response rates of between 79% and
          85%; details have been described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b015">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b017">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b021">21</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Outcomes</title>
        <p>Influenza outcomes are difficult to quantify because influenza infections are typically
          not confirmed. Since outcomes coded as influenza are known to underestimate the true
          burden of influenza, we studied more broadly defined conditions. These mortality and
          health care utilization outcomes vary according to a cyclical
          “baseline” function with winter peaks and summer troughs, but
          typically exhibit spikes during periods of influenza virus activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b022">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b023">23</xref>]. Our primary outcome was defined as
          influenza-associated outcomes, measured as the difference between observed events and
          expected baseline events during influenza seasons. This outcome reflects the excess number
          of events that occur because of influenza activity beyond what would be expected from
          background (baseline) rates. We chose this as our primary outcome because it is only these
          excess events that might be mitigated by a vaccination program.</p>
        <p>For our primary mortality outcome, we included all deaths between 24 August 1997 and 14
          August 2004 (primary study period comprising seven 52-wk periods).</p>
        <p>We included all pneumonia and influenza (P&amp;I) (ICD-9-CM 480–487,
          ICD-10-CA J10-J18) hospitalizations to acute care facilities during the study period,
          excluding admissions of nonresidents, transfers between institutions, and readmissions
          within 1 wk of discharge. Although discharge abstracts list up to 16 diagnoses, we used
          the first five codes to capture cases where influenza may have precipitated another
          condition requiring hospitalization (e.g., congestive heart failure) as well as nosocomial
          spread of influenza, while limiting the potential effects of differential coding practices
          between provinces and over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b024">24</xref>].</p>
        <p>To assess ED use and visits to doctors' offices, we included all physician claims in ED
          and office settings during the study period for P&amp;I. We included only one service
          claim per patient per physician per day, and where possible, we excluded claims that were
          associated with vaccination service codes (i.e., a visit to receive influenza
          vaccination).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>National Viral Surveillance Data</title>
        <sec id="s2e1">
          <title>Respiratory virus detections.</title>
          <p>A national network of hospital and provincial laboratories submit weekly reports of
            numbers of tests performed (using viral culture or direct antigen detection) and numbers
            of positive tests for influenza A, influenza B, and respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) to
            the Public Health Agency of Canada. The four Atlantic provinces were grouped owing to
            small numbers of specimens tested.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2e2">
          <title>Predominance of influenza subtype A(H3N2).</title>
          <p>A subset of laboratories report further case-specific data including subtype. Since
            A(H3N2)-predominant seasons have historically been more severe than A(H1N1)- and/or
            B-predominant seasons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b023">23</xref>], these data were used to measure the proportion of the season's
            subtyped isolates that were influenza subtype A(H3N2) in each province and season (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed-0050211-st001">Table S1</xref>). This
            variable was necessary because weekly subtype-specific data were not available for the
            study period. Predominance of A(H3N2) was generally consistent across provinces.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2e3">
          <title>Vaccine antigenic match.</title>
          <p>A subset of viral isolates is sent to Canada's National Microbiology Laboratory for
            strain characterization. The sample was assumed to represent the distribution of strains
            for all influenza viruses circulating in the population. The percentage of circulating
            strains that did not match vaccine strains was calculated for each province and season
            (percent mismatch) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed-0050211-st001">Table S1</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Periods of Peak Influenza Activity</title>
        <p>Periods of peak influenza activity were defined separately for each province and year,
          starting when the weekly percentage of tests positive for influenza was greater than
          10% and ending when the percentage fell below that threshold for 2 consecutive
          wk (mean period duration = 11 wk) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed-0050211-st001">Table S1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>We estimated influenza-associated events using a two-step procedure. We first ran
          multivariate regression models to estimate weekly events as a function of population and
          influenza season factors, and used this model to generate an expected baseline
          representing the pattern of events occurring in the absence of influenza. We then computed
          influenza-associated events as the difference between the number of observed events and
          expected baseline events during periods of influenza activity.</p>
        <p>In the first step, we ran separate Poisson regression models for each outcome, according
          to province and age group (&lt;5, 5–19, 20–49 [&lt;50
          for mortality], 50–64, 65–74, 75–84, 85+
          y) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b025">25</xref>]. We
          aggregated event counts by week and sex within province-age group combinations. The
          dependent variable was the weekly event count for males and females, and the offset
          parameter was the province-age group-sex population. Models controlled for sex; viral
          surveillance for influenza A, influenza B, and RSV; the seasonal percentage of A(H3N2)
          isolates; the percentage of mismatched strains; linear and quadratic terms to model annual
          trends; and sine and cosine terms with periods of 1 y to model seasonal fluctuations, as
          in previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b027">27</xref>]. To account
          for fluctuations in health service delivery during Christmas and post-Christmas holiday
          periods, categorical terms were included in the health care use models for these time
          periods. The model terms are outlined in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed-0050211-sd001">Text S1</xref>. The expected baseline was generated by setting
          the influenza-related variables in the model (i.e., weekly percentage of tests positive
          for influenza A and B, seasonal percentage of A[H3N2] isolates) to zero
          as these were the terms that tracked influenza season peaks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b027">27</xref>]. We incorporated variance overdispersion in
          the estimates of all standard errors (SE) to account for clustering of outcomes within
          weekly strata since outcomes to individuals within these strata may not be
          independent.</p>
        <p>Weekly influenza-associated events were subsequently computed as the difference between
          the number of observed events and expected baseline events during periods of peak
          influenza activity, where expected counts were based on the adjusted Poisson models (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed-0050211-sg001">Figure S1</xref>). These
          weekly estimates were aggregated to produce annual estimates. Overall and age-specific
          mean annual rates of influenza-associated outcomes were calculated for the periods before
          and after introduction of UIIP (pre-2000 versus post-2000), separately for Ontario and the
          other provinces combined.</p>
        <p>Pre- and post-UIIP influenza-associated event rates were compared by dividing the
          adjusted postintervention rates by the preintervention rates to produce relative rates
          (RR) of UIIP effect separately for Ontario and the other provinces combined. The standard
          error of <italic>ln</italic>(RR) was computed assuming a Poisson distribution for the
          overall counts and incorporating the variance of the predicted baseline events
            [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b028">28</xref>]. The
          pre-/post-RRs for Ontario and other provinces combined were compared using the
            <italic>z-</italic>test and expressed as a ratio.</p>
        <p>Model fit was evaluated by examining the standardized Pearson residuals for outlying
          points and secular trends. We also evaluated the presence of influential provinces by
          removing them individually from the model and reestimating the UIIP effect. Although the
          model did not optimally fit the extreme, short-lived spikes that occurred during the peaks
          of the influenza season, the fit during the remainder of the season was reasonable. We
          used the Durbin-Watson <italic>d</italic>-statistic to test for autocorrelation in the
          residuals, both including and excluding these influenza season spikes, averaging the
          correlations across province- and age group-specific models. Analyses were performed using
          SAS 9.1 (SAS Institute). All statistical tests were computed at the 5% level of
          significance and were two sided.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Sensitivity Analyses</title>
        <p>To confirm the robustness of the findings, several sensitivity analyses were
          conducted.</p>
        <sec id="s2h1">
          <title>Tests of effect consistency.</title>
          <p>To test the consistency of our findings, we used a 5% threshold for defining
            periods of peak influenza activity, leading to longer periods. We also lagged influenza
            and RSV activity forward or backward by 1 wk, in case of delays in viral testing or
            onset of serious illnesses (i.e., reports of positive tests and illness onset
            consistently occurring in different weeks).</p>
          <p>To increase the number of influenza seasons in the study, we included data from the
            1993–1994 to 1996–1997 influenza seasons, but this analysis excluded
            data from Quebec and the Atlantic provinces because prior to 1997–1998, the
            former did not report the number of tests performed, preventing calculation of weekly
            percentages of tests positive, and the latter performed too few tests (&lt;25/wk
            during influenza season periods) to permit reliable calculation of percentages of tests
            positive.</p>
          <p>As another test of consistency, we restricted the analysis to seasons in which A(H3N2)
            detections accounted for greater than 50% of the total isolates
            (A[H3N2]-predominant seasons).</p>
          <p>For hospitalizations, we repeated the primary analysis using all 16 codes (any-listed)
            and using only the first code (primary-listed).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2h2">
          <title>Tests of effect amplification.</title>
          <p>For mortality, we examined deaths from respiratory and circulatory (R&amp;C)
            conditions as a more specific outcome for influenza. Deaths from P&amp;I were not
            assessed because of the small numbers of events at the province- and age-specific level,
            and because of a sharp decrease in P&amp;I deaths coinciding with ICD-10
            introduction in 2000 that is known to be a coding artifact [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b029">29</xref>].</p>
          <p>The 2003–2004 influenza season was noteworthy for the emergence of the novel
            A/Fujian strain that accounted for 92% of the characterized isolates in
            Canada but was not included in that season's vaccine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b030">30</xref>]. Since it was expected that vaccine
            efficacy would be reduced for that year, analyses were repeated excluding that season to
            assess the impact of universal vaccination for post-UIIP seasons with better vaccine
            match. We conducted another analysis that excluded all poor match seasons during the
            study period (i.e., the 1997–1998 A/Sydney season and the 2003–2004
            A/Fujian season).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2h3">
          <title>Tests of effect attenuation.</title>
          <p>For the health care use outcomes, we examined the effect of UIIP on less specific
            outcomes. We examined hospitalizations for all respiratory conditions (ICD-9-CM
            460–519, ICD-10-CA J00-J99), and for ED use and office visits, we examined
            selected respiratory conditions (composite of P&amp;I, acute respiratory diseases
            [ARD] [ICD-9 460–466], otitis media
            [OM] [ICD-9 381–383] among those
            ≤50 y, and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease [COPD]
            [ICD-9 490–492, 496] among those aged ≥20 y)
              [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b031">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b032">32</xref>]. Higher-order sine and
            cosine terms were used in these models to achieve better fit to the observed seasonal
            variation in outcomes.</p>
          <p>Data for the 2004–2005 season were available for hospitalizations, so a
            sensitivity analysis adding that year to the study period was performed. For that
            season, 35% of characterized isolates were A/California and 4%
            were B/Hong Kong strains, both of which were not included in that season's vaccine,
            although the A/Fujian component of the vaccine was believed to provide partial
            protection against A/California [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b033">33</xref>]. Therefore, as a moderately poor match season, it was expected to
            diminish the benefits of the UIIP.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2h4">
          <title>Tests of effect specificity.</title>
          <p>To assess the specificity of our findings, we examined rates of all observed events, as
            opposed to influenza-associated events, during the month of July, since influenza
            viruses are not circulating in the summer and we would not expect any
            influenza-associated events nor any benefit from influenza vaccination.</p>
          <p>As another test of specificity, we examined the effect of the UIIP on selected control
            conditions, by computing RRs for all events during the month of February, when influenza
            viruses are almost always circulating. For mortality, we used all non-R&amp;C
            conditions, for hospitalizations, we examined hernia, and for ED use and office visits,
            we considered lacerations.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2h5">
          <title>Dose-response relationship.</title>
          <p>Regions with greater increases in vaccination rates are expected to have greater
            decreases in influenza-associated outcomes. To assess the presence of such a
            relationship, we plotted age group-, province-, and outcome-specific RRs for mean
            influenza-associated events against absolute changes in vaccination rates. We used the
            mean of the estimates from the three cycles of the Canadian Community Health Survey as
            the measure of post-UIIP vaccine uptake and the 1996–1997 National Population
            Health Survey estimate as the measure of pre-UIIP vaccine uptake. To match with the age
            groupings of the outcomes data, we assumed that the vaccination rates of those aged 12
            to 19 y applied to children as young as 5 y. We fitted weighted linear models separately
            by outcome and age group (&lt;65 y and ≥65 y), weighting by the inverse of
            the variance of the RRs.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Descriptive Results</title>
        <p>Over the study period, mean annual outcome rates were highest in older people and young
          children (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0050211-t001">Table 1</xref>). Plots of weekly
          outcome rates over the study period for Ontario and other provinces demonstrated seasonal
          trends with spikes during periods of influenza activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0050211-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap content-type="2col" id="pmed-0050211-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <p>Study Population Demographics and Mean Annual Event Rates over Study Period</p>
          </caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup><col id="tb1col1" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb1col2" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb1col3" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb1col4" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb1col5" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb1col6" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb1col7" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb1col8" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3"><hr/>Population</td><td rowspan="3"><hr/>Characteristics</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="2"><hr/>Study Population as of 1 July 2000</td><td colspan="4"><hr/>Mean Annual Event Rate per 100,000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><hr/>All-Cause Mortality</td><td colspan="3"><hr/>P&amp;I</td></tr><tr><td><hr/>&times;1,000</td><td><hr/>Percentage</td><td><hr/>Hospitalizations</td><td><hr/>ED Use</td><td><hr/>Office Visits</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>Overall (10 provinces)</bold></td><td><bold>&mdash;</bold></td><td>30,591</td><td>100.0</td><td>717</td><td>390</td><td>882</td><td>3,504</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Sex</bold></td><td><bold>Female</bold></td><td>15,445</td><td>50.5</td><td>694</td><td>366</td><td>861</td><td>3,745</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Male</bold></td><td>15,146</td><td>49.5</td><td>741</td><td>415</td><td>903</td><td>3,258</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Age group (y)</bold></td><td><bold>&lt;5</bold></td><td>1,782</td><td>5.8</td><td>&mdash;</td><td>827</td><td>2,599</td><td>8,137</td></tr><tr><td><bold>5&ndash;19</bold></td><td>6,161</td><td>20.1</td><td>&mdash;</td><td>98</td><td>561</td><td>3,176</td></tr><tr><td><bold>20&ndash;49</bold></td><td>13,956</td><td>45.6</td><td>89<sup>b</sup></td><td>93</td><td>456</td><td>2,530</td></tr><tr><td><bold>50&ndash;64</bold></td><td>4,842</td><td>15.8</td><td>604</td><td>313</td><td>685</td><td>3,334</td></tr><tr><td><bold>65&ndash;74</bold></td><td>2,144</td><td>7.0</td><td>1,993</td><td>982</td><td>1,451</td><td>4,611</td></tr><tr><td><bold>75&ndash;84</bold></td><td>1,299</td><td>4.2</td><td>5,181</td><td>2,346</td><td>3,013</td><td>6,343</td></tr><tr><td><bold>&ge;85</bold></td><td>406</td><td>1.3</td><td>15,100</td><td>4,747</td><td>5,771</td><td>9,080</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Province</bold></td><td><bold>Atlantic provinces<sup>a</sup></bold></td><td>2,349</td><td>7.7</td><td>826</td><td>484</td><td>&mdash;</td><td>&mdash;</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Quebec</bold></td><td>7,357</td><td>24.0</td><td>738</td><td>335</td><td>871</td><td>3,410</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Ontario</bold></td><td>11,685</td><td>38.2</td><td>695</td><td>376</td><td>914</td><td>3,637</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Manitoba</bold></td><td>1,147</td><td>3.8</td><td>853</td><td>537</td><td>414</td><td>3,444</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Saskatchewan</bold></td><td>1,008</td><td>3.3</td><td>585</td><td>408</td><td>&mdash;</td><td>&mdash;</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Alberta</bold></td><td>3,005</td><td>9.8</td><td>882</td><td>651</td><td>961</td><td>3,240</td></tr><tr><td><bold>British Columbia</bold></td><td>4,039</td><td>13.2</td><td>700</td><td>358</td><td>&mdash;</td><td>&mdash;</td></tr></tbody></table> --><!-- <table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p><sup>a</sup>Atlantic provinces: Newfoundland and Labrador, Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, Prince Edward Island</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><p><sup>b</sup>0&ndash;49 y</p></fn></table-wrap-foot> --></table-wrap>
        <fig id="pmed-0050211-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Study Outcome Rates over the Study Period Demonstrating Year-to-Year Variability
              in Mortality and Health Care Use, Temporal Correlation with Ontario Influenza Viral
              Surveillance Data, and Increasing Influenza Vaccination Rates Demonstrating Greater
              Increases in Ontario Compared to Other Provinces Combined</title>
            <p>Event rates (from top to bottom) for doctors' office visits, ED use,
              hospitalizations, and mortality (grey lines are for Ontario and black lines are for
              other provinces combined) are expressed as rates per 100,000 on the upper sections of
              the vertical axis. Viral surveillance data (grey shaded areas) are expressed as the
              weekly percentage of tests positive on the lower section of the vertical axis.
              Vaccination rates for the household population aged ≥12 y (grey vertical bars
              are for Ontario and black vertical bars are for other provinces combined) are
              expressed as the percentage of the population vaccinated on the lower section of the
              vertical axis. The horizontal axis represents time. The black vertical line represents
              UIIP introduction.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Vaccination Rates</title>
        <p>Between the pre-UIIP 1996–1997 estimate to the mean post-UIIP vaccination rate,
          influenza vaccination rates for the household population aged ≥12 y increased 20
          percentage points (18%–38%) for Ontario, compared to 11
          percentage points (13%–24%) for other provinces
            (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0050211-t002">Table 2</xref>). For those &lt;65 y, the vaccination rate increases were greater in
          Ontario than in other provinces, while for those ≥75 y, the increase was smaller in
          Ontario. For all age groups, Ontario always achieved higher vaccination rates than other
          provinces.</p>
        <table-wrap content-type="2col" id="pmed-0050211-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <p>Influenza Vaccination Rates over Time for Ontario and Other Provinces</p>
          </caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup><col id="tb2col1" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col2" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col3" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb2col4" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col5" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb2col6" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col7" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col8" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col9" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col10" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col11" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col12" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col13" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb2col14" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col15" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3"><hr/>Age Group</td><td rowspan="3"><hr/>Province</td><td colspan="12"><hr/>Influenza Vaccination Rates</td><td rowspan="3"><hr/><italic>p</italic>-Value*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/>1996&ndash; 1997</td><td colspan="2"><hr/>2000&ndash; 2001</td><td colspan="2"><hr/>2003</td><td colspan="2"><hr/>2005</td><td colspan="2"><hr/>Mean Post-UIIP<sup>a</sup></td><td colspan="2"><hr/>Change (Percentage Points)<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td><hr/>Percent</td><td><hr/>95&percnt; CI</td><td><hr/>Percent</td><td><hr/>95&percnt; CI</td><td><hr/>Percent</td><td><hr/>95&percnt; CI</td><td><hr/>Percent</td><td><hr/>95&percnt; CI</td><td><hr/>Percent</td><td><hr/>95&percnt; CI</td><td><hr/>Percent</td><td><hr/>95&percnt; CI</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>Overall</bold></td><td><bold>Ontario</bold></td><td>18</td><td>(18&ndash;19)</td><td>36</td><td>(35&ndash;37)</td><td>35</td><td>(34&ndash;36)</td><td>42</td><td>(42&ndash;43)</td><td>38</td><td>(37&ndash;38)</td><td>20</td><td>(19&ndash;20)</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Other provinces</bold></td><td>13</td><td>(12&ndash;13)</td><td>21</td><td>(20&ndash;22)</td><td>23</td><td>(22&ndash;23)</td><td>28</td><td>(28&ndash;29)</td><td>24</td><td>(24&ndash;24)</td><td>11</td><td>(10&ndash;12)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Atlantic provinces<sup>c</sup></bold></td><td>16</td><td>(14&ndash;17)</td><td>19</td><td>(18&ndash;20)</td><td>24</td><td>(24&ndash;25)</td><td>31</td><td>(30&ndash;32)</td><td>25</td><td>(24&ndash;25)</td><td>9</td><td>(7&ndash;10)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Quebec</bold></td><td>8</td><td>(7&ndash;9)</td><td>18</td><td>(17&ndash;20)</td><td>20</td><td>(19&ndash;21)</td><td>25</td><td>(24&ndash;26)</td><td>21</td><td>(20&ndash;22)</td><td>13</td><td>(12&ndash;14)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Manitoba</bold></td><td>14</td><td>(13&ndash;16)</td><td>22</td><td>(19&ndash;25)</td><td>20</td><td>(19&ndash;21)</td><td>28</td><td>(27&ndash;30)</td><td>23</td><td>(22&ndash;25)</td><td>9</td><td>(7&ndash;10)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Saskatchewan</bold></td><td>13</td><td>(11&ndash;15)</td><td>19</td><td>(17&ndash;21)</td><td>24</td><td>(22&ndash;25)</td><td>28</td><td>(27&ndash;30)</td><td>24</td><td>(23&ndash;25)</td><td>10</td><td>(8&ndash;13)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Alberta</bold></td><td>15</td><td>(15&ndash;16)</td><td>23</td><td>(21&ndash;25)</td><td>23</td><td>(22&ndash;24)</td><td>28</td><td>(27&ndash;29)</td><td>25</td><td>(24&ndash;26)</td><td>9</td><td>(8&ndash;10)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>British Columbia</bold></td><td>17</td><td>(15&ndash;19)</td><td>26</td><td>(24&ndash;28)</td><td>27</td><td>(26&ndash;28)</td><td>33</td><td>(32&ndash;34)</td><td>29</td><td>(28&ndash;29)</td><td>11</td><td>(9&ndash;13)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>12&ndash;19 y</bold></td><td><bold>Ontario</bold></td><td>16</td><td>(14&ndash;17)</td><td>29</td><td>(25&ndash;32)</td><td>28</td><td>(26&ndash;30)</td><td>37</td><td>(35&ndash;38)</td><td>31</td><td>(30&ndash;33)</td><td>15</td><td>(13&ndash;17)</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Other provinces</bold></td><td>6</td><td>(4&ndash;7)</td><td>9</td><td>(8&ndash;11)</td><td>10</td><td>(9&ndash;11)</td><td>14</td><td>(13&ndash;15)</td><td>11</td><td>(10&ndash;12)</td><td>5</td><td>(4&ndash;7)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>20&ndash;49 y</bold></td><td><bold>Ontario</bold></td><td>8</td><td>(8&ndash;8)</td><td>27</td><td>(25&ndash;28)</td><td>23</td><td>(22&ndash;24)</td><td>30</td><td>(29&ndash;31)</td><td>27</td><td>(26&ndash;27)</td><td>19</td><td>(18&ndash;20)</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Other provinces</bold></td><td>6</td><td>(5&ndash;6)</td><td>12</td><td>(11&ndash;13)</td><td>13</td><td>(12&ndash;13)</td><td>18</td><td>(17&ndash;19)</td><td>14</td><td>(14&ndash;15)</td><td>9</td><td>(8&ndash;9)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>50&ndash;64 y</bold></td><td><bold>Ontario</bold></td><td>21</td><td>(19&ndash;22)</td><td>42</td><td>(39&ndash;45)</td><td>45</td><td>(44&ndash;47)</td><td>54</td><td>(52&ndash;55)</td><td>47</td><td>(46&ndash;48)</td><td>26</td><td>(25&ndash;28)</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Other provinces</bold></td><td>15</td><td>(13&ndash;16)</td><td>23</td><td>(21&ndash;24)</td><td>29</td><td>(28&ndash;30)</td><td>35</td><td>(34&ndash;36)</td><td>29</td><td>(28&ndash;30)</td><td>14</td><td>(12&ndash;16)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>65&ndash;74 y</bold></td><td><bold>Ontario</bold></td><td>54</td><td>(52&ndash;56)</td><td>69</td><td>(65&ndash;74)</td><td>71</td><td>(69&ndash;72)</td><td>73</td><td>(71&ndash;75)</td><td>71</td><td>(69&ndash;73)</td><td>17</td><td>(14&ndash;19)</td><td>0.86</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Other provinces</bold></td><td>42</td><td>(39&ndash;46)</td><td>58</td><td>(55&ndash;61)</td><td>59</td><td>(57&ndash;60)</td><td>62</td><td>(61&ndash;63)</td><td>59</td><td>(58&ndash;61)</td><td>17</td><td>(13&ndash;21)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>75&ndash;84 y</bold></td><td><bold>Ontario</bold></td><td>70</td><td>(67&ndash;72)</td><td>79</td><td>(74&ndash;83)</td><td>80</td><td>(78&ndash;82)</td><td>84</td><td>(82&ndash;85)</td><td>81</td><td>(79&ndash;82)</td><td>11</td><td>(8&ndash;14)</td><td>0.048</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Other provinces</bold></td><td>54</td><td>(49&ndash;59)</td><td>71</td><td>(68&ndash;74)</td><td>68</td><td>(67&ndash;70)</td><td>73</td><td>(72&ndash;75)</td><td>71</td><td>(69&ndash;72)</td><td>17</td><td>(12&ndash;22)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>&ge;85 y</bold></td><td><bold>Ontario</bold></td><td>67</td><td>(61&ndash;73)</td><td>73</td><td>(63&ndash;84)</td><td>78</td><td>(74&ndash;83)</td><td>82</td><td>(77&ndash;86)</td><td>78</td><td>(74&ndash;82)</td><td>11</td><td>(3&ndash;18)</td><td>0.01</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Other provinces</bold></td><td>44</td><td>(33&ndash;55)</td><td>71</td><td>(64&ndash;77)</td><td>71</td><td>(67&ndash;74)</td><td>76</td><td>(73&ndash;78)</td><td>72</td><td>(70&ndash;75)</td><td>28</td><td>(17&ndash;40)</td></tr></tbody></table> --><!-- <table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt201"><p><sup>a</sup>UIIP in Ontario.</p></fn><fn id="nt202"><p><sup>b</sup>Change represents absolute percentage point difference between mean of the 2000&ndash;2001, 2003, and 2005 rates (post-UIIP) and the 1996&ndash;1997 rate (pre-UIIP).</p></fn><fn id="nt203"><p><sup>c</sup>Atlantic provinces: Newfoundland and Labrador, Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, Prince Edward Island.</p></fn><fn id="nt204"><p>*<italic>p</italic>-Value for difference between the change over time in Ontario and other provinces combined (<italic>z</italic>-test).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot> --></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Influenza-Associated Mortality and Health Care Use</title>
        <p>After UIIP introduction, influenza-associated mortality for the overall population
          decreased 74% in Ontario (RR = 0.26, 95% confidence
          interval [CI], 0.20–0.34) compared to 57% in other
          provinces (RR = 0.43, 95% CI, 0.37–0.50) (ratio of RRs
          = 0.61, <italic>p</italic> = 0.002) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0050211-t003">Table 3</xref>). In age-specific analyses, larger mortality
          decreases in Ontario were found to be statistically significant only in those ≥85
          y.</p>
        <table-wrap content-type="2col" id="pmed-0050211-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
            <p>Effect of UIIP on Influenza-Associated Mortality and Health Care Use Rates</p>
          </caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup><col id="tb3col1" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb3col2" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb3col3" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb3col4" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb3col5" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb3col6" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb3col7" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb3col8" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb3col9" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb3col10" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3"><hr/>Mortality and Health Care Use</td><td rowspan="3"><hr/>Age Groups (y)</td><td colspan="6"><hr/>Mean Annual Influenza-Associated Event Rates (per 100,000)</td><td rowspan="3"><hr/>Ratio of Ontario/ Other RRs</td><td rowspan="3"><hr/><italic>p</italic> Value*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/>Ontario</td><td colspan="3"><hr/>Other Provinces Combined</td></tr><tr><td><hr/>Pre-2000</td><td><hr/>Post-2000</td><td><hr/>Post- Versus Pre-RR (95&percnt; CI)</td><td><hr/>Pre-2000</td><td><hr/>Post-2000</td><td><hr/>Post- Versus Pre-RR (95&percnt; CI)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>Mortality</bold></td><td><bold>All ages</bold></td><td>14.8</td><td>3.9</td><td>0.26 (0.20&ndash;0.34)</td><td>16.1</td><td>6.9</td><td>0.43 (0.37&ndash;0.50)</td><td>0.61</td><td>0.002</td></tr><tr><td><bold>&lt;50</bold></td><td>0.8</td><td>0.4</td><td>0.42 (0.13&ndash;1.42)</td><td>0.6</td><td>0.5</td><td>0.81 (0.28&ndash;2.34)</td><td>0.52</td><td>0.43</td></tr><tr><td><bold>50&ndash;64</bold></td><td>3.9</td><td>1.3</td><td>0.34 (0.06&ndash;2.02)</td><td>5.1</td><td>0.3</td><td>0.07 (0&ndash;23.46)</td><td>4.96</td><td>0.61</td></tr><tr><td><bold>65&ndash;74</bold></td><td>24.7</td><td>6.2</td><td>0.25 (0.09&ndash;0.70)</td><td>33.0</td><td>11.8</td><td>0.36 (0.21&ndash;0.61)</td><td>0.71</td><td>0.55</td></tr><tr><td><bold>75&ndash;84</bold></td><td>126.5</td><td>28.4</td><td>0.22 (0.14&ndash;0.36)</td><td>144.9</td><td>44.7</td><td>0.31 (0.23&ndash;0.41)</td><td>0.73</td><td>0.25</td></tr><tr><td><bold>&ge;85</bold></td><td>562.8</td><td>134.3</td><td>0.24 (0.17&ndash;0.33)</td><td>525.4</td><td>255.8</td><td>0.49 (0.41&ndash;0.58)</td><td>0.49</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Hospitalizations</bold></td><td><bold>All ages</bold></td><td>33.4</td><td>8.5</td><td>0.25 (0.23&ndash;0.28)</td><td>44.9</td><td>19.8</td><td>0.44 (0.42&ndash;0.46)</td><td>0.58</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>&lt;5</bold></td><td>44.5</td><td>23.6</td><td>0.53 (0.41&ndash;0.68)</td><td>44.3</td><td>59.9</td><td>1.35 (1.14&ndash;1.60)</td><td>0.39</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>5&ndash;19</bold></td><td>2.1</td><td>1.3</td><td>0.63 (0.29&ndash;1.39)</td><td>2.0</td><td>5.0</td><td>2.56 (1.42&ndash;4.61)</td><td>0.25</td><td>0.005</td></tr><tr><td><bold>20&ndash;49</bold></td><td>6.0</td><td>1.2</td><td>0.21 (0.13&ndash;0.32)</td><td>10.5</td><td>5.9</td><td>0.56 (0.50&ndash;0.63)</td><td>0.37</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>50&ndash;64</bold></td><td>25.4</td><td>2.0</td><td>0.08 (0.03&ndash;0.18)</td><td>44.4</td><td>15.8</td><td>0.36 (0.32&ndash;0.40)</td><td>0.22</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>65&ndash;74</bold></td><td>88.8</td><td>15.2</td><td>0.17 (0.12&ndash;0.23)</td><td>134.6</td><td>39.1</td><td>0.29 (0.26&ndash;0.33)</td><td>0.59</td><td>0.002</td></tr><tr><td><bold>75&ndash;84</bold></td><td>258.8</td><td>57.2</td><td>0.22 (0.19&ndash;0.26)</td><td>318.6</td><td>93.2</td><td>0.29 (0.27&ndash;0.32)</td><td>0.76</td><td>0.006</td></tr><tr><td><bold>&ge;85</bold></td><td>564.6</td><td>188.5</td><td>0.33 (0.29&ndash;0.39)</td><td>621.9</td><td>240.2</td><td>0.39 (0.35&ndash;0.43)</td><td>0.86</td><td>0.12</td></tr><tr><td><bold>ED use</bold></td><td><bold>All ages</bold></td><td>139.6</td><td>43.6</td><td>0.31 (0.30&ndash;0.32)</td><td>125.0</td><td>85.9</td><td>0.69 (0.67&ndash;0.70)</td><td>0.45</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>&lt;5</bold></td><td>267.9</td><td>149.6</td><td>0.56 (0.51&ndash;0.61)</td><td>134.2</td><td>214.9</td><td>1.60 (1.43&ndash;1.79)</td><td>0.35</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>5&ndash;19</bold></td><td>93.8</td><td>48.4</td><td>0.52 (0.48&ndash;0.55)</td><td>54.5</td><td>98.5</td><td>1.81 (1.68&ndash;1.94)</td><td>0.29</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>20&ndash;49</bold></td><td>88.3</td><td>22.8</td><td>0.26 (0.24&ndash;0.28)</td><td>94.9</td><td>70.4</td><td>0.74 (0.72&ndash;0.77)</td><td>0.35</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>50&ndash;64</bold></td><td>131.8</td><td>17.0</td><td>0.13 (0.11&ndash;0.15)</td><td>145.4</td><td>54.4</td><td>0.37 (0.35&ndash;0.40)</td><td>0.34</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>65&ndash;74</bold></td><td>215.9</td><td>48.7</td><td>0.23 (0.20&ndash;0.26)</td><td>213.4</td><td>66.1</td><td>0.31 (0.28&ndash;0.34)</td><td>0.73</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>75&ndash;84</bold></td><td>431.1</td><td>107.0</td><td>0.25 (0.22&ndash;0.28)</td><td>423.7</td><td>115.6</td><td>0.27 (0.25&ndash;0.30)</td><td>0.91</td><td>0.26</td></tr><tr><td><bold>&ge;85</bold></td><td>853.1</td><td>308.4</td><td>0.36 (0.32&ndash;0.41)</td><td>732.2</td><td>303.0</td><td>0.41 (0.37&ndash;0.46)</td><td>0.87</td><td>0.10</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Doctors' office visits</bold></td><td><bold>All ages</bold></td><td>813.6</td><td>173.0</td><td>0.21 (0.21&ndash;0.22)</td><td>587.7</td><td>306.2</td><td>0.52 (0.51&ndash;0.53)</td><td>0.41</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>&lt;5</bold></td><td>1,007.0</td><td>368.5</td><td>0.37 (0.35&ndash;0.39)</td><td>479.8</td><td>596.6</td><td>1.24 (1.16&ndash;1.33)</td><td>0.29</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>5&ndash;19</bold></td><td>637.4</td><td>274.9</td><td>0.43 (0.42&ndash;0.44)</td><td>430.2</td><td>481.7</td><td>1.12 (1.09&ndash;1.15)</td><td>0.39</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>20&ndash;49</bold></td><td>705.0</td><td>121.4</td><td>0.17 (0.17&ndash;0.18)</td><td>586.0</td><td>286.5</td><td>0.49 (0.48&ndash;0.50)</td><td>0.35</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>50&ndash;64</bold></td><td>935.7</td><td>87.3</td><td>0.09 (0.09&ndash;0.10)</td><td>787.7</td><td>207.3</td><td>0.26 (0.25&ndash;0.27)</td><td>0.35</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>65&ndash;74</bold></td><td>928.5</td><td>120.9</td><td>0.13 (0.12&ndash;0.14)</td><td>605.5</td><td>89.3</td><td>0.15 (0.13&ndash;0.17)</td><td>0.88</td><td>0.14</td></tr><tr><td><bold>75&ndash;84</bold></td><td>1440.1</td><td>245.5</td><td>0.17 (0.16&ndash;0.18)</td><td>720.9</td><td>109.3</td><td>0.15 (0.13&ndash;0.18)</td><td>1.12</td><td>0.16</td></tr><tr><td><bold>&ge;85</bold></td><td>2,610.1</td><td>614.7</td><td>0.24 (0.22&ndash;0.25)</td><td>835.9</td><td>164.5</td><td>0.02 (0.17&ndash;0.23)</td><td>1.20</td><td>0.06</td></tr></tbody></table> --><!-- <table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt301"><p>*<italic>p</italic>-Value for comparison between post- versus pre-RRs for Ontario and other provinces combined (<italic>z</italic>-test).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot> --></table-wrap>
        <p>Overall, influenza-associated health care use decreased more in Ontario than other
          provinces for hospitalizations (RR = 0.25 versus 0.44, ratio of RRs
          = 0.58, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), ED use (RR = 0.31 versus
          0.70, ratio of RRs = 0.45, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and doctors'
          office visits (RR = 0.21 versus 0.53, ratio of RRs = 0.41,
            <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). In age-specific analyses, greater decreases were
          consistently observed in Ontario than other provinces for age groups &lt;65 y. For
          seniors, greater decreases were observed in Ontario than other provinces for
          hospitalizations among those aged 65–84 y and for ED use among those
          65–74 y.</p>
        <p>There were no patterns detected in the standardized residual plots against time, and no
          evidence of influential provinces (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed-0050211-st002">Table S2</xref>). A greater than expected number of outliers
          occurred during the 5 wk each year that influenza activity was most intense, however,
          since the main purpose of the model was to estimate the baseline rate in the absence of
          influenza activity, these were not of major concern. The mean first order autocorrelation
          coefficients (<italic>r</italic>) including (excluding) influenza spikes were 0.051
          (0.039) for mortality, 0.255 (0.209) for hospitalizations, 0.398 (0.312) for ED use, and
          0.548 (0.492) for doctors' office visits.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Sensitivity Analyses</title>
        <p>The sensitivity analyses generally produced similar RR ratios as the primary analysis for
          tests of consistency, smaller RR ratios for tests of amplification, larger RR ratios for
          tests of attenuation, and RR ratios approximately equal to 1 for tests of specificity, as
          expected (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-0050211-t004">Table 4</xref>). Some exceptions
          were noted, in particular mortality for R&amp;C conditions, which was not increased as
          anticipated; the secondary outcomes for ED use and office visits (selected respiratory
          conditions), which were not attenuated as anticipated; and the analysis for health care
          use including only A(H3N2) seasons resulted in attenuation rather than consistency
          compared to the primary analysis.</p>
        <table-wrap content-type="2col" id="pmed-0050211-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
            <p>Sensitivity Analyses</p>
          </caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.t004" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup><col id="tb4col1" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col2" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col3" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col4" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col5" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col6" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col7" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col8" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col9" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col10" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col11" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3"><hr/>Mortality and Health Care Use</td><td rowspan="3"><hr/>Analysis</td><td rowspan="3"><hr/>Parameters</td><td colspan="6"><hr/>Mean Annual Influenza-Associated Event Rates (per 100,000)</td><td rowspan="3"><hr/>Ratio of Ontario/ Other RRs</td><td rowspan="3"><hr/><italic>p</italic>-Value*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/>Ontario</td><td colspan="3"><hr/>Other Provinces Combined</td></tr><tr><td><hr/>Pre-2000</td><td><hr/>Post-2000</td><td><hr/>Post- Versus Pre-RR (95&percnt; CI)</td><td><hr/>Pre-2000</td><td><hr/>Post-2000</td><td><hr/>Post- Versus Pre-RR (95&percnt; CI)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>Deaths</bold></td><td><bold>Primary analysis</bold></td><td>14.8</td><td>3.9</td><td>0.26 (0.20&ndash;0.34)</td><td>16.1</td><td>6.9</td><td>0.43 (0.37&ndash;0.5)</td><td>0.61</td><td>0.002</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of consistency (similar effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Wider influenza season (5&percnt; threshold)</bold></td><td>15.4</td><td>4.1</td><td>0.26 (0.19&ndash;0.36)</td><td>16.4</td><td>7.4</td><td>0.45 (0.38&ndash;0.53)</td><td>0.59</td><td>0.003</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Lag viral data backward 1 wk</bold></td><td>14.4</td><td>3.5</td><td>0.25 (0.18&ndash;0.33)</td><td>16.2</td><td>6.9</td><td>0.42 (0.36&ndash;0.49)</td><td>0.58</td><td>0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Lag viral data forward 1 wk</bold></td><td>13.8</td><td>3.3</td><td>0.24 (0.17&ndash;0.32)</td><td>15.8</td><td>6.8</td><td>0.43 (0.37&ndash;0.51)</td><td>0.54</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Start with 1993&ndash;1994 season</bold></td><td>10.1</td><td>3.2</td><td>0.31 (0.23&ndash;0.43)</td><td>3.8</td><td>1.9</td><td>0.50 (0.35&ndash;0.72)</td><td>0.63</td><td>0.05</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Include only A(H3N2)-predominant seasons</bold></td><td>16.4</td><td>7.2</td><td>0.44 (0.35&ndash;0.55)</td><td>6.2</td><td>4.1</td><td>0.66 (0.51&ndash;0.85)</td><td>0.67</td><td>0.02</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of amplification (increased effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Secondary outcome (R&amp;C conditions)</bold></td><td>12.0</td><td>2.8</td><td>0.23 (0.18&ndash;0.30)</td><td>12.3</td><td>4.1</td><td>0.33 (0.28&ndash;0.39)</td><td>0.70</td><td>0.018</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Exclude 2003&ndash;2004 A/Fujian poor match season</bold></td><td>15.0</td><td>2.0</td><td>0.13 (0.08&ndash;0.23)</td><td>16.7</td><td>5.2</td><td>0.31 (0.25&ndash;0.39)</td><td>0.44</td><td>0.005</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Exclude all poor match seasons (1997&ndash;1998, 2003&ndash;2004)</bold></td><td>14.7</td><td>2.0</td><td>0.14 (0.08&ndash;0.23)</td><td>15.5</td><td>5.5</td><td>0.36 (0.29&ndash;0.44)</td><td>0.38</td><td>0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of specificity (no effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Summer period (events not influenza-associated)</bold></td><td>58.3</td><td>53.0</td><td>0.91 (0.89&ndash;0.93)</td><td>60.7</td><td>56.8</td><td>0.93 (0.92&ndash;0.95)</td><td>0.97</td><td>0.02</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Control condition during February (non-R&amp;C)</bold></td><td>31.5</td><td>31.6</td><td>1.00 (0.98&ndash;1.03)</td><td>32.4</td><td>34.4</td><td>1.06 (1.04&ndash;1.08)</td><td>0.94</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Hospitalizations</bold></td><td><bold>Primary analysis</bold></td><td>33.4</td><td>8.5</td><td>0.25 (0.23&ndash;0.28)</td><td>44.9</td><td>19.8</td><td>0.44 (0.42&ndash;0.46)</td><td>0.58</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of consistency (similar effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Wider influenza season (5&percnt; threshold)</bold></td><td>37.2</td><td>9.6</td><td>0.26 (0.23&ndash;0.29)</td><td>47.7</td><td>21.8</td><td>0.46 (0.44&ndash;0.48)</td><td>0.56</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Lag viral data backward 1 wk</bold></td><td>34.9</td><td>9.1</td><td>0.26 (0.24&ndash;0.29)</td><td>44.1</td><td>19.2</td><td>0.43 (0.41&ndash;0.45)</td><td>0.60</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Lag viral data forward 1 wk</bold></td><td>32.0</td><td>7.7</td><td>0.24 (0.22&ndash;0.27)</td><td>45.2</td><td>20.0</td><td>0.44 (0.42&ndash;0.46)</td><td>0.54</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Start with 1993&ndash;1994 season</bold></td><td>21.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>0.39 (0.35&ndash;0.43)</td><td>13.5</td><td>7.6</td><td>0.57 (0.52&ndash;0.61)</td><td>0.69</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Include only A(H3N2)-predominant seasons</bold></td><td>35.3</td><td>16.0</td><td>0.45 (0.41&ndash;0.49)</td><td>43.6</td><td>29.2</td><td>0.67 (0.64&ndash;0.7)</td><td>0.67</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Any-listed diagnosis</bold></td><td>35.0</td><td>9.2</td><td>0.26 (0.24&ndash;0.29)</td><td>45.6</td><td>19.2</td><td>0.42 (0.40&ndash;0.44)</td><td>0.62</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Main-listed diagnosis</bold></td><td>23.0</td><td>7.3</td><td>0.32 (0.29&ndash;0.35)</td><td>33.3</td><td>16.1</td><td>0.48 (0.46&ndash;0.51)</td><td>0.66</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of amplification (increased effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Exclude 2003&ndash;2004 A/Fujian poor match season</bold></td><td>32.7</td><td>4.0</td><td>0.12 (0.10&ndash;0.15)</td><td>45.1</td><td>16.5</td><td>0.37 (0.35&ndash;0.39)</td><td>0.33</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Exclude all poor match seasons (1997&ndash;1998, 2003&ndash;2004)</bold></td><td>32.8</td><td>3.0</td><td>0.09 (0.07&ndash;0.12)</td><td>45.4</td><td>17.2</td><td>0.38 (0.36&ndash;0.40)</td><td>0.24</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of attenuation (decreased effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Secondary outcome (all respiratory conditions)</bold></td><td>58.5</td><td>19.5</td><td>0.33 (0.31&ndash;0.36)</td><td>85.3</td><td>40.6</td><td>0.48 (0.46&ndash;0.50)</td><td>0.70</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>End with 2004&ndash;2005 season</bold></td><td>35.0</td><td>13.0</td><td>0.37 (0.35&ndash;0.40)</td><td>44.3</td><td>18.8</td><td>0.42 (0.41&ndash;0.44)</td><td>0.87</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of specificity (no effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Summer period (events not influenza-associated)</bold></td><td>25.7</td><td>21.7</td><td>0.84 (0.82&ndash;0.87)</td><td>26.6</td><td>21.2</td><td>0.80 (0.78&ndash;0.82)</td><td>1.05</td><td>0.004</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Control condition during February (hernia)</bold></td><td>16.8</td><td>15.6</td><td>0.93 (0.90&ndash;0.96)</td><td>21.4</td><td>18.2</td><td>0.85 (0.83&ndash;0.87)</td><td>1.09</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>ED use</bold></td><td><bold>Primary analysis</bold></td><td>139.6</td><td>43.6</td><td>0.31 (0.30&ndash;0.32)</td><td>125.0</td><td>85.9</td><td>0.69 (0.67&ndash;0.70)</td><td>0.45</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of consistency (similar effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Wider influenza season (5&percnt; threshold)</bold></td><td>151.6</td><td>46.4</td><td>0.31 (0.29&ndash;0.32)</td><td>127.2</td><td>93.3</td><td>0.73 (0.72&ndash;0.75)</td><td>0.42</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Lag viral data backward 1 wk</bold></td><td>143.4</td><td>45.1</td><td>0.31 (0.30&ndash;0.33)</td><td>123.8</td><td>84.2</td><td>0.68 (0.66&ndash;0.70)</td><td>0.46</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Lag viral data forward 1 wk</bold></td><td>132.4</td><td>38.7</td><td>0.29 (0.28&ndash;0.30)</td><td>120.0</td><td>81.8</td><td>0.68 (0.66&ndash;0.70)</td><td>0.43</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Start with 1993&ndash;1994 season</bold></td><td>93.1</td><td>42.3</td><td>0.45 (0.44&ndash;0.47)</td><td>89.6</td><td>87.1</td><td>0.97 (0.94&ndash;1.00)</td><td>0.47</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Include only A(H3N2)-predominant seasons</bold></td><td>144.3</td><td>70.9</td><td>0.49 (0.47&ndash;0.51)</td><td>123.8</td><td>91.2</td><td>0.74 (0.71&ndash;0.76)</td><td>0.66</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of amplification (increased effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Exclude 2003&ndash;2004 A/Fujian poor match season</bold></td><td>138.7</td><td>30.3</td><td>0.22 (0.21&ndash;0.23)</td><td>124.9</td><td>91.8</td><td>0.74 (0.72&ndash;0.75)</td><td>0.30</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Exclude all poor match seasons (1997&ndash;1998, 2003&ndash;2004)</bold></td><td>139.7</td><td>27.6</td><td>0.20 (0.19&ndash;0.21)</td><td>136.8</td><td>92.9</td><td>0.68 (0.66&ndash;0.70)</td><td>0.29</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of attenuation (decreased effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Secondary outcome (selected respiratory conditions)</bold></td><td>425.7</td><td>162.3</td><td>0.38 (0.37&ndash;0.39)</td><td>337.1</td><td>318.1</td><td>0.94 (0.93&ndash;0.96)</td><td>0.40</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of specificity (no effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Summer period (events not influenza-associated)</bold></td><td>57.5</td><td>51.5</td><td>0.90 (0.88&ndash;0.91)</td><td>46.5</td><td>42.1</td><td>0.91 (0.89&ndash;0.93)</td><td>0.99</td><td>0.44</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Control condition during February (lacerations)</bold></td><td>114.2</td><td>95.6</td><td>0.84 (0.83&ndash;0.85)</td><td>133.2</td><td>122.5</td><td>0.92 (0.91&ndash;0.93)</td><td>0.91</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Doctors' office visits</bold></td><td><bold>Primary analysis</bold></td><td>813.6</td><td>173.0</td><td>0.21 (0.21&ndash;0.22)</td><td>587.7</td><td>306.2</td><td>0.52 (0.51&ndash;0.53)</td><td>0.41</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of consistency (similar effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Wider influenza season (5&percnt; threshold)</bold></td><td>865.7</td><td>198.9</td><td>0.23 (0.23&ndash;0.23)</td><td>596.0</td><td>330.2</td><td>0.55 (0.55&ndash;0.56)</td><td>0.41</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Lag viral data backward 1 wk</bold></td><td>838.2</td><td>182.0</td><td>0.22 (0.21&ndash;0.22)</td><td>566.0</td><td>292.5</td><td>0.52 (0.51&ndash;0.52)</td><td>0.42</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Lag viral data forward 1 wk</bold></td><td>783.3</td><td>159.1</td><td>0.20 (0.20&ndash;0.21)</td><td>578.0</td><td>299.8</td><td>0.52 (0.51&ndash;0.53)</td><td>0.39</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Start with 1993&ndash;1994 season</bold></td><td>528.7</td><td>164.4</td><td>0.31 (0.31&ndash;0.32)</td><td>491.2</td><td>343.3</td><td>0.70 (0.69&ndash;0.71)</td><td>0.44</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Include only A(H3N2)-predominant seasons</bold></td><td>858.5</td><td>284.9</td><td>0.33 (0.33&ndash;0.34)</td><td>585.0</td><td>260.6</td><td>0.45 (0.44&ndash;0.45)</td><td>0.74</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of amplification (increased effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Exclude 2003&ndash;2004 A/ Fujian poor match season</bold></td><td>804.1</td><td>125.3</td><td>0.16 (0.15&ndash;0.16)</td><td>582.6</td><td>353.0</td><td>0.61 (0.60&ndash;0.61)</td><td>0.26</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Exclude all poor match seasons (1997&ndash;1998, 2003&ndash;2004)</bold></td><td>812.1</td><td>106.3</td><td>0.13 (0.13&ndash;0.14)</td><td>638.3</td><td>361.3</td><td>0.57 (0.56&ndash;0.57)</td><td>0.23</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of attenuation (decreased effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Secondary outcome (selected respiratory conditions<sup>a</sup>)</bold></td><td>3130.8</td><td>907.4</td><td>0.29 (0.28&ndash;0.30)</td><td>1922.0</td><td>1486.5</td><td>0.77 (0.76&ndash;0.79)</td><td>0.37</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tests of specificity (no effect expected)</bold></td><td><bold>Summer period (events not influenza-associated)</bold></td><td>194.6</td><td>138.9</td><td>0.71 (0.71&ndash;0.72)</td><td>172.7</td><td>109.9</td><td>0.64 (0.63&ndash;0.64)</td><td>1.12</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Control condition during February (lacerations)</bold></td><td>127.6</td><td>109.0</td><td>0.85 (0.84&ndash;0.87)</td><td>235.1</td><td>190.3</td><td>0.81 (0.80&ndash;0.82)</td><td>1.06</td><td>&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table> --><!-- <table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt401"><p><sup>a</sup>Selected respiratory conditions: P&amp;I, acute respiratory diseases, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, and otitis media.</p></fn><fn id="nt402"><p>*<italic>p</italic>-Value for comparison between post- versus pre-RRs for Ontario and other provinces combined (<italic>z</italic>-test).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot> --></table-wrap>
        <p>We found a dose-response relationship where greater increases in vaccine uptake were
          associated with greater decreases in influenza-associated outcomes for all health care use
          outcomes for age groups &lt;65 y (all slopes negative, <italic>p</italic> &lt;
          0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0050211-g002">Figure 2</xref>). For the elderly,
          the opposite relationship was observed for mortality and hospitalizations, and no
          relationship was noted for ED use and office visits.</p>
        <fig id="pmed-0050211-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Sensitivity Analysis to Assess the Presence of a Dose-Response Relationship in
              Age Groups Older (A) and Younger (B) than 65 y for (from Left to Right) Mortality
              [(A) only], Hospitalizations, ED Use, and Doctors' Office
              Visits</title>
            <p>The vertical axis represents the age group-, province-, and outcome-specific post-
              versus pre-2000 RRs. The horizontal axis represents the absolute post- versus pre-2000
              change in influenza vaccination rates (%). The bubble sizes represent the
              inverse of the variances of the post- versus pre-2000 RRs. The
              <italic>p-</italic>values correspond to the significance of the estimates for the
              slope of the lines from weighted linear regression models
              (<italic>t-</italic>tests).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>After introduction of the world's first large-scale UIIP, we found that
        influenza-associated mortality, hospitalizations, ED use, and office visits decreased more
        overall in Ontario compared with other provinces. Age-specific analyses revealed greater
        temporal drops in health care use in Ontario compared to other provinces for younger age
        groups (i.e., ratios of pre-/post-RRs for Ontario versus other provinces being closer to
        zero), with the gap between the RRs narrowing with increasing age (i.e., ratios of RRs being
        closer to one). This is consistent with the age-specific pattern for temporal changes in
        vaccine uptake, with greater increases over time in Ontario compared to other provinces for
        younger age groups leading to greater expectations of benefits from the UIIP. However, for
        older age groups, in particular those ≥75 y, greater incremental increases in vaccine
        uptake over time were observed in other provinces compared to Ontario, yet among all the
        outcomes, none of the RR ratios were greater than one. This result is contrary to what one
        would expect based on the assumption that greater increases in vaccine uptake in those
        populations should have been associated with greater decreases in outcome rates, and
        therefore suggests that influenza vaccines may not be as effective in reducing mortality and
        health care use in older people compared to younger age groups.</p>
      <p>Sensitivity analyses demonstrated consistency, specificity, and the presence of a
        dose-response relationship between temporal changes in vaccination rates and outcomes among
        those &lt;65 y. A limited number of inconsistent results warrant discussion. While the
        analysis restricted to A(H3N2)-predominant seasons was expected to be a test of consistency,
        the results for the three health care use outcomes suggested effect attenuation. This was
        likely because that analysis over-weighted the influence of the 2003–2004 poor
        match season by excluding the 2000–2001 and 2002–2003
        non-A(H3N2)-predominant seasons. Other unexpected results were the lack of attenuation when
        examining the less specific secondary outcomes for ED use and office visits. This may have
        been because the selected conditions are nearly as specific to influenza as the primary
        outcome. Another inconsistency was the lack of amplification for the supposedly more
        specific secondary outcome for mortality, respiratory, and circulatory conditions. This lack
        of amplification may be because R&amp;C mortality accounts for the bulk of the mortality
        from all causes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b034">34</xref>]. Regardless, the totality of
        these results suggest that introduction of universal influenza vaccination in Ontario has
        been associated with incremental benefits in terms of mortality and health care use compared
        to targeted programs.</p>
      <p>A previous study reported that UIIP introduction did not lead to reduced influenza
        incidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b035">35</xref>], but
        used numbers of laboratory-confirmed cases as the outcome. Their negative finding may have
        been a result of ascertainment bias arising from a 10-fold increase in testing for influenza
        over the study period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b036">36</xref>].</p>
      <p>Although many studies have found that for years with good vaccine match, influenza vaccines
        are effective in preventing hospitalizations and mortality in the elderly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b002">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b003">3</xref>], the true extent of vaccine effectiveness
        versus the effects of healthy user biases has been the subject of much recent debate
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b006">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b009">9</xref>]. This study does not resolve
        that debate, however, the findings suggest that in elderly populations, increasing
        vaccination levels were not associated with decreases in influenza-associated outcomes, and
        may have even been associated with increased risk of mortality and hospitalizations.
        Potential explanations include immune senescence, or a decline in immune responsiveness with
        advancing age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b037">37</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b040">40</xref>],
        and uncontrolled confounding. In working age adults, the effectiveness of influenza vaccines
        for preventing influenza infection and health care use is less controversial, and the
        results from this study are consistent with this literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b004">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b005">5</xref>]. While previous studies have failed to demonstrate reductions in
        hospitalizations among working age adults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b041">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b042">42</xref>] and in health care use among children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b005">5</xref>], the findings from this study suggest that
        increasing population-level vaccine uptake in these age groups may be associated with
        substantial reductions in these outcomes.</p>
      <p>Despite universal availability of publicly insured health care services, enhanced access to
        free influenza vaccines in Ontario since 2000, and extensive media communications, only an
        estimated average of 38% of the overall household population reported receiving
        them during the post-UIIP introduction period. Although vaccine uptake was higher in older
        age groups (e.g., approximately 80% among those ≥75 y), it is uncertain
        that levels required for appreciable herd immunity effects were obtained in the overall
        population, particularly in younger age groups. Several studies have claimed the existence
        of indirect benefits arising from vaccinating children, including a report on the impact of
        vaccinating a community's children on illness rates in the adult population during the 1968
        pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b043">43</xref>], a
        retrospective ecological analysis of a mass vaccination program for schoolchildren and
        trends in seniors' mortality in Japan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b044">44</xref>], and a clinical trial that reported decreased
        rates of visits for acute respiratory infections among adults after vaccinating children
        with live-attenuated influenza vaccines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b045">45</xref>]. Furthermore, a modeling study of the
        potential effects of vaccinating children on outcomes in the population suggested that
        increasing vaccination rates of children from 20% to 40% would lead to
        approximately 50% reductions in cases of influenza, hospitalizations, and deaths
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b046">46</xref>]. In Ontario,
        vaccination rates among those aged 12 to 19 y increased from 16% to
        31% over the study period, while in other provinces, rates increased from
        6% to 11%. We observed more than 50% reductions in both
        influenza-associated mortality and health care use over the study period among seniors in
        both Ontario and other provinces. The bulk of these decreases are likely attributable to
        less severe influenza seasons across Canada in the postintervention period, but the larger
        observed decreases in mortality for seniors aged ≥85 y, hospitalizations for seniors
        aged 65–84 y, and ED use for those aged 65–74 y in Ontario compared to
        other provinces may be compatible with some indirect benefits as previously posited
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b046">46</xref>].
        Unfortunately, this study does not permit determination of the direct versus indirect
        benefits of universal vaccination.</p>
      <p>Strengths of the study include the unique opportunity for a “natural
        experiment” and the fact that size of the populations of Ontario and the other
        provinces combined are comparable. We addressed most of the criteria outlined recently in a
        framework for addressing residual bias by Simonsen et al., including: the selection of more
        specific outcomes for the primary study outcomes (with the exception of all-cause mortality)
        and the use of consistent modeling techniques and laboratory surveillance data to estimate
        influenza-associated events to reduce the potential dilution of benefits from universal
        vaccination that might arise from employing all influenza season-associated events as the
        outcome measure (end-point specificity); the sensitivity analyses with poor match seasons
        excluded (vaccine match); and the inclusion of events only during periods of peak influenza
        activity and the sensitivity analysis using a summer period (seasonality) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b008">8</xref>]. Lastly, it is notable that the
        results are consistent across three distinct outcomes (hospitalizations, ED use, and office
        visits), reducing the likelihood of spurious findings attributable to data quality or other
        biases.</p>
      <p>This study has a number of limitations. Individual-level vaccination and outcome data were
        not available, necessitating an ecological study. However, use of this design is appropriate
        for assessing the public health impact of a population-wide intervention. As with other
        influenza studies using health databases, the selected outcomes are nonspecific and may be
        due to causes other than influenza, but the strategies described above partly address this
        issue. The quality and reliability of the outcome data over time, for multiple
        jurisdictions, and across different classification systems (i.e., ICD-9 versus ICD-10)
        remain uncertain. The validity of statistical models to estimate influenza-associated events
        is limited by uncertainty of their accuracy, in spite of our best efforts to achieve optimal
        model fit. Laboratory viral surveillance data are potentially susceptible to ascertainment
        and reporting biases; the weekly proportion of tests positive is felt to be the most robust
        measure of viral activity. Another drawback of the study is that no vaccination rate data
        are available for those &lt;12 y of age, an age group that experiences particularly high
        rates of less severe influenza-associated outcomes, or for institutionalized seniors, a
        group that experiences higher rates of more severe outcomes. Relatively high residual
        autocorrelation was likely due to the difficulty in modeling a baseline influenza rate that
        did not display purely cyclical behaviour despite inclusion of higher order Fourier series
        terms; however, it suggests the possibility of residual confounding due to season-specific
        factors such as temperature or relative humidity. We were also not able to include other
        potential confounders such as strain-specific influenza surveillance data, prevalence of
        individual comorbidities, socioeconomic status, smoking rates, polysaccharide or conjugated
        pneumococcal vaccination, antiviral medication use, and provincial health care system
        capacity, but we have no reason to believe that these factors changed more over time in
        Ontario compared to other provinces. For example, pneumococcal vaccination of children has
        been shown to reduce rates of pneumonia-related admissions in older age groups
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b047">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed-0050211-b048">48</xref>] and might have contributed to temporal changes
        in health care use for pneumonia, but Ontario's infant pneumococcal vaccination program was
        introduced in January 2005, subsequent to the introduction of pneumococcal vaccination
        programs in four other provinces (September 2002 in Alberta, September 2003 in British
        Columbia, October 2004 in Manitoba, and December 2004 in Quebec) (personal correspondence,
        A.-M. Frescura, Public Health Agency of Canada). Therefore the greater drops in
        influenza-associated outcomes observed in Ontario after 2000 are unlikely to be attributable
        to pneumococcal vaccination. Because of the observational nature of our study, we cannot
        rule out the possibility of “healthy population” bias (i.e., healthier
        populations are more likely to get vaccinated and have better outcomes), but our study
        design and various tests of specificity support the absence of such a bias. Most of the
        limitations arise from the necessity of using existing health data. As we are not aware of
        other data or approaches that can resolve these limitations, we believe this study
        represents the best possible evaluation of a real-world natural experiment that Ontario's
        unique strategy to offer influenza vaccination to the entire population represents.</p>
      <p>Despite these limitations, this study provides suggestive evidence of the population-based
        effectiveness of universal vaccination programs using inactivated influenza vaccines. It is
        not possible to definitively declare superiority of universal programs over targeted
        programs, as the findings from this study may not generalize to other settings. But by
        reducing financial barriers and increasing awareness and accessibility, universal
        vaccination may be an effective strategy for increasing a population's protection against
        influenza. Future studies to develop more immunogenic influenza vaccines, to test novel
        strategies for further increasing vaccine uptake, and to examine the cost-effectiveness of
        universal influenza vaccination may be valuable.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pmed-0050211-sg001" mimetype="application/mspowerpoint" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.sg001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Estimating Influenza-Associated Events, Using P&amp;I Hospitalizations for
            Ontario Females ≥85 y as an Example</title>
          <p>The left vertical axis represents hospitalization rate per 100,000. The horizontal axis
            represents time. The solid black line represents observed hospitalizations, the dashed
            black line represents baseline hospitalizations in the hypothetical absence of
            influenza, and the black vertical bars represent influenza-associated hospitalizations
            (observed hospitalizations minus baseline hospitalizations). Viral surveillance data
            (grey shaded areas) are expressed as the weekly percentage of tests positive on the
            right vertical axis. The grey dashed vertical lines denote periods of peak influenza
            activity.</p>
          <p>(539 KB PPT)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pmed-0050211-st001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.st001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Duration of Periods of Peak Influenza Activity, Influenza A(H3N2) Predominance, and
            Vaccine Antigenic Mismatch between Circulating and Vaccine Strains, by Influenza Season
            and Province</title>
          <p>(97 KB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pmed-0050211-st002" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.st002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Analysis to Evaluate the Presence of Influential Provinces by Removing Them
            Individually from the Model</title>
          <p>(74 KB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pmed-0050211-sd001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050211.sd001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Description of the Multivariate Poisson Regression Model</title>
          <p>(43 KB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank the sentinel laboratories participating in the Respiratory Virus Detection
        Surveillance System and the FluWatch team at the Public Health Agency of Canada for
        providing the viral surveillance data, and Charles Burchill and Wendy Au for assistance with
        data preparation and analyses of the Manitoba data. JCK had full access to all of the data
        in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the
        data analysis.</p>
    </ack>
    
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>CI</term>
          <def>
            <p>confidence interval</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>ED</term>
          <def>
            <p>emergency department</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>P&amp;I</term>
          <def>
            <p>pneumonia and influenza</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>R&amp;C</term>
          <def>
            <p>respiratory and circulatory</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>RR</term>
          <def>
            <p>relative rate</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>UIIP</term>
          <def>
            <p>universal influenza immunization program</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b001">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nichol</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>The efficacy, effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of inactivated influenza
            virus vaccines.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>1769</fpage>
          <lpage>1775</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b002">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Rivetti</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Jefferson</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Rudin</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Rivetti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Vaccines for preventing influenza in the elderly.</article-title>
          <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>CD004876</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b003">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nichol</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nordin</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>DB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Mullooly</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hak</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Effectiveness of influenza vaccine in the community-dwelling
            elderly.</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <volume>357</volume>
          <fpage>1373</fpage>
          <lpage>1381</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b004">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Jefferson</surname>
              <given-names>TO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Rivetti</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Di</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Rivetti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Demicheli</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Vaccines for preventing influenza in healthy adults.</article-title>
          <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
          <comment>CD001269.</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b005">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Jefferson</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Rivetti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Harnden</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Di Pietrantonj</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Demicheli</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Vaccines for preventing influenza in healthy children.</article-title>
          <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
          <comment>CD004879.</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b006">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Simonsen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Reichert</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Viboud</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Blackwelder</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Impact of influenza vaccination on seasonal mortality in the US elderly
            population.</article-title>
          <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
          <volume>165</volume>
          <fpage>265</fpage>
          <lpage>272</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b007">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Jackson</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Jackson</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Neuzil</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Weiss</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Evidence of bias in estimates of influenza vaccine effectiveness in
            seniors.</article-title>
          <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>337</fpage>
          <lpage>344</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b008">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Simonsen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Viboud</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Jackson</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Mortality benefits of influenza vaccination in elderly people: an ongoing
            controversy.</article-title>
          <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>658</fpage>
          <lpage>666</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b009">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Jackson</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Weiss</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Neuzil</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Barlow</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Influenza vaccination and risk of community-acquired pneumonia in
            immunocompetent elderly people: a population-based, nested case-control
            study.</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <volume>372</volume>
          <fpage>398</fpage>
          <lpage>405</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b010">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Fiore</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Shay</surname>
              <given-names>DK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Haber</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Iskander</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Uyeki</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Prevention and control of influenza. Recommendations of the Advisory
            Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP), 2007.</article-title>
          <source>MMWR Recomm Rep</source>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b011">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <collab xlink:type="simple">National Advisory Committee on Immunization (NACI)</collab>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Statement on influenza vaccination for the 2007–2008 season. An
            Advisory Committee Statement (ACS).</article-title>
          <source>Can Commun Dis Rep</source>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b012">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <collab xlink:type="simple">Canada NewsWire</collab>
          <year>2000 July 25</year>
          <source>Ontario invests $38 million to ease emergency room pressures with universal
            vaccination program</source>
          <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ogov.newswire.ca/ontario/GPOE/2000/07/25/c6018.html?lmatch=&amp;lang=_e.html" xlink:type="simple">http://ogov.newswire.ca/ontario/GPOE/2000/07/25/c6018.html?lmatch=&amp;lang=_e.html</ext-link>.</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b013">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Schabas</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>Mass influenza vaccination in Ontario: a sensible move.</article-title>
          <source>Can Med Assoc J</source>
          <volume>164</volume>
          <fpage>36</fpage>
          <lpage>37</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b014">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Demicheli</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>Mass influenza vaccination in Ontario: is it worthwhile.</article-title>
          <source>Can Med Assoc J</source>
          <volume>164</volume>
          <fpage>38</fpage>
          <lpage>39</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b015">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kwong</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Rosella</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Johansen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Trends in influenza vaccination in Canada, 1996/97 to 2005.</article-title>
          <source>Health Rep</source>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b016">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Last</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <source>A dictionary of epidemiology</source>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b017">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Beland</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Canadian community health survey–methodological
            overview.</article-title>
          <source>Health Rep</source>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>9</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b018">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Tambay</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Catlin</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1995</year>
          <article-title>Sample design of the national population health survey.</article-title>
          <source>Health Rep</source>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>29</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b019">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Johansen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Mao</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Marcoux</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Influenza vaccination.</article-title>
          <source>Health Rep</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>33</fpage>
          <lpage>43</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b020">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Johansen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Sambell</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Flu shots - national and provincial/territorial trends.</article-title>
          <source>Health Rep</source>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>49</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b021">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kwong</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Sambell</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Johansen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Stukel</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Manuel</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>The effect of universal influenza immunization on vaccination rates in
            Ontario.</article-title>
          <source>Health Rep</source>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>31</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b022">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Lui</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kendal</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1987</year>
          <article-title>Impact of influenza epidemics on mortality in the United States from
            October 1972 to May 1985.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Public Health</source>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <fpage>712</fpage>
          <lpage>716</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b023">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Simonsen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Clarke</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Williamson</surname>
              <given-names>GD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Stroup</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Arden</surname>
              <given-names>NH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>1997</year>
          <article-title>The impact of influenza epidemics on mortality: introducing a severity
            index.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Public Health</source>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>1944</fpage>
          <lpage>1950</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b024">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <collab xlink:type="simple">[Anonymous]</collab>
          <year>2005</year>
          <source>Improving health care data in Ontario: ICES investigative report to the Ontario
            Ministry of Health and Long-Term Care</source>
          <publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b025">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>McCullagh</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nelder</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1989</year>
          <source>Generalized linear models</source>
          <edition>2nd edition.</edition>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b026">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Shay</surname>
              <given-names>DK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Weintraub</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Brammer</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Mortality associated with influenza and respiratory syncytial virus in the
            United States.</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <volume>289</volume>
          <fpage>179</fpage>
          <lpage>186</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b027">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Shay</surname>
              <given-names>DK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Weintraub</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Brammer</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Bridges</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Influenza-associated hospitalizations in the United States.</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <volume>292</volume>
          <fpage>1333</fpage>
          <lpage>1340</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b028">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Rothman</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1998</year>
          <source>Modern epidemiology</source>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Lippincott-Raven</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b029">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>RN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Minino</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hoyert</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Rosenberg</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>Comparability of cause of death between ICD-9 and ICD-10: preliminary
            estimates.</article-title>
          <source>Natl Vital Stat Rep</source>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b030">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <collab xlink:type="simple">Anonymous</collab>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Influenza in Canada: 2003–2004 season.</article-title>
          <source>Can Commun Dis Rep</source>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>18</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b031">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Gaglani</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Piedra</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Herschler</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Griffith</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kozinetz</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Direct and total effectiveness of the intranasal, live-attenuated,
            trivalent cold-adapted influenza virus vaccine against the 2000–2001 influenza
            A(H1N1) and B epidemic in healthy children.</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med</source>
          <volume>158</volume>
          <fpage>65</fpage>
          <lpage>73</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b032">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Menec</surname>
              <given-names>VH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Black</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>MacWilliam</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Aoki</surname>
              <given-names>FY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>The impact of influenza-associated respiratory illnesses on
            hospitalizations, physician visits, emergency room visits, and
            mortality.</article-title>
          <source>Can J Public Health</source>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>59</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b033">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <collab xlink:type="simple">Anonymous</collab>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Influenza in Canada–2004–2005 season.</article-title>
          <source>Can Commun Dis Rep</source>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>74</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b034">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Dushoff</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Plotkin</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Viboud</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Earn</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Simonsen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Mortality due to influenza in the United States–an annualized
            regression approach using multiple-cause mortality data.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>
          <volume>163</volume>
          <fpage>181</fpage>
          <lpage>187</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b035">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Groll</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Thomson</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Incidence of influenza in Ontario following the Universal Influenza
            Immunization Campaign.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>5245</fpage>
          <lpage>5250</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b036">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kwong</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Stukel</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>McGeer</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Manuel</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Appropriate measures of influenza immunization program
            effectiveness.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>967</fpage>
          <lpage>969</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b037">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Goodwin</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Viboud</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Simonsen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Antibody response to influenza vaccination in the elderly: a quantitative
            review.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>1159</fpage>
          <lpage>1169</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b038">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Vallejo</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Immune remodeling: lessons from repertoire alterations during chronological
            aging and in immune-mediated disease.</article-title>
          <source>Trends Mol Med</source>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>94</fpage>
          <lpage>102</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b039">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kang</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hong</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nolasco</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Dan</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Age-associated change in the frequency of memory CD4+ T cells
            impairs long term CD4+ T cell responses to influenza vaccine.</article-title>
          <source>J Immunol</source>
          <volume>173</volume>
          <fpage>673</fpage>
          <lpage>681</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b040">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Goronzy</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Fulbright</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Crowson</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Poland</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>O'Fallon</surname>
              <given-names>WM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>Value of immunological markers in predicting responsiveness to influenza
            vaccination in elderly individuals.</article-title>
          <source>J Virol</source>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <fpage>12182</fpage>
          <lpage>12187</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b041">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Bridges</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Meltzer</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Reeve</surname>
              <given-names>GR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Talamonti</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>Effectiveness and cost-benefit of influenza vaccination of healthy working
            adults: A randomized controlled trial.</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <volume>284</volume>
          <fpage>1655</fpage>
          <lpage>1663</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b042">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Mogabgab</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Leiderman</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1970</year>
          <article-title>Immunogenicity of 1967 polyvalent and 1968 Hong Kong influenza
            vaccines.</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <volume>211</volume>
          <fpage>1672</fpage>
          <lpage>1676</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b043">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Monto</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Davenport</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Napier</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Francis</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1970</year>
          <article-title>Modification of an outbreak of influenza in Tecumseh, Michigan by
            vaccination of schoolchildren.</article-title>
          <source>J Infect Dis</source>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <fpage>16</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b044">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Reichert</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Sugaya</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Fedson</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Glezen</surname>
              <given-names>WP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Simonsen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>The Japanese experience with vaccinating schoolchildren against
            influenza.</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <volume>344</volume>
          <fpage>889</fpage>
          <lpage>896</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b045">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Piedra</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Gaglani</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kozinetz</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Herschler</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Riggs</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Herd immunity in adults against influenza-related illnesses with use of the
            trivalent-live attenuated influenza vaccine (CAIV-T) in children.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>1540</fpage>
          <lpage>1548</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b046">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Weycker</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Edelsberg</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Halloran</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Longini</surname>
              <given-names>IM</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nizam</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Population-wide benefits of routine vaccination of children against
            influenza.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>1284</fpage>
          <lpage>1293</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b047">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Metlay</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Fishman</surname>
              <given-names>NO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Joffe</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Edelstein</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Impact of pediatric vaccination with pneumococcal conjugate vaccine on the
            risk of bacteremic pneumococcal pneumonia in adults.</article-title>
          <source>Vaccine</source>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>468</fpage>
          <lpage>475</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pmed-0050211-b048">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Grijalva</surname>
              <given-names>CG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nuorti</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Arbogast</surname>
              <given-names>PG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Edwards</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2007</year>
          <article-title>Decline in pneumonia admissions after routine childhood immunisation with
            pneumococcal conjugate vaccine in the USA: a time-series analysis.</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <volume>369</volume>
          <fpage>1179</fpage>
          <lpage>1186</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>