<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PGENETICS-D-13-01681</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular types</subject><subject>Molecular cell biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene regulatory networks</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene function</subject><subject>Molecular genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Cell Type-Specific Functions of <italic>Period</italic> Genes Revealed by Novel Adipocyte and Hepatocyte Circadian Clock Models</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Cell Type-Specific Clock Gene Function</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramanathan</surname><given-names>Chidambaram</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Haiyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Sanjoy K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gitis</surname><given-names>Paula J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>David K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogenesch</surname><given-names>John B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Andrew C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Biological Sciences, University of Memphis, Memphis, Tennessee, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Psychiatry, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, California, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Center for Chronobiology, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, California, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Veterans Affairs San Diego Healthcare System, San Diego, California, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Department of Pharmacology and Institute for Translational Medicine and Therapeutics, University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>Feinstone Genome Research Center, University of Memphis, Memphis, Tennessee, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>Hiroki R.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>RIKEN, Japan</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">acliu@memphis.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CR DKW JBH ACL. Performed the experiments: CR HX SKK YS PJG DKW ACL. Analyzed the data: CR PJG DKW. Wrote the paper: CR DKW JBH ACL.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<elocation-id>e1004244</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article, free of all copyright, and may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose. The work is made available under the Creative Commons CC0 public domain dedication.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In animals, circadian rhythms in physiology and behavior result from coherent rhythmic interactions between clocks in the brain and those throughout the body. Despite the many tissue specific clocks, most understanding of the molecular core clock mechanism comes from studies of the suprachiasmatic nuclei (SCN) of the hypothalamus and a few other cell types. Here we report establishment and genetic characterization of three cell-autonomous mouse clock models: 3T3 fibroblasts, 3T3-L1 adipocytes, and MMH-D3 hepatocytes. Each model is genetically tractable and has an integrated luciferase reporter that allows for longitudinal luminescence recording of rhythmic clock gene expression using an inexpensive off-the-shelf microplate reader. To test these cellular models, we generated a library of short hairpin RNAs (shRNAs) against a panel of known clock genes and evaluated their impact on circadian rhythms. Knockdown of <italic>Bmal1</italic>, <italic>Clock</italic>, <italic>Cry1</italic>, and <italic>Cry2</italic> each resulted in similar phenotypes in all three models, consistent with previous studies. However, we observed cell type-specific knockdown phenotypes for the <italic>Period</italic> and <italic>Rev-Erb</italic> families of clock genes. In particular, <italic>Per1</italic> and <italic>Per2</italic>, which have strong behavioral effects in knockout mice, appear to play different roles in regulating period length and amplitude in these peripheral systems. <italic>Per3</italic>, which has relatively modest behavioral effects in knockout mice, substantially affects period length in the three cellular models and in dissociated SCN neurons. In summary, this study establishes new cell-autonomous clock models that are of particular relevance to metabolism and suitable for screening for clock modifiers, and reveals previously under-appreciated cell type-specific functions of clock genes.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>Various aspects of our daily rhythms in physiology and behavior such as the sleep-wake cycle are regulated by endogenous circadian clocks that are present in nearly every cell. It is generally accepted that these oscillators share a similar biochemical negative feedback mechanism, consisting of transcriptional activators and repressors. In this study, we developed cell-autonomous, metabolically relevant clock models in mouse hepatocytes and adipocytes. Each clock model has an integrated luciferase reporter that allows for kinetic luminescence recording with an inexpensive microplate reader and thus is feasible for most laboratories. These models are amenable to high throughput screening of small molecules or genomic entities for impacts on cell-autonomous clocks relevant to metabolism. We validated these new models by RNA interference via lentivirus-mediated knockdown of known clock genes. As expected, we found that many core clock components have similar functions across cell types. To our surprise, however, we also uncovered previously under-appreciated cell type-specific functions of core clock genes, particularly <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>, and <italic>Per3</italic>. Because the circadian system is integrated with, and influenced by, the local physiology that is under its control, our studies provide important implications for future studies into cell type-specific mechanisms of various circadian systems.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported in part by the National Science Foundation (IOS-0920417 to ACL), FedEx Institute of Technology (to ACL), and the National Institutes of Health (NINDS R01NS054794 to JBH and ACL; NIMH R01MH082945 to DKW; and R01MH051573 and R01GM074868 to Steve A. Kay). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>In mammals, many aspects of daily behavior and physiology such as the sleep-wake cycle, body temperature, and liver metabolism are regulated by endogenous circadian clocks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Reppert1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Hastings1">[2]</xref>. The circadian time-keeping system is a hierarchical, multi-oscillator network, with the hypothalamic suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) acting as a central pacemaker at the top of the hierarchy. The SCN integrates external time cues and, through complex signaling cascades, synchronizes and coordinates extra-SCN oscillators in the brain and in peripheral clocks throughout the body, culminating in overt, coherent circadian rhythms at the organismal level <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Mohawk1">[4]</xref>. This time-keeping system is critical for normal physiology and behavior, and its disruption can lead to sleep disorders, metabolic syndrome, premature aging, and cancer (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Hastings1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Green1">[5]</xref>).</p>
<p>Virtually all cells in our body have circadian oscillators <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Nagoshi1">[6]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Yoo1">[8]</xref>. Despite tissue-specific physiological differences, these oscillators share a highly conserved molecular mechanism – a negative feedback loop. This consists of transcriptional activators BMAL1 and CLOCK, which bind to E-box enhancers and activate the transcription of the <italic>Per</italic> and <italic>Cry</italic> families of repressors. These repressors then feed back to inhibit BMAL1/CLOCK activity and their own expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Young1">[9]</xref>. Each molecular component in the core clock loop is represented by multiple paralogs (<italic>Bmal1, Bmal2; Clock, Npas2; Per1, Per2, Per3; Cry1, Cry2</italic>), which provides the potential for functional redundancy and cell type specificity. In addition, post-translational modifications play critical roles in clock function. For example, the ubiquitin ligases FBXL3 and FBXL21 regulate period length and amplitude through ubiquitin-mediated degradation of CRY proteins and regulation of REV-ERBα activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Busino1">[10]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Hirano1">[15]</xref>.</p>
<p>This core clock loop integrates with other transcriptional systems such as the ROR/REV-ERB (via RORE) and DBP/E4BP4 (via D-box) accessory loops <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ueda1">[16]</xref>. In the RORE loop, retinoic acid receptor-related orphan nuclear receptors (RORA, RORB, and RORC) act as activators, and REV-ERBs (REV-ERBα known as NR1D1 and REV-ERBβ known as NR1D2; referred to hereafter as NR1D1 and NR1D2) act as repressors to regulate rhythmic <italic>Bmal1</italic> expression via the RORE cis-element in the <italic>Bmal1</italic> promoter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu2">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Koike1">[19]</xref>. Similarly, DBP/TEF/HLF and E4BP4 serve as activators and repressors, respectively, to regulate D-box-mediated transcription of genes such as <italic>Per3</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ueda1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Koike1">[19]</xref>. These interlocking loops mediated by E-box, RORE, and D-box cis-elements form a complex clock network. These loops act individually or in combination to give rise to distinct waves of gene transcription <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ueda1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-DeBruyne1">[20]</xref>. For example, while <italic>Nr1d1</italic>, <italic>Bmal1</italic>, and <italic>Per3</italic> transcription are each mediated primarily by a single cis-element (i.e., primarily E-box, RORE, and D-box, respectively), many other clock genes (e.g., <italic>Cry1</italic>) are regulated via a combinatorial mechanism involving multiple circadian elements <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-UkaiTadenuma1">[21]</xref>.</p>
<p>Cell-based models were instrumental in the identification and characterization of clock gene function in mammals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Hogenesch1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ramanathan1">[23]</xref>. These studies relied on immortalized cell lines that display circadian rhythms of gene expression in a cell-autonomous manner (i.e., without systemic cues). We and others have used fibroblasts derived from clock component mutant mice expressing a clock gene reporter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-UkaiTadenuma1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Khan1">[24]</xref>. Cellular clock models for comprehensive genetic analysis, however, have so far been limited to 3T3 mouse fibroblasts and U2OS human osteosarcoma cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Hogenesch1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Hogenesch2">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ukai1">[26]</xref>. In the U2OS model, knockdowns of all clock components have been evaluated for impact on period length and amplitude <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Baggs1">[27]</xref>. In mice, 3T3 fibroblasts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Hogenesch1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Sato1">[28]</xref> and more recently MMH-D3 hepatocytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Atwood1">[29]</xref> have been introduced as cellular clock models; however, unlike the U2OS model, these models haven't been fully characterized genetically.</p>
<p>An implicit assumption in all these studies is that the clock works the same way in all cell and tissue types, such that gene function determined in one cell or tissue type applies to all cells, regardless of local physiological inputs to the clock. However, while 3T3 cells may be an appropriate model of the fibroblast clock, it is likely not an appropriate model for other cells. Recent studies point to bidirectional interactions between circadian clocks and other cellular and physiological processes. Thus, the circadian system is integrated with, and influenced by, the local physiology. Of particular interest is the reciprocal interaction between clock function and metabolism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Green1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Panda1">[30]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Asher1">[33]</xref>. However, as yet, there aren't any characterized cellular models appropriate for the study of clock control of metabolism. Therefore, to reveal cell type-specific molecular, cellular, and physiological mechanisms of circadian clocks, new cell-autonomous, physiologically relevant peripheral clock models are needed.</p>
<p>To facilitate cell type-specific genetic characterization, we explored mouse cell lines relevant to major metabolic functions, focusing on 3T3-L1 adipocytes and MMH-D3 hepatocytes. The mouse 3T3-L1 adipocyte cell line reflects adipose tissue function and has been pivotal in advancing the understanding of basic cellular mechanisms associated with diabetes, obesity, and related disorders in thousands of studies (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Green2">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Kallen1">[35]</xref>). In recent years, mouse MMH-D3 hepatocytes have become a prominent model reflecting hepatocyte function in the liver <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Amicone1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Feigelstock1">[37]</xref>. Both cell lines have been shown to exhibit rhythmic expression of clock genes and other genes that are involved in and modulated by local physiology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Atwood1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Otway1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Aoyagi1">[39]</xref>.</p>
<p>In this study, we used luciferase reporters of clock gene expression and established three high amplitude cell-autonomous clock models: 3T3 fibroblasts, 3T3-L1 adipocytes, and MMH-D3 hepatocytes, with 3T3 fibroblasts as a reference model. These reporter cells displayed persistent, high amplitude rhythms, which allowed longitudinal recording of clock gene rhythms with high temporal resolution using an inexpensive off-the-shelf microplate reader. For genetic perturbations, we developed a pipeline to produce high-quality lentiviral shRNAs to knock down any gene of interest, and validated these cellular models with shRNAs against a selected panel of known clock genes. We show that knockdown of many clock genes resulted in expected phenotypes in all tested cell lines. Unexpectedly, however, we also observed cell type-specific knockdown phenotypes, particularly within the <italic>Per</italic> gene family. This study has important implications for the tissue-specific mechanisms of circadian clocks.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results and Discussion</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Development of New Cell-Autonomous Clock Models</title>
<p>As an initial effort to develop new cellular clock models pertinent to metabolism, we screened cell lines for robust rhythms and chose 3T3-L1 adipocytes and MMH-D3 hepatocytes. We introduced a lentiviral reporter harboring the rapidly degradable firefly luciferase (d<italic>Luc</italic>) gene under the control of either mouse <italic>Per2</italic> or <italic>Bmal1</italic> gene promoters into cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ramanathan1">[23]</xref>. Whereas the 3T3 reporter cells were directly used in bioluminescence recording, 3T3-L1 and MMH-D3 cells were first differentiated into mature adipocytes and hepatocytes, respectively, prior to recording. These cells displayed persistent bioluminescence rhythms in 35 mm culture dishes monitored in a LumiCycle luminometer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). In each cell line, <italic>Per2</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic> and <italic>Bmal1</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic> reporters displayed anti-phasic rhythms of bioluminescence, consistent with the function of E-box- and RORE-containing promoters in regulating distinct and opposite phases of gene expression.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1004244-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Fibroblasts, adipocytes, and hepatocytes display bioluminescence rhythms.</title>
<p>(A) Representative bioluminescence rhythms of reporter cells recorded in a LumiCycle luminometer on 35 mm dishes. Reporter cells were generated via lentiviral infection of either <italic>Per2</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic> or <italic>Bmal1</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic> luciferase reporter, and infected cell populations were recorded in a LumiCycle. Baseline-subtracted bioluminescence data of both reporter lines are plotted together to show the expected, approximately anti-phasic reporter expression for each cell type. (B) Representative bioluminescence rhythms of homogenous clonal cell lines recorded in a Synergy microplate reader on 96 well plates. Baseline-subtracted bioluminescence data of selected clonal lines representing both reporter types are plotted together to show anti-phasic reporter expression for each cell type. High reproducibility is illustrated by showing overlapping traces from 24 of the 96 wells for each reporter. The period lengths are highly consistent (mean ± SD, n = 24 for each line): 3T3 <italic>Per2</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic>, 25.62 hr±0.21; 3T3 <italic>Bmal1</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic>, 26.72 hr±0.31; 3T3-L1 <italic>Per2</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic>, 24.60 hr±0.32; 3T3-L1 <italic>Bmal1</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic>, 25.01 hr±0.19; MMH-D3 <italic>Per2</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic>, 24.49 hr±0.18; MMH-D3 <italic>Bmal1</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic>, 25.33 hr±0.13.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Next, we adapted the LumiCycle reporter assay to high-throughput screening (HTS) formats on 96 well plates. For this, we performed single cell cloning and selected clonal cell lines that expressed high levels of bioluminescence. These reporter lines displayed persistent rhythms under optimized growth conditions when monitored on a microplate reader (Synergy 2 SL) with highly consistent period lengths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). These highly reproducible rhythms seen in 96 well plates were similar to those in the LumiCycle, a lower throughput but much more expensive recorder. Therefore, these lines represent a tangible advantage to many labs interested in exploring circadian biology in these metabolically relevant cell lines.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Generation of Lentiviral shRNAs for Gene Knockdown</title>
<p>For genetic perturbations, we developed a pipeline to produce high-quality, validated lentiviral shRNA vectors to knock down any mouse gene. We chose lentiviral shRNAs over transfected siRNAs because lentivirus-mediated delivery mediates potent transduction and stable integration in both dividing and non-dividing cells of various types <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>, thus circumventing low transfection efficiency for certain cells. We designed 6 target oligonucleotide sequences for each gene and cloned the shRNA expression cassette into the lentiviral pLL3.7GW Gateway vector, in which shRNA expression is under the control of the mouse U6 promoter, as we reported previously (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s001">Figure S1</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu2">[17]</xref>. Infectious lentiviral particles were produced in 293T cells using standard procedures and used to infect reporter cells. Infection efficiency was estimated by observing GFP co-expressed from a separate expression cassette under control of the CMV promoter (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s001">Figure S1</xref>).</p>
<p>We used this pipeline to generate a panel of shRNA constructs targeting the following selected 13 clock genes: <italic>Bmal1</italic>, <italic>Bmal2</italic>, <italic>Clock</italic>, <italic>Npas2</italic> (core loop activators); <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>, <italic>Per3</italic>, <italic>Cry1</italic>, <italic>Cry2</italic> (core loop repressors); <italic>Fbxl3</italic> (core loop post-translational modifier); <italic>Nr1d1</italic>, <italic>Nr1d2</italic> (RORE repressors); and <italic>E4bp4</italic> (D-box repressor). Because of the more prominent roles of repressors in clock function, we chose to examine <italic>Nr1d1</italic>, <italic>Nr1d2</italic>, and <italic>E4bp4</italic>, the RORE and D-box negative factors, rather than the corresponding activators <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Gachon1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Yamajuku1">[41]</xref>.</p>
<p>We tested shRNA knockdown (KD) efficiency for the 13 clock genes. Co-transfection of shRNA with Flag-tagged cDNA in 293T cells followed by Western blot analysis showed efficient KD of each gene at the protein level by at least two shRNAs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s002">Figure S2</xref>). To check the KD efficiency for endogenous gene expression, mRNA levels of targeted clock genes were also measured using qPCR. For each gene, at least two shRNAs were effective in knocking down gene expression, a requirement to filter out off-target effects of shRNAs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Echeverri1">[42]</xref>. The versatility and efficiency of lentiviral shRNA allowed us to study all 13 known clock genes in all three cell type-specific clock models in parallel, which allows direct phenotypic comparison.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Ubiquitous Functions of <italic>Bmal1</italic>, <italic>Clock</italic>, <italic>Cry1</italic>, <italic>Cry2</italic>, and <italic>Fbxl3</italic></title>
<p>Knockdown of <italic>Bmal1</italic>, <italic>Clock</italic>, <italic>Cry1</italic>, <italic>Cry2</italic>, and <italic>Fbxl3</italic> in all three cellular models resulted in expected phenotypes similar to those in LumiCycle assays using 35 mm dishes and consistent with previous knockout and knockdown studies using human and mouse cellular models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Baggs1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Zhang1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ko1">[45]</xref>. Specifically, KD of <italic>Bmal1</italic> or <italic>Clock</italic> results in rapid damping or arrhythmicity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g002">Figure 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1004244-t001">Tables 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s007">S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s008">S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s009">S3</xref>); <italic>Cry1</italic> KD leads to low amplitude or rapid damping depending on KD efficiency, whereas <italic>Cry2</italic> KD lengthens period and increases rhythm amplitude (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). The phenotypic defects correlate with KD efficiency of the endogenous genes by the individual shRNAs as determined by qPCR analysis. Taken together, our data demonstrate that <italic>Bmal1</italic>, <italic>Clock</italic>, <italic>Cry1</italic>, and <italic>Cry2</italic> play similar roles in the clock mechanism across tested cell types, which provides validation for the three cellular models.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1004244-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Knockdowns of <italic>Bmal1</italic>, <italic>Clock</italic>, <italic>Cry1</italic>, <italic>Cry2</italic>, and <italic>Fbxl3</italic> lead to cell type-ubiquitous circadian phenotypes.</title>
<p>Bioluminescence expression patterns upon KD of <italic>Bmal1</italic> or <italic>Clock</italic> (A), <italic>Cry1</italic> or <italic>Cry2</italic> (B), and <italic>Fbxl3</italic> (C) in all three cell types. For clock phenotyping, both reporters were used for each cell line and phenotypes were independent of the reporter used. For phenotyping, we selected 3T3 cells expressing the <italic>Bmal1</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic> reporter, and 3T3-L1 and MMH-D3 cells expressing the <italic>Per2</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic> reporter. Cells were infected with specific lentiviral shRNAs as indicated. Real-time bioluminescence expression was recorded by Synergy microplate reader as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g001">Figure 1</xref>. Out of the 6 shRNAs tested, two validated shRNAs (orange and green) are shown. NS, non-specific shRNA as control (black). While KD of <italic>Bmal1</italic> or <italic>Clock</italic> resulted in low amplitude, rapid damping or arrhythmicity, <italic>Fbxl3</italic> KD led to long period and low amplitude in 3T3, long period in 3T3-L1, and low amplitude and rapid damping in MMH-D3 cells. <italic>Cry1</italic> KD caused rapid damping or low amplitude, and <italic>Cry2</italic> KD lengthened period and increased rhythm amplitude. Bioluminescence data are representative of four independent experiments for 3T3 and 3T3-L1 cells, and three independent experiments for MMH-D3 cells. Knockdown of endogenous mRNA expression in non-synchronized cells was determined by qPCR (insert). Values for each gene are expressed as percentage of gene expression in NS control cells. qPCR data are mean ± SD (two samples/wells from one experiment).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pgen-1004244-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Summary of knockdown phenotypes.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pgen-1004244-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene KD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3T3 Fibroblasts</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3T3-L1 Adipocytes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMH-D3 Hepatocytes</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U20S Osteosarcoma cells</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Bmal1</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Bmal2</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Clock</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR, LA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Npas2</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Cry1</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Cry2</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long, HA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Per1</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short, LA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR, LA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Per2</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short, LA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long, LA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Per3</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Fbxl3</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long, LA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RD, LA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Nr1d1</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Nr1d2</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>E4bp4</italic></bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short, RD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Notes:</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>1) Knockdown phenotypes in 3T3 fibroblasts, 3T3-L1 adipocytes, and MMH-D3 hepatocytes are from this study, and those in U2OS osteosarcoma cells are from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Baggs1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Zhang1">[31]</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>2) Detailed circadian parameter analyses and phenotypes in 3T3, 3T3-L1 and MMH-D3 cells are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s007">Tables S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s008">S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s009">S3</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>3) Phenotypes: WT, wild type; short, shorter period length than WT; long, longer period length than WT; LA, rhythmic but low amplitude; HA, rhythmic but high amplitude; RD, rapid damping (i.e., rapid decline in amplitude over time) and only transiently rhythmic; AR, arrhythmic.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Knockdown of <italic>Bmal2</italic> and <italic>Npas2</italic> did not exhibit any obvious circadian phenotypes in any of the three cellular models (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s003">Figure S3</xref>), even though their expression was knocked down to levels similar to those for <italic>Bmal1</italic> or <italic>Clock</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g002">Figure 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1004244-t001">Table 1</xref>). These results are consistent with absence of observable circadian phenotypes of liver and lung tissues from <italic>Npas2<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-DeBruyne2">[46]</xref>, though these mice do have deficits in circadian behavior and sleep homeostasis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Dudley1">[47]</xref>. Despite potential functional redundancy between <italic>Bmal1</italic> and <italic>Bmal2</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ko1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Shi2">[48]</xref>, and between <italic>Clock</italic> and <italic>Npas2</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-DeBruyne2">[46]</xref>, our data suggest that <italic>Bmal2</italic> and <italic>Npas2</italic> are not necessary for the clock to operate in these cells.</p>
<p>We show that <italic>Fbxl3</italic> KD caused long period and low amplitude in 3T3, long period in 3T3-L1, and low amplitude and rapid damping in MMH-D3 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). This cell-autonomous phenotype is much more extreme compared to the relatively modest period-lengthening phenotypes seen at the SCN tissue and behavioral levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Busino1">[10]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Godinho1">[12]</xref>, or in human U2OS cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Baggs1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Maier1">[44]</xref>. Notably, although KD of <italic>Fbxl3</italic> or <italic>Cry2</italic> both produced long periods, <italic>Cry2</italic> down-regulation increased rhythm amplitude, whereas <italic>Fbxl3</italic> silencing resulted in low amplitude, consistent with its dual role in ubiquitin-mediated degradation of CRY proteins and in regulation of NR1D1-mediated transcriptional suppression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Busino1">[10]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Shi1">[13]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title><italic>Nr1d1</italic>, <italic>Nr1d2</italic>, and <italic>E4bp4</italic> Knockdown Caused Cell Type-Dependent Clock Phenotypes</title>
<p><italic>Nr1d1</italic> and <italic>Nr1d2</italic> play overlapping but essential functions in regulating RORE-mediated transcription, and knockdown of either gene results in low amplitude rhythms, and in some cases, short period <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Baggs1">[27]</xref>. We examined the effects of <italic>Nr1d1</italic> or <italic>Nr1d2</italic> KD on clock function in our cellular clock models. Knockdown of <italic>Nr1d1</italic> resulted in largely normal rhythms in these cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g003">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1004244-t001">Table 1</xref>), indicating potential overlapping functions of <italic>Nr1d2</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu2">[17]</xref>. This is different from the period lengthening produced by siRNA knockdown in U2OS cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Baggs1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Zhang1">[31]</xref> or the period shortening and greater variability seen in behavioral rhythms of <italic>Nr1d1<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Cho1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Preitner1">[49]</xref>. <italic>Nr1d2</italic> KD, on the other hand, resulted in period shortening in MMH-D3 and 3T3-L1 cells but low amplitude in 3T3 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g003">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1004244-t001">Table 1</xref>). The <italic>Nr1d2</italic> impact on overall rhythms was at least similar to, if not substantially stronger than, for <italic>Nr1d1</italic>. This is consistent with the reported redundant functions of <italic>Nr1d1</italic> and <italic>Nr1d2</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu2">[17]</xref>, but contrasts with previous studies showing that <italic>NR1D2</italic> deficiency has no observable rhythm phenotype in U2OS cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Baggs1">[27]</xref> or in mice at the behavioral level <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Cho1">[18]</xref>. Thus, <italic>Nr1d1</italic> and <italic>Nr1d2</italic> play different roles in clock function depending on tissue or cell type, and <italic>Nr1d2</italic> may be more important than previously recognized.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1004244-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Knockdowns of <italic>Nr1d1</italic>, <italic>Nr1d2</italic>, and <italic>E4bp4</italic> lead to cell type-specific circadian phenotypes.</title>
<p>Bioluminescence expression patterns upon KD of <italic>Nr1d1</italic> and <italic>Nr1d2</italic> (A) and <italic>E4bp4</italic> (B) in all three cell types. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g002">Figure 2</xref> for details. Note that, compared to the more prominent role of <italic>Nr1d1</italic> in clock function previously found in U2OS cells or mouse behavioral rhythms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Cho1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Baggs1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Preitner1">[49]</xref>, <italic>Nr1d2</italic> plays a more prominent role in all three cells. <italic>E4bp4</italic> KD caused period length and/or amplitude phenotypes depending cell type.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Despite the widely accepted role of E4BP4 as the repressor of D-box-mediated transcription, definitive genetic evidence of clock function has been lacking. We show here that <italic>E4bp4</italic> KD resulted in short period and rapid damping in 3T3 fibroblasts, low amplitude in 3T3-L1 cells, and short period in MMH-D3 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g003">Figure 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1004244-t001">Table 1</xref>). These data are in line with recent studies suggesting a prominent role of <italic>E4bp4</italic> in regulating the phase of <italic>Cry1</italic> transcription in mouse embryonic fibroblasts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-UkaiTadenuma1">[21]</xref> and period length in Rat-1 fibroblasts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Yamajuku1">[41]</xref>. Studies of E4BP4's function in the clock mechanism using <italic>E4bp4<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice are therefore needed to validate our findings in cellular clock models.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Cell Type-Specific Clock Functions of <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>, and <italic>Per3</italic></title>
<p>The shRNA constructs against <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>, and <italic>Per3</italic> down-regulated mRNA and protein expression (Figures S2 and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g004">4</xref>). However, unlike <italic>Cry1</italic> and <italic>Cry2</italic> KDs, knockdown of the <italic>Per</italic> genes in our clock models resulted in cell type-specific clock phenotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g004">Figure 4</xref>). First, compared to the dramatic circadian defects observed in peripheral tissue explants and fibroblasts of <italic>Per1<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, or upon siRNA-mediated <italic>Per1</italic> KD in U2OS cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Zhang1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Pendergast1">[50]</xref>, <italic>Per1</italic> KD in our clock models had milder effects on clock function. Interestingly, these less dramatic phenotypes are cell type-specific: WT phenotype in 3T3 and 3T3-L1 cells, but significantly shorter period and low amplitude in MMH-D3 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g004">Figures 4A and 4D</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1004244-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pgen-1004244-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>shRNA-mediated knockdowns of <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic> and <italic>Per3</italic> lead to cell type-specific circadian phenotypes.</title>
<p>Bioluminescence expression patterns upon KD of <italic>Per1</italic> (A), <italic>Per2</italic> (B), and <italic>Per3</italic> (C) in all three cell types. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g002">Figure 2</xref> for details. Whereas <italic>Per3</italic> KD led to short periods in all three cell types, <italic>Per1</italic> and <italic>Per2</italic> KDs caused different clock phenotypes depending on cell type. (D) Summary of period length phenotypes. Data are mean ± SD (n = 4 independent experiments for 3T3 cells; n = 3 samples/wells of one experiment for 3T3-L1 and MMH-D3 cells). NS, non-specific shRNA. Compared to NS controls, significant difference in period length was detected in the following KDs: NS vs. <italic>Per1</italic> KD in MMH-D3, t-test, p&lt;0.001; NS vs. <italic>Per2</italic> KD in 3T3, t-test, p = 0.013; NS vs. <italic>Per2</italic> KD in MMH-D3, t-test, p&lt;0.001; NS vs. <italic>Per3</italic> KD in 3T3, t-test, p&lt;0.001; NS vs. <italic>Per3</italic> KD in 3T3-L1, t-test, p = 0.003; NS vs. <italic>Per3</italic> KD in MMH-D3, t-test, p&lt;0.001). *p&lt;0.01; ** p&lt;0.001. (E) <italic>Per3</italic> deletion led to short period length defects in SCN explants (left) and even stronger defects in dissociated SCN neurons (right). <italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic> SCN explants show a slightly shorter period than WT (mean ± SEM: WT, 24.4 hr±0.17, n = 5; <italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic>, 23.78 hr±0.18, n = 5). The mean period of rhythms in <italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic> neurons was substantially shorter than in WT cells (mean ± SEM: WT, 27.23 hr±0.24, n = 106; <italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic>, 25.58 hr±0.12, n = 157; t-test, p&lt;10E-10; ** p&lt;0.001).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Similarly, <italic>Per2</italic> KD did not cause arrhythmicity in any of the three cellular clock models: only a modest reduction of amplitude in 3T3-L1 cells, but significantly shorter period in 3T3 and short period and low amplitude in MMH-D3 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g004">Figures 4B and 4D</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1004244-t001">Table 1</xref>). The amplitude reduction in MMH-D3 cells was evident in both the subtracted data and raw data (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g004">Figure 4</xref> with <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s005">Figure S5</xref>). Although it is possible that the more modest phenotypes may be due to incomplete silencing, the knockdown levels were comparable to those of <italic>Bmal1</italic>, <italic>Clock</italic>, and <italic>Fbxl3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g002">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g004">4B</xref>); and as in the case of <italic>Per1</italic> KD, the different phenotypes resulted from similar <italic>Per2</italic> KD efficiency in different cells. This is unexpected given its essential role in circadian rhythms of mice at the behavioral level and in cultured fibroblasts and U2OS cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Baggs1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Bae1">[51]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Brown1">[53]</xref>. Interestingly, however, our finding of non-essential but cell type-specific role of <italic>Per2</italic> is in line with a recent report showing that <italic>Per2<sup>−/−</sup></italic> SCN explants displayed persistent rhythms with short periods, whereas <italic>Per2<sup>−/−</sup></italic> pituitary explant rhythms were normal and lung explants displayed slightly long periods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Pendergast2">[54]</xref>. Thus, even though genetic knockout and knockdown (incomplete silencing) may cause variations in phenotypes, the loss-of-function phenotypes of <italic>Per1</italic> and <italic>Per2</italic> are largely consistent and are cell or tissue type specific.</p>
<p>While <italic>Per2</italic> appears to be more important than <italic>Per1</italic> for normal clock function in mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Zheng1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Chen1">[55]</xref>, deletion of <italic>Per3</italic> has only subtle effects on the SCN clock and is often not considered part of the core clock mechanism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Pendergast2">[54]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Shearman1">[56]</xref>. However, we show here that KD of <italic>Per3</italic> in all three models produced significantly shorter periods than in control cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g004">Figures 4C and 4D</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1004244-t001">Table 1</xref>). These results are consistent with recent reports showing that tissue explants of <italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, including liver, lung, and pituitary, also displayed short periods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Pendergast2">[54]</xref>. In addition, knockdowns of <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>, and <italic>Per3</italic> showed similar phenotypes in cells expressing a different reporter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g004">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s004">S4</xref>), confirming that the knockdown effects are reporter independent. Furthermore, the <italic>Per1</italic> and <italic>Per3</italic> knockdown effects are largely consistent with data of liver explants from <italic>Per1</italic> and <italic>Per3</italic> knockouts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Yagita1">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Pendergast3">[58]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title><italic>Per3</italic> Plays an Important Role in the SCN Clock</title>
<p>The prominent role of <italic>Per3</italic> in peripheral clock function led us to examine its function more carefully in both intact SCN explants and dissociated SCN neurons derived from <italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic>:<italic>mPer2<sup>Luc</sup></italic> mice. We detected persistent <italic>mPer2<sup>Luc</sup></italic> rhythms in <italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic> SCN explants with a slightly shorter period than WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g004">Figure 4E</xref>). This is consistent with the original study of <italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, where a slightly shorter period of behavioral rhythms was reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Shearman1">[56]</xref>. We then dissociated <italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic> SCN neurons and examined <italic>mPer2<sup>Luc</sup></italic> bioluminescence from dispersed neurons at the single-cell level, as we have done previously for other genotypes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>. We found that dissociated WT and <italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic> neurons generally exhibited persistent rhythms with high amplitude. However, the mean period of rhythms in <italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic> neurons was substantially shorter than in WT cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g004">Figure 4E</xref>). The weaker circadian defect at the SCN tissue level than in cell-autonomous preparations (either our cellular models or dissociated SCN neurons) is consistent with the principle that the SCN network confers robustness against genetic perturbations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Evans1">[59]</xref>, such that <italic>Per3</italic> plays a less prominent role in the intact SCN due to compensation by the SCN network. Based on these results, we conclude that <italic>Per3</italic> plays an important role in the SCN cellular clock as well as in peripheral oscillators and thus represents a <italic>bona fide</italic> clock component.</p>
<p>The more prominent role of <italic>Per3</italic> in peripheral oscillators is in line with several recent studies showing that disruption of <italic>Per3</italic> resulted in internal phase misalignment or desynchrony, or aberrant metabolic and sleep phenotypes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Pendergast3">[58]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Hasan1">[60]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Costa1">[62]</xref>, all pointing to the role of <italic>Per3</italic> in coherence of circadian organization. Thus, our findings suggest that tissue-specific function or dysfunction of clock genes in peripheral tissues can be an important contributing factor to human diseases, even when the behavioral effect of gene knockout is subtle. In this context, it is interesting to note that human polymorphisms in <italic>PER3</italic> are associated with sleep and metabolic disorders <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Barnard1">[63]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Dijk1">[64]</xref>.</p>
<p>Taken together, our study expands our knowledge of the distinct functions of known clock genes across tissues. In particular, <italic>Per3</italic> plays a more important role in both SCN and non-SCN cells than previously appreciated, and <italic>Per1</italic> and <italic>Per2</italic> appear to have different roles in different cell types. Results from this study are broadly consistent with previous findings from loss-of-function studies and collectively point to the previously under-appreciated cell type specificity of <italic>Per</italic> gene function in circadian physiology (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s006">Figure S6</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2g">
<title>Composite Knockdown of the <italic>Per</italic> Genes in MMH-D3 Hepatocytes</title>
<p>Compared to other cell-autonomous models, the short period length in MMH-D3 cells after knockdown of each of the <italic>Per</italic> genes is unique (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s006">Figure S6</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1004244-t001">Table 1</xref>), and therefore we sought to perform single and composite knockdowns for further phenotyping using the LumiCycle assay. Consistent with the Synergy assay, <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>, and <italic>Per3</italic> single gene KD each gave short period phenotypes, about 2 hrs shorter than the control cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g005">Figures 5A and 5B</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s010">Table S4</xref>). Composite <italic>Per1</italic>/<italic>Per2</italic> double KD and <italic>Per1</italic>/Per2/<italic>Per3</italic> triple KD caused complete arrhythmicity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g005">Figure 5A</xref>), indicating the prominent roles of <italic>Per1</italic> and <italic>Per2</italic> in the hepatocyte clock. Interestingly, <italic>Per1</italic>/<italic>Per3</italic> and <italic>Per2</italic>/<italic>Per3</italic> double KDs did not cause any further period shortening over single <italic>Per</italic> gene KDs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g005">Figures 5A and 5B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pgen-1004244-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>shRNA-mediated single and composite knockdown effects of <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic> and <italic>Per3</italic> in MMH-D3 hepatocytes.</title>
<p>(A) Representative bioluminescence expression patterns recorded on LumiCycle upon knockdowns of <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>, <italic>Per3</italic> (single KD); <italic>Per1</italic>/<italic>Per2</italic>, <italic>Per1</italic>/<italic>Per3</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>/<italic>Per3</italic> (double KD); and <italic>Per1</italic>/<italic>Per2</italic>/<italic>Per3</italic> (triple KD) in MMH-D3 hepatocytes. sh62, sh67 and sh74 were used to knock down <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic> and <italic>Per3</italic>, respectively. All single KDs led to short periods in all three cell types, consistent with Synergy assays. <italic>Per1</italic>/<italic>Per2</italic> double and <italic>Per1</italic>/<italic>Per2</italic>/<italic>Per3</italic> triple KDs caused arrhythmicity. All other double composite KDs caused short period phenotype. (B) Summary of period length phenotypes. Data are mean ± SD (n = 3 independent samples/wells from one experiment). NS, non-specific shRNA. Compared to NS controls, significant difference in period length was detected (NS vs. <italic>Per1</italic> KD, t-test, p&lt;0.001; NS vs. <italic>Per2</italic> KD, t-test, p&lt;0.001; NS vs. <italic>Per3</italic> KD, t-test, p&lt;0.001; NS vs. <italic>Per1</italic>/<italic>Per3</italic> KD, t-test, p&lt;0.001; NS vs. <italic>Per2</italic>/<italic>Per3</italic> KD, t-test, p&lt;0.001). (C) qPCR analysis of clock gene expression upon <italic>Per</italic> KD in non-synchronized MMH-D3 cells. Values for each gene are expressed as percentage of gene expression in NS control cells. Data represent two samples/wells from one experiment.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>As an initial effort to probe the network features of the hepatocyte clock, we examined effects of <italic>Per</italic> KD on the expression of endogenous clock genes by qPCR. <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>, and <italic>Per3</italic> were each knocked down in both single and composite KDs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). Compared to the U2OS model, paralog compensation among the <italic>Per</italic> genes in MMH-D3 cells is more pervasive. In our MMH-D3 model, both <italic>Per1</italic> KD and <italic>Per2</italic> KD upregulated <italic>Per3</italic>, and <italic>Per3</italic> KD upregulated <italic>Per2</italic>. While composite <italic>Per1</italic>/<italic>Per2</italic> KD upregulated <italic>Per3</italic> and <italic>Per1</italic>/<italic>Per3</italic> KD greatly upregulated <italic>Per2</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>/<italic>Per3</italic> KD did not increase <italic>Per1</italic> expression. Interestingly, <italic>Per1</italic> and/or <italic>Per2</italic> KD had milder effects on the expression of E-box-containing genes (e.g., <italic>Nr1d1</italic> and <italic>Nr1d2</italic>) than on RORE-containing genes such as <italic>Bmal1</italic>, <italic>E4bp4</italic>, and <italic>Cry1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g005">Figure 5C</xref>), in line with the notion that the PERs can directly and indirectly affect <italic>Bmal1</italic> transcription <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Shearman2">[65]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Schmutz1">[66]</xref>. Overall, the network interactions in MMH-D3 cells appear to differ from those in the U2OS model in which <italic>PER1</italic> plays a more dominant role than <italic>PER2</italic> and <italic>PER3</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Baggs1">[27]</xref>, and is expected to differ from those in 3T3 and 3T3-L1 models. Thus, extensive investigation into the network features of these cellular models will require additional experiments and is warranted in future studies, as we have done with the U2OS model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Baggs1">[27]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2h">
<title>Concluding Remarks</title>
<p>Cell type-specific function of clock genes may result from their differential tissue expression and activity (i.e., expression levels, ratio of repressors to activators, rhythmicity, and relative amplitudes), compensatory mechanisms, alternative splice variants, and post-translational modifications (PMTs), all of which can be rendered cell type specific by local physiology. Recent studies have suggested a role for stoichiometric balance among clock proteins in circadian clock robustness and periodicity, and call for mechanistic studies in a tissue specific manner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Kim1">[67]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ye1">[69]</xref>. In the context of the liver and adipose tissue function, it is plausible that the basic core clock mechanism incorporates cell type-specific factors and forms distinctive functional networks to regulate (and in turn be regulated by) different local physiologies. It is interesting to note, as PTMs of clock factors (e.g., phosphorylation, ubiquitination, ADP-ribosylation, acetylation, and O-GlcNAcylation) represent critical regulatory mechanisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Asher1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Hart1">[70]</xref>, tissue-specific cellular functions and metabolic states that affect the PTMs would provide important inputs to adjust local circadian clocks, and <italic>vice versa</italic>. Thus, cell type specific clock gene function starts to make sense when local physiology is considered as inputs to the clock. This challenge surely provides an opportunity for deeper insights into mechanism of tissue specific clocks, akin to the recent realization that cyclin-dependent kinase networks in the cell cycle control program are tissue specific <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Pagano1">[71]</xref>.</p>
<p>In summary, we established three new mouse cellular clock models: fibroblasts, adipocytes, and hepatocytes. These cellular clock models offer experimental tractability, efficiency, and versatility, which are more difficult or impossible to apply to traditional tissue or animal models. Of note, in contrast to previous cellular clock models, the new clock models are amenable to high throughput experiments with inexpensive off-the-shelf recording systems, making these lines especially suitable for screening small molecules or genomic entities for impacts on cell autonomous clocks relevant to metabolism. We validated these models by developing and testing an shRNA panel of selected known clock genes. Results from this study and others point to the previously under-appreciated cell type specificity of clock gene function in circadian physiology (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s006">Figure S6</xref>). The prevalence of tissue-specific clock gene function will have important implications for future studies of clock factors that affect local clock function. It is our hope that our findings in this study, along with the new cellular clock models, approaches, and tools developed here, can be applied to a greater variety of cell types in future studies, to reveal the full range of tissue-specific clock properties underlying local circadian biology.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Animals</title>
<p><italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice were obtained from David Weaver at the University of Massachusetts. Knockout mice were bred with <italic>mPer2<sup>Luc</sup></italic> reporter mice to obtain homozygous knockouts harboring the <italic>mPer2<sup>Luc</sup></italic> reporter. Wheel-running assays were performed and analyzed as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Yoo1">[8]</xref>. All animal studies were conducted in accordance with the regulations of the Committees on Animal Care and Use at University of Memphis and UCSD.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Cell and Tissue Culture</title>
<p>All cell culture media were from HyClone. 3T3 (also known as NIH 3T3) and 3T3-L1 cells were cultured in regular medium in which DMEM was supplemented with 10% FBS and 1× penicillin-streptomycin-glutamine (PSG). For 3T3-L1 differentiation, pre-adipocytes were first grown to confluence (Day 0). On Day 2, cells were fed with induction medium (regular medium with 1 µM dexamethasone, 0.5 mM isobutylmethylxanthine, and 2 µg/ml insulin). On Day 4, cells were changed to maintenance medium (regular medium containing 2 µg/ml insulin). From day 6 onward, cells were grown in regular medium until use. For bioluminescence recording, 3T3 and 3T3-L1 cells were grown in 25 mM HEPES-buffered regular medium (pH 7.4) containing 1 nM forskolin and 1 mM luciferin. Fully differentiated 3T3-L1 cells were used in all experiments.</p>
<p>MMH-D3 cells were grown in regular medium in which RPMI medium was supplemented with 10% FBS, 1× PSG, 10 µg/ml insulin, 55 ng/ml epidermal growth factor (EGF), and 16 ng/ml insulin like growth factor-II (IGF-II). For differentiation, pre-hepatocytes were first grown to 100% confluence. Two days later, cells were replaced with differentiation medium (regular medium with 2% DMSO). Medium change was repeated every 48 hours for 6–8 days for cells to be fully differentiated for use. Circadian rhythms of differentiated cells were synchronized with 200 nM dexamethasone followed by bioluminescence recording in 25 mM HEPES-buffered serum-free explant medium (pH 7.4) containing B-27 and 1 mM luciferin, as we have done previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>. Fully differentiated MMH-D3 cells were used in all experiments.</p>
<p>SCN explants and dissociated neuronal cells were prepared and cultured as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>. Bioluminescence recording of explants, single cell-imaging of individual SCN neurons, and respective data analysis were performed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Generation of Reporter Cell Lines</title>
<p>Lentiviral luciferase reporters of the <italic>Per2</italic> or <italic>Bmal1</italic> promoter were described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>. Reporter cells and clonal lines were generated as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ramanathan1">[23]</xref>. Briefly, reporter viral particles of high titer (&gt;10<sup>8</sup> viral particles/ml) were obtained by ultracentrifugation and used to infect 3T3, 3T3-L1, and MMH-D3 cells. Clonal cell lines of homogenous cell populations were obtained by single cell sorting and cloning in 96 well plates. We then selected the clones that expressed high levels of luciferase and exhibited circadian properties comparable to infected parental cell populations. These brighter cells were used in high-throughput assays on 96 well plates. Knockdown phenotypes were confirmed to be independent of the reporter, either <italic>Per2</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic> or <italic>Bmal1</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic>, and thus phenotypic differences across cell types are unlikely due to different reporter insertion sites.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Construction of Lentiviral shRNA Vectors and Viral Preparation</title>
<p>We used an optimized shRNA design algorithm adapted from Aza-Blanc et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-AzaBlanc1">[72]</xref> for target sequence prediction. This adapted algorithm selects for optimal target sequence for knockdown, and against homologous sequences to minimize off-target effects. We selected 6 target sequences for each gene as listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s011">Table S5</xref>. Each shRNA construct contained a sense and an antisense target sequence of 19 nucleotides (nts) in length, separated by 9 nts for a hairpin loop, and flanked by TTTG at 5′ and GATC at 3′ ends for cohesive end cloning. All oligos (55 nts) were synthesized by Integrated DNA Technologies (IDT). The annealed oligonucleotides were first cloned into the BbsI and SpeI sites of a pGWL-si2/U6 vector, in which the shRNA expression cassette is driven by an RNA polymerase III- based mouse U6 promoter. Subsequently, the U6-shRNA cassette was cloned into the lentiviral pLL3.7GW vector (modified from pLL3.7) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Rubinson1">[73]</xref> in a Gateway LR Clonase reaction (Life Technologies), according to manufacturer's instructions.</p>
<p>Viral particles were prepared using standard methods in 293T cells on 12-well plates as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ramanathan1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Tiscornia1">[74]</xref>. Culture medium containing viral particles (∼10<sup>6</sup> viral particles/ml) were collected and used for subsequent infection of reporter cells. Transfection and infection efficiency were estimated by observing GFP co-expressed from a CMV promoter. To produce high titer viruses, crude viral particles were concentrated through ultracentrifugation and appropriate titers were used, as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Tiscornia1">[74]</xref>. This pipeline allowed us to generate a panel of shRNA constructs against all known clock factors for genetic perturbation and phenotyping.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Bioluminescence Recording and Data Analysis</title>
<p>We used a LumiCycle luminometer (version 2.31, Actimetrics) for bioluminescence recording of cells grown on 35 mm culture dishes, as described elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ramanathan1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>. The LumiCycle Analysis program version 2.53 (Actimetrics) was used to determine circadian parameters. Briefly, raw data were fitted to a linear baseline, and the baseline-subtracted data were fitted to a sine wave (damped), from which period length and goodness of fit and damping constant were determined. For samples that showed persistent rhythms, goodness-of-fit of &gt;80% was usually achieved. Due to high transient luminescence upon medium change, the first cycle was usually excluded from rhythm analysis. Damping rate = 1/damping constant. For amplitude analysis, raw data from day 3 to day 5 were fitted to a linear baseline, and the baseline-subtracted (polynomial number = 1) data were fitted to a sine wave, from which the amplitude was determined.</p>
<p>We used a Synergy 2 SL microplate reader (Bio Tek) for bioluminescence recording of cells grown on 96 well plates, as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ramanathan1">[23]</xref>. Synergy data were analyzed with the MultiCycle Analysis program (Actimetrics), in which bioluminescence data were baseline-subtracted and fit to a damped sine wave to determine period length, goodness of fit, and amplitude, as with LumiCycle Analysis. Due to the various reporter expression levels and for direct comparison of different rhythms, baseline subtracted data were plotted. Because there is no damping rate output function in the MultiCycle Analysis, we used a curve fitting program of “CellulaRhythm” to determine damping rate from Synergy data as previously developed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Hirota1">[75]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3f">
<title>Western Blot Analysis</title>
<p>For testing shRNA knockdown efficiency targeting each clock gene, the cDNA was cloned into a p3XFlag-CMV-14 vector. Flag-tagged cDNA was co-transfected with the indicated shRNA in 3T3 or 293T cells. Forty eight hours post-transfection, cells were lysed in RIPA buffer containing complete protease (Roche) and phosphatase inhibitors (Sigma). Protein expression was determined by Western blot analysis using an anti-Flag monoclonal antibody (Sigma). For all Western assays, PVDF membrane was used in protein transfer, and SuperSignal West Pico substrate (Thermo Scientific) was used for chemiluminescent detection.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3g">
<title>Quantitative PCR (qPCR) Analysis</title>
<p>For qPCR analysis, parallel infection experiments were performed as with bioluminescence recording. Cells were harvested prior to medium change and were therefore unsynchronized. Total RNAs were prepared using the RNeasy 96 kit (Qiagen), as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Zhang1">[31]</xref>. Reverse transcription was performed using a high-capacity RNA to cDNA kit (Applied Biosystems), and qPCR was performed using SYBR Green PCR master mix (Thermo Scientific) on an iCycler thermal cycler (BioRad). The primers used in qPCR analysis are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004244.s012">Table S6</xref>. Transcript levels for each gene were normalized to Gapdh and values were expressed as percentage of expression in NS control cells, as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu2">[17]</xref>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1004244.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p>Outline of generation of lentiviral shRNAs for gene knockdown.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004244.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p>Western blot analysis of shRNA-mediated gene knockdown.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004244.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p>Knockdowns of <italic>Bmal2</italic> and <italic>Npas2</italic> lead to no obvious circadian phenotypes. Bioluminescence expression patterns upon KD of <italic>Bmal2</italic> and <italic>Npas2</italic> in all three cell types. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g002">Figure 2</xref> for details.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004244.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p>Knockdowns of <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>, and <italic>Per3</italic> lead to cell type-specific circadian phenotypes. Bioluminescence expression patterns upon KD of <italic>Per1</italic> (A), <italic>Per2</italic> (B), and <italic>Per3</italic> (C) in 3T3 cells harboring the <italic>Per2</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic> reporter and in 3T3-L1 and MMH-D3 cells harboring the <italic>Bmal1</italic>-d<italic>Luc</italic> reporter. KD of <italic>Per1</italic> leads to short period in MMH-D3 cells. KD of <italic>Per2</italic> leads to short period in 3T3 and MMH-D3 cells. KD of <italic>Per3</italic> leads to short period in all cell lines. These data are consistent with and complement those in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g004">Figure 4</xref> where a different reporter was used for each cell type.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004244.s005" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S5</label><caption>
<p>Bioluminescence expression patterns upon knockdowns of <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>, and <italic>Per3</italic> in MMH-D3 cell line. The raw data of <italic>Per1</italic>, <italic>Per2</italic>, and <italic>Per3</italic> KDs in MMH-D3 cells were plotted. The amplitude reduction upon knockdown is evident in both the raw data plots presented here and the subtracted data plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004244-g004">Figure 4</xref>.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004244.s006" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S6</label><caption>
<p>Summary of knockdown and knockout circadian phenotypes. Phenotypes of 3T3, 3T3-L1, MMH-D3, and <italic>Per3<sup>−/−</sup></italic> SCN neurons are from this study, and those of other cells and tissues are from several previous studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Baggs1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Zhang1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Liu3">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Ko1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-DeBruyne2">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Pendergast1">[50]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Pendergast2">[54]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004244-Pendergast3">[58]</xref>. Loss-of-function of <italic>Bmal1</italic> and <italic>Clock</italic> leads to arrhythmic phenotype, but this clock defect may be masked in the SCN. <italic>Cry1</italic> is also required in cell-autonomous preparations, but its KD can lead to arrhythmicity, rapid damping or short period, depending on KD efficiency. <italic>Cry2</italic> loss-of-function, on the other hand, leads to long period phenotypes in all cells and tissues examined. In comparison, the <italic>Per</italic> genes show tissue- or cell type-specific phenotypes. MEF, mouse embryonic fibroblasts; MAF, mouse adult fibroblasts; neuron, dissociated SCN neurons. WT, wild type; long, longer period than WT; short, shorter period than WT; LA, rhythmic but low amplitude; RD, transiently rhythmic and rapid damping; AR, arrhythmic.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004244.s007" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.s007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p>Parameter analysis of knockdowns in 3T3 cells.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004244.s008" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.s008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p>Parameter analysis of knockdowns in 3T3-L1 cells.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004244.s009" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.s009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S3</label><caption>
<p>Parameter analysis of knockdowns in MMH-D3 cells.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004244.s010" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.s010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S4</label><caption>
<p>Parameter analysis of <italic>Per</italic> composite knockdowns in MMH-D3 cells.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004244.s011" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.s011" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S5</label><caption>
<p>List of target sequences against a panel of known clock genes.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004244.s012" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004244.s012" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S6</label><caption>
<p>List of primers used in qPCR analysis.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Tony Orth and Myleen Medina at the Genomics Institute of Novartis Research Foundation for shRNA target sequence design.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Reppert1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reppert</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Coordination of circadian timing in mammals</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>418</volume>: <fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>941</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Hastings1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maywood</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A clockwork web: circadian timing in brain and periphery, in health and disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>649</fpage>–<lpage>661</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Liu1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mammalian circadian signaling networks and therapeutic targets</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>630</fpage>–<lpage>639</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Mohawk1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohawk</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Central and peripheral circadian clocks in mammals</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>462</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Green1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The meter of metabolism</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>728</fpage>–<lpage>742</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Nagoshi1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laroche</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naef</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Circadian gene expression in individual fibroblasts: cell-autonomous and self-sustained oscillators pass time to daughter cells</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>705</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Welsh1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Bioluminescence imaging of individual fibroblasts reveals persistent, independently phased circadian rhythms of clock gene expression</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>2289</fpage>–<lpage>2295</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Yoo1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowrey</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimomura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>PERIOD2::LUCIFERASE real-time reporting of circadian dynamics reveals persistent circadian oscillations in mouse peripheral tissues</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>5339</fpage>–<lpage>5346</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Young1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Time zones: a comparative genetics of circadian clocks</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>702</fpage>–<lpage>715</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Busino1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Busino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bassermann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maiolica</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>SCFFbxl3 controls the oscillation of the circadian clock by directing the degradation of cryptochrome proteins</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>316</volume>: <fpage>900</fpage>–<lpage>904</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Siepka1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siepka</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Circadian mutant Overtime reveals F-box protein FBXL3 regulation of cryptochrome and period gene expression</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>1011</fpage>–<lpage>1023</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Godinho1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Godinho</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maywood</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tucci</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The after-hours mutant reveals a role for Fbxl3 in determining mammalian circadian period</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>316</volume>: <fpage>897</fpage>–<lpage>900</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Shi1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Dual roles of FBXL3 in the mammalian circadian feedback loops are important for period determination and robustness of the clock</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>4750</fpage>–<lpage>4755</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Yoo2"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohawk</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siepka</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Competing E3 ubiquitin ligases govern circadian periodicity by degradation of CRY in nucleus and cytoplasm</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>152</volume>: <fpage>1091</fpage>–<lpage>1105</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Hirano1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yumimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsunematsu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>FBXL21 regulates oscillation of the circadian clock through ubiquitination and stabilization of cryptochromes</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>152</volume>: <fpage>1106</fpage>–<lpage>1118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Ueda1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Machida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>System-level identification of transcriptional circuits underlying mammalian circadian clocks</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Liu2"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Redundant function of REV-ERBalpha and beta and non-essential role for Bmal1 cycling in transcriptional regulation of intracellular circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000023</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Cho1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hatori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barish</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Regulation of circadian behaviour and metabolism by REV-ERB-alpha and REV-ERB-beta</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>485</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Koike1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional architecture and chromatin landscape of the core circadian clock in mammals</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>338</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-DeBruyne1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeBruyne</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hogenesch</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A CRY in the Night</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-UkaiTadenuma1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ukai-Tadenuma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ripperger</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Delay in feedback repression by cryptochrome 1 is required for circadian clock function</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>144</volume>: <fpage>268</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Hogenesch1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogenesch</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Understanding systems-level properties: timely stories from the study of clocks</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>416</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Ramanathan1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramanathan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kathale</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Monitoring cell-autonomous circadian clock rhythms of gene expression using luciferase bioluminescence reporters</article-title>. <source>J Vis Exp</source> <fpage>e4234</fpage> <comment>doi <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/4210.37914234.:4210.3791/4234." xlink:type="simple">4210.37914234.:4210.3791/4234.</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Khan1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ukai-Tadenuma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Identification of a novel cryptochrome differentiating domain required for feedback repression in circadian clock function</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>287</volume>: <fpage>25917</fpage>–<lpage>25926</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Hogenesch2"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogenesch</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Intracellular and intercellular processes determine robustness of the circadian clock</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source> <volume>585</volume>: <fpage>1427</fpage>–<lpage>1434</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Ukai1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ukai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Systems biology of mammalian circadian clocks</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Physiol</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>579</fpage>–<lpage>603</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Baggs1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baggs</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DiTacchio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Network features of the mammalian circadian clock</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e52</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Sato1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ukai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baggs</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miraglia</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Feedback repression is required for mammalian circadian clock function</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Atwood1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atwood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeConde</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mockler</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sabir</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Cell-autonomous circadian clock of hepatocytes drives rhythms in transcription and polyamine synthesis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>18560</fpage>–<lpage>18565</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Panda1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antoch</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schook</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Coordinated transcription of key pathways in the mouse by the circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Zhang1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miraglia</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A genome-wide RNAi screen for modifiers of the circadian clock in human cells</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-EckelMahan1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eckel-Mahan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sassone-Corsi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Metabolism control by the circadian clock and vice versa</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>467</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Asher1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schibler</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Crosstalk between components of circadian and metabolic cycles in mammals</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Green2"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kehinde</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>An established preadipose cell line and its differentiation in culture. II. Factors affecting the adipose conversion</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Kallen1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kallen</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Antidiabetic thiazolidinediones inhibit leptin (ob) gene expression in 3T3-L1 adipocytes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>5793</fpage>–<lpage>5796</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Amicone1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amicone</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spagnoli</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spath</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tommasini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Transgenic expression in the liver of truncated Met blocks apoptosis and permits immortalization of hepatocytes</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>503</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Feigelstock1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feigelstock</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Growth of hepatitis A virus in a mouse liver cell line</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>2950</fpage>–<lpage>2955</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Otway1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Otway</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Circadian rhythmicity in murine pre-adipocyte and adipocyte cells</article-title>. <source>Chronobiol Int</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1340</fpage>–<lpage>1354</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Aoyagi1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aoyagi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tezuka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Characteristics of Circadian Gene Expression in Mice White Adipose Tissue and 3T3-L1 Adipocytes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Science</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Gachon1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gachon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olela</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaad</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Descombes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schibler</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The circadian PAR-domain basic leucine zipper transcription factors DBP, TEF, and HLF modulate basal and inducible xenobiotic detoxification</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Yamajuku1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamajuku</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitazawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katakura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Cellular DBP and E4BP4 proteins are critical for determining the period length of the circadian oscillator</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source> <volume>585</volume>: <fpage>2217</fpage>–<lpage>2222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Echeverri1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Echeverri</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beachy</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boutros</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchholz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Minimizing the risk of reporting false positives in large-scale RNAi screens</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>779</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Liu3"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Intercellular coupling confers robustness against mutations in the SCN circadian clock network</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>–<lpage>616</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Maier1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanselow</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallach</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reischl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A large-scale functional RNAi screen reveals a role for CK2 in the mammalian circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>708</fpage>–<lpage>718</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Ko1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buhr</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Emergence of noise-induced oscillations in the central circadian pacemaker</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1000513</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-DeBruyne2"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeBruyne</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reppert</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Peripheral circadian oscillators require CLOCK</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>R538</fpage>–<lpage>539</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Dudley1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erbel-Sieler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Estill</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franken</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Altered patterns of sleep and behavioral adaptability in NPAS2-deficient mice</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>301</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>383</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Shi2"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGuinness</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wasserman</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Circadian clock gene Bmal1 is not essential; functional replacement with its paralog, Bmal2</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Preitner1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Preitner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Damiola</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Molina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zakany</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duboule</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The orphan nuclear receptor REV-ERBalpha controls circadian transcription within the positive limb of the mammalian circadian oscillator</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>260</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Pendergast1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pendergast</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friday</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Endogenous rhythms in Period1 mutant suprachiasmatic nuclei in vitro do not represent circadian behavior</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>14681</fpage>–<lpage>14686</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Bae1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maywood</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reppert</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Differential functions of mPer1, mPer2, and mPer3 in the SCN circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>525</fpage>–<lpage>536</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Zheng1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaasik</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Nonredundant roles of the mPer1 and mPer2 genes in the mammalian circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>683</fpage>–<lpage>694</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Brown1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fleury-Olela</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagoshi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Juge</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The period length of fibroblast circadian gene expression varies widely among human individuals</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e338</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Pendergast2"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pendergast</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friday</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Distinct functions of Period2 and Period3 in the mouse circadian system revealed by in vitro analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e8552</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Chen1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schirmer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Rhythmic PER abundance defines a critical nodal point for negative feedback within the circadian clock mechanism</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>430</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Shearman1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shearman</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reppert</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Targeted disruption of the mPer3 gene: subtle effects on circadian clock function</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>6269</fpage>–<lpage>6275</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Yagita1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yagita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamanini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Der Horst</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of the biological clock in cultured fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>292</volume>: <fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Pendergast3"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pendergast</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niswender</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Tissue-specific function of Period3 in circadian rhythmicity</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e30254</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Evans1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Cry1−/− circadian rhythmicity depends on SCN intercellular coupling</article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Hasan1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Veen</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winsky-Sommerer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dijk</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Altered sleep and behavioral activity phenotypes in PER3-deficient mice</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</source> <volume>301</volume>: <fpage>R1821</fpage>–<lpage>1830</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Dallmann1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dallmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Altered body mass regulation in male mPeriod mutant mice on high-fat diet</article-title>. <source>Chronobiol Int</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1317</fpage>–<lpage>1328</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Costa1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>So</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaasik</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pillsbury</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Circadian rhythm gene period 3 is an inhibitor of the adipocyte cell fate</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>9063</fpage>–<lpage>9070</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Barnard1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>When clocks go bad: neurobehavioural consequences of disrupted circadian timing</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000040</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Dijk1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijk</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>PERIOD3, circadian phenotypes, and sleep homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Sleep Med Rev</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Shearman2"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shearman</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sriram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maywood</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Interacting molecular loops in the mammalian circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>288</volume>: <fpage>1013</fpage>–<lpage>1019</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Schmutz1"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmutz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ripperger</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baeriswyl-Aebischer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The mammalian clock component PERIOD2 coordinates circadian output by interaction with nuclear receptors</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Kim1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forger</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A mechanism for robust circadian timekeeping via stoichiometric balance</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>630</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Lee1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Stoichiometric relationship among clock proteins determines robustness of circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>7033</fpage>–<lpage>7042</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Ye1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selby</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ozturk</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Annayev</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sancar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Biochemical analysis of the canonical model for the mammalian circadian clock</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>25891</fpage>–<lpage>25902</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Hart1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>How sugar tunes your clock</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Pagano1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Wagging the dogma; tissue-specific cell cycle control in the mouse embryo</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>538</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-AzaBlanc1"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aza-Blanc</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Batalov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deveraux</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Identification of modulators of TRAIL-induced apoptosis via RNAi-based phenotypic screening</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>627</fpage>–<lpage>637</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Rubinson1"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubinson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kwiatkowski</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A lentivirus-based system to functionally silence genes in primary mammalian cells, stem cells and transgenic mice by RNA interference</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Tiscornia1"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiscornia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Production and purification of lentiviral vectors</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004244-Hirota1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A chemical biology approach reveals period shortening of the mammalian circadian clock by specific inhibition of GSK-3beta</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>20746</fpage>–<lpage>20751</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>