<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS Genetics</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PGENETICS-D-15-01389</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Arabidopsis Flower and Embryo Developmental Genes are Repressed in Seedlings by Different Combinations of Polycomb Group Proteins in Association with Distinct Sets of Cis-regulatory Elements</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Combinatorial Functions of PcGs and Tissue Specificity</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Hua</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Chunmei</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>Jingfei</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Jian</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Lei</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>He</surname>
<given-names>Chongsheng</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="currentaff001"><sup>¤</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>Wen-Hui</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Jin</surname>
<given-names>Hong</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Lin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Yijing</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>National Laboratory of Plant Molecular Genetics, CAS Center for Excellence in Molecular Plant Sciences, Institute of Plant Physiology and Ecology, Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shanghai, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Department of Chemistry, Fudan University, Shanghai, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Collaborative Innovation Center of Genetics and Development, International Associated Laboratory of CNRS-Fudan-HUNAU on Plant Epigenome Research, Department of Biochemistry, Institute of Plant Biology, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>Institut de Biologie Moléculaire des Plantes, UPR2357 CNRS, Université de Strasbourg, Strasbourg, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff005"><label>5</label> <addr-line>Institute of Biomedical Science, Fudan University, Shanghai, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Colot</surname>
<given-names>Vincent</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>IBENS, FRANCE</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LX YZ. Performed the experiments: HW CL CH LZ. Analyzed the data: JC JL LZ WHS HJ LX YZ. Wrote the paper: WHS HJ LX YZ.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="current-aff" id="currentaff001">
<label>¤</label><p>Current address: Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, The Perelman School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">Jinhong@fudan.edu.cn</email> (HJ); <email xlink:type="simple">xulin01@sibs.ac.cn</email> (LX); <email xlink:type="simple">zhangyijing@sibs.ac.cn</email> (YZ)</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>13</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>1</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<elocation-id>e1005771</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>6</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>4</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Wang et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771"/>
<abstract>
<p>Polycomb repressive complexes (PRCs) play crucial roles in transcriptional repression and developmental regulation in both plants and animals. In plants, depletion of different members of PRCs causes both overlapping and unique phenotypic defects. However, the underlying molecular mechanism determining the target specificity and functional diversity is not sufficiently characterized. Here, we quantitatively compared changes of tri-methylation at H3K27 in Arabidopsis mutants deprived of various key PRC components. We show that CURLY LEAF (CLF), a major catalytic subunit of PRC2, coordinates with different members of PRC1 in suppression of distinct plant developmental programs. We found that expression of flower development genes is repressed in seedlings preferentially <italic>via</italic> non-redundant role of CLF, which specifically associated with LIKE HETEROCHROMATIN PROTEIN1 (LHP1). In contrast, expression of embryo development genes is repressed by PRC1-catalytic core subunits AtBMI1 and AtRING1 in common with PRC2-catalytic enzymes CLF or SWINGER (SWN). This context-dependent role of CLF corresponds well with the change in H3K27me3 profiles, and is remarkably associated with differential co-occupancy of binding motifs of transcription factors (TFs), including MADS box and ABA-related factors. We propose that different combinations of PRC members distinctively regulate different developmental programs, and their target specificity is modulated by specific TFs.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary">
<title>Author Summary</title>
<p>Polycomb group proteins (PcGs) are essential for development in both animals and plants. Studies in plants are advantageous for elucidation of specific effects of PcGs during development, since most PcG mutants are viable in plants but not in animals. Previous efforts in genetic study of plant PcGs revealed that different PcGs have both common and unique effects on plant development, but the mechanisms underlying the specific regulation of different developmental programs by PcGs are still far from clear. In this study, we quantitatively compared the change in H3K27me3 and gene expression profiles between mutants of key PcG members on a genome-wide scale in Arabidopsis seedlings, and successfully unraveled different developmental programs that are specifically regulated by different combinations of PcGs. This context specific effect of PcGs is closely associated with different sets of transcription factor binding motifs. Together, we revealed on a genome-wide scale that different combinations of PcGs, as well as their association with the binding sites of different TFs, serve to explain the specific regulation of different developmental programs by PcGs.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This work was supported by grants from National Basic Research Program of China (973 Programs, 2012CB910500/2014CB943500) and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (91419302, 31422005 and 31570319), and sponsored by Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shanghai Pujiang Program (15PJ1409600) and Youth Innovation Promotion Association CAS. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="7"/>
<table-count count="0"/>
<page-count count="25"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>The ChIP-seq and RNA-seq data were deposited in Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) under the accession number GSE67322. Tracks for all sequencing data and related public data can be visualized through our local genome browser: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.sibs.ac.cn/gb2/gbrowse/tair10/" xlink:type="simple">http://bioinfo.sibs.ac.cn/gb2/gbrowse/tair10/</ext-link></meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The evolutionarily conserved Polycomb group proteins (PcGs) are the major epigenetic machinery regulating differentiation and development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref001">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref004">4</xref>]. PcGs mediated repression is achieved by establishment and maintenance of epigenetic modifications surrounding target genes. In both plants and animals, PcGs are classified into two major multi-protein complexes PRC1 and PRC2, which participate in transcriptional repression by catalyzing H3K27 tri-methylation and H2A ubiquitination, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref001">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref004">4</xref>]. Depletion of various PcG components in plants lead to varied developmental defects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref005">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref013">13</xref>]raising a major question about how the functional specificity of PcGs is established.</p>
<p>Study of the functional specificity of PcGs in both plant and animals is non-trivial. Firstly, the majority of PcG components are ubiquitously expressed, and do not have sequence-specific DNA recognition properties. Secondly, members of PcGs generally have functional redundancy and diversity, and it is difficult to distinguish the specific effect of individual members. Plants are advantageous for studying the effect of PcGs in development since most plant PcG mutants are viable, while animal development is generally vulnerable to PcG mutations. Previous efforts in genetic dissection of PcGs’ functions provide important clues as to the specialized functions of PcG members. For example, CURLY LEAF (CLF) and SWINGER (SWN) are two highly similar enzymatic subunits of the PRC2 complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref011">11</xref>], and they play redundant roles in plant development as double mutants <italic>clf swn</italic> show a much more severe phenotype than each of the single mutants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref011">11</xref>]. However, this redundancy is partial since SWN cannot rescue the phenotypic defects upon loss of <italic>CLF</italic>, including early flowering and curly leaf [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref011">11</xref>]. Similarly, lack of either <italic>AtRING1</italic> or <italic>AtBMI1</italic>, the core catalytic factors of PRC1, leads to depression of embryonic traits in seedlings, while only the <italic>atring1a atring1b</italic> double mutant displays severely fused flower phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref013">13</xref>]. In addition, LIKE HETEROCHROMATIN PROTEIN1 (LHP1, also known as Terminal Flower-2, TFL2) is a PRC1 component [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref010">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref014">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref015">15</xref>] capable of interacting with both PRC1 components AtBMI1 and AtRING1 in vitro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref013">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref016">16</xref>]. However, <italic>lhp1</italic> displays some similar phenotypic defects to those of the PRC2 mutant <italic>clf</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref010">10</xref>], and more recent evidence showed that LHP1 co-purifies with PRC2 complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref017">17</xref>]. Moreover, studies on different loci led to different conclusions on the interplay between PRC1 and PRC2, including their orders of recruitment into the corresponding complexes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref007">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref019">19</xref>]. It seems that different PcGs tend to repress specific gene sets with distinct functions. However, target genes and the mechanisms of specificity for different PcGs are not sufficiently characterized, particularly from a genome-wide point of view.</p>
<p>Multiple mechanisms had been proposed in Arabidopsis to explain the target specificity of PcGs, <italic>e</italic>.<italic>g</italic>. specific recruitment of PcGs by diverse strategies for transcription repression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref007">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref020">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref027">27</xref>] and selective displacement of PcGs by some transcription factors for transcription de-repression during developmental transitions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref028">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref029">29</xref>]. However, most of these proposed mechanisms are based on studies of some specific genes without an overview at genome-wide scale. It is also worth to note that some conclusions drawn from genome-wide studies may not be always consistent with results obtained at specific gene loci. An example case is regarding the H3K27me3 modification change in the <italic>lhp1</italic> mutant. The global H3K27me3 pattern in the mutant was similar to that in wild-type Col-0 plant, leading to a conclusion that LHP1 is responsible for recognizing H3K27me3 and facilitating PRC1 binding but not for depositing H3K27me3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref014">14</xref>]. However, some more recent ChIP-qPCR results revealed that several PRC2 targets show an obvious reduction of H3K27me3 levels in <italic>lhp1</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref017">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref023">23</xref>]. This discrepancy between genome-wide and ChIP-qPCR results could be due to H3K27me3 differences in <italic>lhp1</italic> being localized to some specific genomic regions, which had been missed in detection by genome-wide profiling with relatively low resolution. Therefore, for unraveling the locus selectivity and distinguishing the specific effects of different PcGs, combining high-resolution genome-scale data with quantitative analyses methods are indispensable.</p>
<p>The next-generation sequencing technology has enabled the detection of epi-genome profiles with high sensitivity and specificity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref030">30</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref032">32</xref>]. We have recently developed a package for quantitative comparison of epi-genomic data, showing a high quality in dissecting specific epigenomic modifications in animal development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref033">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref036">36</xref>]. Using these newly developed methods, here we quantitatively compared genome-wide changes of H3K27me3 and gene expression profiles in loss-of-function mutants in PRC1 (AtBMI1, AtRING1 and LHP1) and PRC2 (CLF) components in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings. We revealed that CLF collaborates with different PRC1 subunits to repress flower and embryo development. We further demonstrated that the target specificity of these different combinations of PcGs is closely associated with different sets of TF binding motifs, pointing to an active interplay between particular TFs and the specific activity of different PcGs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>LHP1 co-purified with FIE PRC2 complex</title>
<p>To dissect the composition of PRC2 complex in Arabidopsis, we used the FIE-3XFLAG fusion protein in immunoprecipitation experiments to identify associated proteins from leaf explants cultured in callus-induction medium. Following mass spectrometry analysis (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec013">Methods</xref>), we identified the well-documented PRC2 components, including SWN, CLF, EMF2 and VRN2, as well as the previously considered PRC1 component LHP1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s018">S1 Table</xref>), consistent with recent report in inflorescence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref017">17</xref>], indicating that the interaction between LHP1 and PRC2 complex is relatively stable across different tissues. It is worth noting that although LHP1 has the ability to bind the core catalytic subunits of PRC1 including AtBMI1 and AtRING1 <italic>in vitro</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref013">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref016">16</xref>], neither component was identified here, suggesting a special role for LHP1 in association with PRC2 complex.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Different PcG subunits have non-redundant roles in repressing particular gene sets via H3K27me3</title>
<p>To compare roles of different PcGs, we used chromatin immunoprecipitation followed by high-throughput sequencing (ChIP-seq) to characterize the genome-wide profiles of H3K27me3 in Col-0, <italic>clf-29</italic>, <italic>tfl2-2</italic>, <italic>atbmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>, and <italic>atring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s019">S2A Table</xref>). In Col-0, 5,055 read enriched H3K27me3 regions (peaks) were identified (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s019">S2B Table</xref>), 84% of which localized in promoter and genic regions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s002">S1 Fig</xref>). The top enriched functions for those peak targets include transcription regulation, carpel and petal development (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s019">S2C Table</xref>). Notably, almost half of the annotated MADS box proteins are marked by H3K27me3 in seedlings (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s019">S2C Table</xref>). To compare H3K27me3 marks across samples, we first ranked the read intensities of Col-0 H3K27me3 peaks from high to low (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g001">Fig 1A</xref> panel I), which is positively correlated with the binding of PcG components including FIE, EMF1 and LHP1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g001">Fig 1A</xref> panel VII), and is inversely associated with the expression level of surrounding genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g001">Fig 1B</xref>). Next, the level of H3K27me3 mark in the corresponding regions in mutants were plotted side-by-side with that of Col-0 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g001">Fig 1A</xref> panel III-VI), which showed highly similar patterns, with the global level slightly lower in some mutants as compared to Col-0. Similarly, slight reduction of H3K27me3 has also been reported in Arabidopsis mutant lacking <italic>EMBRYONIC FLOWER</italic>1 (<italic>EMF1</italic>)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref032">32</xref>], a plant specific PcG member [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref037">37</xref>]. These results indicate that lack of any of these PcGs does not lead to complete loss of H3K27me3.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005771.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Local difference of H3K27me3 marks in mutants of PcG components.</title>
<p>(A) ChIP-seq density heatmaps in Col-0 and PcG mutants, ranked by H3K27me3 read intensity within ±500 bp of peak summits in Col-0. The Pearson correlation coefficient between H3K27me3 intensity in Col-0 and FIE binding within ±50 bp of peak summits is 0.52. ChIP-seq data of H3K27me3 in panel II and FIE binding in panel VII were published previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref040">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref041">41</xref>]. To compare H3K27me3 level with the bindings of LHP1 and EMF1 based on published ChIP-chip data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref015">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref032">32</xref>], the fraction of EMF1 peaks (blue) or LHP1 peaks (red) Col-0 overlapped with Col-0 H3K27me3 peaks were plotted. (B) RNA-seq intensity heatmap for the targets of H3K27me3 peaks in Col-0 with the same order as in (A). The expression intensity is measured by Reads Per Kilobase per Million of mapped reads (RPKM). (C) (C) IGV screen shots showing the distribution of H3K27me3 mark intensity in Col-0 and different mutants of PcG components. Negative control is Col-0 sample immunoprecipitated with beads but without antibody. Regions showing quantitative reduction of H3K27me3 marks are highlighted by blue box.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>However, we observed different sets of loci showing apparent reduction of H3K27me3 in Arabidopsis deprived of different PcG members, suggesting PcG subunits have non-redundant roles in H3K27me3 deposition in local regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g001">Fig 1C</xref>). Traditional peak overlap method showed poor performance in characterizing H3K27me3 changes in PcG mutants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s003">S2 Fig</xref>). Thus, we used the pipeline of MAnorm, a software package specifically designed for quantitative comparison of ChIP-seq datasets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref033">33</xref>]. MAnorm derives its power from definition of M value, a statistic characterizing the strength of differential binding, the higher the absolute M value, the larger the difference, with the sign (+/-) representing higher intensity in PcG mutants or Col-0. In <italic>clf-29</italic>, we identified substantially more regions with reduced H3K27me3 modification than with increased H3K27me3 marks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g002">Fig 2A</xref>), consistent with a major role for CLF in catalyzing H3K27me3. Intriguingly, similar pattern was also observed in <italic>tfl2-2</italic> and <italic>atbmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s004">S3 Fig</xref>), thus, PRC1 factors possibly contribute to H3K27me3 establishment. We also found hundreds of regions with increased H3K27me3 in <italic>clf-29</italic>, majority (68%) of which overlapped with H3K27me3 peaks in Col-0, while those non-overlapping regions also tend to be marked by H3K27me3 in Col-0, which are below peak detection cutoff, as shown by the read intensity distribution plot (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s005">S4 Fig</xref>). This increase of H3K27me3 in <italic>clf-29</italic> could be possibly due to the effect of other PcGs. Previous studies in both human and <italic>Drosophila</italic> also observed hyper-methylation of H3K27 in Ezh2 mutants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref038">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref039">39</xref>], but no consensus has been made about the underlying mechanism.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005771.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Quantitative difference of H3K27me3 marks are inversely correlated with the change of target gene expression in PcG mutants.</title>
<p>(A) MA plot of all peaks from comparison of <italic>clf-29</italic> and Col-0 after normalization by MAnorm. Each dot represents a peak. X-axis is the A value, which represents the average intensity. Y-axis is the M value, which represents the difference of the intensity. Here, positive M value indicates higher H3K27me3 level in <italic>clf-29</italic> as compared to that in Col-0, and negative M value represents lower H3K27me3 level in <italic>clf-29</italic>. The color range represents -log10 P value associated with normalized peaks. (B) Enrichment of H3K27me3 peak targets with different M values in gene sets whose expression are regulated by different PcGs. The target genes were grouped by the M values of nearby peaks. For each group, the overlap with differentially expressed genes in a given PcG mutant was compared to the expected overlap at random; x-axis represents enrichment score. Fishers’ exact test was used to test the significance of overlap. *, P value &lt;5e-2; **, P value &lt;1e-2; ***, P value &lt;1e-3. (C) Bar plot showing the percentage of H3K27me3 peaks with different M values in <italic>tlf2-2</italic> overlapped with LHP1 binding sites.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>To test if the quantitative difference of H3K27me3 has an effect on differential expression of target genes, H3K27me3 regions were partitioned to consecutive groups ranked by M value, and the gene targets for each group were identified (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec013">Methods</xref>). The percentage of genes showing differential expression, up or down regulation separately, are depicted for each group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g002">Fig 2B</xref>). In general, target genes associated with negative M value—that is, peaks with reduced H3K27me3 in mutants—were enriched in genes more highly expressed in mutants, and vice versa, which is consistent with the repressive role of H3K27me3. This indicates that the M value determined by MAnorm reflects authentic H3K27me3 changes.</p>
<p>Since loss of <italic>LHP1</italic> affects the H3K27me3 level for thousands of genes, we wondered whether the effect of LHP1 on H3K27me3 is direct or indirect. Previous evidence suggested that LHP1 co-localizes with H3K27me3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref014">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref015">15</xref>]. We compared the overlap between LHP1 binding peaks and genomic regions with change of H3K27me3 in <italic>tfl2-2</italic> characterized by M value (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g002">Fig 2C</xref>). Notably, nearly 1/4 regions with reduced H3K27me3 level (M&lt;0) overlap with LHP1 binding sites as determined by previous ChIP-chip study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref015">15</xref>]. The overlap is significantly higher (P value &lt; 1e-3) than expected by chance based on permutation test (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec013">Methods</xref>). In addition, we observed that the higher the effect of LHP1 on deposition of H3K27me3—as indicated by low M values—the higher the percentage of corresponding H3K27me3 regions overlapping with LHP1 binding, indicating a direct relationship between LHP1 binding and H3K27me3 change.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Different sets of H3K27me3 loci are preferentially regulated by distinct combinations of PcGs</title>
<p>To dissect the cooperation of these PcGs on H3K27me3 modification, we collected 3,289 H3K27me3 regions regulated by at least one PcG component, and clustered the M values of H3K27me3 change in these regions to 3 clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g003">Fig 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s020">S3A Table</xref>). Although LHP1 physically interacts with AtRING1 and AtBMI1 <italic>in vitro</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref013">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref016">16</xref>], the H3K27me3 change profile in <italic>tfl2-2</italic> is closely correlated with that of <italic>clf-29</italic>, with 1,982 regions (peak set I) showing concerted reduction of H3K27me3 in both mutants. On the other hand, loss of AtBMI1A and AtBMI1B or AtRING1A and AtRING1B specifically reduced H3K27me3 level in 566 regions (peak set II), which represents PRC2 target sites affected by AtBMI1 and AtRING1 directly or indirectly, but is independent of LHP1. Thus, the dependence of H3K27me3 on LHP1 seems tightly correlated with the specific effect of CLF. In addition, 741 regions belonging to class III show increased H3K27me3 levels.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005771.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>clf-29</italic> and <italic>tfl2-2</italic> show coordinated H3K27me3 change profiles distinct from those in <italic>atring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic> and <italic>atbmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>.</title>
<p>K-means clustering of M values characterizing the quantitative change of H3K27me3 in PcG mutants. Definition of H3K27me3 quantitative change regions were based on combined criteria |M|&gt;1 and P value &lt;1e-3. Green and red colors represent lower and higher H3K27me3 levels in PcG mutants compared to that in Col-0. IGV screenshots support CLF and LHP1 participate in H3K27me3 elongation. Grey areas represent regions where significant H3K27me3 reductions happen mainly in surrounding regions but not in summit regions in <italic>tfl2-2</italic> and <italic>clf-29</italic> compared to Col-0. It’s worth noting that no smooth should be applied while preparing data for IGV screenshots, or else the difference between Col and <italic>clf-29</italic> or <italic>tfl-2</italic> would not be as obvious as the raw data. (C) Visualization of the profile of average read intensity around peak summits. All regions from peak set I were aligned such that peak summit is in the center of each region. Next, average read intensities were calculated and plotted for each consecutive 50 bp. (D) The diagram illustrates the finding based on H3K27me3 ChIP-seq data comparisons that LHP1 and CLF participate in elongation of H3K27me3 mark.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>It is remarkable to find that CLF and LHP1 have a coordinated effect on H3K27me3 modifications at many genome regions. We wondered how these two factors control H3K27me3 around similar loci. A closer look at regions in peak set I indicates that loss of <italic>CLF</italic> or <italic>LHP1</italic> lead to apparent reduction of H3K27me3 in surrounding regions, but for most cases the signal at the summit is only slightly reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g003">Fig 3B</xref>). A similar finding was reported supporting CLF-dependent disperse of H3K27me3 around transgenes carrying AG regulatory sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref042">42</xref>]. Heatmap in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g003">Fig 3C</xref> showed the average read intensity around summits of peak set I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g003">Fig 3D</xref>). Statistical analysis detected this phenomenon for 51% and 53% H3K27me3 reduction regions in <italic>clf-29</italic> and <italic>tfl2-2</italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s020">S3B and S3C Table</xref>), indicating that CLF and LHP1 participate in H3K27me3 spreading.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>The expression of genes involved in different developmental processes are regulated by distinct combinations of PcGs</title>
<p>To investigate the functional consequence of the distinct H3K27me3 profile controlled by different combinations of PcGs, we first characterized the transcriptome change in each PcG mutant, including <italic>atring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>, <italic>atbmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>, <italic>clf-29</italic>, <italic>lhp1-6</italic>,and <italic>tfl2-2</italic>. Next, 2,438 genes with differential expression in at least one of the five mutants were collected, and partitioned to 3 groups according to the expression change pattern across the 5 samples via k-means clustering (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g004">Fig 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s021">S4A Table</xref>). Genes in group I are specifically up-regulated in <italic>lhp1-6</italic>, <italic>tfl2-2</italic> and <italic>clf-29</italic>, some of which are also induced in <italic>atring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic> to some extent, but have no obvious change in at<italic>bmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>. Comparison with expression change in <italic>clf-29</italic> and <italic>swn-21</italic> indicated that genes specifically increased in <italic>clf-29</italic> as compared to <italic>swn-21</italic> showing significant enrichment in group I (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s006">S5 Fig</xref>). Group II represents genes specifically higher expressed in <italic>atring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic> and <italic>atbmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>. Group III are genes repressed in all samples, which is perhaps not a direct effect of PcG components. It is interesting that genes from both group I and group II are upregulated in <italic>clf-29swn-21</italic> double mutants, whose transcriptome change is closely correlated with that in <italic>atring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g004">Fig 4B</xref>), indicating RING1 and BMI1 regulated genes tend to be concertedly controlled by PRC2.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005771.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>The profile of transcriptome change reveals two distinct combinations of PcGs with different functions.</title>
<p>Three groups of genes showing distinct expression change profiles across mutants of PcG components. Green and red colors represent lower and higher expression in PcG mutants. Heatmap including another 1,290 genes whose expression affected only in <italic>clf-29swn-21</italic> is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s006">S5A Fig</xref>. RNA-seq data sets were clustered via unsupervised hierarchical clustering based on Pearson correlation coefficients of log<sub>2</sub> expression fold-change across samples. (C-D) Functional terms enriched in genes from group 1 (C) and group 2 (D) as shown in (A).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Next, we wondered whether genes from different groups participate in distinct functions or pathways. GO enrichment analysis showed that gene set of group I is closely related with flowering, floral development and transcription (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g004">Fig 4C</xref>), whereas genes in group II are involved in nutrient reservoir, seed storage, and lipid localization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g004">Fig 4D</xref>). Enriched terms and genes are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s021">S4B and S4C Table</xref>. These functional transcriptome analyses could serve to explain the specific phenotypic defects observed in corresponding PcG mutants.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Different combinations of PcGs repress specific developmental programs via H3K27me3 remodeling of tissue-biased genes</title>
<p>To dissect the relationship between genes with distinct change profiles of H3K27me3 and differential expression, the targets for both peak set I and peak set II shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g003">Fig 3A</xref> were identified followed by statistical testing of their enrichment in each of the three expression groups identified in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g004">Fig 4A</xref>. As expected, genes in expression group I are significantly over-represented in targets of peak set I, representing genes showing decreased H3K27me3 marks and increased expression level in mutants of <italic>CLF</italic> and <italic>LHP1</italic>, and thus most likely to be the direct targets of CLF and LHP1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g005">Fig 5A</xref>). Similarly, genes in expression group II are preferentially enriched in targets of peak set II, representing genes affected by AtBMI1 and AtRING1 via H3K27me3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g005">Fig 5B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005771.g005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g005</object-id>
<label>Fig 5</label>
<caption>
<title>Targets of different combinations of PcGs and their expression bias.</title>
<p>(A) Enrichment analysis of peak set I targets in three expression groups shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g004">Fig 4A</xref>. ***, Fishers’ exact test P value &lt; 1e-3. (B) Enrichment analysis of peak set II targets in three expression groups shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g004">Fig 4A</xref>. ***, Fishers’ exact test P value &lt; 1e-3. (C-D) Box plot showing the distribution of expression changes and H3K27me3 changes for 108 genes (C) and 164 genes (D) in PcG mutants. (E-F) Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) showing a significant normalized enrichment score (NES) for flower biased expression of 108 genes (E) and embryo biased expression of 164 genes (F). The x axis represents all expressed genes ranked by tissue specificity as determined by expression profile, y axis presents the running enrichment score. (G) Heatmap showing NES calculated by GSEA for 108 genes and 164 genes in different gene sets with distinct tissue biased expressions.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>To dissect the repressive function of PcGs via H3K27me3, 108 genes with increased expression and reduced H3K27me3 marks in mutants of <italic>CLF</italic> and <italic>LHP1</italic> are extracted (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s022">S5A Table</xref>). 164 targets regulated by AtBMI1 and AtRING1 were identified in the same way (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s022">S5B Table</xref>). The distribution of both expression and H3K27me3 change in different PcG mutants were plotted for the 108 and 164 genes, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g005">Fig 5C and 5D</xref>). The induced expression of 164 genes in <italic>clf-29swn-21</italic> double mutant but in neither <italic>clf-29</italic> nor <italic>swn-7</italic> confirms that CLF and SWN could complement each other’s function for these genes. It’s also worth noting that mutation of <italic>CLF</italic> but not <italic>SWN</italic> is responsible for the induction of 108 genes.</p>
<p>To investigate the function of the 108 and 164 genes during development, we first classified all tissues with gene expression information into 8 groups based on their gene expression profiles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s007">S6 Fig</xref>). Next, we calculated the enrichment of the 108 and 164 genes in the different tissue-biased genes using Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref043">43</xref>]. The 108 genes are significantly more highly expressed in flowers, while the 164 genes are preferentially expressed in embryo (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s008">S7 Fig</xref>). GSEA using RNA-seq data showed consistent profiles with much lower P values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g005">Fig 5E and 5F</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s023">S6 Table</xref>). Notably, neither gene sets was significantly enriched in other tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g005">Fig 5G</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s005">S4 Fig</xref>), indicating a prominent relationship between PcGs and specific regulation of reproductive and embryo development.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Context-dependent regulation of H3K27me3 by different PcG combinations is closely associated with binding motifs of specific TFs</title>
<p>We asked whether this different combination of PcGs is associated with different TFs. We started by searching for the enriched motifs surrounding all Col-0 H3K27me3 peak summits. The top enriched motifs include the binding motifs of ABI3 type transcription factor B3 (ABI3/FUS3/LEC1), ABI4, ABF1, SPL and MYB (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s009">S8 Fig</xref>). The first three are binding motifs of ABA related TFs, which mainly participate in embryo development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref044">44</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref047">47</xref>], and is consistent with the well-documented function of PcGs in regulation of embryo development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref016">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref031">31</xref>]. Despite the fact that some MADS-box TFs are reported to modulate specific H3K27me3 deposition for regulation of meristem identity, flowering and floral development in individual loci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref022">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref023">23</xref>], CArG box, the binding motifs of MADS box transcription factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref048">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref049">49</xref>], show no enrichment when all H3K27me3 regions are considered (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s019">S2D Table</xref>).</p>
<p>Next, we identified motifs over-represented in peak sets I and II (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g006">Fig 6A and 6B</xref>). Of note, binding motifs for MADS box and Homeobox were specifically enriched in peak set I, indicating a close relationship between transcription factors from these families and H3K27me3 levels synergically regulated by CLF and LHP1. On the other hand, motifs enriched in peak set II were similar to the result from all H3K27me3 peaks in Col-0, including ABI4 and ABF1 binding sites. The binding motif for B3 domain TFs are enriched in all H3K27me3 regions, to a higher extent in peak set II, consistent with the major role of their targets in embryogenesis, seed maturation and dormancy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref050">50</xref>].</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005771.g006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g006</object-id>
<label>Fig 6</label>
<caption>
<title>TF binding motifs and TFs whose bindings enriched in peak set I and peak set II.</title>
<p>(A) Heatmap showing enriched motifs (P value &lt; 0.01) in either peak set I or peak set II. Their enrichment in H3K27me3 peaks in Col-0 are also shown. (B) Sequence LOGOs of motifs enriched in peak set I and peak set II. (C) Enrichment of the binding sites of FIE and TFs in peak set I. (D) IGV screen shots showing examples of co-occupancy between H3K27me3 in seedlings and the bindings of MADS-box TFs in inflorescence. The motif sites of MADS box TFs are indicated by pink and blue bars at bottom of the screen shots, and are highlighted by grey area. (E) GSEA showing the common target genes of peak set I and AP1 binding peaks are preferentially expressed in inflorescence.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Since multiple TFs could bind to the same cis-regulatory sites, to identify TFs closely associated with different sets of peaks, we first collected and processed published ChIP-seq data characterizing TF binding profiles from Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>). By querying against these processed binding sites, we found that the binding regions of some MADS box TFs are significantly enriched in peak set I but not in other H3K27me3 regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g006">Fig 6C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s024">S7 Table</xref>). The top enriched TFs are floral organ identity genes, including AP1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref051">51</xref>], AG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref052">52</xref>], AP3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref053">53</xref>] and SEP3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref051">51</xref>]. IGV screenshots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g006">Fig 6D</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s010">S9A Fig</xref> illustrate some examples of co-occupancy between H3K27me3 in seedlings and these MADS-box TFs. The source of the TF ChIP-seq data, the enrichment statistics and co-occupied regions are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s024">S7 Table</xref>. It should be noted that these TFs mainly expressed in inflorescence where these ChIP-seq data were generated from, while our ChIP-seq data were generated in seedlings. Thus, it is likely that specific binding of these TFs in some H3K27me3 regions from peak set I is responsible for selective de-repression of common target genes. In support of this, target genes of peak set I co-occupied by these TFs in inflorescence show apparent flower biased expression, while the other target genes of peak set I have no such expression bias (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g006">Fig 6E</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s010">S9B Fig</xref>), indicating the displacement of H3K27me3 by these TFs participating in activation of their common target genes. Consistently, it has been reported that some floral organ identity genes could interact with REF6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref054">54</xref>], the H3K27me3 demethylase in Arabidopsis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref041">41</xref>], which possibly work together with MADS-box TFs to remove H3K27me3 marks. Taken together, our genome-wide analyses based on both motif and ChIP-seq data revealed that the bindings of MADS box TFs are closely associated with H3K27me3 peak set I regulated by CLF and LHP1, suggesting that it might be a widespread mechanism by which the specific activities of PcG family proteins is modulated by tissue specific TFs, resulting in distinct transcriptional outputs in different tissues.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this study, based on quantitative comparison of epigenomic and transcriptomic data in mutants of core PcG components, we revealed that CLF collaborates with different PcGs partners to achieve transcriptional repression in distinct developmental programs. Importantly, target specificity of different combination of PcGs are closely associated with different sets of TF binding motifs, suggesting a widespread mechanism for modulation of PcGs specificity by particular TFs. We propose a context-dependent model for PcGs in selective repression of flower or embryo development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g007">Fig 7</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005771.g007" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g007</object-id>
<label>Fig 7</label>
<caption>
<title>Working model for specific regulation of plant development by PcG components.</title>
<p>(A) In seedlings, CLF and LHP1 work concertedly to repress flower specific genes, and some targets are also regulated by RING1. While repression of embryonic development requires cooperative regulation of AtBMI1, AtRING1, and the redundant role of CLF and SWN. (B) In inflorescence, significant parts of CLF and LHP1 target sites in seedlings are occupied by inflorescence specific TFs, which participate in de-repression of the common target genes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Distinct compositions of PcGs preferentially repress different transcriptional programs</title>
<p>As an ancient machinery for developmental regulation, PcGs employed multiple protein families which underwent duplication and diversification, and thus they share common targets but also have specialized functions. The common targets may represent those that are involved in more ancient processes in development, while the unique features may have evolved more recently. In support of this, we observed that embryo development, presenting in an overwhelming majority of land plant (embryophyte)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref055">55</xref>], is regulated by majority core components of PRC1 and PRC2, while flower development, a relatively recently evolved process in plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref056">56</xref>], is specifically regulated by only a subset of PcGs, with LHP1 and CLF as the major players. Then does the emergence of LHP1 or CLF parallel the appearance of flowering plant (angiosperms)? LHP1 is present in ancient plant species including <italic>Selaginella moellendorffii</italic> and <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref057">57</xref>]. Interestingly, our phylogenetic analysis revealed that the divergence of CLF and SWN likely occurred accompanying the emergence of angiosperms (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s011">S10 Fig</xref>), with the duplication existing in all angiosperm species collected, including <italic>Amborella trichopoda</italic>, the oldest known angiosperm, but not in more ancient species, including moss, <italic>Selaginella</italic> or plant from <italic>Gymnospermae</italic>. Thus, it is possible that after the duplication event, CLF preferentially acquired the ability of regulating floral development. Similarly, AtRING1 and AtBMI1, the catalytic subunits of PRC1, have both joint and individual functions. It is likely that in addition to the common targets with AtBMI1, AtRING1 also participate in regulating H3K27me3 modifications and expression for several target genes of CLF and LHP1 (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g003">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g004">4</xref>), which possibly serves to explain aberrant flower development only observed in <italic>atring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic> but not <italic>atbmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref013">13</xref>].</p>
<p>Our finding that PRC2 composition regulates differential transcriptional programs is analogous to a recent genome-wide study about human blood cell development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref034">34</xref>]. It was demonstrated that histone methyltransferase Enhancer of zeste1 (EZH1) and EZH2, the counterparts of CLF and SWN in human, form alternative PRC2 complexes with distinct subsets of PcGs, occupy different chromatin domains and regulate distinct transcriptional activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref034">34</xref>]. Given that epigenetic machineries generally have multiple family members, and thus could form a suite of different combinations, different compositions of epigenetic complexes could at least partially explain their selectivity in transcriptional regulation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Crosstalk between specific TFs and PcGs in developmental regulation</title>
<p>Target selection by PcGs in different developmental stages is critical for correct developmental regulation. Specific recruitment of PcGs by particular factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref007">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref020">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref023">23</xref>], Polycomb response elements (PREs)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref027">27</xref>], or non-coding RNAs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref024">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref025">25</xref>] have been a major explanation for both PRC1 and PRC2 binding in plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref058">58</xref>]. Recent reports proposed that release of PcG by a particular MADS protein AG is the prerequisite for activation of KNU [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref028">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref029">29</xref>]. Whereas all these conclusions are drawn from analyses based on limited loci, we provide clues from the genome-wide scale that MADS box TFs are possibly associated with specific release of PcGs. Specific recruitment of PcGs by MADS box TF has recently been reported. SHORT VEGETATIVE PHASE (SVP), the major flowering repressor in seedlings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref059">59</xref>], was shown to be able to interact with LHP1, and contribute to <italic>SEP3</italic> repression via H3K27me3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref023">23</xref>]. Consistently, we found SVP binding sites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref059">59</xref>] show good correlation with K27me3 modification in peak set I (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s012">S11 Fig</xref>). However, it’s binding sites are also enriched in peak set II, while the common binding sequences have no obvious relationship with CArG-box motifs. We observed that SVP ChIP-seq data have relatively high noise, and the binding regions tend to be broad, thus some coincident bindings could possibly be due to noise. Alternatively, SVP has diverse functions in addition to recruit PcGs for flowering repression.</p>
<p>MADS box TFs play a central role in flower development, and their family size increased explosively with the origin of angiosperm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref060">60</xref>]. We found almost half of the Arabidopsis MADS box TFs have the H3K27me3 modification in seedlings, indicating a strict control of MADS gene expression by PcGs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s019">S2C Table</xref>). On the other hand, we demonstrated that binding sites of MADS box TFs specifically enriched in genes controlled by CLF and LHP1, and possibly contribute to modulate the target selectivity. These findings close the loop of the transcription network regulating development processes, in which expression of tissue specific TFs is controlled by epigenetic marks, and specific TFs cooperate with epigenetic complexes in determining target selection and developmental regulation. How the epigenetic machinery co-evolved with specific TFs to cooperatively fine-tune the regulation of plant development is an intriguing phenomenon deserving further in-depth exploration.</p>
<p>It is intriguing that telo-box, a widespread short motif identical to the repeat (AAACCCT)<sub>n</sub> of plant telomeres [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref061">61</xref>], is specifically enriched in peak set I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g006">Fig 6A and 6B</xref>). Telo-box is reported to be involved in regulating gene expression in cycling cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref062">62</xref>], and whether the association between telo-box and the function of CLF or LHP1 involved in maintaining H3K27me3 marks during cell cycle is an interesting issue for further study. Genome-wide Hi-C analyses revealed telomeric regions and H3K27me3 modifications form local interactive hot spots [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref064">64</xref>]. And a recent study showed complementary activities of TELOMERE REPEAT BINDING proteins and PcGs in transcriptional regulation of target genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref063">63</xref>]. It is possible that telo-box also mediates local interaction among H3K27me3 marked regions. Collectively, our study provides rich resource as well as insightful clues for further exploration of the relationship between cis-elements, TFs and PcGs in specific regulation of developmental processes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Role of chromo-domain proteins in H3K27me3 spread and maintenance</title>
<p>The chromo-domain protein Heterochromatin protein 1 (HP1) and Polycomb (Pc) in animals bind H3K9me3 and H3K27me3, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref065">65</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref068">68</xref>]. Despite LHP1 sharing relatively higher level of sequence similarity with HP1, it can bind H3K27me3 in vitro and co-localize with H3K27me3 in vivo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref014">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref015">15</xref>], and was originally proposed to be the counterpart of Pc, responsible for recruitment of PRC1 to H3K27me3 catalyzed by PRC2. If this is the case, LHP1 should function downstream of PRC2. However, recent studies showed that H3K27me3 modifications also require LHP1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref017">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref023">23</xref>]. Here, our genome-wide results revealed that H3K27me3 levels of thousands of loci are controlled by LHP1. Further quantitative comparison of H3K27me3 change profiles across PcG mutants revealed that the effects of LHP1 on H3K27me3 modification and target gene repression are coordinated with the non-redundant role of CLF (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g003">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g004">4</xref>). In addition, both CLF and LHP1 are involved in spread of H3K27me3 marks since loss of either component lead to localized H3K27me3 signals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g003">Fig 3B, 3C and 3D</xref>). These findings not only confirmed previous report from studying AG transgene that CLF is indispensable for H3K27me3 spreading [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref042">42</xref>], but also identified LHP1 as an important cofactor with CLF in H3K27me3 elongation, which could finally contribute to inheritance and stability of epigenetic silencing.</p>
<p>Notably, LHP1 has no effect on genes jointly controlled by both PRC1 and PRC2 (targets of peak set II) despite the coincident binding of LHP1 and H3K27me3 in these regions. If the requirement of chromo-domain protein for H3K27me3 maintenance is a widespread mechanism, then there may be other chromo-domain proteins functional for spreading of H3K27me3 in these H3K27me3 regions. Alternatively, PcGs employ multiple strategies for H3K27me3 maintenance at different loci, either using LHP1 or cooperating with core subunits of PRC1 to create compacted chromatin structures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref069">69</xref>]. There are 13 Arabidopsis proteins that have chromo-domain, and further epigenomic studies are required to have a deeper understanding about the role of chromo-domain proteins on epigenetic modifications. Due to the functional redundancy and localized effects of epigenetic machineries, the quantitative comparison pipeline applied in this study will be of great help for further exploration based on high throughput data.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec014" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Experimental procedures</title>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Affinity purification of FIE complex</title>
<p>We constructed pFIE: FLAG-FIE transgenic plants (refer to <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s001">S1 Text</xref> for details), and collected 5 g of leaf explants (8 days cultured in callus induced medium) from T2 plants. Next, FIE complex is purified using the FLAG anti-body conjugated DynaBeads, which were further released by incubation with elution buffer (refer to <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s001">S1 Text</xref> for details).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Tandem mass spectrometry analyses</title>
<p>For Mass spectrometric analyses, samples were run in 1D SDS-PAGE gel and stained by silver nitrate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref070">70</xref>]. The SDS-PAGE gels were cut into pieces according to the silver staining result. The gel pieces were digested with trypsin (Promega) overnight, and then analyzed via liquid chromatography combined with electrospray tandem mass spectrometry on an LTQ Orbitrap (Thermo Fisher) with lock mass calibration. All of the raw data files were searched against Mascot Daemon software (Version 2.3.0, Matrix Science, London, UK) based on the Mascot algorithm. The database used was Swiss-Prot (Taxonomy: Arabidopsis Thaliana; release 2012_12_28, with 11571 entries). To reduce false positive identification results, a decoy database containing the reverse sequences was appended. The searching parameters were set up as following: full trypsin (KR) cleavage with two missed cleavage sites was considered. Oxidation on methionine and acetylation of the protein N-terminus were set as variable modifications. The peptide mass tolerance was 20 ppm and the fragment ion tolerance was 1.0 Da. Peptides with Percolater scores exceeding 13 were accepted as correct matches, the FDR is 0.01 (refer to <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s001">S1 Text</xref> for details).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Plant materials and growth conditions</title>
<p><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mutants <italic>clf-29</italic> (SALK_N521003)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref071">71</xref>], <italic>swn-21</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref072">72</xref>], <italic>lhp1-6</italic> (SALK_011762)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref057">57</xref>], <italic>tfl2-2</italic> (CS3797)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref073">73</xref>], <italic>atring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref013">13</xref>] and <italic>atbmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref016">16</xref>] in Col-0 background have been described previously. All plants except <italic>clf-29swn-21</italic> were grown in soil under long day (16 hour) photoperiods at 22°C in green house, and seedlings were harvested after 2 weeks. <italic>clf-29swn-21</italic> was grown on half-strength Murashige and Skoog (MS) medium in the same long day conditions as above, and the whole plants were harvested after 2 weeks. Harvested materials were frozen in liquid nitrogen for total RNA isolation or directly vacuum-infiltrated with formaldehyde crosslinking solution for ChIP assay. Quantitative real-time PCR analysis of ChIPed DNA with specific primers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s025">S8 Table</xref>) was performed on the two-color real-time PCR detection system (BIO-RAD, Hercules, CA, USA) using the SYBR Green Realtime PCR Master mix (TOYOBO) to represent the relative methylation levels.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>H3K27me3 ChIP-seq and RNA sample preparation</title>
<p>Both ChIP-seq and RNA-seq experiments were performed in biological duplicates for <italic>clf-29</italic> and <italic>atbmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>, or in independent lines of <italic>LHP1</italic> mutants <italic>lhp1-6</italic> and <italic>tf</italic>l2-2. Biological replicates of <italic>ring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic> RNA-seq were performed. ChIP assay was performed with the antibody against H3 trimethyl-Lys 27 (Upstate, USA, Cat. 07–449) as previously described (He et al. 2012). Samples without antibody were used as a negative control. More than 10 ng ChIP DNA or 2 μg total RNA from each sample was used for Illumina library generation following the manufacturer’s instructions (Illumina, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.illumina.com/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.illumina.com/</ext-link>). Library construction and deep sequencing were performed by Genergy Biotechnology Co. Ltd. (Shanghai, China) using Illumina HiSeq 2000 following the manufacturer’s instructions (Illumina). Raw data comprise 50 bp of single-end sequences for ChIP-seq and 100 bp of pair-end sequences for RNA-seq.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019">
<title>ChIP-seq, ChIP-chip and RNA-seq data analysis</title>
<p>We started by cleaning the sequencing reads, including removing bases with low quality score (&lt;20) and irregular GC content, cutting sequencing adaptor followed by filtering short reads. As a result, 12–36 million reads with MAPQ&gt;20 were obtained for further analysis (detailed statistics summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s019">S2A Table</xref>). The cleaned reads were mapped to <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> genome (TAIR10) using BWA 0.7.5a-r405 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref074">74</xref>] for DNA sequencing and TOPHATv2.0.8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref075">75</xref>] for RNA sequencing, both with default settings. Tracks for all sequencing data can be visualized through <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.sibs.ac.cn/gb2/gbrowse/tair10/" xlink:type="simple">http://bioinfo.sibs.ac.cn/gb2/gbrowse/tair10/</ext-link>. The genotype for each sample was validated by RNA-seq data (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s013">S12 Fig</xref>). ChIP-seq results were verified for selected sites by qPCR (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s014">S13 Fig</xref>).</p>
<p>MACS1.4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref076">76</xref>] was used to identify read enriched regions (peaks). Next, MAnorm, a software designed for quantitative comparison of ChIP-seq datasets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref033">33</xref>], was applied to characterize the change of genome-wide H3K27me3 profile in PcG mutants as compared to that of Col-0, including <italic>atbmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>, <italic>atring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>, <italic>clf-29</italic> and <italic>tfl2-2</italic>. 3,289 regions with differential binding in at least one of the three comparisons were selected based on the following criteria: P value &lt;1e-3 and |M|&gt;1, where M represents the log2 fold change of binding intensity. K-means clustering was performed to partition these sites according to their M values. The target gene of each peak was defined as the genes closest to a given peak localized around the gene body (from 1 kb upstream of transcription start site (TSS) to transcription end site (TES)), The gene annotation file was downloaded from the TAIR homepage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.arabidopsis.org</ext-link>). Published data sets including FIE ChIP-seq and LHP1 ChIP-chip data were downloaded from Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link> with accession numbers GSE48857 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref040">40</xref>] and GSE8169 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref015">15</xref>], respectively. Peaks for ChIP-seq data were identified using MACS14 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref076">76</xref>], and ChIP-chip peaks were identified using TileMap implemented in CisGenome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref077">77</xref>]. For IGV viewing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref078">78</xref>], we normalized H3K27me3 samples such that the numbers of reads in common peak regions between Col-0 and PcG mutants are the same. For input sample, we fitted Poisson distribution model for read in both input and H3K27me3 peak free regions in Col-0, and made these two Poisson distributions the sample λ value (λ = mean and variance of Poisson distribution).</p>
<p>Permutation test was used to test the significance of peak overlap between LHP1 binding sites and regions with reduced H3K27me3 in <italic>tfl2-2</italic>. Firstly, we shuffled LHP1 binding sites for 1,000 times, and obtained 1,000 random genomic regions with the same length distribution of LHP1 binding sites. Secondly, we calculated and recorded the numbers of these random sites overlapping with LHP1 binding. Since none of the 1000 overlapping numbers exceeds the actual overlap number between LHP1 and regions with reduced H3K27me3 in <italic>tfl2-2</italic>., the P value is thus lower than 1e-3.</p>
<p>Differentially expressed genes were detected by DESeq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref079">79</xref>], based on the combined criteria: |log2-foldchange| &lt; 1 and P value &lt;0.05. To dissect the relationship of transcriptomic change across samples, genes with differential expression in at least one of the five mutants (<italic>clf-29</italic>, <italic>lhp1-6</italic>, <italic>tfl2-2</italic>, <italic>atring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic> and <italic>atbmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>) were collected, resulting in 2,438 genes, which were further classified to 3 groups via k-means clustering. The <italic>clf-29swn-21</italic> double mutant has effect on much larger range of genes, and only the expression change profile for 2,438 genes are shown here. Transcriptomic data for different tissues were downloaded from GENEVESTIGATOR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref080">80</xref>]. Gene Set Enrichment Analysis was performed with default settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref043">43</xref>].</p>
<p>The replicates of ChIP-seq and RNA-seq data show good correlation in terms of log<sub>2</sub> (fold-change) of read intensity between Col-0 and PcG mutants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s015">S14</xref>–<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s017">S16</xref> Figs). Robust Index was calculated for each genomic region or gene to measure the repeatability between replicates. Robust <inline-formula id="pgen.1005771.e001"><alternatives><graphic id="pgen.1005771.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.e001" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Index </mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. FC1 and FC2 represent fold change in replicated dataset 1 and dataset 2, respectively. Genomic regions or genes with lower Robust Index are more credible in terms of the change of binding (i.e. M value) or expression (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s020">S3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s021">S4</xref> Tables).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020">
<title>Motif and TF binding enrichment analyses in H3K27me3 peaks</title>
<p>To detect TF binding motifs enriched in H3K27me3 peak regions, we downloaded the position weight matrixes (PWMs) of 269 motifs identified from both mammals and plants collected by JASPAR database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref081">81</xref>], and performed motif scan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1005771.ref082">82</xref>] applied to a 1,000 bp window centered at the peak center. For each motif M, the raw motif matching score at each peak P was calculated as: <inline-formula id="pgen.1005771.e002"><alternatives><graphic id="pgen.1005771.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.e002" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M2"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>⊆</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, in which S is a sequence fragment of the same length as the motif, and B is the background frequency of four types of nucleotides (A, C, G, T) estimated from the genome. The enrichment of motif M in a peak list was defined as the ratio of the motif occurrence in the peak list as compared to its occurrence in random genomic regions. Fisher’s exact test was used to calculate the enrichment P value. Motifs enriched with an enrichment P value of 0.01 were presented in a heat map.</p>
<p>To identify TFs whose binding enriched in different peak sets, we collected ChIP-seq data sets from 695 publicly available studies (till May 2015) from Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) and processed the data to peak lists as described above. Next, we calculated the enrichment of the overlap between peak set I or peak set II with each of these peak lists using Fisher’s exact test, and the top enriched TF bindings are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g006">Fig 6C</xref>. The GEO accession numbers, the enrichment statistics, as well as overlapping regions for enriched TFs are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s024">S7 Table</xref>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec021">
<title>Data access</title>
<p>The ChIP-seq and RNA-seq data were deposited in Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) under the accession number GSE67322. Tracks for all sequencing data and related public data can be visualized through our local genome browser: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.sibs.ac.cn/gb2/gbrowse/tair10/" xlink:type="simple">http://bioinfo.sibs.ac.cn/gb2/gbrowse/tair10/</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec022">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Text</label>
<caption>
<title>Detailed description of experimental procedures for FIE complex purification and tandem mass spectrometry analyses.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s002" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s002" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Distribution of 5,055 Col-0 H3K27me3 peaks in relation to gene annotation.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s003" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s003" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>IGV screenshots illustrate regions with quantitative H3K27me3 difference that can’t be characterized by peak overlap analysis.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s004" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s004" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S3 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>MA plots of all peaks from comparisons of PcG mutants and Col-0 after normalization by MAnorm.</title>
<p>(A-D) represent comparisons between Col-0 and (A) <italic>clf-29</italic> (B) <italic>tlf2-2</italic> (C) <italic>atring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic> and (D) <italic>atbmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>. Each dot represents a peak. X-axis is the A value, which represents the average intensity. Y-axis is the M value, which represents the difference of the intensity. The color range represents -log10 P value associated with normalized peaks. Here, positive M value indicates higher H3K27me3 level in PcG mutants as compared to that in Col-0, and negative M value represents lower H3K27me3 level in PcG mutants. The numbers of regions with elevated or depressed H3K27me3 levels in each mutant as compared to wild type are labeled based on combined criteria |M| &gt; 1 and P value &lt; 1e-3.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s005" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s005" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S4 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Col-0 ChIP-seq read distributions of Col-0 peak regions and peak free regions overlapping with H3K27me3 increased loci in <italic>clf-29</italic> (M&gt;0).</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s006" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s006" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S5 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Genes specifically induced in <italic>clf-29</italic> as compared to <italic>swn-21</italic> are significantly enriched in gene set in group I repressed by CLF and LHP1 as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g004">Fig 4A</xref>.</title>
<p>(A) Heatmap includes another 1,290 genes whose expressions are only affected in <italic>clf-29swn-21</italic> not depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g004">Fig 4A</xref>. (B) Enrichment of class 1 genes in group I. ***, Fishers’ exact text P &lt; 1e-3.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s007" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s007" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S6 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Different tissues are partitioned to 8 clusters based on gene expression profile across tissues.</title>
<p>K-means clustering is used.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s008" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s008" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S7 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Tissue biased expression analyses of 108 and 164 genes as revealed by GSEA.</title>
<p>The microarray expression data were downloaded from GENEVESTIGATOR. Tissues are partitioned to 8 tissue clusters as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1005771.s007">S6 Fig</xref>. GSEA calculated the normalized enrichment score (NES) representing the enrichment of 108 or 164 genes in different tissue biased genes. The x-axis represents all genes targeted by H3K27me3 in Col-0, y axis presents the running enrichment score. Heatmap in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g005">Fig 5G</xref> summarized the NESs of tissue biased expression of these two gene sets.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s009" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s009" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S8 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>The logo and distribution around peak summits for motifs enriched in H3K27me3 peaks identified in Col-0.</title>
<p>X-axis represents the distance of given motifs to peak summit (bp), y-axis represent the fraction of motifs located in a given position.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s010" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s010" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S9 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>TFs whose bindings associated with peak set I.</title>
<p>(A) IGV screenshots showing examples of co-occupancy between H3K27me3 in seedlings and the bindings of MADS-box TFs in inflorescence. The positions of MADS box TF binding motif CArG-box are indicated by pink bars at bottom of the screen shots, and are highlighted by grey area. (B) Those peak set I targets also occupied by floral organ identity TFs show significant inflorescence biased expression.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s011" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s011" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S10 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>The phylogenetic tree showing the divergence of CLF and SWN after the origin of angiosperms.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s012" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s012" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S11 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>IGV screen shots showing examples of co-occupancy between H3K27me3 and SVP in seedlings.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s013" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s013" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S12 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>IGV screen shots showing the genotype of each mutant as validated by RNA-seq data.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s014" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s014" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S13 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>ChIP-qPCR validation of ChIP-seq data for selected sites.</title>
<p>(A-B) ChIP-qPCR validations of regions with decreased (A) or increased (B) H3K27me3 in <italic>clf-29</italic> and <italic>tfl2-2</italic> as revealed by ChIP-seq data. Top panel is qPCR result. Shown are mean ±s.d. For each loci, input, ChIPed, and negative control samples were repeated for 3 times. Y-axis represents % input = 2<sup>(Ctiput—CtIP)</sup> -2<sup>(Ctinput-Ctneg)</sup>. CtIP: cycle threshold (Ct) value of samples immunoprecipitated using H3K27me3 antibody; Ctneg: Ct value of negative control, which is the samples immunoprecipitated with beads but without antibody; Ctinput: Ct value of input DNA without immunoprecipitation. Bottom panel shows read count of regions where ChIP-qPCR validations were performed. (C-D) ChIP-qPCR validations of regions with decreased (A) or increased (B) H3K27me3 in <italic>atring1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic> and <italic>atbmi1a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s015" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s015" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S14 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Replicates of ChIP-seq (A) and RNA-seq (B) samples show good correlation in terms of log<sub>2</sub> fold-change of read intensity.</title>
<p>Correlation between M values of ChIP-seq replicates. Left panel: scatter plots in lower left triangle showed the correlation of M values between replicates, and numbers in upper right triangle showed Pearson correlation coefficients, with larger numbers having bigger font sizes; right panel: heatmap showing the correlation coefficients across samples. (A) Boxplots showing high correlation between replicated ChIP-seq data in terms of the M value distribution of peak set I and peak set II shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g003">Fig 3A</xref>. (B) Boxplots showing high correlation between replicated RNA-seq data in terms of the expression change of gene group I and gene group II shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g004">Fig 4A</xref>.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s016" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s016" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S15 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Result in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g005">Fig 5C</xref> is reproducible using replicated data.</title>
<p>(A) Distribution of H3K27me3 changes (measured by M values) for 108 genes and 164 genes in PcG mutants. (B) Distribution of expression changes for 108 genes and 164 genes in PcG mutants.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s017" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s017" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S16 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>motifs enriched in regions with reduced H3K27me3 in each mutant.</title>
<p>Regions in each PcG mutant with reduced H3K27me3 were identified, followed by motif enrichment analysis. The heatmap shows the enrichment P values in each mutant for motifs shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1005771.g006">Fig 6A</xref>.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s018" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s018" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>FIE co-purifies with PcG proteins.</title>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s019" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s019" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Statistics of ChIP-seq and RNA-seq reads, and Col-0 H3K27me3 peaks, targets, and enriched biological functions and motifs.</title>
<p>(A) ChIP-seq and RNA-seq read statistics for each sample. (B) 5,055 H3K27me3 peaks identified in Col-0, as well as list of peak target, which is defined as the nearest gene whose gene body is located within 1 kb upstream or 1 kb downstream of the peak region. (C) Biological functions enriched in Col-0 H3K27me3 peak targets, including GO terms of biological process (BP), molecular function (MF), cellular compartment (CC), and Interpro domains. (D) Motifs enriched in 5,055 Col-0 H3K27me3 peaks with P&lt;1e-5, as well as the enrichment statistics of CArG box motifs.</p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s020" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s020" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S3 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Statistics of differentially H3K27me3-marked regions identified based on MAnorm.</title>
<p>(A) Genomic coordinates, motifs and target genes information for 3,289 H3K27me3 regions regulated by at least one PcG component with cutoff: |M|&gt;1 &amp; P&lt;1e-3. (B) 51% regions with reduced H3K27me3 in clf-29 show less reduction in summit regions. (C) 53% regions with reduced H3K27me3 in tfl2-2 show less reduction in summit regions.</p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s021" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s021" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S4 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>List of differentially expressed genes in PcG mutants, expression class, as well as the enriched functions for different classes of genes.</title>
<p>(A) 2,438 differentially expressed genes in PcG mutants with the following criteria: |FC|&gt;1 and P &lt;0.05 in at least one mutant. (B) Biological functions enriched in Col-0 H3K27me3 peak targets, including GO terms, Interpro domains, and SP_PIR keywords. (C) Biological functions enriched in Col-0 H3K27me3 peak targets, including GO terms, Interpro domains, and SP_PIR keywords.</p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s022" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s022" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S5 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Lists of target genes whose expression and H3K27me3 are controlled by different combinations of PcGs.</title>
<p>(A) 108 target genes whose expression and H3K27me3 are controlled by CLF and LHP1. (B) 164 target genes whose expression and H3K27me3 are controlled by RING1 and BMI1.</p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s023" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s023" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S6 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>List of PcG targets with inflorescence (A) or embryo (B) biased expression.</title>
<p>(A) 108 genes ranked by their extent of inflorescence biased expression. Column B is the enrichment score of GSEA, and Column C represents whether the given gene has strong inflorescence biased expression as returned by leading edge analysis implemented in GSEA. (NOTE: low expressed genes across RNA-seq samples (read density in given gene &lt;2) were removed before GSEA). (B) 164 genes ranked by their extent of embryo biased expression. Column B is the enrichment score of GSEA, and Column C represents whether the given gene has strong embryo biased expression as returned by leading edge analysis implemented in GSEA. (NOTE: low expressed genes across RNA-seq samples (read density in given gene &lt;2) were removed before GSEA).</p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s024" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s024" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S7 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>TFs whose bindings are enriched in peak set I.</title>
<p>The enrichment statistics and co-occupied genomic regions are listed.</p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005771.s025" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005771.s025" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S8 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Primers used in this study.</title>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Prof. H. Huang for discussions, support, and advice, and Dr. A. Sugathan and Dr. Z. Shao for helpful comments and revisions on this study. We also wish to acknowledge Y. Wang and M. Qi. for LHP1 ChIP-chip data processing and phylogenetic analysis of plant EZH2.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bemer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grossniklaus</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Dynamic regulation of Polycomb group activity during plant development</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>529</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pbi.2012.09.006" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.pbi.2012.09.006</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22999383</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mozgova</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hennig</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The Polycomb Group Protein Regulatory Network</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grossniklaus</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paro</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional silencing by polycomb-group proteins</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>a019331</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/cshperspect.a019331" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/cshperspect.a019331</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25367972</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Polycomb repression in the regulation of growth and development in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>23C</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodrich</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Puangsomlee</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyerowitz</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A Polycomb-group gene regulates homeotic gene expression in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>386</volume>: <fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9052779</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinoshita</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Polycomb repression of flowering during early plant development</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>14156</fpage>–<lpage>14161</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11698668</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bratzel</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hohmann</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turck</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>VAL- and AtBMI1-mediated H2Aub initiate the switch from embryonic to postgerminative growth in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1324</fpage>–<lpage>1329</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2013.05.050" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cub.2013.05.050</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23810531</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thong</surname> <given-names>ZH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname> <given-names>XM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname> <given-names>YB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The putative PRC1 RING-finger protein AtRING1A regulates flowering through repressing MADS AFFECTING FLOWERING genes in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>141</volume>: <fpage>1303</fpage>–<lpage>U1238</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1242/dev.104513" xlink:type="simple">10.1242/dev.104513</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24553292</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grossniklaus</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vielle-Calzada</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeppner</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gagliano</surname> <given-names>WB</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Maternal control of embryogenesis by MEDEA, a polycomb group gene in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>280</volume>: <fpage>446</fpage>–<lpage>450</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9545225</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaudin</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Libault</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pouteau</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Juul</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Mutations in LIKE HETEROCHROMATIN PROTEIN 1 affect flowering time and plant architecture in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>4847</fpage>–<lpage>4858</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11731464</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chanvivattana</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bishopp</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schubert</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Interaction of Polycomb-group proteins controlling flowering in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>5263</fpage>–<lpage>5276</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15456723</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bratzel</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Torrejon</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Del Pozo</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calonje</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Keeping cell identity in Arabidopsis requires PRC1 RING-finger homologs that catalyze H2A monoubiquitination</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1853</fpage>–<lpage>1859</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2010.09.046" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cub.2010.09.046</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20933424</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Polycomb silencing of KNOX genes confines shoot stem cell niches in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1966</fpage>–<lpage>1971</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2008.11.019" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cub.2008.11.019</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19097900</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turck</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roudier</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farrona</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin-Magniette</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guillaume</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis TFL2/LHP1 specifically associates with genes marked by trimethylation of histone H3 lysine 27</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e86</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17542647</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Germann</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blus</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khorasanizadeh</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaudin</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis LHP1 protein colocalizes with histone H3 Lys27 trimethylation</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>869</fpage>–<lpage>871</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17676062</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molitor</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis PRC1-like ring-finger proteins are necessary for repression of embryonic traits during vegetative growth</article-title>. <source>Cell Res</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1332</fpage>–<lpage>1344</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/cr.2010.151" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/cr.2010.151</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21060339</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Derkacheva</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steinbach</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wildhaber</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mozgova</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahrez</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis MSI1 connects LHP1 to PRC2 complexes</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>2073</fpage>–<lpage>2085</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/emboj.2013.145" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/emboj.2013.145</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23778966</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merini</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calonje</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>PRC1 is taking the lead in PcG repression</article-title>. <source>Plant J Accepted Article</source>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molitor</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bu</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis AL PHD-PRC1 complexes promote seed germination through H3K4me3-to-H3K27me3 chromatin state switch in repression of seed developmental genes</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e1004091</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004091" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004091</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24465219</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Photoperiodic control of the floral transition through a distinct polycomb repressive complex</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>727</fpage>–<lpage>736</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2014.01.029" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.devcel.2014.01.029</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24613395</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lodha</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marco</surname> <given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Timmermans</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The ASYMMETRIC LEAVES complex maintains repression of KNOX homeobox genes via direct recruitment of Polycomb-repressive complex2</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>596</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gad.211425.112" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/gad.211425.112</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23468429</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yumul</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>AGAMOUS terminates floral stem cell maintenance in Arabidopsis by directly repressing WUSCHEL through recruitment of Polycomb Group proteins</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>3654</fpage>–<lpage>3670</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.111.091538" xlink:type="simple">10.1105/tpc.111.091538</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22028461</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Regulation of floral patterning by flowering time genes</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>711</fpage>–<lpage>722</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2009.03.011" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.devcel.2009.03.011</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19460347</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heo</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Vernalization-mediated epigenetic silencing by a long intronic noncoding RNA</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>331</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1197349" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1197349</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21127216</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swiezewski</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magusin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dean</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Cold-induced silencing by long antisense transcripts of an Arabidopsis Polycomb target</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>462</volume>: <fpage>799</fpage>–<lpage>802</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature08618" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature08618</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20010688</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adrian</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farrona</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reimer</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Albani</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coupland</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>cis-Regulatory elements and chromatin state coordinately control temporal and spatial expression of FLOWERING LOCUS T in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1425</fpage>–<lpage>1440</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.110.074682" xlink:type="simple">10.1105/tpc.110.074682</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20472817</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubreucq</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roudier</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubos</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lepiniec</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of Arabidopsis LEAFY COTYLEDON2 involves RLE, a cis-element that regulates trimethylation of histone H3 at lysine-27</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>4065</fpage>–<lpage>4078</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.111.087866" xlink:type="simple">10.1105/tpc.111.087866</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22080598</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Looi</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Timing mechanism dependent on cell division is invoked by Polycomb eviction in plant stem cells</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>343</volume>: <fpage>1248559</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1248559" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1248559</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24482483</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crevillen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greeff</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trick</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Epigenetic reprogramming that prevents transgenerational inheritance of the vernalized state</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>515</volume>: <fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature13722" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature13722</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25219852</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roudier</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarazin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mary-Huard</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Integrative epigenomic mapping defines four main chromatin states in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1928</fpage>–<lpage>1938</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/emboj.2011.103" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/emboj.2011.103</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21487388</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouyer</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roudier</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heese</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gey</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Polycomb repressive complex 2 controls the embryo-to-seedling phase transition</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002014</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002014" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002014</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21423668</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eshed-Williams</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zilberman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname> <given-names>ZR</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>EMF1 and PRC2 cooperate to repress key regulators of Arabidopsis development</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002512</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002512" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002512</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22457632</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orkin</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waxman</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>MAnorm: a robust model for quantitative comparison of ChIP-Seq data sets</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>R16</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2012-13-3-r16" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/gb-2012-13-3-r16</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22424423</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Developmental control of polycomb subunit composition by GATA factors mediates a switch to non-canonical functions</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>304</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2014.12.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.molcel.2014.12.009</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25578878</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glass</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinello</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Combinatorial assembly of developmental stage-specific enhancers controls gene expression programs during human erythropoiesis</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>796</fpage>–<lpage>811</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2012.09.003" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.devcel.2012.09.003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23041383</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname> <given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beyaz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Apostolou</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinello</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Distinct and combinatorial functions of Jmjd2b/Kdm4b and Jmjd2c/Kdm4c in mouse embryonic stem cell identity</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2013.11.011" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.molcel.2013.11.011</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24361252</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aubert</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castle</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>EMF1, a novel protein involved in the control of shoot architecture and flowering in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1865</fpage>–<lpage>1875</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11487698</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sneeringer</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuntz</surname> <given-names>KW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knutson</surname> <given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollock</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Coordinated activities of wild-type plus mutant EZH2 drive tumor-associated hypertrimethylation of lysine 27 on histone H3 (H3K27) in human B-cell lymphomas</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>20980</fpage>–<lpage>20985</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1012525107" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1012525107</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21078963</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stepanik</surname> <given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harte</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A mutation in the E(Z) methyltransferase that increases trimethylation of histone H3 lysine 27 and causes inappropriate silencing of active Polycomb target genes</article-title>. <source>Developmental Biology</source> <volume>364</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22182520</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname> <given-names>WW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buzas</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ying</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis Polycomb Repressive Complex 2 binding sites contain putative GAGA factor binding motifs within coding regions of genes</article-title>. <source>Bmc Genomics</source> <volume>14</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jenuwein</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname> <given-names>XF</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis REF6 is a histone H3 lysine 27 demethylase</article-title>. <source>Nature Genetics</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>715</fpage>–<lpage>U144</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.854" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ng.854</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21642989</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schubert</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Primavesi</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bishopp</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doonan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Silencing by plant Polycomb-group genes requires dispersed trimethylation of histone H3 at lysine 27</article-title>. <source>Embo Journal</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>4638</fpage>–<lpage>4649</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16957776</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamayo</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mootha</surname> <given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ebert</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>15545</fpage>–<lpage>15550</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16199517</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCarty</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Regulation of the seed to seedling developmental phase transition by the LAFL and VAL transcription factor networks</article-title>. <source>Wiley Interdiscip Rev Dev Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/wdev.126" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/wdev.126</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24902838</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nambara</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayama</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuchiya</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishimura</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaide</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The role of ABI3 and FUS3 loci in Arabidopsis thaliana on phase transition from late embryo development to germination</article-title>. <source>Developmental Biology</source> <volume>220</volume>: <fpage>412</fpage>–<lpage>423</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10753527</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname> <given-names>MAL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yee</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Danao</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmerman</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Leafy Cotyledon1 Is an Essential Regulator of Late Embryogenesis and Cotyledon Identity in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1731</fpage>–<lpage>1745</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12244233</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumbusch</surname> <given-names>LO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galau</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jakobsen</surname> <given-names>KS</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>LEC1, FUS3, ABI3 and Em expression reveals no correlation with dormancy in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14676287</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizukami</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Isolation and characterization of the binding sequences for the product of the Arabidopsis floral homeotic gene AGAMOUS</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>4769</fpage>–<lpage>4776</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7901838</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riechmann</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyerowitz</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>DNA-binding properties of Arabidopsis MADS domain homeotic proteins APETALA1, APETALA3, PISTILLATA and AGAMOUS</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>3134</fpage>–<lpage>3141</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8774892</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bian</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Systematic analysis of plant-specific B3 domain-containing proteins based on the genome resources of 11 sequenced species</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Rep</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>6267</fpage>–<lpage>6282</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11033-012-1448-8" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s11033-012-1448-8</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22302388</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pajoro</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madrigal</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muino</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matus</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Dynamics of chromatin accessibility and gene regulation by MADS-domain transcription factors in flower development</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>R41</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2014-15-3-r41" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/gb-2014-15-3-r41</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24581456</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DS</surname> <given-names>OM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wuest</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rae</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raganelli</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname> <given-names>PT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Control of reproductive floral organ identity specification in Arabidopsis by the C function regulator AGAMOUS</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2482</fpage>–<lpage>2503</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.113.113209" xlink:type="simple">10.1105/tpc.113.113209</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23821642</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wuest</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Maoileidigh</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rae</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kwasniewska</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raganelli</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Molecular basis for the specification of floral organs by APETALA3 and PISTILLATA</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>13452</fpage>–<lpage>13457</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1207075109" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1207075109</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22847437</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smaczniak</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Immink</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muino</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanvillain</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Busscher</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Characterization of MADS-domain transcription factor complexes in Arabidopsis flower development</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>1560</fpage>–<lpage>1565</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1112871109" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1112871109</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22238427</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marin</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Streptophyte algae and the origin of embryophytes</article-title>. <source>Ann Bot</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>999</fpage>–<lpage>1004</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/aob/mcp044" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/aob/mcp044</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19273476</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Theissen</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melzer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular mechanisms underlying origin and diversification of the angiosperm flower</article-title>. <source>Ann Bot</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>603</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17670752</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Exner</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aichinger</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wildhaber</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alfarano</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Chromodomain of LIKE HETEROCHROMATIN PROTEIN 1 Is Essential for H3K27me3 Binding and Function during Arabidopsis Development</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source> <volume>4</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms guiding Polycomb activities during gene silencing in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Front Plant Sci</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>454</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2013.00454" xlink:type="simple">10.3389/fpls.2013.00454</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24312106</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregis</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andres</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sessa</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guerra</surname> <given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simonini</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Identification of pathways directly regulated by SHORT VEGETATIVE PHASE during vegetative and reproductive development in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>R56</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-6-r56" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/gb-2013-14-6-r56</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23759218</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gramzow</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Theissen</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A hitchhiker's guide to the MADS world of plants</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>214</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2010-11-6-214" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/gb-2010-11-6-214</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20587009</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Regad</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lebas</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lescure</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Interstitial Telomeric Repeats within the Arabidopsis-Thaliana Genome</article-title>. <source>Journal of Molecular Biology</source> <volume>239</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8196051</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tremousaygue</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garnier</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bardet</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dabos</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herve</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Internal telomeric repeats and 'TCP domain' protein-binding sites co-operate to regulate gene expression in Arabidopsis thaliana cycling cells</article-title>. <source>Plant Journal</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>957</fpage>–<lpage>966</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12631321</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartwig</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Velikkakam</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneeberger</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turck</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Complementary activities of TELOMERE REPEAT BINDING proteins and Polycomb Group complexes in transcriptional regulation of target genes</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cokus</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schubert</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname> <given-names>JX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pellegrini</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide Hi-C Analyses in Wild-Type and Mutants Reveal High-Resolution Chromatin Interactions in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Molecular Cell</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>694</fpage>–<lpage>707</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2014.07.008" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.molcel.2014.07.008</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25132175</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bannister</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zegerman</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miska</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>JO</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Selective recognition of methylated lysine 9 on histone H3 by the HP1 chromo domain</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>410</volume>: <fpage>120</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11242054</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lachner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Carroll</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rea</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mechtler</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jenuwein</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Methylation of histone H3 lysine 9 creates a binding site for HP1 proteins</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>410</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11242053</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erdjument-Bromage</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Role of histone H3 lysine 27 methylation in Polycomb-group silencing</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>298</volume>: <fpage>1039</fpage>–<lpage>1043</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12351676</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Structural basis for specific binding of Polycomb chromodomain to histone H3 methylated at Lys 27</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1823</fpage>–<lpage>1828</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12897052</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kingston</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woodcock</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Chromatin compaction by a polycomb group protein complex</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>306</volume>: <fpage>1574</fpage>–<lpage>1577</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15567868</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mortz</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krogh</surname> <given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vorum</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gorg</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Improved silver staining protocols for high sensitivity protein identification using matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization-time of flight analysis</article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1359</fpage>–<lpage>1363</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11922595</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouveret</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schonrock</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gruissem</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hennig</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Regulation of flowering time by Arabidopsis MSI1</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>1693</fpage>–<lpage>1702</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16554362</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>XF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Reprogramming of H3K27me3 Is Critical for Acquisition of Pluripotency from Cultured Arabidopsis Tissues</article-title>. <source>Plos Genetics</source> <volume>8</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landberg</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meeks-Wagner</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The TERMINAL FLOWER2 (TFL2) gene controls the reproductive transition and meristem identity in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>149</volume>: <fpage>597</fpage>–<lpage>605</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9611176</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durbin</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1754</fpage>–<lpage>1760</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp324" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp324</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pertea</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trapnell</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pimentel</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelley</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>TopHat2: accurate alignment of transcriptomes in the presence of insertions, deletions and gene fusions</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>R36</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23618408</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eeckhoute</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Model-based analysis of ChIP-Seq (MACS)</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>R137</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2008-9-9-r137" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/gb-2008-9-9-r137</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18798982</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>TileMap: create chromosomal map of tiling array hybridizations</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>3629</fpage>–<lpage>3636</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16046496</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorvaldsdottir</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mesirov</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Integrative Genomics Viewer (IGV): high-performance genomics data visualization and exploration</article-title>. <source>Brief Bioinform</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bib/bbs017" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bib/bbs017</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22517427</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anders</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>R106</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979621</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirsch-Hoffmann</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hennig</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gruissem</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>GENEVESTIGATOR. Arabidopsis microarray database and analysis toolbox</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>2621</fpage>–<lpage>2632</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15375207</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathelier</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parcy</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Worsley-Hunt</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>JASPAR 2014: an extensively expanded and updated open-access database of transcription factor binding profiles</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>D142</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkt997" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/nar/gkt997</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24194598</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005771.ref082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>GC</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Prediction of Polycomb target genes in mouse embryonic stem cells</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ygeno.2010.03.012" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ygeno.2010.03.012</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20353814</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>