<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PGENETICS-D-14-00515</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA processing</subject><subject>RNA stability</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell processes</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell death</subject><subject>Cell growth</subject><subject>Cellular stress responses</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular cell biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Epigenetics</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA interference</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cancer genetics</subject><subject>Gene expression</subject><subject>Gene function</subject><subject>Genetics of disease</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Toxicology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic toxicology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancers and neoplasms</subject><subj-group><subject>Gynecological tumors</subject><subj-group><subject>Cervical cancer</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cancer treatment</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Pharmacology</subject><subj-group><subject>Behavioral pharmacology</subject><subj-group><subject>Drug dependence</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Drug research and development</subject><subj-group><subject>Drug discovery</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>tRNA Modifying Enzymes, NSUN2 and METTL1, Determine Sensitivity to 5-Fluorouracil in HeLa Cells</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">tRNA Modifying Enzymes and 5-FU Sensitivity</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>Mayumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>Mamoru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>Masato</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>Kaoru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yazama</surname><given-names>Futoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>Hiroaki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Yegui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Guangying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimamoto</surname><given-names>Fumio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ota</surname><given-names>Takahide</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Temme</surname><given-names>Achim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatsuka</surname><given-names>Masaaki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Life Sciences, Faculty of Life and Environmental Sciences, Prefectural University of Hiroshima, Shoubara, Hiroshima, Japan</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Management Information Systems, Faculty of Management and Information System, Prefectural University of Hiroshima, Minami-ku, Hiroshima, Japan</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Health Sciences, Faculty of Human Culture and Science, Prefectural University of Hiroshima, Minami-ku, Hiroshima, Japan</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Life Science, Medical Research Institute, Kanazawa Medical University, Uchinada, Ishikawa, Japan</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Department of Neurosurgery, University Hospital Carl Gustav Carus, Technical University Dresden, Dresden, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horwitz</surname><given-names>Marshall S.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Washington, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">tatsuka@pu-hiroshima.ac.jp</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MT. Performed the experiments: MO MF MH KO FY HK GQ TO MT. Analyzed the data: YX FS TO AT MT. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: FY HK FS TO AT MT. Wrote the paper: AT MT.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<elocation-id>e1004639</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Okamoto et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Nonessential tRNA modifications by methyltransferases are evolutionarily conserved and have been reported to stabilize mature tRNA molecules and prevent rapid tRNA decay (RTD). The tRNA modifying enzymes, NSUN2 and METTL1, are mammalian orthologs of yeast Trm4 and Trm8, which are required for protecting tRNA against RTD. A simultaneous overexpression of NSUN2 and METTL1 is widely observed among human cancers suggesting that targeting of both proteins provides a novel powerful strategy for cancer chemotherapy. Here, we show that combined knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 in HeLa cells drastically potentiate sensitivity of cells to 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) whereas heat stress of cells revealed no effects. Since NSUN2 and METTL1 are phosphorylated by Aurora-B and Akt, respectively, and their tRNA modifying activities are suppressed by phosphorylation, overexpression of constitutively dephosphorylated forms of both methyltransferases is able to suppress 5-FU sensitivity. Thus, NSUN2 and METTL1 are implicated in 5-FU sensitivity in HeLa cells. Interfering with methylation of tRNAs might provide a promising rationale to improve 5-FU chemotherapy of cancer.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>The cellular mechanisms for sensing and responding to stress on nucleic acid metabolism or to genotoxic stress are the fundamental and ancient evolutionary biological activities with conserved and diverse biological functions. In yeast, hypomodified mature tRNA species are rapidly decayed under heat stress by the RTD pathway. Yet, it has been shown that tRNA-specific methyltransferases Trm4 and Trm8 protect from tRNA decay. 5-FU, a pyrimidine analog used for cancer treatment, is generally known to act as a thymidylate synthase inhibitor although other ways for the mechanisms of action are suggested. We studied NSUN2 and METTL1, the human orthologs of Trm4 and Trm8 in yeast, and demonstrated that these RTD-related tRNA modifying enzymes are involved in 5-FU sensitivity in cervical cancer HeLa cells. We conclude that the evolutionarily conserved regulation of tRNA modifications is a potential mechanism of chemotherapy resistance in cancer cells.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by grants from Prefectural University of Hiroshima (Important Research Project, Interdisciplinary/Priority Research H-25 for MT, FY, HK, YX, and FS), and Prefectural University of Hiroshima Graduate School of Comprehensive Scientific Research to MO (Research Associate Grant H-25). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>5-Fluorouracil (5-FU) is a pyrimidine analog and is the most widely used chemotherapeutic agent for the treatment of a variety of solid cancers. Its mechanism of action has been attributed to the production of cytotoxic metabolites incorporated into RNA and DNA and inhibiting thymidylate synthase, finally leading to cell cycle arrest and apoptosis in cancer cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Longley1">[1]</xref>. 5-FU is used against cancer for about 40 years and it is known that systemic administration of 5-FU might result in drug resistance of tumor cells. Furthermore, treatment regimens with increased dosage of 5-FU have been reported to cause severe side effects such as myelosuppression, mucositis, dermatitis and diarrhea., In order to address this dilemma, different strategies were pursued to improve outcomes for patients and to reduce side effects of 5-FU therapy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Benz1">[2]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Wolmark1">[9]</xref>. However, also with current approaches, there is still a need to develop new compounds or novel strategies by which cancer cells are killed more effectively and more selectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Hung1">[10]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-delaCruzMorcillo1">[12]</xref>.</p>
<p>Overexpression of tRNA-modifying enzymes NSUN2 and METTL1 is widely observed among human cancers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Cartlidge1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Wikman1">[16]</xref>. NSUN2 (NOP2/Sun domain family, member 2), also known as SAKI (Substrate of AIM-1/Aurora kinase B), is a NOL1/NOP2/SUN domain-containing tRNA (cytosine-5-)-methyltransferase. It is phosphorylated at Ser139 by Aurora-B to inhibit its enzymatic activity during mitosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>. Trm4, a yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> homologue of human NSUN2, participates in the nonessential modification of tRNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Motorin1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Wu1">[19]</xref>, and a yeast mutant deficient in Trm4 shows no defect in cell growth and has normal sensitivities to various stresses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Motorin1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Wu1">[19]</xref>.</p>
<p>On the other hand, another tRNA modification enzyme Trm8, which is also nonessential and catalyzes tRNA 7-methylguanosine modification <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Alexandrov1">[20]</xref>, acts together with Trm4 to stabilize tRNA under heat stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Alexandrov2">[21]</xref>. If tRNA modifications caused by Trm4 and Trm8 are defective, a rapid degradation of tRNA is induced under heat stress, resulting in the expression of heat-sensitive phenotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Alexandrov2">[21]</xref>. The tRNA surveillance system that monitors compromised tRNAs with no modification by Trm4 and Trm8 uses a rapid tRNA degradation (RTD) pathway to decay non-modified tRNAs, leading to cell death <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Alexandrov2">[21]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Whipple1">[23]</xref>.</p>
<p>A human tRNA (guanine-N7-)-methyltransferase, a homologue of yeast Trm8, is known as METTL1 (methyltransferase like 1) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Alexandrov1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Bahr1">[24]</xref>. Whereas NSUN2 has been initially identified as a substrate of protein kinase (Aurora-B) in HeLa cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>, METTL1 has been initially identified as a substrate of Akt/protein kinase Bα (PKBα) in HeLa cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Cartlidge1">[13]</xref>. Interestingly, phosphorylated METTL1 at Ser27 by Akt is also enzymatically inactive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Cartlidge1">[13]</xref>. The fact that both tRNA methyltransferases are evolutionally conserved suggests a similar tRNA surveillance system including Trm4 and Trm8 in human cells. Furthermore, the observation that the cytotoxic effect of 5-FU in yeast is enhanced by heat stress in a <italic>trm8</italic> mutant strain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Gustavsson1">[25]</xref> leads us to the hypothesis that nonessential tRNA modifications catalyzed by NSUN2 and METTL1 impacts the efficiency of 5-FU treatment in human cancer cells.</p>
<p>Here, we provide evidence that tRNA methyltransferases, NSUN2 and METTL1, strongly influences 5-FU sensitivity in human cancer cells. Therefore, targeting these methyltransferases might represent a promising rationale to improve 5-FU-treatment of tumors and to reduce 5-FU-related side effects in patients.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>NSUN2 did not affect cell growth</title>
<p>NSUN2 (SAKI) has been reported to be overexpressed and with gain in gene copy-number in various of human cancers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Okamoto1">[15]</xref>. Furthermore, NSUN2 has been implicated in myc-induced proliferation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Frye2">[26]</xref>. In line with these observations, the siRNA-mediated knockdown of NSUN2 negatively affects cancer cell growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Frye1">[14]</xref> and homozygous knockout of the <italic>NSUN2</italic> gene locus causes delayed cell growth in bulge stem cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Blanco1">[27]</xref>. However, in our previous studies, NSUN2 expression was not altered during the cell cycle of HeLa cervix carcinoma cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>. When we investigated normal human diploid fibroblasts, NSUN2 expression was found to be very low compared with HeLa cells and again NSUN2 was not differentially expresses during the cell cycle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>.</p>
<p>In initial studies we sought to analyze the impact of increased or decreased NSUN2 expression on the growth properties of HeLa cells. We therefore utilized cell lines clonally derived from stable transfectants described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>. These studies indicated that there was a difference in the growth properties that arise as a result of heterogeneity among clones although we found that NSUN2 did not alter the growth properties of HeLa cells both onto plastic dish culture and in semisolid agar culture (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004639.s001">Figure S1</xref>). Subsequently, we pooled cells from five independent clones for further experiments and examined expression levels of NSUN2 and METTL1. We then generated Xpress-NSUN2-overexpressing HeLa cells as well as NSUN2 knockdown cells, the latter by using an shRNA targeting the 5′-UTR of NSUN2 mRNA. Successively we tested cell growth both onto plastic dish culture and in semisolid agar culture. The data clearly indicated that NSUN2 is related to neither cell multiplication nor cancerous cell growth (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004639.s002">Figure S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004639.s003">S3</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Co-overexpression of NSUN2 and METTL1 confers a protective effect of 5-FU-induced cytotoxicity</title>
<p>To further elucidate NSUN2 function in mammalian cells, we focused on mechanisms involved in tRNA methylation. NSUN2 is a mammalian homolog of yeast Trm4. In yeast system, Trm4-mediated tRNA modification is nonessential, but the additional knockout of Trm8, which is tRNA (guanine-N7-)-methyltransferase, under Trm4 knockout background leads to an unstable tRNA situation, resulting in a temperature-sensitive growth. Based on cooperative functions of Trm4 and Trm8 in yeast, we sought to analyze the effects of overexpressed NSUN2 and METTL1 in HeLa cells suffering heat stress. For this we used HeLa cell lines engineered to express NSUN2, METTL1 and both methyltransferases. The ectopic expression of the methyltransferases was confirmed by Western blot analysis as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g001">Figure 1A</xref>. Contrary to our expectations, overexpression of NSUN2 and METTL1 did not affect heat stress-induced cytotoxicity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g001">Figure 1A, 1B and 1C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pgen-1004639-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Effects of increased expression of NSUN2 and METTL1 on 5-FU-treatment and heat stress and 5-FU.</title>
<p>(A) Immunoblot analysis of proteins from Xpress-NSUN2-overexpressing cells (lane <italic>Xpress-NSUN2</italic>), Xpress-METTL1-overexpressing cells (lane <italic>Xpress-METTL1</italic>), Xpress-NSUN2 and Xpress-METTL1-co-overexpressing cells (lane <italic>Xpress-NSUN2 + Xpress-METTL1</italic>), and control vector-transfected cells (lane <italic>empty</italic>) with anti-Xpress, anti-NSUN2, anti-METTL1 and anti-α-tubulin antibodies. (B) Time-dependent cell survival in response to heat stress in Xpress-NSUN2-overexpressing cells (<italic>open circle</italic>), Xpress-METTL1-overexpressing cells (<italic>open triangle</italic>), Xpress-NSUN2 and Xpress-METTL1-co-overexpressing cells (<italic>open square</italic>), and control vector-transfected cells (<italic>closed circle</italic>) with the MTT viability assay. There was no significant difference in survival of Xpress-NSUN2- or Xpress-METTL-1-overexpressing cells compared with control vector-transfected cells in all of each duration period. (C) Comparison of the average IC<sub>50</sub> values for heat stress between Xpress-NSUN2- or Xpress-METTL-1-overexpressing cells and control vector-transfected cells. NS, not significant. (D) Dose-dependent cell survival in response to 5-FU in Xpress-NSUN2-overexpressing cells (<italic>open circle</italic>), Xpress-METTL1-overexpressing cells (<italic>open triangle</italic>), Xpress-NSUN2 and Xpress-METTL1-co-overexpressing cells (<italic>open square</italic>), and control vector-transfected cells (<italic>closed circle</italic>) with the MTT viability assay. *Significant difference compared with control vector-transfected cells (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05). (E) Comparison of the average IC<sub>50</sub> values for 5-FU between Xpress-NSUN2- and/or Xpress-METTL-1-overexpressing cells and control vector-transfected cells. Data throughout this study represent the mean ± SD for three independent experiments, and error bars represent the SD. Difference between values were analyzed using a two-tailed Welch's <italic>t</italic>-test. <italic>P</italic>-values of &lt;0.05 were considered significant. NS, not significant. *Significant difference compared with control vector-transfected cells (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Next, we sought to investigate whether overexpression of NSUN2 and METTL1 protects from 5-FU-induced cytotoxicity, since tRNA modifying enzymes have been implicated as <italic>in vivo</italic> targets for 5-FU in yeast <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Gustavsson1">[25]</xref>. Although we could not observe a protective effect after 5-FU-treatment in HeLa cells expressing NSUN2 or METTL1 alone, we revealed that combined overexpression of NSUN2 and METTL1 significantly protected HeLa cells from 5-FU-induced cell death (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g001">Figure 1D and 1E</xref>). Noteworthy, co-overexpression of NSUN2 and METTL1 did not affect cell proliferation growth in soft agar (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004639.s004">Figure S4</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 potentiated the cytotoxic effect of 5-FU</title>
<p>To examine the effects of double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 on heat stress-induced cytotoxicity and 5-FU-induced cytotoxicity, we established stable HeLa cells with knockdown of NSUN2, METTL1, or NSUN2 and METTL1. As depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g002">Figure 2A</xref> we fully knocked down NSUN2, METTL1 protein expression and were also able to achieve an effective NSUN2/METTL1 double knockdown.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1004639-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Effects of decreased NSUN2 and METTL1 expression on 5-FU-treatment and heat stress and 5-FU.</title>
<p>(A) Immunoblot analysis of total proteins lysates and immunoprecipitated NSUN2 and METTL1 proteins from indicated NSUN2-, METTL1-, and double NSUN2/METTL1 knockdowns and control transfectant. As loading control the western blot was probed with an anti-α-tubulin antibody. (B) Time-dependent cell survival in response to heat stress in NSUN2 knockdown cells (<italic>open circle</italic>), METTL1 knockdown cells (<italic>open triangle</italic>), NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells (<italic>open square</italic>), and control vector-transfected cells (<italic>closed circle</italic>) with the MTT viability assay. There was no significant difference in survival of NSUN2 knockdown cells, METTL-1 knockdown cells, or NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells compared with control vector-transfected cells in all of each duration period. (C) Comparison of the average IC<sub>50</sub> values for heat stress between NSUN2 knockdown cells, METTL-1 knockdown cells, or NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells and control vector-transfected cells. NS, not significant. (D) Dose-dependent cell survival in response to 5-FU in NSUN2 knockdown cells (<italic>open circle</italic>), METTL1 knockdown cells (<italic>open triangle</italic>), NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells (<italic>open square</italic>), and control vector-transfected cells (<italic>closed circle</italic>) with the MTT viability assay. *Significant difference compared with control vector-transfected cells (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05). (E) Comparison of the average IC<sub>50</sub> values for 5-FU between NSUN2 knockdown cells, METTL-1 knockdown cells, or NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells and control vector-transfected cells. NS, not significant. *Significant difference compared with control vector-transfected cells (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Interestingly, the knockdown of NSUN2 did not affect cell multiplication and cancerous cell growth (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004639.s005">Figure S5</xref>). Also, we noted that knockdown of METTL1 and double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 did not affect cell multiplication and cancerous cell growth (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004639.s005">Figure S5</xref>).</p>
<p>Since it was of special interest whether the knockdown of NSUN2, METTL1 and double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 results in a temperature-sensitive growth phenotype as reported in yeast we incubated the cells at 43°C for a time period of 1 h to 6 h. Contrary to our expectations, the double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 did not enhance heat stress-induced cytotoxicity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g002">Figure 2B and 2C</xref>).</p>
<p>Subsequently we examined whether the double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 affects 5-FU-induced cytotoxicity. Consistent with our observation of NSUN2 and METTL1 overexpression experiments, which shows protective effects of tRNA methyltransferases, we revealed that double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 significantly sensitized HeLa cells to 5-FU treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g002">Figure 2D and 2E</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 did not affect cisplatin- and paclitaxel-induced cytotoxicity</title>
<p>To examine the effects of double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 on further chemotherapeutic agents other than 5-FU, we used cisplatin, a platinum-containing anti-cancer drug that binds to and causes crosslinking of DNA, and paclitaxel, a microtubule-stabilizing mitotic inhibitor. Contradictory to 5-FU treatment, both agents caused no detectable differences in induced cytotoxicity between control cells and double knockout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pgen-1004639-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Effect of cisplatin and paclitaxel treatment in NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown and double knockdown cells.</title>
<p>(A) Dose-dependent cell survival in response to cisplatin in NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells (<italic>open circle</italic>) and control vector-transfected cells (<italic>closed circle</italic>) with the MTT viability assay. There was no significant difference in survival of NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells compared with control vector-transfected cells in all of each concentration. (B) Comparison of the average IC<sub>50</sub> values for cisplatin between NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells and control vector-transfected cells. NS, not significant. (C) Dose-dependent cell survival in response to paclitaxel in NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells (<italic>open circle</italic>) and control vector-transfected cells (<italic>closed circle</italic>) with the MTT viability assay. There was no significant difference in survival of NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells compared with control vector-transfected cells in all of each concentration. (D) Comparison of the average IC<sub>50</sub> values for paclitaxel between NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells and control vector-transfected cells. NS, not significant.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 caused increased sensitivity to 5-FU-induced cell death measured by colony formation assay</title>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g002">Figure 2</xref>, we found that double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 potentiated the cytotoxic effect of 5-FU, measured by MTT assay. To confirm our results, colony formation assay, a method capable to essentially test every cell in the population for its ability to cell multiplication escaping cell reproductive death, was used to determine the effectiveness of 5-FU. The data revealed that double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 caused increased sensitivity to 5-FU-treatment resulting in a dose-dependent and significant decreased clonal survival when compared to scrambled shRNA control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g004">Figure 4</xref>). NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells treated with 5–20 µM 5-FU showed a 60 - 68% decreased values of the average IC<sub>50</sub> (4.54±0.12 µM) compared with those of the parent cells (12.85±0.25 µM) and control vector-transfected cells (12.79±1.05 µM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g004">Figure 4C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pgen-1004639-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Colony formation assay showing synergistic effects of NSUN2 and METTL1 double knock down and 5-FU-treatment.</title>
<p>(A) Depiction of colonies formed after 5-FU treatment at various concentrations on Giemsa-stained dishes. (B) Dose-dependent cell survival in response to 5-FU in NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells (<italic>open triangle</italic>), the parent cells (<italic>closed circle</italic>), and control vector-transfected cells (<italic>open circle</italic>) in colony formation assay. (C) Comparison of the average IC<sub>50</sub> values for 5-FU assessed by colony formation assay between NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells and control vector-transfected cells. *Significant difference compared with control vector-transfected cells (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 caused rapid tRNA(Val<sup>AAC</sup>) degradation induced by 5-FU</title>
<p>In the yeast system, a double knockout of Trm4 and Trm8, the orthologs of human NSUN2 and METTL1, shows an increased sensitivity to heat stress, resulting in a rapid tRNA(Val<sup>AAC</sup>) degradation. A similar situation may therefore occur when exposing HeLa cells depleted of NSUN2 and METTL1 to 5-FU. To address this question we performed tRNA stability assays using HeLa cells with double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 and as control HeLa cells transfected wit scramble shRNA. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g005">Figure 5</xref>, tRNA(Val<sup>AAC</sup>) was unstable in HeLa cells with double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 when exposed to 5-FU whereas in control cells the amount of tRNA(Val<sup>AAC</sup>) remained stable. Interestingly, we monitored a rapid degradation of initiator tRNA<sup>Met</sup> (tRNA(iMet)) in both control cells and knockdown cells when exposed to heat stress and even when exposed to 5-FU whereas the amounts of elongator tRNA<sup>Met</sup> (tRNA(eMet)) molecules were not affected.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1004639-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Degradation of tRNAs in HeLa cells treated with heat stress or 5-FU.</title>
<p>(A) Northern blot analysis of tRNA(Val<sup>AAC</sup>), tRNA(iMet), tRNA(eMet), and 5S rRNA. NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells and control vector-transfected cells were treated with 37°C (control), 43°C (heat stress), or 5-FU (7.69 mM) for indicated time. Total RNA (20 µg) was loaded and blotted. (B) Degradation profile of tRNA(Val<sup>AAC</sup>), tRNA(iMet), and tRNA(eMet) in NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells (closed symbols) and control vector-transfected cells (open symbols). The cells were treated with 37°C (<italic>circle</italic>), 43°C (<italic>triangle</italic>), and 5-FU (<italic>square</italic>). 5S rRNA transcribed by RNA polymerase III was used as a control, and quantitative data were indicated.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2g">
<title>Co-expression of a dephosphorylation-mimic NSUN2 and a dephosphorylation-mimic METTL1 conferred significant protection against 5-FU-induced cytotoxicity but phosphorylation-mimic forms did not</title>
<p>NSUN2 is phosphorylated at Ser139 by Aurora-B, and the phosphorylation of this site is critical for repression of its methyltransferase activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>. The same regulation of enzymatic activity has been reported for METTL1, which is phosphorylated at Ser27 by Akt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Cartlidge1">[13]</xref>. If decreased sensitivities to 5-FU by double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 are due to decreased methyltransferase activities resulting from decreased expression levels of both proteins, co-expression of enzymatic active forms of both methyltransferases in NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells may confer resistance to 5-FU. To test this hypothesis, we established stable clones originating from UTR-targeting shRNA-mediated NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells with co-expression of both NSUN2 and METTL1 using expression plasmids containing only the wild type coding region of NSUN2 and METTL1 or genetically engineered to encode phosphorylation- or dephosphorylation-mimetic proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). Then 5-FU sensitivities were examined in these stable clones. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g006">Figure 6B and 6C</xref>, co-expression of wild type proteins NSUN2 and METTL1 conferred protection against 5-FU-induced cytotoxicity on NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells. Compared to wild type, dephosphorylation-mimic forms were more effective (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g006">Figure 6C</xref>). On the other hand, phosphorylation-mimic forms had no effect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g006">Figure 6B and 6C</xref>). Thus, the combined activity of NSUN2 and METTL1 seems to be critical for 5-FU sensitivity of cancer cells, suggesting the presence of a conserved RTD-like pathway regulated by NSUN2 and METTL1 for participating in a surveillance system for tRNA quality control in human.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1004639-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Effects of co-expression of NSUN2 and METTL1 on the cytotoxic effects of heat stress and 5-FU in NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells.</title>
<p>(A) Immunoblot analysis of proteins from NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells co-expressing Xpress-tagged wild type NSUN2 and Xpress-tagged wild type METTL1 (lane <italic>WT/WT</italic>), NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells co-expressing Xpress-tagged phosphorylation-mimic NSUN2 and Xpress-tagged phosphorylation-mimic METTL1 (lane <italic>SE/SE</italic>), NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells co-expressing Xpress-tagged dephosphorylation-mimic NSUN2 and Xpress-tagged dephosphorylation-mimic METTL1 (lane <italic>SA/SA</italic>), and NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells transfected with control vector (lane <italic>empty</italic>) with anti-Xpress and anti-α-tubulin antibodies. Five independent clones that co-expressed Xpress-NSUN2 and Xpress-METTL1 or were transfected with the empty vector, originating from UTR-targeting shRNA-mediated NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells, were pooled and used as a stable transfectant. (B) Dose-dependent cell survival in response to 5-FU in NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells co-expressing Xpress-tagged wild type NSUN2 and Xpress-tagged wild type METTL1 (<italic>open circle, DKD + WT/WT</italic>), NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells co-expressing Xpress-tagged phosphorylation-mimic NSUN2 and Xpress-tagged phosphorylation-mimic METTL1 (<italic>open triangle, DKD + SE/SE</italic>), NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells co-expressing Xpress-tagged dephosphorylation-mimic NSUN2 and Xpress-tagged dephosphorylation-mimic METTL1 (<italic>open square, DKD + SA/SA</italic>), and NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells transfected with control vector (<italic>closed circle, DKD + empty</italic>) with the MTT viability assay. (C) Comparison of the average IC<sub>50</sub> values for 5-FU between NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells co-expressing NSUN2 and METTL1 and control vector-transfected cells. NS, not significant. *Significant difference compared with control vector-transfected cells (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>NUSN2 is not a critical regulator of cancer cell growth</title>
<p>The upregulated expression of NSUN2 in cancer cells is notable because the overexpression is accompanied by gene copy number gain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Frye1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Okamoto1">[15]</xref>. NSUN2 has an enzyme activity that can methylate tRNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>. Over the past several decades, many reports have shown elevations of tRNA methyltranferase activity and tRNA level in cancer cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Kuchino1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-PavonEternod1">[29]</xref>. These observations indicate tRNAs as potential biomarkers for tumor progression and malignancy. Yet, there have been no mechanistic explanation linking increased expression of modifier enzymes of tRNAs to growth advantage of cancer cells. In this study we revealed that NSUN2 is not a critical regulator of cancer cell growth. We conclusively show that forced overexpression and knockdown of NSUN2 do not impact proliferation and cancerous growth properties in soft agar. Indeed, forced overexpression of NSUN2 did not have any oncogenic activity per se and did not potentiate <italic>ras</italic>-induced <italic>in vitro</italic> neoplastic transformation in BALB/c 3T3 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004639.s006">Figure S6</xref>).</p>
<p>Although NSUN2 overexpression does not act as oncogene, the likelihood that NSUN2 overexpression might confer a growth advantage or a cancer stem cell property in cancer cells remains. Through the generation and phenotypic analysis of knockout mice, murine NSUN2 as a target of proto-oncogene Myc <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Frye2">[26]</xref> is required to stem cell growth and normal stem cell differentiation in skin and is also required to testis differentiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Blanco1">[27]</xref>. NSUN2 catalyzes the formation of cytosine-5-methylation in nucleic acids including tRNA, rRNA, coding and non-coding RNA, and possibly genome DNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Auxilien1">[30]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Zhang1">[34]</xref>. The altered expression levels of NUSUN2 might affect cell properties of certain tissues in an epigenetic fashion. Notably, mutations in <italic>NSUN2</italic> gene resulting in the gene expression defect are found in patients with intelligence deficiencies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Martinez1">[35]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-AbbasiMoheb1">[37]</xref>.</p>
<p>Previous studies suggest an alternative mechanism by which NSUN2 overexpression contributes to cancer development. NSUN2 is phosphorylated by Aurora-B, resulting in the repression of enzymatic activity, and distributed to the cytoplasm for participating in spindle stability during mitotic cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Hussain2">[38]</xref>. Although the elucidation of the roles of NSUN2 overexpression in cancer cells is still challenging, mitotic spindle-related NSUN2 functions involved in chromosome segregation processes might induce chromosome instability leading to cancer progression.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Cooperation between NSUN2 and METTL1 is responsible for determining 5-FU sensitivity in cancer cells</title>
<p>In yeast <italic>trm4</italic>/<italic>trm8</italic> double mutant, certain hypo-modified tRNAs, particularly tRNA(Val<sup>AAC</sup>), are destabilized by RTD pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Alexandrov2">[21]</xref>. Due to this tRNA quality check, the double mutant is temperature-sensitive. The RTD pathway in yeast can also be triggered without coincident temperature sensitivity or without loss of modifications in different tRNA variants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Whipple1">[23]</xref>. In our present study, double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 in HeLa cells did not affect heat stress-induced cytotoxicity. Thus, it is likely that RTD is not evolutionarily conserved with respect to heat stress-induced rapid tRNA decay involving Trm4 and Trm8.</p>
<p>Wild type yeast cells are temperature-sensitive in the presence of higher 5-FU concentrations. Moreover, synthetic interaction between <italic>trm8</italic> and <italic>pus1</italic> (pseudouridylation defective) mutations is observed under heat stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Gustavsson1">[25]</xref>. Reduced pseudouridylation is the most likely cause of 5-FU-induced tRNA damage(s) that mediate tRNA destabilization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Gustavsson1">[25]</xref>. Similarly, HeLa cells is 5-FU-sensitive under heat stress. However, the 5-FU-sensitive phenotype of yeast <italic>trm8</italic> mutant under heat stress is not evolutionarily conserved because heat stress potentiates the sensitivity of those cells to the cytotoxicity of 5-FU in the same way as control cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004639.s007">Figure S7</xref>).</p>
<p>At normal temperature in the presence of 5-FU, analysis of double mutants showed that yeast <italic>trm8</italic> genetically interacts with other genes encoding tRNA modification activities such as <italic>trm10</italic>, <italic>pus1</italic>, and <italic>mod5</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Gustavsson1">[25]</xref>. Only <italic>trm8</italic> mutant, but not <italic>trm4</italic> mutant, is found to be 5-FU sensitive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Gustavsson1">[25]</xref>. Although it is not clear whether yeast <italic>trm4</italic>/<italic>trm8</italic> double mutant displays hypersensitivity to 5-FU, tRNA modifying enzymes should be important factors for determining 5-FU sensitivity in yeast. Here, our experiments using HeLa cells demonstrated that these RTD-related tRNA modifying enzymes are associated with 5-FU sensitivity. Apparently the effect of 5-FU is different in yeast when compared to HeLa cells. Knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 in HeLa cells potentiates sensitivity of the cells to 5-FU, whereas heat stress of cells revealed no effects. In contrast, yeast tRNA modification mutants show similar synthetic interactions for temperature sensitivity and sensitivity to 5-FU. These differences are related to tRNA stability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g005">Figure 5</xref>). This result supports the idea that 5-FU-substituted and hypomodified tRNA that is caused by knockdown of tRNA methylases (NSUN2 and METTL1) after 5-FU exposure is possibly monitored and checked by RTD pathway in mammalian cells. Although the sites of specific tRNA modifications have not been yet determined in HeLa cells used here, METTL1 and NSUN2 target sites are mostly conserved between mammals and yeasts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Khoddami1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Towns1">[39]</xref>. In our model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g007">Figure 7</xref>), loss of tRNA modification causes tRNA destabilization, which is detected as temperature sensitivity in yeast but not in mammals, but may be detected as 5-FU sensitivity in mammals.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1004639-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Model for how loss of NSUN2- and METTL1-dependent tRNA(Val<sup>AAC</sup>) modifications causes 5-FU-induced tRNA destabilization.</title>
<p>(A) Synthetic interaction between <italic>trm4</italic> and <italic>trm8</italic> mutations in yeast. The temperature-sensitive phenotype of yeast <italic>trm4</italic>/<italic>trm8</italic> double mutant is due to rapid decay of hypomodified tRNA. A melted loop indicates destabilized tRNA. Although 5-FU-induced tRNA damage(s) that mediate tRNA destabilization remains to be fully determined, reduced pseudouridylation is the most likely cause of this. Only <italic>trm8</italic> mutant, but not <italic>trm4</italic> mutant, is sensitive to 5-FU. And so hypomodified tRNA caused by <italic>trm4</italic> and <italic>trm8</italic> mutations is probably hypersensitive to 5-FU (shown as a melted loop with question mark). (B) Cooperative effect between NSUN2 and METTL1 in HeLa cells. Hypomodified tRNA caused by double knockdown of NSUN2 and METTL1 is not heat-sensitive but is 5-FU-sensitive. A melted loop indicates destabilized tRNA.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Interestingly, in our study, degradation of tRNA(iMet) is heat-sensitive but is also 5-FU-sensitive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1004639-g005">Figure 5</xref>). From these data, the tRNA(iMet) stability is not likely to be related to tRNA modifications generated by NSUN2 and METTL1. This observation is of particular interest when considering stress responses that undergo a quality control check by RTD, because tRNA(iMet) stability is not affected by stresses other than heat or 5-FU, such as ethanol, hydrogen peroxide (oxidative stresses), low-pH (pH 5.0), cycloheximide, and sodium chloride (high salt concentrations) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Watanabe1">[40]</xref>.</p>
<p>Loss of tRNA(iMet) at high temperature was reported previously by Watanabe et al. who has shown that degradation of initiator tRNA, tRNA(iMet), depends on Xrn1/2 nucleases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Watanabe1">[40]</xref>. Yeast RTD pathway that includes Rat1 and Xrn2, monitors the structural integrity of the acceptor and T-stem of tRNA and degrades unstable tRNA species. Since the problem of the structural stabilization of the acceptor and T-stem in tRNA(iMet) in HeLa has been not clarified, Watanabe and colleagues suggest that the degradation pathway in human may resemble the RTD pathway in yeast. A role of Xrn1/2 in degradation of tRNA(Val<sup>AAC</sup>) in HeLa exposed to 5-FU is unknown. Yeast Trm4 and Trm8 are required for protecting yeast tRNA against RTD, but the functional analogy of their mammalian orthologs NSUN2 and METTL1 would need further study to determine more precisely.</p>
<p>DNA and RNA species other than tRNA, such as rRNA, snRNA, mRNA and pre-mRNA, are targets for 5-FU <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Longley1">[1]</xref>. Those are also targets for NSUN2 with broad substrate specificity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Frye2">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Squires1">[31]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Zhang1">[34]</xref>. However, the possibility that the nucleic acid species other than tRNA are involved in the NSUN2 and METTL1-dependent potentiation mechanism under 5-FU treatment is probably eliminated, because METTL1 is evolutionarily conserved and catalyzes the formation of N7-methylguanine at position 46 in tRNA in a substrate-specific manner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Cartlidge1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Alexandrov1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Bahr1">[24]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>tRNA and cancer</title>
<p>It has long been suggested that deregulation of translation contributes to cancer development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Ruggero1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Pandolfi1">[42]</xref>. Forced overexpression of components of translation machinery can lead to cell transformation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-LazarisKaratzas1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Tatsuka1">[44]</xref>. Elevations of tRNA methyltransferase activities and elevated expression levels of tRNA have also long been recognized in cancer cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Kuchino1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-PavonEternod1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Borek1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-PavonEternod2">[46]</xref>. Although such several circumstantial evidences suggests that deregulation of translation might be a common cause for human cancer, one viewpoint still argues that such tRNA deregulation might be only characteristics of cancer cells like a by-product, which is associated with increased proliferation and elevated levels of protein synthesis. The tRNA overexpression that leads to increase the translation efficiency of genes is indeed characteristic of cancer cells but does not necessarily need to be related to their growth advantage. In our view, based on the present study, tRNA modifications are likely to contribute to cancer cell survival under certain stresses that interferes with tRNA stability. We therefore envisage new approaches implementing RNA-methyltransferase inhibitors or tRNA-modifying molecules as amplifier for chemotherapy of cancer.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Cells, cell culture and reagents</title>
<p>The human cervical cancer cell line HeLa was provided by the late Professor Masakatsu Horikawa, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Kanazawa University <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Suzuki1">[47]</xref>. The cells were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's minimum essential medium containing 10% fetal bovine serum at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and 95% air.</p>
<p>5-FU (Nakarai Tesque, Kyoto, Japan) was dissolved in distilled water. Cisplatin (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) was dissolved in phosphate buffered saline solution without Ca<sup>2+</sup> and Mg<sup>2+</sup>. Paclitaxel (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) was dissolved in dimethyl sulfoxide. The chemical treatment was performed carefully under a protocol approved for evaluation in <italic>in vitro</italic> cultured cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Kakunaga1">[48]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Antibodies</title>
<p>Rabbit polyclonal anti-NSUN2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref> and anti-METTL1 (ProteinTech Group, Chicago, IL, USA) antibodies were used to detect endogenous tRNA modifying enzymes. Monoclonal anti-Xpress (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and anti-α-tubulin (Cedarlane Laboratories, Burlington, Ontario, Canada) antibodies were also used.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Protein extraction and immunoblot analysis</title>
<p>Whole cell lysates were prepared using Laemmli SDS-sample buffer. Protein concentration of lysed cells was quantified via the Bradford assay (Bio-Rad Protein Assay, Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA). Proteins were resolved by sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (20 µg/lane), electroblotted onto a polyvinylidene difluoride membrane, Immobilon P (Millipore Corporation, Billerica, MA, USA), using an electroblotter (ATTO, Tokyo, Japan), and incubated with an appropriate antibody. The immunoblots were developed using electrogenerated chemiluminescence reagents kit (GE-Amersham, Princeton, NJ, USA).</p>
</sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Plasmids</title>
<p>Expression plasmids for Xpress-tagged NSUN2 and its constitutively dephosphorylated and phosphorylated forms (Xpress-tagged NSUN2-S139A and Xpress-tagged NSUN2-S139E) have been described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>. The coding region of METTL1 cDNA (GenBank: BC000550.1, Open Biosystems, Huntsville, AL, USA) was amplified by polymerase chain reaction and subcloned into pcDNA3.1/His, generating plasmid pcDNA3.1-Xpress-METTL1. The following mutant METTL1 expression plasmids were also constructed: pcDNA3.1-Xpress-METTL1-SA, producing dephosphorylation-mimic METTL1-S27A, in which Ser27 of METTL1 was replaced with Ala by site-directed mutation at T79G; and pcDNA3.1-Xpress-METTL1-SE, producing phosphorylation-mimic METTL1-S27E in which Ser27 of METTL1 was replaced with Glu by site-directed mutation at T79G, C80A and C81A.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4e">
<title>Stable transfectants with forced overexpression of tRNA modifying enzymes</title>
<p>HeLa cells were transfected with constructs encoding tRNA modifying enzymes or control vector by using lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). G418-resistant colonies (over twenty colonies) were cloned in each transfection, and the protein expression of each clone was checked by immunoblot analysis. Five independent clones that overexpressed Xpress-tagged proteins were pooled and used as a stable transfectant.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4f">
<title>Knockdown of endogeneous tRNA modifying enzymes using short hairpin RNA (shRNA)</title>
<p>Oligonucleotides targeted to the 5′-untranslated region (UTR) of NSUN2 and METTL1 were synthesized, and were ligated into pSUPERIOR.PURO (OligoEngine, Seattle, WA, USA). Puromycin-resistant colonies (thirty colonies) were cloned in each transfection, and the protein expression of each clone was checked by immunoblot analysis as shown previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>. Five independent clones that repress expression of endogenous tRNA modifying enzymes were pooled and used as a knockdown clone.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4g">
<title>Analysis of cell growth curves</title>
<p>Doubling times were calculated from growth curves in logarithmic growth phase.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4h">
<title>Ability to form colonies in semisolid medium</title>
<p>Colony-forming abilities in semisolid medium were determined by the method described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Suzuki2">[49]</xref>. Anchorage-independent colonies grown in 0.2% washed agar medium were counted.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4i">
<title>Analysis of cell viability with water-soluble tetrazolium-1 (WST-1) assay</title>
<p>Cells were inoculated into 96-well plates. After 4 h of culture, each drug solution was added. For hyperthermia experiments, cells were cultured at 43°C for various periods. The treated cells were cultured for additional 72 h. Cell viability was determined by WST-1 assay (Roche Applied Science, Indianapolis, IN, USA). The IC<sub>50</sub> value represents the drug concentration resulting in 50% viability.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4j">
<title>Analysis of cell viability with colony formation assay</title>
<p>Colony formation assay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Franken1">[50]</xref>, also known as clonogenic assay, was used to confirm the cytotoxic effect of 5-FU. Cells were plated onto a plastic surface and allowed to attach for 24 h. Each drug solution was added directly into each dish, as mentioned previously<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Kakunaga1">[48]</xref>. Colonies formed were stained and counted. The IC<sub>50</sub> value represents the drug concentration resulting in 50% survival.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4k">
<title>Northern blot analysis of RNA</title>
<p>Total RNA was isolated from HeLa cells treated with heat stress or 5-FU by using RNAiso Plus (Takara-Clontech, Tokyo, Japan). RNA gel electrophoresis and Northern blot analysis identified tRNA(Val<sup>AAC</sup>), tRNA(iMet), tRNA(eMet), and 5S rRNA by using each specific labeled probes as described below. Quantification of band intensity was calculated by Multi Gauge (Fujifilm, Tokyo, Japan). The probe sequences are tRNA(Val<sup>AAC</sup>): <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">GGACCTTTCGCGTGTTAGG</named-content>, tRNA(iMet): <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">GCAGAGGATGGTTTCGATCCATC</named-content>, tRNA(eMet): <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">CCCCGTGTGAGGATCGAACTCAC</named-content>, and 5S rRNA: <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">CAGGGTGGTATGGCCGTAGAC</named-content>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4l">
<title>Statistics</title>
<p>All experiments to obtain quantitative data were repeated independently three times (n = 3). Differences between values were analyzed using a two-tailed Welch's <italic>t</italic>-test. <italic>P</italic>-values of &lt;0.05 were considered significant. Data is presented as the mean +/− one standard deviation (SD).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1004639.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p>Effects of decreased NSUN2 expression on cell growth and on anchorage-independent growth. HeLa cells and their derived five clones transfected with NSUN2-shRNA #1, #2, or #3 were used. Expression levels of NSUN2 were previously checked by immunoblot analysis (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1004639.s004">Figure S4</xref> in ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1">[17]</xref>). NSUN2 expression is completely repressed in clones #2-1, #2-8, and #3-5, moderately repressed in clone #1-7, and not repressed in clone #3-3. (A) <italic>In vitro</italic> growth curves of these clones (#1-7, #2-1, #2-8 #3-3, and #3-5) and parental HeLa cells. (B) Colony-forming abilities of these clones (lanes <italic>#1-7, #2-1, #2-8 #3-3, and #3-5</italic>) and parental HeLa cells (lane <italic>HeLa</italic>) in 0.2% washed agar medium. All experiments to obtain quantitative data were repeated independently three times (n = 3). Data throughout this study represent the mean ± SD for three independent experiments, and error bars represent the SD. Difference between values were analyzed using a two-tailed Welch's <italic>t</italic>-test. <italic>P</italic>-values of &lt;0.05 were considered significant. NS, not significant.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004639.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p>Effects of increased NSUN2 expression on cell growth and on anchorage-independent growth. (A) Immunoblot analysis of proteins from Xpress-NSUN2-overexpressing cells (lane <italic>Xpress-NSUN2</italic>) and control vector-transfected cells (lane <italic>empty</italic>) with anti-Xpress, anti-NSUN2 and anti-α-tubulin antibodies. Five independent clones that overexpressed Xpress-NSUN2 or were transfected with the empty vector were pooled and used as a stable transfectant. (B) <italic>In vitro</italic> doubling times of Xpress-NSUN2-overexpressing cells (lane <italic>Xpress-NSUN2</italic>) and control vector-transfected cells (lane <italic>empty</italic>). (C) Colony-forming abilities of Xpress-NSUN2-overexpressing cells (lane <italic>Xpress-NSUN2</italic>) and control vector-transfected cells (lane <italic>empty</italic>) in 0.2% washed agar medium. NS, not significant.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004639.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p>Effects of decreased NSUN2 expression on cell growth and on anchorage-independent growth. Newly isolated clones transfected with NSUN2-shRNA targeted to UTR were used. (A) Immunoblot analysis of proteins from NSUN2 knockdown cells (lane <italic>NSUN2</italic>) and scrambled control vector-transfected cells (lane <italic>scrambled</italic>) with anti-NSUN2 and anti-α-tubulin antibodies. Five independent clones that decreased endogenous NSUN2 expression or were transfected with the scrambled control vector were pooled and used as a stable transfectant. (B) <italic>In vitro</italic> doubling times of NSUN2 knockdown cells (lane <italic>NSUN2</italic>) and scrambled control vector-transfected cells (lane <italic>scrambled</italic>). (C) Colony-forming abilities of NSUN2 knockdown cells (lane <italic>NSUN2</italic>) and scrambled control vector-transfected cells (lane <italic>scrambled</italic>) in 0.2% washed agar medium. NS, not significant.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004639.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p>Effects of increased NSUN2 and METTL1 co-expression on cell growth and on anchorage-independent growth. (A) <italic>In vitro</italic> doubling times of Xpress-METTL1-overexpressing cells (lane <italic>Xpress-METTL1</italic>), Xpress-NSUN2- and Xpress-METTL1-co-overexpressing cells (lane <italic>Xpress-NSUN2 + Xpress-METTL1</italic>) and control vector-transfected cells (lane <italic>empty</italic>). (B) Colony-forming abilities of Xpress-METTL1-overexpressing cells (lane <italic>Xpress-METTL1</italic>), Xpress-NSUN2- and Xpress-METTL1-co-overexpressing cells (lane <italic>Xpress-NSUN2 + Xpress-METTL1</italic>) and control vector-transfected cells (lane <italic>empty</italic>) in 0.2% washed agar medium. NS, not significant.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004639.s005" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S5</label><caption>
<p>Effects of decreased expression of NSUN2 and METTL1 on cell growth and on anchorage-independent growth in UTR-targeting shRNA-mediated newly established knockdown cells. (A) <italic>In vitro</italic> doubling times of NSUN2 knockdown cells (lane <italic>NSUN2</italic>), METTL1 knockdown cells (lane <italic>METTL1</italic>), NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells (lane <italic>NSUN2 + METTL1</italic>) and scrambled control vector-transfected cells (lane <italic>scrambled</italic>). (B) Colony-forming abilities of NSUN2 knockdown cells (lane <italic>NSUN2</italic>), METTL1 knockdown cells (lane <italic>METTL1</italic>), NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells (lane <italic>NSUN2 + METTL1</italic>) and scrambled control vector-transfected cells (lane <italic>scrambled</italic>) in 0.2% washed agar medium. NS, not significant.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004639.s006" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S6</label><caption>
<p>Effects of overexpression of NSUN2, NSUN2<sup>S139A</sup>, and NSUN2<sup>S139E</sup> on H-Ras<sup>G12V</sup>-induced cell transformation in vitro. A BALB/c 3T3 A31-1-1 cell transformation assay system was utilized, and quantification of the number of transformed foci was determined using standard criteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Tatsuka2">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1004639-Kanda1">[52]</xref>. The inset shows an immunoblot of cells transfected with empty vectors (lane <italic>1</italic>), NSUN2 (lane <italic>2</italic>), NSUN2<sup>S139A</sup> (lane <italic>3</italic>), NSUN2<sup>S139E</sup> (lane <italic>4</italic>), H-Ras<sup>G12V</sup> (lane <italic>5</italic>), NSUN2 + H-Ras<sup>G12V</sup> (lane <italic>6</italic>), NSUN2<sup>S139A</sup> + H-Ras<sup>G12V</sup> (lane <italic>7</italic>), and NSUN2<sup>S139E</sup> + H-Ras<sup>G12V</sup> (lane <italic>8</italic>). NS, not significant.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1004639.s007" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1004639.s007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S7</label><caption>
<p>Cell survival in response to 5-FU (IC<sub>50</sub> concentrations) under heat stress (43°C for 1.5 h) in NSUN2 and METTL1 knockdown cells (lane <italic>NSUN2 + METTL1</italic>), and control vector-transfected cells (lane <italic>scrambled</italic>) with the MTT viability assay. NS, not significant.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Mami Ueda, Miyako Urayama, and Ami Kitahara for assistance with cell culture experiments; Mami Ueda, Satomi Koga, and Yuya Inoue for assistance with immunoblot experiments; and Mami Ueda, Mikoko Fujii, and Takahiko Tsuno for assistance with plasmid construction experiments.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Longley1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Longley</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harkin</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>5-fluorouracil: mechanisms of action and clinical strategies</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Benz1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tillis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tattelman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cadman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Optimal schedule of methotrexate and 5-fluorouracil in human breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>2081</fpage>–<lpage>2086</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Bertino1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertino</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Sequential methotrexate and 5-fluorouracil: mechanisms of synergy</article-title>. <source>Semin Oncol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Bonnefoi1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnefoi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powles</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Phase II study of continuous infusional 5-fluorouracil with epirubicin and carboplatin (instead of cisplatin) in patients with metastatic/locally advanced breast cancer (infusional ECarboF): a very active and well-tolerated outpatient regimen</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>396</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Greco1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Figlin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>York</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Einhorn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schilsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Phase III randomized study to compare interferon alfa-2a in combination with fluorouracil versus fluorouracil alone in patients with advanced colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>2674</fpage>–<lpage>2681</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Jones1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DV</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winn</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Randomized phase III study of 5-fluorouracil plus high dose folinic acid versus 5-fluorouracil plus folinic acid plus methyl-lomustine for patients with advanced colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>1709</fpage>–<lpage>1714</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Marsoni1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsoni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Fluorouracil and folinic acid in colon cancer. IMPACT Investigators</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>345</volume>: <fpage>1582</fpage>–<lpage>1583</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Nadal1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadal</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Groeningen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinedo</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>In vivo potentiation of 5-fluorouracil by leucovorin in murine colon carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Biomed Pharmacother</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Wolmark1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolmark</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grem</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allegra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Adjuvant 5-fluorouracil and leucovorin with or without interferon alfa-2a in colon carcinoma: National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project protocol C-05</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>1810</fpage>–<lpage>1816</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Hung1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mody</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Govindarajan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Overcoming nucleoside analog chemoresistance of pancreatic cancer: a therapeutic challenge</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source> <volume>320</volume>: <fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Shi1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Combinational therapy: new hope for pancreatic cancer?</article-title> <source>Cancer Lett</source> <volume>317</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-delaCruzMorcillo1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Cruz-Morcillo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valero</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Callejas-Valera</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arias-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melgar-Rojas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>P38MAPK is a major determinant of the balance between apoptosis and autophagy triggered by 5-fluorouracil: implication in resistance</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>1073</fpage>–<lpage>1085</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Cartlidge1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cartlidge</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knebel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peggie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandrov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phizicky</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The tRNA methylase METTL1 is phosphorylated and inactivated by PKB and RSK in vitro and in cells</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1696</fpage>–<lpage>1705</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Frye1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dragoni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spiteri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genomic gain of 5p15 leads to over-expression of Misu (NSUN2) in breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source> <volume>289</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Okamoto1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Frequent increased gene copy number and high protein expression of tRNA (cytosine-5-)-methyltransferase (NSUN2) in human cancers</article-title>. <source>DNA Cell Biol</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>660</fpage>–<lpage>671</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Wikman1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wikman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nymark</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vayrynen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jarmalaite</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kallioniemi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>CDK4 is a probable target gene in a novel amplicon at 12q13.3-q14.1 in lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Genes Chromosomes Cancer</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-SakitaSuto1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakita-Suto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Aurora-B regulates RNA methyltransferase NSUN2</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1107</fpage>–<lpage>1117</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Motorin1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Motorin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grosjean</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Multisite-specific tRNA:m5C-methyltransferase (Trm4) in yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae: identification of the gene and substrate specificity of the enzyme</article-title>. <source>RNA</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1105</fpage>–<lpage>1118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Wu1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brockenbrough</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paddy</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aris</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>NCL1, a novel gene for a non-essential nuclear protein in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>220</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Alexandrov1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandrov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martzen</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phizicky</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Two proteins that form a complex are required for 7-methylguanosine modification of yeast tRNA</article-title>. <source>RNA</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1253</fpage>–<lpage>1266</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Alexandrov2"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandrov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chernyakov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiley</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Rapid tRNA decay can result from lack of nonessential modifications</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Chernyakov1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chernyakov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whipple</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kotelawala</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grayhack</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phizicky</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Degradation of several hypomodified mature tRNA species in Saccharomyces cerevisiae is mediated by Met22 and the 5′-3′ exonucleases Rat1 and Xrn1</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1369</fpage>–<lpage>1380</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Whipple1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whipple</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chernyakov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D'Silva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phizicky</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The yeast rapid tRNA decay pathway primarily monitors the structural integrity of the acceptor and T-stems of mature tRNA</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1184</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Bahr1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hankeln</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hegemann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Molecular analysis of METTL1, a novel human methyltransferase-like gene with a high degree of phylogenetic conservation</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>424</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Gustavsson1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gustavsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Evidence that tRNA modifying enzymes are important in vivo targets for 5-fluorouracil in yeast</article-title>. <source>RNA</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>666</fpage>–<lpage>674</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Frye2"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The RNA methyltransferase Misu (NSun2) mediates Myc-induced proliferation and is upregulated in tumors</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>971</fpage>–<lpage>981</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Blanco1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benitah</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The RNA-methyltransferase Misu (NSun2) poises epidermal stem cells to differentiate</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002403</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Kuchino1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuchino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Changes in transfer RNA's in human malignant trophoblastic cells (BeWo line)</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>2932</fpage>–<lpage>2936</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-PavonEternod1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavon-Eternod</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geslain</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosner</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>tRNA over-expression in breast cancer and functional consequences</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>7268</fpage>–<lpage>7280</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Auxilien1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Auxilien</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guerineau</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szweykowska-Kulinska</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Golinelli-Pimpaneau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The human tRNA m (5) C methyltransferase Misu is multisite-specific</article-title>. <source>RNA Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1331</fpage>–<lpage>1338</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Squires1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Squires</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nousch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sibbritt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Widespread occurrence of 5-methylcytosine in human coding and non-coding RNA</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>5023</fpage>–<lpage>5033</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Khoddami1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoddami</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Identification of direct targets and modified bases of RNA cytosine methyltransferases</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>458</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Hussain1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sajini</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dietmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lombard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>NSun2-mediated cytosine-5 methylation of vault noncoding RNA determines its processing into regulatory small RNAs</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Zhang1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The tRNA methyltransferase NSun2 stabilizes p16INK(4) mRNA by methylating the 3′-untranslated region of p16</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>712</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Martinez1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Whole exome sequencing identifies a splicing mutation in NSUN2 as a cause of a Dubowitz-like syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Med Genet</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>380</fpage>–<lpage>385</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Khan1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rafiq</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Mutation in NSUN2, which encodes an RNA methyltransferase, causes autosomal-recessive intellectual disability</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>856</fpage>–<lpage>863</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-AbbasiMoheb1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbasi-Moheb</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mertel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonsior</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nouri-Vahid</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kahrizi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Mutations in NSUN2 cause autosomal-recessive intellectual disability</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>847</fpage>–<lpage>855</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Hussain2"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benavente</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dragoni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The nucleolar RNA methyltransferase Misu (NSun2) is required for mitotic spindle stability</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source> <volume>186</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Towns1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Towns</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Begley</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Transfer RNA methytransferases and their corresponding modifications in budding yeast and humans: activities, predications, and potential roles in human health</article-title>. <source>DNA Cell Biol</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>454</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Watanabe1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miyagawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tomikawa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Degradation of initiator tRNAMet by Xrn1/2 via its accumulation in the nucleus of heat-treated HeLa cells</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>4671</fpage>–<lpage>4685</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Ruggero1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruggero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pandolfi</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Does the ribosome translate cancer?</article-title> <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Pandolfi1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandolfi</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Aberrant mRNA translation in cancer pathogenesis: an old concept revisited comes finally of age</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>3134</fpage>–<lpage>3137</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-LazarisKaratzas1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazaris-Karatzas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montine</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sonenberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Malignant transformation by a eukaryotic initiation factor subunit that binds to mRNA 5′ cap</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>345</volume>: <fpage>544</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Tatsuka1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatsuka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nojima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Elongation factor-1 alpha gene determines susceptibility to transformation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>359</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Borek1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>1972</year>) <article-title>Atypical transfer RNA's and their origin in neoplastic cells</article-title>. <source>Adv Cancer Res</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-PavonEternod2"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavon-Eternod</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosner</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of initiator methionine tRNA leads to global reprogramming of tRNA expression and increased proliferation in human epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>RNA</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Suzuki1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>A replica plating method of cultured mammalian cells</article-title>. <source>Methods Cell Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Kakunaga1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Kakunaga T (1981) Approaches toward developing a human transformation assay system. In: Myron AM, Nawin CM, editors. Mammalian Cell Transformation by Chemical Carcinogens. Washington, DC, U.S.A.: Senate Press. pp. 355–382.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Suzuki2"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikaido</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>An improved soft agar method for determining neoplastic transformation in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Tissue Cult Methods</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Franken1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franken</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodermond</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stap</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haveman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Bree</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Clonogenic assay of cells in vitro</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>2315</fpage>–<lpage>2319</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Tatsuka2"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatsuka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitajima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of Aurora-A potentiates HRAS-mediated oncogenic transformation and is implicated in oral carcinogenesis</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1122</fpage>–<lpage>1127</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1004639-Kanda1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitajima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Aurora-B/AIM-1 kinase activity is involved in Ras-mediated cell transformation</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>7266</fpage>–<lpage>7272</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>