<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07-PLGE-RA-0538R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Computational Biology/Evolutionary Modeling</subject><subject>Computational Biology/Population Genetics</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Chromosome Biology</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Population Genetics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Inexorable Spread of a Newly Arisen Neo-Y Chromosome</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">The Establishment of Neo-XY Karyotypes</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veltsos</surname><given-names>Paris</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>Irene</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>¤</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>Richard A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">          <addr-line>School of Biological and Chemical Sciences, Queen Mary University of London, London, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schierup</surname><given-names>Mikkel H.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Aarhus, Denmark</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">r.a.nichols@qmul.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="current-aff" id="fn1"><label>¤</label><p>Current address: Eawag, Dübendorf, Switzerland</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: PV IK RN. Performed the experiments: PV. Analyzed the data: PV RN. Wrote the paper: PV RN. Supervised: PV RN.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e1000082</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2008</year></date></history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Veltsos et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A newly arisen Y-chromosome can become established in one part of a species range by genetic drift or through the effects of selection on sexually antagonistic alleles. However, it is difficult to explain why it should then spread throughout the species range after this initial episode. As it spreads into new populations, it will actually enter females. It would then be expected to perform poorly since it will have been shaped by the selective regime of the male-only environment from which it came. We address this problem using computer models of hybrid zone dynamics where a neo-XY chromosomal race meets the ancestral karyotype. Our models consider that the neo-Y was established by the fusion of an autosome with the ancestral X-chromosome (thereby creating the Y and the ‘fused X’). Our principal finding is that sexually antagonistic effects of the Y induce indirect selection in favour of the fused X-chromosomes, causing their spread. The Y-chromosome can then spread, protected behind the advancing shield of the fused X distribution. This mode of spread provides a robust explanation of how newly arisen Y-chromosomes can spread. A Y-chromosome would be expected to accumulate mutations that would cause it to be selected against when it is a rare newly arrived migrant. The Y can spread, nevertheless, because of the indirect selection induced by gene flow (which can only be observed in models comprising multiple populations). These results suggest a fundamental re-evaluation of sex-chromosome hybrid zones. The well-understood evolutionary events that initiate the Y-chromosome's degeneration will actually fuel its range expansion.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><p>Comparisons between related species have shown that, over evolutionary time scales, Y-chromosomes tend to degenerate and can be completely lost. How then can we explain the persistence of Y-chromosomes to the present? One possibility is that losses are counter-balanced by the origin of new Y chromosomes, which then spread throughout the species in which they have arisen. The first of these two processes, the generation of new Y chromsomes, is more readily understood: it can occur if an autosome (a non sex chromosome) fuses with an X chromosome. This form might become established in one locality. However, its subsequent geographic spread has been more challenging to explain. Problems arise if gene flow carries them to another part of the species range. Crosses can then occur which introduce the new Y chromosome into females, who are expected to suffer reduced fitness. The new sex chromosomes are therefore selected against when they are in the minority. We use simulations to show that they can nevertheless spread, if they meet the ancestral forms at a front so the chromosomes intermingle in a hybrid zone. Paradoxically, the degeneration of the Y will actually intensify selection, thereby speeding its spread.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was financially supported by a Natural Environment Research Council grant to RAN. (NER-B-S-2003-00859) and a studentship from Queen Mary University of London to PV.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Our understanding of sex chromosome evolution has increased immensely in the past decade. Theoretical expectations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth1">[1]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth2">[2]</xref> have been experimentally verified in a wide variety of organisms, including fish, fruitflies, mammals and plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Kondo1">[3]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Steinemann1">[8]</xref>. For example, it is widely documented that over a series of generations, a Y-chromosome will eventually stop recombining with the X over most of its length. As a consequence there are increased rates of transposition, degeneration, heterochromatinization and loss of function of genes on the Y, amongst other changes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Bachtrog1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Steinemann1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Bachtrog2">[13]</xref>.</p><p>It appears then, that the inexorable fate of Y-chromosomes is degeneration and perhaps loss. It is even possible that all sexually dimorphic species lacking a Y have previously passed through a Y-possessing stage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth1">[1]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-White1">[14]</xref>, as is the case for <italic>Caernohabditis elegans</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Larsson1">[15]</xref> (the logic would also apply to equivalent W chromosomes in species with heterogametic females). The persistence of Y-chromosomes to the present day therefore suggests that they can repeatedly arise <italic>de novo.</italic> One straightforward way in which new Ys can be created is by the fusion between an autosome and X-chromosome followed by its fixation. This paper models the evolution of such neo-XY sex chromosome systems and, in particular, asks why they should become established throughout a species' range. The analysis suggests that the spread of neo-Ys is much more likely than suggested by current models, and that this new proposal could be tested by analysis of sex chromosome hybrid zones.</p><p>A concrete example can be a useful guide for explaining and constructing evolutionary models, so we make use of the well-studied example of the neo-XY race of the grasshopper <italic>Podisma pedestris</italic>. Phylogenetic comparison <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-White2">[16]</xref> suggests that the ancestral <italic>P. pedestris</italic> karyotype had females with two X-chromosomes and males with one (but no Y): this is known as an XX/XO sex-determining system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-John1">[17]</xref>. The system changed following the centric fusion of the X with an autosome (A<sub>u</sub>) to create a larger metacentric neo-X. The fused karyotype has become fixed in populations in the southern part of the species' distribution in the French Alps. In these fixed populations, the females contain two neo-X chromosomes, and hence no unfused A<sub>u</sub>. In males, however, the unfused A<sub>u</sub> chromosomes have continued to pair with the homologous section of the neo-X. These unfused A<sub>u</sub> are now restricted to males and are consequently designated neo-Y chromosomes. The karyotypes of the original unfused, and derived fused race are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g001">Figure 1 (karyotypes A, B, F, G)</xref>.</p><fig id="pgen-1000082-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>The karyotypes occurring in the hybrid zone.</title><p>The karyotypes are organised by sex and the generation they first appear (in a cross between neo-XY and XO populations). The lower pink chromosome is the ancestral X. The upper chromosome can be an unfused A<sub>u</sub> (yellow), or fused to the X (as part of the neo-X, also shown in yellow), or a Y-chromosome (green). Each karyotype has been labelled by a letter, for reference. The expected frequency of each karyotype at equilibrium is shown for the neutral case after a cross between equal numbers of new-XY and XO. Note the 1∶4 ratio of the Y to unfused A<sub>u</sub> in the parental populations (made of A, B, F, G).</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.g001" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><p>Sex chromosomes are often involved in fusions. Indeed, human sex chromosomes are believed to be the products of at least three chromosomal fusions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Graves1">[6]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Watson1">[18]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Graves2">[19]</xref>, as is the <italic>Drosophila</italic> Y-chromosome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Carvalho2">[20]</xref>. The occurrence of a fusion is insufficient to explain the genesis of a neo-XY system however. Following the fusion event, the new karyotypes must also become fixed throughout the species range (or part of it). The establishment of neo-XY systems does appear to occur repeatedly in evolution. Good evidence comes from the Orthoptera, which have conveniently large chromosomes for surveys of karyotype. White calculates that there have probably been six independent fixations of the XY system from an ancestral XO condition in the Australian subfamily Morabinae alone (based on karyotypes from about 80 species). More generally, the fixation of the XY system has been reported in at least 21 genera of Acrididae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-White2">[16]</xref>(and references therein).</p><p>Attempts to explain this establishment fall broadly into two traditions. Firstly, cytogeneticists have noticed that chromosomal rearrangements often confer reduced fertility in heterozygotes. The cause may be a direct effect of meiotic aberrations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-White3">[21]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-White4">[22]</xref>; in other cases selection against changed recombination patterns is suspected (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Shaw1">[23]</xref> for an example). These forms of selection actually act against the fusion when it is rare; but it could nevertheless become established in small isolated populations if genetic drift elevated its frequency until it became the commoner type and hence favoured by selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Lande1">[24]</xref>. The difficulty with this explanation is to account for how the fusion would subsequently spread from a single isolated population to other populations. Lande <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Lande1">[24]</xref> proposed that the fused race could colonize sites left vacant by local extinctions, whereas Hewitt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Hewitt1">[25]</xref> argues that spreading would be more effective if the initial population was located on the expanding margin of the species range, as it spreads into new territory–most likely during an episode of rapid climatic change.</p><p>A second perspective comes from consideration of the alleles that were segregating on autosomes before the fusion occurred. Fusion with a sex chromosome might bring alleles into linkage with the newly created sex chromosome and confer a fitness benefit; the key alleles might be sexually antagonistic (benefiting one sex at the expense of the other) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth3">[26]</xref> or deleterious recessives <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth4">[27]</xref> (especially in strongly inbreeding populations). In both cases the selection is expected to be much more effective in promoting Y-autosome fusions, and such events might repeatedly add new genetic material to existing Y-chromosomes. Linkage with sexually antagonistic alleles could also produce selection for the fixation of new X-autosome fusions, and hence the creation of neo-Ys.</p><p>There is some evidence that sexually antagonistic alleles may indeed have appreciable effects. Rice conducted an imaginative breeding design in which a haploid <italic>Drosophila</italic> genome was restricted to one sex for several generations and then returned to the other sex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Rice1">[28]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Rice3">[30]</xref>. The results were striking. In less than 30 generations, sex specific fitness differences had become established in the sex-restricted genome. The rapidity of the response was interpreted as showing that sexually antagonistic alleles had been segregating in the founder population.</p><p>Even with strong selection on sexually antagonistic alleles, the advantage provided to the fused chromosome would be weak <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth3">[26]</xref>. Nonetheless, this selective process, or the action of drift, might establish the neo-XY system locally in part of the species distribution. The spread throughout the whole species range is more difficult to explain. Any advantage to the fusion when rare is expected to be transient, because of the well-understood evolutionary events affecting new sex chromosomes. Alleles reducing female fitness, can accumulate readily on the Y <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth1">[1]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth2">[2]</xref>, particularly if they also had beneficial effects in males.</p><p>Our analysis, has uncovered a paradoxical effect that nevertheless favours the geographic spread of the neo-XY system. If sexually antagonistic alleles have become established on the Y, the genetic interactions at the boundary between neo-XY and ancestral populations can favour the spread of the neo-X. Surprisingly, the results hold even if the net effect of selection against the neo-Y in females outweighs the benefits in males.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>The pattern of chromosome segregation in crosses involving individuals with different sex chromosome combinations is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g002">Figure 2</xref>. The letters correspond to the karyotypes shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g001">Figure 1</xref>, the area of each cell is proportional to the number of each karyotype in the offspring. This scheme was translated into a set of equations for the frequency of each karyotype as a function of the frequencies in the previous generation, assuming random mating and after weighting each karyotype by its fitness. A program to iterate the equations was written in the statistical language R <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-R1">[31]</xref>, and is listed in the supporting information (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1000082.s001">Dataset S1</xref>). The initial analysis revisited, and then extended the results of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth3">[26]</xref>. Consider two sexually antagonistic alleles that might be segregating on the autosome A<sub>u</sub> during the period before the chromosomal fusion. The two alleles (<bold><italic>a</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>b</italic></bold>) have different fitness in the two sexes (specified by <italic>w<sub>♀aa</sub></italic>, <italic>w<sub>♀ab</sub></italic> &amp; <italic>w<sub>♀bb</sub></italic> for females, and <italic>w<sub>♂aa</sub></italic>, <italic>w<sub>♂ab</sub></italic> &amp; <italic>w<sub>♂bb</sub></italic> for males). The <bold><italic>a</italic></bold> allele was assumed to be favored in males, and the <bold><italic>b</italic></bold> in females so <italic>w<sub>♀bb</sub></italic> = <italic>w<sub>♂aa</sub></italic> = 1. The program calculated the outcome of selection for all possible combinations of <italic>w<sub>♂bb</sub></italic> and <italic>w<sub>♀aa</sub></italic> in the range 0–1 at intervals of 1/40 (with a specified dominance). If there is polymorphism at this locus before the fusion takes place, the fusion will (in some cases) generate linkage disequilibrium leading to selection for the fixation of the fusion. The fitness combinations leading to such polymorphism can be illustrated by initiating a simulation with only the ancestral XX∶XO karyotypes, and including a chromosome carrying the <bold><italic>a</italic></bold> allele (equivalent to the green chromosome in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g001">Figure 1</xref>) at low frequency. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3A</xref> illustrates a range of fitness combinations producing polymorphism (achieved from an initial <bold><italic>a</italic></bold> frequency of 0.1% with all genotypes in Hardy-Weinberg proportions).</p><fig id="pgen-1000082-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>The karyotypes produced by each possible mating.</title><p>The letters refer to the karyotypes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g001">Figure 1</xref>. The area of each cell indicates the relative proportion of each karyotype in a mating. Offspring with the same karyotypes as their parents are indicated in bold. This matrix forms the basis of the computer simulations.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.g002" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pgen-1000082-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>The fate of sexually antagonistic alleles in a single population.</title><p>We consider an ancestral autosomal locus, which had two sexually antagonistic alleles: <italic>a</italic> was favoured in males and <italic>b</italic> in females. 3A. The outcome of selection on the <italic>b</italic> allele in the ancestral population as a function of the fitnesses of the two homozygotes. The central area of fitness combinations results in a stable polymorphism (delineated by the contours <italic>p<sub>a</sub> = </italic>0.001 and <italic>p<sub>a</sub></italic> = 0.999). In this example the alleles were additive. 3B. The evolutionary dynamics change if one of the <italic>b</italic>-bearing autosomes fuses to the X-chromosome. We illustrate this effect by plotting the frequency of the <italic>b</italic>-neo-X haplotype 1 000 generations after it has been introduced at low frequency (0.04). The neo-X spreads for some fitness combinations (the central area enclosed by 0.001 and 0.999 contours). The spread of the neo-X was opposed by weak selection against females heterozygous for the fusion (genotypes H and I from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g001">Figure 1</xref> were assumed to suffer a 1% reduction in fertility). Note, that mild sexually antagonistic selection (i.e. the region near the point (1,1)) is insufficient to favour the fused X.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.g003" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><p>The combinations of fitness that can lead to selection for the fixation of the fusion have been explored in some detail <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth3">[26]</xref>. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3</xref>, they correspond to the <bold><italic>b</italic></bold> allele becoming linked to the X by the fusion. This selection for the fusion could be demonstrated in our simulations by initiating the fusion at a low frequency (0.4%, corresponding to the frequency of the fusion, if migration had introduced the Y at 0.1%) and then iterating the equations for 1000 generations. The analysis was extended to investigate the effect of the slightly reduced fertility that is expected in females heterozygous for the fusion. This additional selection was set at <italic>s</italic> = 0.01, the value estimated for <italic>P. pedestris.</italic> The recombination rate between the <bold><italic>b</italic></bold> allele and the X centromere was set at zero to maximize the selection for the fusion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth3">[26]</xref>. As the Y-chromosome evolves, recombination is expected to be reduced over a greater proportion of the Y <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth1">[1]</xref>, hence the modelled effects are increasingly likely to occur. Indeed, in the case of <italic>P. pedestris</italic>, which is assumed to have a young neo-XY system, the recombination is already displaced way from the Y centromere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-John2">[32]</xref>, perhaps simply as effect of the fusion itself, and very strong linkage disequilibrium has been found even in the middle of the zone for an X-marker <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Dallas1">[33]</xref>.</p><sec id="s2a"><title>Simulation of a Contact Zone between XO and Neo-XY Populations</title><p>These initial calculations involved a single panmictic population. The outcome can be different when the population is subdivided. The next step was therefore to consider a situation in which the neo-XY system had become established in an isolated area, and come into contact with the ancestral (XX:XO) karyotype. Gene flow between the two chromosomal races would then produce a hybrid zone. A computer simulation of a linear array of 40 populations was used to model this situation. Initially the left hand 20 populations were fixed for the ancestral karyotype and the remainder for the neo-XY. There was gene flow of 8% between adjacent populations (total gene flow of 16%). Population size was uniform across the simulated populations. In other words there was no density trap to pin the zone down to a particular location (as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Hewitt2">[34]</xref>). The two ends of the array could either be set to receive gene flow from populations fixed for the ancestral karyotypes, or to only receive gene flow from their more central neighbour. Both options were used to check for any effect on the outcome of the simulations. For each generation, after gene flow, the expected frequencies of genotypes in the next generation were calculated as before.</p><p>In this extension of the model, the green chromosome in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g001">Figure 1</xref> is considered to be a neo-Y-chromosome. The <bold><italic>a</italic></bold> allele would have been fixed on the neo-Y which could also have accumulated additional sexually antagonistic alleles tightly linked to the X centromere (due to the extension of the non-recombining region). We have argued that we would expect some alleles to be selected against in males and favoured in females, and for there to be selection against the chromosomal heterozygotes. However, it is helpful to understand the combination of these effects by first examining the behaviour of these three forms of selection individually. We therefore summarize the results by defining three selection regimes. The first two correspond to points on the X and Y axes of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3</xref>: Firstly, male-beneficial variants could have become established on the Y (<italic>w<sub>♂(AU·)</sub></italic>&lt;1), were ‘A<sub>u</sub><italic>·</italic>’ represents genotypes containing A<sub>u</sub>– the autosomal homologue of the neo-Y; secondly, female-deleterious variants could occur on the Y (<italic>w<sub>♀(Y·)</sub></italic>&lt;1). The third simple case is selection against females heterozygous for the fused X (<italic>w<sub>♀(FU)</sub></italic>&lt;1). We then simulated all possible combinations of the fitness regimes. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000082-t001">Table 1</xref> sets out the karyotypes with reduced fitness in each regime.</p><table-wrap id="pgen-1000082-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>The finesses of the karyotypes under different forms of selection.</title></caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pgen-1000082-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Karyotype fitness</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Female</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">D</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">J</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">K</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Sexually antagonistic selection</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−<italic>s<sub>m</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−<italic>s<sub>m</sub> d<sub>m</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−<italic>s<sub>m</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−<italic>s<sub>f</sub> d<sub>f</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−<italic>s<sub>f</sub> d<sub>f</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−<italic>s<sub>f</sub></italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Heterozygote disadvantage</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−<italic>s<sub>h</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−<italic>s<sub>h</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Dosage compensation</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−0.5<italic>s<sub>d</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−0.5<italic>s<sub>d</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−0.5<italic>s<sub>d</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−0.5<italic>s<sub>d</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−0.5<italic>s<sub>d</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−<italic>s<sub>d</sub></italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Sex chromosome coadaptation</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−0.5<italic>s<sub>c</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−<italic>s<sub>c</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−<italic>s<sub>c</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−0.5<italic>s<sub>c</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−0.5<italic>s<sub>c</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−0.5<italic>s<sub>c</sub></italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1−<italic>s<sub>c</sub></italic></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>If more than one form of selection was acting, the values in the corresponding columns were multiplied. The forms of section shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g004">Figure 4</xref> correspond to the following:</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><p><bold><italic>w<sub>♂ (AU·)</sub></italic></bold>&lt;1≡<italic>s<sub>m</sub></italic> = 0.1, <italic>s<sub>f</sub></italic> = 0, <italic>d<sub>m</sub></italic> = 1; <bold><italic>w<sub>♀(Y·)</sub></italic></bold>&lt;1≡<italic>s<sub>m</sub></italic> = 0.1, <italic>s<sub>f</sub></italic> = 0, <italic>d<sub>m</sub></italic> = 1; <bold><italic>w<sub>♀(FU)</sub></italic></bold>&lt;1≡<italic>s<sub>h</sub></italic> = 0.1.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Having determined the basic patterns produced by the different fitness regimes, we assessed the spread of the neo-XY system throughout the possible parameter range shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3</xref>. The simulations were run until fixation or until 10 000 generations. We explored the full range of values for <italic>s<sub>f</sub></italic> and <italic>s<sub>m</sub></italic> in the presence of selection against chromosomal heterozygotes, which was set to that estimated in <italic>P. pedestris</italic> of <italic>s<sub>h</sub></italic> = 0.01 (fitnesses specified in the first and second rows of <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000082-t001">Table 1</xref>, combined multiplicatively). The dominance of the sexually antagonistic selection (<italic>d<sub>m</sub></italic> and <italic>d<sub>f</sub></italic> in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000082-t001">Table 1</xref>) was varied: from <italic>d<sub>m</sub> = </italic>1 or 0.5 for the male effect (not zero since recessive male-beneficial alleles would have had no advantage on the Y), and <italic>d<sub>f</sub></italic> = 1, 0.5 or 0 for the female effect. In addition to these forms of selection, we also considered the possibility that there had also been evolution of coadaptation or dosage compensation between the sex chromosomes in the established neo-XY and XO populations, giving rise to the fitnesses in the last two rows of <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000082-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>The model zone width was converted to values that could be observed in the field using the relationship <italic>σ</italic><sup>2</sup> = <italic>mD<sup>2</sup>,</italic> were <italic>σ</italic><sup>2</sup> is the variance in parent-offspring dispersal and is a measure of migration. For <italic>P. pedestris</italic>, it has been estimated by mark-release-recapture experiments to be 400 m<sup>2</sup> per generation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Barton1">[35]</xref>. The value <italic>D</italic> represents the distance in the field equivalent to that between adjacent simulated populations. Since the simulated migration rate, <italic>m,</italic> was 0.16, the real hybrid zone width of 800 m <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Hewitt2">[34]</xref> is equivalent to the distance between 16 simulated populations.</p><p>When all fitnesses were set to one, the simulated width of the zone increased with time–matching the neutral expectation <italic>w</italic> = 2.51<italic>σ√t</italic>, where <italic>w</italic> is the width, <italic>σ</italic> is the parent-offspring dispersal per generation and <italic>t</italic> is time in generations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Endler1">[36]</xref> (results not shown). Similarly, in the case <italic>w<sub>♀(FU)</sub></italic>&lt;1, the simulated width of the fusion cline fitted analytical expectations, as long as the female-specific nature of selection was taken into account (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Results</xref>). The program to simulate the structured populations was written in Java and the full source is available from the authors upon request.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3B</xref> shows the neo-XY chromosomes can invade an ancestral XO population when they are introduced at low frequency, if there is strong sexually antagonistic selection (the central area of the Figure). The spread of the fused X (the neo-X) was accompanied by fixation of the <bold><italic>a</italic></bold> allele. The model included weak selection against females heterozygous for the fusion, hence the fusion was selected against when rare. Consequently there were combinations of low to moderate selection (i.e. around (1,1)) for which the fusion did not spread. This failure to spread occurred irrespective of the dominance of the <bold><italic>a</italic></bold> allele in males, or the <bold><italic>b</italic></bold> allele in females (results not shown).</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g004">Figure 4</xref> summarizes the various outcomes of the simulated meeting between the two chromosomal races to form a hybrid zone. The relative frequency of the fusion has been plotted as against distance along the array of populations. This relative frequency was calculated as <italic>f<sub>f</sub>/(f<sub>f</sub> + f<sub>u</sub>)</italic>, where <italic>f<sub>i</sub></italic> specifies the frequency of the chromosome of type <italic>i</italic>∈{f, u, Y, Au}, representing fused X, unfused X, Y and autosome respectively. Similarly, the frequency of the Y was calculated as <italic>f<sub>Y</sub>/(f<sub>Y</sub> + f<sub>Au</sub>)</italic>. Note that the denominator increases with <italic>f<sub>u</sub></italic>, since unfused individuals carry more of these chromosome (i.e. more Au and/or Ys, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Once the two races meet, gene flow produces a sigmoidal transition in the frequency of the fused X and the Y-chromosomes. For some parameter values the Y cline or the fusion cline spread as a wave of advance, indicated by arrows in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g002">Figure 2</xref>, in other cases the clines were stable or decayed (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Discussion</xref>).</p><fig id="pgen-1000082-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Summary of the simulation results for the Y and fusion clines.</title><p>The selection is described according to the genotype with reduced fitness (<italic>w<sub>♂(AU·)</sub></italic>, <italic>w<sub>♀(Y·)</sub></italic>, <italic>w<sub>♀(FU)</sub></italic>) as set out in the first row of <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000082-t001">Table 1</xref>. In the particular examples illustrated here the fitness was reduced by setting the selection coefficent (<italic>s<sub>m</sub>, or s<sub>f</sub>)</italic> to 0.1 (with <italic>d<sub>m</sub> = d<sub>f</sub> = </italic>1). The only exceptions are in the upper two panels, in which case the extreme selection coefficient was set to 0.9.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.g004" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><p>Existing analytical models do not describe much of this behaviour, but there are well known results for the case of heterozygote disadvantage <italic>w<sub>♀(FU)</sub></italic>&lt;1 under which the fusion cline would assume a fixed position and width. The relationship between the strength of selection (in the range 0.05–0.9) and width (the inverse of the maximum slope <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Barton2">[37]</xref>) closely fitted the expected relationship <italic>w = √</italic>8<italic>σ/√s</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Bazykin1">[38]</xref> as long as the selection coefficient, <italic>s</italic>, was multiplied by 2/3 to compensate for selection acting on females only (r<sup>2</sup>&gt;99.99%, regression coefficient = 1.016).</p><p>The examples in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g004">Figure 4</xref>, in which the neo-XY system spreads (upper two panels), involve strong sexually antagonistic selection–chosen to clearly illustrate the qualitative difference in outcome from single population models (in which it did not for these values). The neo-XY system spreads even when there is strong selection against the Y in females.</p><p>We investigated the rate of spread of the neo-XY system under less severe selection (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000082-t002">Table 2</xref>). Selection against the X chromosome heterozygotes of 1% (<italic>s<sub>h</sub></italic> = 0.01) slowed down the rate of spread slightly (up to 50%), but did not prevent it even when the sexually antagonistic selection was weak (e.g. <italic>s<sub>m</sub> = s<sub>f</sub></italic> = 0.005). Other forms of selection against introgression could both accelerate or retard the rate of spread. We investigated the fitnesses that might be generated by coadaptation and dosage compensation of the sex chromosomes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000082-t001">Table 1</xref>). Both forms of selection accelerated the spread when the selection for the Y in males was greater than the disadvantage in females (<italic>s<sub>m</sub></italic>&gt;<italic>s<sub>f</sub></italic>) and retarded or even slightly reversed the direction of spread under the converse (<italic>s<sub>m</sub></italic>&lt;<italic>s<sub>f</sub></italic>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000082-t002">Table 2</xref>). The effect of dominance was minor over most fitness combinations and the outcomes were qualitatively unaffected. We show the effects of male dominance in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000082-t002">Table 2</xref>, but omit the female for brevity.</p><table-wrap id="pgen-1000082-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>The speed of the fusion cline's advance.</title></caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pgen-1000082-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>D<sub>m</sub></italic></bold><bold> = </bold><bold><italic>D<sub>f</sub></italic></bold><bold> = 0.5</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>D<sub>m</sub></italic></bold><bold> = 1, </bold><bold><italic>D<sub>f</sub></italic></bold><bold> = 0.5</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>m</sub></italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>m</sub></italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>f</sub></italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1950</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>f</sub></italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">800</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1050</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">950</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">650</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">550</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1950</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">650</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">350</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2150</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2150</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">950</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2750</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1750</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1050</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2750</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1750</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1250</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">650</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1250</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">650</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>h</sub></italic></bold><bold> = 0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>m</sub></italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>h</sub></italic></bold><bold> = 0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>m</sub></italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>f</sub></italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>f</sub></italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5750</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1750</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1600</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5950</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2050</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1150</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">900</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1050</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5750</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2050</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3650</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3750</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3950</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">650</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>d</sub></italic></bold><bold> = 0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>m</sub></italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>d</sub></italic></bold><bold> = 0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>m</sub></italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>f</sub></italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6050</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>f</sub></italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3050</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">300</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3150</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1650</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">950</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">300</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3750</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30650</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−100000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−100000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7250</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−13500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10950</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3750</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−33350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3750</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>c</sub></italic></bold><bold> = 0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>m</sub></italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>c</sub></italic></bold><bold> = 0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>m</sub></italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>f</sub></italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−66700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>S<sub>f</sub></italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−66700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">300</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−33300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−13350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2350</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">300</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−12200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">950</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−22250</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2650</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−33300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6550</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">650</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−33300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">650</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−100000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−200000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−25000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7250</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1950</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.9</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−14000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><p>The speed is expressed as the number of generations for the fusion cline to advance 1 Km. The location of the cline centre was output every 50 generations, and speed was estimated as the time taken to reach the end of the array (equivalent to 1 Km in <italic>P. pedestris</italic>). In those cases where the end was not reached within 10000 generations, the speed was estimated from the movement to that time.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In the Introduction we outlined how the fixation of an X-autosome fusion could be explained by selection in favour of sexually antagonistic alleles linked to the fused centromere. Charlesworth and Charlesworth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth3">[26]</xref> have shown that there is net selection in favor of the fusion for fitness combinations that lead to polymorphism at the sexually antagonistic locus: which fall in the central shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3A</xref>. However, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3B</xref> suggests that this form of selection might be readily counteracted, even by a very minor (1%) reduction in the fertility of female fusion heterozygotes, <italic>w</italic><sub>♀<italic>(FU)</italic></sub>. In particular, even relatively strong sexually antagonistic selection is overwhelmed: notice that when this additional selection is applied (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3B</xref>) the fusion does not spread for fitness values within 0.15 of the point (1,1) (i.e. selection coefficients of up to 15%) even if they fall within the polymorphic area in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3A</xref>. Selection against female fusion heterozygotes is considered likely because of non-disjunction at meiosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-White3">[21]</xref>, and is indeed suspected to occur in <italic>P. pedestris</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Barton2">[37]</xref>. In these circumstances, it is easier to envisage the fusion becoming established by genetic drift, than deterministically under the action of selection.</p><p>Whatever the reason for the fusion initially becoming established in one locality, once it is fixed, the A<sub>u</sub> autosome will then be restricted to males, and would consequently have become a neo-Y. The subsequent evolution of the sex chromosomes would therefore take a course that would at first sight seem to make the spread of the neo-XY system even more unlikely. In particular the neo-Y is expected to accumulate further sexually antagonistic effects, which would in turn select for the loss of recombination, and its eventual degeneration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth1">[1]</xref>. The selection acting would therefore be stronger (further away from the point (1,1) in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3B</xref>) and for the most part this would lead to even stronger selection to eliminate the neo-XY system: only if selection is strong and of similar order in males and females (the triangular area) would selection favour its spread.</p><p>The model illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3B</xref> assumes a small starting number of neo-XY individuals. Remarkably, the outcome is completely overturned if the XO and neo-XY populations are assumed to meet in a hybrid zone. The spread of the neo-XY system would actually be driven by the selection regimes that lead to its elimination in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3B</xref>.</p><sec id="s4a"><title>Understanding the Simulations of a Hybrid Zone</title><p>It may be simplest to start interpreting the results using the biologically unrealistic case of selection only against females containing Y-chromosomes, <italic>w</italic><sub>♀<italic>(Y·)</italic></sub>&lt;1. Since only females with an unfused X chromosome can contain a Y, this regime leads to selection against them, causing the fusion cline to advance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g004">Figure 4</xref>, <italic>w</italic><sub>♀<italic>(Y·)</italic></sub>&lt;1). However, in the absence of other selection, this effect is transient since the direct selection on the Y removes it from populations containing unfused chromosomes. In other words, the autosome (A<sub>u</sub>) advances because it is favoured by selection. The Y persists only in the heartlands of the fused chromosome range, because there it experiences no disadvantage because it cannot enter females.</p><p>There is a comparable indirect effect on the fusion in the case of selection only in favour of Y-chromosomes in males, <italic>w</italic><sub>♂<italic>(Au·)</italic></sub>&lt;1. In populations that are polymorphic (for Y/A<sub>u</sub>), unfused males are more likely to contain at least one advantageous Y because they have double the number of these chromosomes (in fused males, the X replaces one of them). Hence <italic>w</italic><sub>♂<italic>(Au·)</italic></sub>&lt;1 results in selection against the fusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g004">Figure 4</xref>, <italic>w</italic><sub>♂<italic>(Au·)</italic></sub>).</p><p>We can extend these explanations to the most interesting and biologically relevant result–the wave of advance for both the Y and the fusion clines under sexually antagonistic selection (<italic>w</italic><sub>♂<italic>(Au·)</italic></sub>&lt;1 &amp; <italic>w</italic><sub>♀<italic>(Y·)</italic></sub>&lt;1). When the selection against the Y in females is stronger, the Y-chromosome tends to be removed from the fusion cline as under <italic>w</italic><sub>♀<italic>(Y·)</italic></sub>&lt;1. However, as the fusion advances (for the same reason as under <italic>w</italic><sub>♀<italic>(Y·)</italic></sub>&lt;1) the Y follows behind, up to the margins of the fusion cline, thereby indefinitely maintaining the selection for the advance of the fusion. Note that this neo-XY success depends on the gene flow continually bringing the Y-chromosomes into the zone, which is why it did not occur in the single partially isolated population of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3B</xref>.</p><p>The neo-XY system also spread when there is a net advantage to the Y (under sexually antagonistic selection). However, in this case, the Y spreads as a traveling wave ahead of the fusion cline. The fused X will also spread because, as the Y becomes common, the selection against unfused females gets stronger whereas the benefit to unfused males is reduced (since both fused and unfused males tend to carry the favourable Ys once they become common).</p><p>The observed speed of spread of the fusion was relatively small compared to dispersal: the fastest being equivalent to 450 generations to move 1 km in <italic>P. pedestris</italic>, or 1/10th of the dispersal distance per generation. It would be difficult to observe by repeated sampling, but would cause consistent movement over evolutionary time. In addition, the sexually antagonistic effects could increase in magnitude with time, because newly evolved sexually antagonistic alleles arising in within the neo-XY range would be expected to spread until they met the hybrid zone.</p><p>We consider the forms of dominance in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1000082-t002">Table 2</xref> to be most likely, although we have explored other combinations and found no qualitatively different outcomes. Dominant male beneficial effects would fix faster initially, making them more likely to evolve, however such alleles could spread in XO or neo-XY populations, so they need not be restricted to the neo-XY race; hence there could be a range of dominance for male beneficial effects. The first female deleterious effects on the Y would probably be due to loss of function mutations, and would therefore be less than fully dominant because the functional ancestral allele would still be present.</p><p>In addition to heterozygote disadvantage we also considered alternative forms of selection that might act against recombinant karyotypes in the hybrid zone. As long as these additional effects are of the same order as the sexually antagonistic selection, the results are essentially unchanged. It is, of course, possible to find some fitness combinations that slow down, or even slight reverse the spread, and it could be counter-acted by assymetrical gene flow (e.g. due to a density gradient <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Hewitt2">[34]</xref>) or other selection (e.g. due to change in the environment). However, Rice's experiments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Rice1">[28]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Rice3">[30]</xref> suggest that the alleles with large sexually antagonistic effects are segregating in natural populations, so we would expect their effects to predominate in the zone as soon as it was formed. If this interpretation is correct, more detailed analysis of hybrid zones should provide additional evidence of this sexually antagonistic selection (see below).</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Strong Selection Can Produce Broad Clines</title><p>Interestingly, strong selection on the Y chromosome resulted in a broad fusion cline (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g004">Figure 4</xref>). The result emphasizes that the width of the cline in the character for which the hybrid zone was originally discovered, need not indicate the strength of selection. In fact the term “hybrid zone” can be misleading in these cases; it is preferable to refer to different clines. The broad fusion cline in the presence of strong selection is particularly relevant to the <italic>P. pedestris</italic> hybrid zone, where strong selection is detected in the F<sub>1</sub> in lab crosses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Barton2">[37]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Barton3">[39]</xref> and in the field <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Nichols1">[40]</xref>, yet the fusion cline is much wider than expected from the observed selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Hewitt3">[41]</xref>. Previously, this discrepancy has been explained by a model in which selection is spread over many loci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Hewitt3">[41]</xref> only some of which need be linked to the fusion, but our results offer an alternative possibility: that the action of the selection is indirect and due to the well understood initial events in sex chromosome evolution.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Sex Chromosome Hybrid Zones as Natural Sex Chromosome Evolution Experiments</title><p>One implication of the results is that sex chromosome hybrid zones are a valuable, yet unexploited, source of information on early sex chromosome evolution. We suggest that it will be rewarding to obtain markers that distinguish the Y-chromosome from its homologous autosome (A<sub>u</sub> in our notation) and to survey their geographic distribution across known sex chromosome hybrid zones. Often the clines of different characters coincide (have the same centre) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Slatkin1">[42]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Barton4">[43]</xref>, however we would expect them to be displaced in the case of sexually antagonistic selection. Comparing the Y and the fusion cline as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g004">Figure 4</xref> using real hybrid zone data is a robust way to identify the selection regime operating.</p><p>The conventional explanation for a narrow sex chromosome hybrid zone is that there is selection against the chromosomal heterozygotes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Hewitt2">[34]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Barton2">[37]</xref>. In that case there would be a narrow transition for the chromosomal fusion, but the distribution of the Y would be very similar to the neutral case (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g004">Figure 4</xref>, w<sub>♀(FU)</sub>&lt;1 with the neutral case). However, if sexually antagonistic selection is operating, then these two clines will be displaced and the position on the Y cline relative to the fusion cline will indicate the relative strength of male beneficial and female deleterious effects on the Y. For example faster male evolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Wu1">[44]</xref> would be supported if the Y cline were ahead of the fusion. This novel information on the forms of selection affecting young Y-chromosomes in natural populations has not previously been tapped.</p><p>A second indication of sexually antagonistic selection would be cline movement. In some cases it has proved possible to detect the actual movement of hybrid zones by repeated surveys or reviewing museum collections e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Dasmahapatra1">[45]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Dorken1">[46]</xref>. In other cases the movement would be too slow, or held back by barriers to gene flow or gradients in population density <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Barton5">[47]</xref>. It should still prove possible to identify slow or historical movement by surveys of other loci throughout the nuclear and cytoplasmic genome (for a review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Buggs1">[48]</xref>).</p><p>The realisation that surveys of sex chromosome hybrid zones can answer questions relating to the early evolution of sex chromosomes is exciting because such hybrid zones are already known and waiting to be analyzed. Examples include <italic>Drosophila americana</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-McAllister1">[49]</xref>, the morabine grasshopper <italic>Vandiemenella (Warramaba) viatica</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Hewitt1">[25]</xref> and the grasshopper <italic>Podisma pedestris</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Hewitt2">[34]</xref>. A great advantage of hybrid zone studies is that they involve wild populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1000082-Hewitt1">[25]</xref> and some may represent snapshots of the actual establishment of a neo-XY system in nature, thus allowing the testing of theoretical predictions in biologically realistic conditions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material id="pgen.1000082.s001" mimetype="application/rtf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000082.s001" xlink:type="simple"><label>Dataset S1</label><caption><p>Listing of the simulation which generated <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1000082-g003">Figure 3</xref>. It is code which runs in R: the free software environment for statistical computing and graphics.</p><p>(0.04 MB RTF)</p></caption></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful for helpful suggestions from Gabriel Marais, Andrew Leitch. Three anonymous reviewers and an editor made suggestions that substantially improved the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>The evolution of chromosomal sex determination and dosage compensation.</article-title>             <source>Curr Biol</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>149</fpage>             <lpage>162</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>The degeneration of Y chromosomes.</article-title>             <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>             <volume>355</volume>             <fpage>1563</fpage>             <lpage>1572</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Kondo1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Genomic organization of the sex-determining and adjacent regions of the sex chromosomes of <italic>medaka</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Genome Res</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>815</fpage>             <lpage>826</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Nicolas1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marais</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hykelova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janousek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laporte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>A gradual process of recombination restriction in the evolutionary history of the sex chromosomes in dioecious plants.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>47</fpage>             <lpage>56</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Bachtrog1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachtrog</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Adaptation shapes patterns of genome evolution on sexual and asexual chromosomes in <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Nat Genet</source>             <volume>34</volume>             <fpage>215</fpage>             <lpage>219</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Graves1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>JAM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Evolution of the mammalian Y chromosome and sex-determining genes.</article-title>             <source>J Exp Zool</source>             <volume>281</volume>             <fpage>472</fpage>             <lpage>481</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Carvalho1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Y Chromosome of <italic>D. pseudoobscura</italic> is not homologous to the ancestral <italic>Drosophila</italic> Y.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>307</volume>             <fpage>108</fpage>             <lpage>110</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Steinemann1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinemann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinemann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Enigma of Y chromosome degeneration: Neo-Y and Neo-X chromosomes of <italic>Drosophila miranda</italic> a model of sex chromosome evolution.</article-title>             <source>Genetica</source>             <volume>102/103</volume>             <fpage>409</fpage>             <lpage>420</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Zluvova1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zluvova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janousek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Negrutiu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vyskot</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Comparison of the X and Y chromosome organization in <italic>Silene latifolia</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>170</volume>             <fpage>1431</fpage>             <lpage>1434</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Turner1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Sex chromosomes make their mark.</article-title>             <source>Chromosoma</source>             <volume>114</volume>             <fpage>300</fpage>             <lpage>306</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Emerson1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaessmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Betrán</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Extensive gene traffic on the mammalian X chromosome.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>303</volume>             <fpage>537</fpage>             <lpage>540</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Bone1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bone</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Dosage compensation regulatory proteins and the evolution of sex chromosomes in <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>144</volume>             <fpage>705</fpage>             <lpage>713</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Bachtrog2"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachtrog</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Protein evolution and codon usage bias on the Neo-sex chromosomes of <italic>Drosophila miranda</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>165</volume>             <fpage>1221</fpage>             <lpage>1232</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-White1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>MJD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1960</year>             <article-title>Are there no mammal species with XO males - and if not, why not?</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>94</volume>             <fpage>301</fpage>             <lpage>304</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Larsson1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meller</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Dosage compensation, the origin and the afterlife of sex chromosomes.</article-title>             <source>Chromosome Res</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>417</fpage>             <lpage>431</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-White2"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>MJD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1957</year>             <article-title>Cytogenetics and systematic entomology.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>71</fpage>             <lpage>90</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-John1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1968</year>             <article-title>Patterns and pathways of chromosome evolution within the Orthoptera.</article-title>             <source>Chromosoma</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>40</fpage>             <lpage>74</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Watson1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riggs</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>JAM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Sex chromosome evolution: platypus gene mapping suggests that part of the human X chromosome was orignally autosomal.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>88</volume>             <fpage>11256</fpage>             <lpage>11260</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Graves2"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>JAM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>The origin and function of the mammalian Y chromosome and Y-borne genes - an evolving understanding.</article-title>             <source>BioEssays</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>311</fpage>             <lpage>320</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Carvalho2"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Origin and evolution of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> Y chromosome.</article-title>             <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>664</fpage>             <lpage>668</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-White3"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>MJD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1973</year>             <source>Animal cytology and evolution</source>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>961</fpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-White4"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>MJD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1978</year>             <source>Modes of speciation</source>             <publisher-loc>San Francisco</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>W. H. Freeman</publisher-name>             <fpage>455</fpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Shaw1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1980</year>             <article-title>Chromosomal reorganization, geogaphic differentiation and the mechanism of speciatin in the genus <italic>Caledia</italic>.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Insect Cytogenetics</source>             <publisher-name>Blackwell Scientific Publications Ltd</publisher-name>             <fpage>171</fpage>             <lpage>194</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Lande1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1979</year>             <article-title>Effective deme sizes during long-term evolution estimated from rates of chromosomal rearrangement.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>234</fpage>             <lpage>251</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Hewitt1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>Hybrid zones-natural laboratories for evolutionary studies.</article-title>             <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>158</fpage>             <lpage>167</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth3"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1980</year>             <article-title>Sex differences and selection for centric fusions between sex-chromosomes and autosomes.</article-title>             <source>Genet Res</source>             <volume>35</volume>             <fpage>205</fpage>             <lpage>214</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Charlesworth4"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Inbreeding, heterozygote advantage and the evolution of neo-X and neo-Y sex chromosomes.</article-title>             <source>Proc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>             <volume>266</volume>             <fpage>51</fpage>             <lpage>51</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Rice1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Sexually antagonistic male adaptation triggered by experimental arrest of female evolution.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>381</volume>             <fpage>232</fpage>             <lpage>234</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Rice2"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Male fitness increases when females are eliminated from gene pool: Implications for the Y chromosome.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>95</volume>             <fpage>6217</fpage>             <lpage>6221</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Rice3"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>The accumulation of sexually antagonistic genes as a selective agent promoting the evolution of reduced recombination between primitive sex chromosomes.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>41</volume>             <fpage>911</fpage>             <lpage>914</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-R1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">R development Core Team</collab>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria. ISBN 3-900051-07-0.</article-title>             <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.R-project.org</ext-link>. Accessed 27 April 2008</comment>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-John2"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1970</year>             <article-title>Inter-population sex chromosome polymorphism in the grasshopper <italic>Podisma pedestris</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Chromosoma</source>             <volume>31</volume>             <fpage>291</fpage>             <lpage>308</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Dallas1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dallas</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dover</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>Interracial rDNA variation in the grasshopper <italic>Podisma pedestris</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>660</fpage>             <lpage>674</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Hewitt2"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1975</year>             <article-title>A sex chromosome hybrid zone in the grasshopper <italic>Podisma pedestris</italic> (Orthoptera: Acrididae).</article-title>             <source>Heredity</source>             <volume>35</volume>             <fpage>375</fpage>             <lpage>387</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Barton1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1982</year>             <article-title>A measurement of dispersal in the grasshopper <italic>Podisma pedestris</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Heredity</source>             <volume>48</volume>             <fpage>237</fpage>             <lpage>249</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Endler1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Endler</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1977</year>             <source>Geographic variation, speciation, and clines</source>             <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ.</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>455</fpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Barton2"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>The genetic basis of hybrid inviability in the grasshopper <italic>Podisma pedestris</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Heredity</source>             <volume>47</volume>             <fpage>367</fpage>             <lpage>383</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Bazykin1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bazykin</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1969</year>             <article-title>Hypothetical mechanism of speciation.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>685</fpage>             <lpage>687</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Barton3"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1980</year>             <article-title>The fitness of hybrids between two chromosomal races of the grasshopper <italic>Podisma pedestris</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Heredity</source>             <volume>45</volume>             <fpage>47</fpage>             <lpage>59</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Nichols1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>Genetical and ecological differentiation across a hybrid zone.</article-title>             <source>Ecol Entomol</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>39</fpage>             <lpage>49</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Hewitt3"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1980</year>             <article-title>The structure and maintenance of hybid zones as exemplified by <italic>Podisma pedestris</italic>.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Insect Cytogenetics</source>             <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>The Royal Entomological Society</publisher-name>             <fpage>149</fpage>             <lpage>169</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Slatkin1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slatkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1975</year>             <article-title>Gene flow and selection in a two locus system.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>75</volume>             <fpage>733</fpage>             <lpage>756</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Barton4"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1985</year>             <article-title>Analysis of hybrid zones.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Ecol Syst</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>113</fpage>             <lpage>148</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Wu1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C-I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palopoli</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Haldane's rule and its legacy: why are there so many sterile males?</article-title>             <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>281</fpage>             <lpage>284</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Dasmahapatra1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasmahapatra</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aiello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hackwel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Inferences from a rapidly moving hybrid zone.</article-title>             <source>Evolution</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>741</fpage>             <lpage>753</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Dorken1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorken</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pannell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>The maintenance of hybrid zones across a disturbance gradient.</article-title>             <source>Heredity</source>             <volume>99</volume>             <fpage>89</fpage>             <lpage>101</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Barton5"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Adaptation, speciation and hybrid zones.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>341</volume>             <fpage>497</fpage>             <lpage>503</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-Buggs1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buggs</surname><given-names>RJA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Empirical study of hybrid zone movement.</article-title>             <source>Heredity</source>             <volume>99</volume>             <fpage>301</fpage>             <lpage>312</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1000082-McAllister1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McAllister</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Chromosomal and allelic variation in <italic>Drosophila americana</italic>: selective maintenance of a chromosomal cline.</article-title>             <source>Genome</source>             <volume>45</volume>             <fpage>13</fpage>             <lpage>21</lpage>          </element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>