<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS Genetics</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PGENETICS-D-14-03320</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Pelle Modulates dFoxO-Mediated Cell Death in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Pelle Modulates dFoxO-Mediated Cell Death</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Chenxi</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Yujun</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Feng</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Changyan</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Shiping</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Chaojie</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Wenzhe</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Shian</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Xue</surname>
<given-names>Lei</given-names>
</name>
<xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Interventional Radiology, Shanghai 10th People's Hospital, Shanghai Key Laboratory of Signaling and Disease Research, School of Life Science and Technology, Tongji University, Shanghai, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Medicinal Chemical Biology and College of Life Sciences, Nankai University, Tianjin, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Perrimon</surname>
<given-names>Norbert</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Harvard Medical School, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CW LX. Performed the experiments: CW YC FW CC SZ CL WL. Analyzed the data: CW SW LX. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CW YC FW. Wrote the paper: CW LX.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">lei.xue@tongji.edu.cn</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>16</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>10</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<elocation-id>e1005589</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>15</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2014</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>17</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Wu et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589" xlink:type="simple"/>
<abstract>
<p>Interleukin-1 receptor-associated kinases (IRAKs) are crucial mediators of the IL-1R/TLR signaling pathways that regulate the immune and inflammation response in mammals. Recent studies also suggest a critical role of IRAKs in tumor development, though the underlying mechanism remains elusive. Pelle is the sole <italic>Drosophila</italic> IRAK homolog implicated in the conserved Toll pathway that regulates Dorsal/Ventral patterning, innate immune response, muscle development and axon guidance. Here we report a novel function of <italic>pll</italic> in modulating apoptotic cell death, which is independent of the Toll pathway. We found that loss of <italic>pll</italic> results in reduced size in wing tissue, which is caused by a reduction in cell number but not cell size. Depletion of <italic>pll</italic> up-regulates the transcription of pro-apoptotic genes, and triggers caspase activation and cell death. The transcription factor dFoxO is required for loss-of-<italic>pll</italic> induced cell death. Furthermore, loss of <italic>pll</italic> activates dFoxO, promotes its translocation from cytoplasm to nucleus, and up-regulates the transcription of its target gene <italic>Thor/4E-BP</italic>. Finally, Pll physically interacts with dFoxO and phosphorylates dFoxO directly. This study not only identifies a previously unknown physiological function of <italic>pll</italic> in cell death, but also shed light on the mechanism of IRAKs in cell survival/death during tumorigenesis.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary">
<title>Author Summary</title>
<p>In the present study we report a Toll pathway independent function of Pll in modulating apoptotic cell death. Our major findings include: 1) loss of <italic>pll</italic> generates Toll pathway-independent wing phenotypes, which are caused by a reduction in cell number but not cell size; 2) depletion of <italic>pll</italic> up-regulates the transcription of pro-apoptotic genes <italic>hid</italic>, <italic>reaper</italic> and <italic>grim</italic>, and triggers caspase-mediated cell death, whereas cell proliferation remains unaffected; 3) <italic>pll</italic> modulates caspase activation and cell death through the transcription factor dFoxO; 4) loss of <italic>pll</italic> promotes dFoxO translocation from cytoplasm to nucleus, and activates the transcription of dFoxO target gene <italic>Thor/4E-BP</italic>; 5) Pll physically interacts with dFoxO and phosphorylates dFoxO directly. Thus, this work characterizes a previously unknown physiological function of <italic>pll</italic> that is independent of the Toll pathway.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This work is supported by the National Basic Research Program of China (973 Program) (2011CB943903), National Natural Science Foundation of China (31071294, 31171413, 31371490), the Specialized Research Fund for the Doctoral Program of Higher Education of China (20120072110023), and Shanghai Committee of Science and Technology (09DZ2260100, 14JC1406000). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="10"/>
<table-count count="0"/>
<page-count count="27"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Interleukin-1 receptor-associated kinases (IRAKs) are evolutionarily conserved Serine/Threonine (Ser/Thr) kinases that modulates Toll-like receptors (TLRs) and interleukin-1 receptors (IL-1Rs) signaling in the immune and inflammation response [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. IRAKs transduce TLR/IL-1R signals to regulate subcellular distribution and activity of NF<bold>-</bold>κB transcription factor family via highly conserved downstream signaling molecules, including IκB kinase (IκK) complex and IκB [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. While there are four IRAK family members (IRAK-1, IRAK-2, IRAK-4 and IRAK-M) in mammals, Pelle (Pll) is the only IRAK homolog in <italic>Drosophila</italic> [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Although Tube was initially characterized as a <italic>Drosophila</italic> IRAK homolog, it lacks the catalytic domain and thus functions as an adaptor protein in the Toll pathway [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. As such, <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> offers unique opportunities to investigate the physiological functions of IRAK with reduced genetic redundancy.</p>
<p>The Toll pathway in <italic>Drosophila</italic> has been implicated as a crucial regulator in embryonic Dorsal/Ventral (D/V) patterning [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], innate immune response against Gram-positive bacteria and fungi [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], proper muscle development and axon guidance [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. This pathway is equivalent to the mammalian IL-1R/TLR pathway, with Toll/Cactus/Dorsal representing the respective homologs of IL-1R/IκB/NF<bold>-</bold>κB [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, the <italic>Drosophila</italic> IκK is not involved in the Toll pathway [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], and Pll has been shown to be the only kinase implicated in Cactus phosphorylation [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Besides its role in the conserved pathway, it remains unknown whether Pll performs any Toll pathway independent functions <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p>
<p>Programmed cell death (PCD) or apoptosis is an important physiological regulator for tissue homeostasis and correct development. Cancer cells generally obtain the ability to evade cell death signaling pathways, which act as a protective tumor suppressive mechanism to remove damaged cells from the tissue. The central roles of caspases (<underline>c</underline>ysteine <underline>asp</underline>artate-specific protein<underline>ases</underline>) have been widely studied in the context of apoptosis, and the core machinery of caspases signaling pathway, including the initiator caspases and the effector caspases, has been conserved throughout evolution [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In <italic>Drosophila</italic>, apoptosis is activated by the intrinsic and extrinsic cell death signals through transcriptional up-regulation of three pro-apoptotic genes <italic>reaper</italic> (<italic>rpr</italic>), <italic>head involution defective</italic> (<italic>hid</italic>) and <italic>grim</italic> [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Rpr, Hid and Grim (RHG) proteins subsequently bind to and antagonize the <italic>Drosophila</italic> inhibitor of apoptosis protein 1 (DIAP1), which in turn dampens caspases [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. DIAP1 functions as an E3-ubiquitin ligase to block cell death by targeting the initiator caspase Dronc (<italic>Drosophila</italic> caspase-9) for degradation, and thus suppresses the activation of the downstream effector caspase Drice (<italic>Drosophila</italic> caspase-3) [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Hence, apoptosis is the consequence of a train of complex interactions between RHG proteins, DIAP1 and caspases in <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</p>
<p>Forkhead Box O (FoxO) transcription factors were originally identified in C. <italic>elegans</italic> as DAF-16 for its role in aging, and have been highly conserved in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (dFoxO) and mammals (FoxO1, FoxO3a, FoxO4 and FoxO6) [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. FoxO proteins are known to modulate various physiological processes including cell proliferation and differentiation, DNA repair, apoptosis, metabolism, oxidative stress and lifespan [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In general, the multiple functions of FoxO transcription factors are regulated by various post-translational modifications (PTMs), including methylation, acetylation, ubiquitination, glycosylation and phosphorylation [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. For example, FoxOs are targeted for phosphorylation by a number of kinases in response to different cellular stresses, which in turn regulate the nuclear-cytoplasmic shuttling of FoxOs and their transcriptional activity [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In <italic>Drosophila</italic>, dFoxO was reported as a key modulator in the UV-induced caspase-mediated apoptotic response by directly regulating the expression of pro-apoptotic gene <italic>hid</italic> [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p>
<p>In this study, we examined the physiological function of <italic>pelle</italic> (<italic>pll</italic>) in <italic>Drosophila</italic> development, and found that <italic>pll</italic> negatively regulates FoxO-mediated apoptotic cell death <italic>in vivo</italic>. First, loss of <italic>pll</italic> in the developing wing generates Toll/NF<bold>-</bold>κB pathway independent phenotypes, which are caused by a reduction in cell number but not cell size. Secondly, depletion of <italic>pll</italic> triggers caspase-mediated cell death, whereas cell proliferation remains unaffected. Thirdly, <italic>pll</italic> modulates caspase activation and cell death through dFoxO. Fourthly, loss of <italic>pll</italic> results in activation of dFoxO, as manifested by its translocation from cytoplasm to nucleus and the expression of its target gene <italic>Thor/4E-BP</italic>. Finally, Pll physically interacts with and phosphorylates on dFoxO, which likely contributes to the cytoplasmic retention of dFoxO. Therefore, we have identified a previously uncharacterized physiological function of <italic>pll</italic> in cell death, which is independent of the canonical Toll/NF<bold>-</bold>κB pathway.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Loss of <italic>pll</italic> produces Toll pathway-independent wing phenotype</title>
<p>As a crucial component of the Toll pathway, Pll is known to regulate the dorsal-ventral polarity in early embryos [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and the immune response in fat body [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Despite its ubiquitous lower level expression throughout development [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], the post-embryonic functions of Pll remain poorly understood. To explore the physiological function of <italic>pll</italic> in late development, we employed the UAS/Gal4 binary system to knockdown <italic>pll</italic> in a specific temporal and spatial manner. We found that expression of a <italic>pll</italic> RNA interference (RNAi) driven by <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 (<italic>ptc&gt;pll-IR</italic>) along the anterior/posterior (A/P) compartment boundary resulted in a consistent loss of <underline>a</underline>nterior <underline>c</underline>ross-<underline>v</underline>ein (ACV) phenotype (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1C and 1M</xref>), compared with <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 control (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A</xref>) or RFP expression (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>). To exclude the possibility that the phenotype is a result of RNAi’s off-target effect, we examined two additional <italic>pll</italic> RNAi that target distinct regions of the <italic>pll</italic> transcript, and observed the same loss-of-ACV phenotype (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1A, S1F and S1H Fig</xref>). In addition, this phenotype could be rescued by expression of Pll (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1D and 1M</xref>; <xref rid="pgen.1005589.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1G and S1H Fig</xref>), which by itself has no effect on ACV development (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1E and 1M</xref>). The knock-down efficiencies of three <italic>pll</italic> RNAi lines were verified by their abilities to suppress the <italic>GMR</italic>&gt;Pll rough eye phenotype (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2A–S2E Fig</xref>) and by real-time quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) assay (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2L Fig</xref>). To further verify the physiological function of <italic>pll</italic> in ACV development, we examined two <italic>pll</italic> mutant alleles: <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> and <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup>. While the heterozygous mutants show no obvious ACV defect, they could significantly increase the percentage of loss-of-ACV phenotype in the <italic>ptc&gt;pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>W</italic></sup> background (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1A–S1E and S1H Fig</xref>). Together these data suggest that <italic>pll</italic> is physiologically required for ACV development in <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005589.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Loss of <italic>pll</italic> produces Toll/NF-κB pathway independent wing phenotype.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>-<bold>L</bold>) Light micrographs showing <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings, anterior is to the left and distal up. Compared with <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 control (<bold>A</bold>), expression of <italic>pll</italic> RNAi (<italic>pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>) induced a loss-of-ACV phenotype (<bold>C</bold>) that was rescued by expression of Pll (<bold>D</bold>), while expression of Pll alone showed no obvious defects (<bold>E</bold>). Expression of RFP was included as a negative control (<bold>B</bold>). Down-regulation of Toll/NF<bold>-</bold>κB pathway by expressing RNAi of <italic>Toll</italic> (<bold>F</bold>), <italic>tube</italic> (<bold>G</bold>), <italic>dorsal</italic> (<bold>I</bold>) or <italic>Dif</italic> (<bold>J</bold>), or the negative regulator Cactus (<bold>H</bold>), had no effect on wing development. <italic>ptc&gt;pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> was not rescued by co-expressing a <italic>cactus</italic> RNAi (<bold>K</bold> and <bold>L</bold>). The lower panels show high magnification view of the ACV area, boxed in panel A, in upper panels. (<bold>M</bold>) Quantification of the ACV phenotype as shown in figures <bold>A</bold>-<bold>L</bold>. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). ns stands for not significant. Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/+ (B) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS</italic>-RFP/+ (C) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (D) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll; (E) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+ (F) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-Toll-IR</italic>/+ (G) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-tube-IR</italic>/+ (H) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS</italic>-Cactus (I) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-dorsal-IR</italic>/+ (J) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-Dif-IR</italic>/+ (K) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-cactus-IR</italic>/+ (L) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS-cactus-IR</italic>/+.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Pll has been implicated in the Toll/NF<bold>-</bold>κB pathway that directly phosphorylates the <italic>Drosophila</italic> IκB factor Cactus [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. To examine whether the Toll/NF<bold>-</bold>κB pathway is required for the development of ACV, we down-regulated the pathway by knocking-down the positive regulators such as <italic>Toll</italic>, <italic>tube</italic>, <italic>dorsal</italic> and <italic>Dif</italic>, or ectopically expressing the negative regulator Cactus. At least two independent RNAi lines were tested for each gene, including a previously reported RNAi for <italic>Toll</italic> [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and <italic>tube</italic> [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The knock-down efficacies of the RNAi lines were verified by their ability to suppress the rough eye phenotype of <italic>GMR</italic>&gt;Toll<sup>10B</sup> (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2F–S2K Fig</xref>), which expresses the activated form of Toll in the developing eye. Intriguingly, down-regulation of the Toll/NF<bold>-</bold>κB pathway failed to recapitulate the loss-of-ACV phenotype produced by <italic>ptc&gt;pll-IR</italic> (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1F–1J and 1M</xref>), and this phenotype was not rescued by RNAi inactivation of <italic>cactus</italic> (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1K–1M</xref>), the <italic>Drosophila</italic> I<bold>-</bold>κB homolog, implying that the physiological function of <italic>pll</italic> in wing development is independent of the canonical Toll/NF-κB pathway.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title><italic>pelle</italic> regulates cell number, but not cell size in wing development</title>
<p>To further characterize the physiological function of <italic>pll</italic> in wing development, we knocked down <italic>pll</italic> in distinct regions of the wing disc by using additional wing specific Gal4 drivers: <italic>Optomotor-blind</italic> (<italic>Omb</italic>)-Gal4, <italic>Scalloped</italic> (<italic>Sd)</italic>-Gal4 and <italic>engrailed</italic> (<italic>en</italic>)-Gal4. We noted that loss of <italic>pll</italic> in the distal part (<italic>Omb&gt;pll-IR</italic>), wing pouch (<italic>Sd</italic>&gt;<italic>pll-IR</italic>) or posterior compartment (<italic>en</italic>&gt;<italic>pll-IR</italic>) of the wing disc caused severe reduction in corresponding areas of the adult wing, which were rescued by co-expression of Pll, but not that of GFP (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2A–2N and 2Q</xref>; <xref rid="pgen.1005589.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Fig</xref>), confirming that <italic>pll</italic> is required for proper wing development.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005589.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>pll</italic> regulates cell number, but not cell size in adult wing.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>-<bold>D</bold>, <bold>F</bold>-<bold>I</bold> and <bold>K</bold>-<bold>N</bold>) Light micrographs of <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings are shown, anterior is to the left and distal up. Compared with the Gal4 controls (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>F</bold> and <bold>K</bold>), expression of <italic>pll</italic> RNAi (<italic>pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>) driven by <italic>Omb</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>B</bold>), <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>G</bold>) or <italic>en</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>L</bold>) resulted in reduced wing tissue in the corresponding areas, which were rescued by expression of Pll (<bold>D</bold>, <bold>I</bold> and <bold>N</bold>), but not that of GFP (<bold>C</bold>, <bold>H</bold> and <bold>M</bold>). (<bold>E</bold> and <bold>J</bold>) Quantifications of adult wing size/wild type (WT) ratio are shown for figures <bold>A</bold>-<bold>D</bold> and <bold>F</bold>-<bold>I</bold> respectively (n = 10). One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). (<bold>O</bold> and <bold>P</bold>) Quantifications of cell size (<bold>O</bold>) and cell number (<bold>P</bold>) in wings shown in <bold>K</bold> and <bold>L</bold>. The P/A ratio of cell size showed no difference while that of cell number decreased significantly when <italic>pll</italic> was knocked down in the P compartment by <italic>en</italic>-Gal4. Unpaired t test was used to calculate statistical significance, indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001, n = 10 in each group). (<bold>Q</bold>) Statistic analysis of total size P/A ratio are shown for figures <bold>K-N</bold>. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). ns stands for not significant. Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (B) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+ (C) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>GFP/+ (D) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Pll/+ (F) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (G) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+ (H) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>GFP/+ (I) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Pll/+ (K) <italic>en</italic>-Gal4/+ (L) <italic>en</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (M) <italic>en</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS-</italic>GFP/+ (N) <italic>en</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS-</italic>Pll/+.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>To investigate the underlying mechanism by which loss of <italic>pll</italic> results in reduced wing tissue, we compared the cell number and cell size in the posterior (P) compartment with that in the anterior (A) compartment of the adult wing. We found that when <italic>pll</italic> was specifically knock-down in the P compartment by <italic>en</italic>-Gal4 (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2L</xref>), the P/A ratio of cell size remained unaffected (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2O</xref>), whereas the P/A ratio of cell number and total size decreased significantly (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2P and 2Q</xref>), suggesting that <italic>pll</italic> regulates cell number, but not cell size, in wing development. To further verify this conclusion, we generated <italic>pll</italic> loss-of-function clones in larvae and found that the size of clones, labeled by GFP expression, was significantly smaller than that of wild-type (WT) controls in wing discs (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A–3C</xref>), confirming the role of <italic>pll</italic> in regulating tissue growth. However, the sizes of cells inside the clones (marked by GFP expression) were similar to that of wild-type controls in fat body (FB) and salivary gland (SG) (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3G and 3H</xref>). Furthermore, wing margin bristles in <italic>pll</italic> knock-down clones, marked by loss of the <italic>yellow</italic> (<italic>y</italic>) gene, are not statistically different in size from their wild-type neighbors (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3D–3F</xref>). Together, these data indicate that <italic>pll</italic> modulates tissue growth via regulating cell number but not cell size.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005589.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>pll</italic> regulates cell number but not cell size in development.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) Fluorescence micrographs of third instar larval wing discs with clones (marked by GFP) expressing no (<bold>A</bold>) or <italic>pll</italic> RNAi (<bold>B</bold>). Clones were induced by heat shock at 37°C for 1 hour and recovered at 25°C for 42 hours. Nuclei were labeled with DAPI (blue). (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of clone size shown in <bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>. Unpaired t test was used to calculate statistical significance, indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001, n = 10 in each group). (<bold>D</bold> and <bold>E</bold>) Clones (marked by y<sup>-</sup>, yellow) expressing no (<bold>D</bold>) or <italic>pll</italic> RNAi (<bold>E</bold>) in adult wing margin bristles, 7 days after induction. (<bold>F</bold>) Quantification of bristle size as shown in <bold>D</bold> and <bold>E</bold>. The ratio of bristle size within clones (Y)/bristle size of internal control (I) remained unchanged when <italic>pll</italic> was knocked down in the clone. (<bold>G</bold> and <bold>H</bold>) Fluorescence micrographs of clones (marked by GFP) expressing <italic>pll</italic> RNAi in third instar larval fat body (FB, <bold>G</bold>) and salivary gland (SG, <bold>H</bold>) 42 hours after induction. Nuclei were labelled with DAPI (blue), cell membranes were stained by anti-Dlg antibody (red). (<bold>I</bold> and <bold>J</bold>) Fluorescence micrographs of wing discs are shown. The P compartment was labelled by GFP, while cell proliferation was detected by anti-pH3 staining (red) (<bold>I’</bold> and <bold>J’</bold>), nuclei were labelled with DAPI (blue). (<bold>K</bold>) Quantification of pH3 positive cells shown in <bold>I</bold> and <bold>J</bold>. The P/A ratio of pH3 positive cells remained unchanged when <italic>pll</italic> was knocked down in the P compartment. ns stands for not significant. For all wing discs, anterior is to the left and dorsal up. Detailed genotypes: (A and D) <italic>y w hs</italic>-Flp/+; <italic>act</italic>&gt;y+&gt;Gal4 <italic>UAS</italic>-GFP/+ (B, E, G, H) <italic>y w hs</italic>-Flp/+; <italic>act</italic>&gt;y+&gt;Gal4 <italic>UAS</italic>-GFP/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (I) <italic>en</italic>-Gal4 <italic>UAS-</italic>GFP/+ (J) <italic>en</italic>-Gal4 <italic>UAS-</italic>GFP/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Loss of <italic>pll</italic> triggers caspase-mediated cell death</title>
<p>Loss of <italic>pll</italic> results in reduced cell number, which could be a consequence of decreased cell proliferation or increased cell death. To distinguish between the two possibilities, we first checked the cell proliferation rate by phospho-Histone H3 (pH3) staining in wing discs. We found that knock-down <italic>pll</italic> in the P compartment of wing discs (<italic>en</italic>&gt;<italic>pll-IR</italic>) did not affect cell proliferation, as the P/A ratio of pH3 positive cells in such discs was not statistically different from that in control discs (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3I–3K</xref>).</p>
<p>Apoptosis plays a crucial role in maintaining tissue homeostasis, making the decision between cell death and survival in response to various intracellular and extracellular stress [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. To examine the role of <italic>pll</italic> in regulating cell death, we performed acridine orange (AO) staining and TdT-mediated dUTP nick end labelling (TUNEL) assay, both are commonly used to detect apoptosis [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. We found that knock-down <italic>pll</italic> in the wing disc resulted in increased AO (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A, 4B, 4E and 4F</xref>; <xref rid="pgen.1005589.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A and 5B</xref>; <xref rid="pgen.1005589.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4A, S4B, S4K and S4L Fig</xref>) and TUNEL staining (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4Q, 4R, 4U and 4V</xref>; <xref rid="pgen.1005589.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4G–S4J Fig</xref>) in the corresponding regions, which were soundly suppressed by the expression of Pll (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4D, 4H, 4T and 4X</xref>), but not that of GFP (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4C, 4G, 4S and 4W</xref>), indicating <italic>pll</italic> negatively regulates cell death in wing development.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005589.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Loss of <italic>pll</italic> elicits apoptotic cell death.</title>
<p>(<bold>A-H</bold>) AO staining of third instar larval wing discs. Compared with controls (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>E</bold>), knock down <italic>pll</italic> along the A/P boundary by <italic>ptc</italic>-gal4 (<bold>B</bold>) or in the wing pouch by <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>F</bold>) triggered cell death in the corresponding areas, which was suppressed by expressing Pll (<bold>D</bold> and <bold>H</bold>), but not GFP (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>G</bold>). (<bold>I-P</bold>) X-Gal staining of a <italic>hid</italic>-LacZ and an <italic>rpr</italic>-LacZ reporters in wing discs. Compared with controls (<bold>I</bold> and <bold>M</bold>), knock down <italic>pll</italic> in the wing pouch induced <italic>hid</italic> (<bold>J</bold>) and <italic>rpr</italic> (<bold>N</bold>) transcription, which was blocked by expressing Pll (<bold>L</bold> and <bold>P</bold>), but not GFP (<bold>K</bold> and <bold>O</bold>). (<bold>Q-X</bold>) TUNEL staining of third instar larval wing discs. Compared with Gal4 controls (<bold>Q</bold> and <bold>U</bold>), knock down <italic>pll</italic> by <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>R</bold>) or <italic>Omb</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>V</bold>) induced cell death in the corresponding areas, which was impeded by expressing Pll (<bold>T</bold> and <bold>X</bold>), but not GFP (<bold>S</bold> and <bold>W</bold>). In all figures, anterior is to the left and dorsal up. Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (B) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (C) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS</italic>-GFP/+ (D) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+ (E and Q) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (F and R) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+ (G and S) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS</italic>-GFP/+ (H and T) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+ (I) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>hid</italic>-LacZ/+ (J) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>hid</italic>-LacZ/+ (K) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>hid</italic>-LacZ/<italic>UAS</italic>-GFP (L) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>hid</italic>-LacZ/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll (M) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>rpr</italic>-LacZ/+ (N) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>rpr</italic>-LacZ/+ (O) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>rpr</italic>-LacZ/<italic>UAS</italic>-GFP (P) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>rpr</italic>-LacZ/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll (U) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (V) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+ (W) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS</italic>-GFP/+ (X) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<fig id="pgen.1005589.g005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g005</object-id>
<label>Fig 5</label>
<caption>
<title>Loss-of-<italic>pll</italic> induces dFoxO-dependent cell death.</title>
<p>Fluorescence micrographs of third instar larval wing discs stained with AO (<bold>A-F</bold>) or anti-Cleaved Caspase-3 (CC-3) antibody (<bold>G-L</bold>), anterior is to the left and dorsal up. Compared with controls (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>G</bold>), loss of <italic>pll</italic> resulted in increased cell death (<bold>B</bold>) and caspase activity (<bold>H</bold>), both of which were suppressed by knocking-down <italic>dFoxO</italic> (<bold>D</bold> and <bold>J</bold>), or deleting one or both copies of endogenous <italic>dFoxO</italic> (<bold>E</bold>, <bold>F</bold>, <bold>K</bold> and <bold>L</bold>). <italic>GFP-IR</italic> was used here as a negative control (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>I</bold>). (<bold>M</bold> and <bold>N</bold>) Quantifications of cell death by AO (<bold>M</bold>) and CC-3 antibody (<bold>N</bold>) staining as shown in figures <bold>A-F</bold> and <bold>G-L</bold> respectively. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). ns stands for not significant. Detailed genotypes: (A and G) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (B and H) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+ (C and I) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS-GFP-IR</italic>/+ (D and J) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS-dFoxO-IR</italic>/+ (E and K) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup>Δ94/+</sup> (F and L) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup>Δ94/Δ94</sup>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Apoptosis in <italic>Drosophila</italic> is triggered by transcriptional up-regulation of three pro-apoptotic genes <italic>rpr</italic>, <italic>hid</italic> and <italic>grim</italic>, and is mediated by the cleavage and activation of caspases [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Consistent with its role in cell death, loss of <italic>pll</italic> in the wing pouch results in up-regulated transcription of <italic>hid</italic> and <italic>rpr</italic> as revealed by X-gal staining of a <italic>hid</italic>-LacZ and an <italic>rpr</italic>-LacZ reporters (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4I, 4J, 4M and 4N</xref>; <xref rid="pgen.1005589.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4C–S4F Fig</xref>), which is suppressed by expressing Pll, but not GFP (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4K, 4L, 4O and 4P</xref>). Furthermore, we found that a ubiquitous knock-down of <italic>pll</italic> (<italic>act&gt;pll-IR</italic>) was able to activate the transcription of endogenous <italic>hid</italic>, <italic>rpr</italic> and <italic>grim</italic>, as compared to the <italic>act</italic>-Gal4 control, via executing a real-time qRT-PCR assay (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4M Fig</xref>). In addition, depletion of <italic>pll</italic> leads to enhanced antibody staining for the activated form of Caspase-3 (CC-3, <xref rid="pgen.1005589.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5G and 5H</xref>), a read-out of the initiator caspase Dronc activity [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Moreover, we found that the loss-of-ACV phenotype induced by <italic>ptc&gt;pll-IR</italic> was suppressed partially by the deficiency <italic>Df(3L)H99</italic> that deletes <italic>rpr</italic>, <italic>hid</italic> and <italic>grim</italic> (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5A–S5C Fig</xref>), and significantly by expressing the inhibitor of apoptosis protein DIAP1 or a dominant-negative form of Dronc (Dronc<sup>DN</sup>), but not LacZ (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>). Accordingly, the phenotype of reduced distal-most area in <italic>Omb</italic>&gt;<italic>pll-IR</italic> wing is considerably rescued by <italic>Df(3L)H99</italic> (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5D–S5F Fig</xref>). Thus, we conclude from these data that depletion of <italic>pll</italic> is sufficient to activate caspase-mediated cell death.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005589.g006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g006</object-id>
<label>Fig 6</label>
<caption>
<title>Depletion of <italic>pll</italic> elicits caspases-dependent cell death in adult wing.</title>
<p>(<bold>A-D</bold>) Light micrographs showing <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings, anterior is to the left and distal up. The loss-of-ACV phenotype in <italic>ptc&gt;pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> flies (<bold>A</bold>) was significantly suppressed by the expression of DIAP1 (<bold>C</bold>) or Dronc<sup>DN</sup> (<bold>D</bold>), but not that of LacZ (<bold>B</bold>), which served as a negative control. The lower panels are high magnification of the boxed areas in upper panels (<bold>A-D</bold>). (<bold>E</bold>) Quantification of the ACV phenotypes as shown in figures <bold>A-D</bold>. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). ns stands for not significant. Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (B) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS</italic>-LacZ/+ (C) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS</italic>-DIAP1/+ (D) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS</italic>-Dronc<sup>DN</sup>/+.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>dFoxO is required for loss-of-<italic>pll</italic> induced cell death</title>
<p>To understand the mechanism by which loss of <italic>pll</italic> induces caspase-dependent cell death, we considered the transcription factor dFoxO as a putative downstream factor negatively regulated by Pll. Firstly, dFoxO is known to be negatively regulated by other kinase, e.g. Akt [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Secondly, previous studies reported that dFoxO is required for the apoptotic response and regulates the expression of pro-apoptotic gene <italic>hid</italic> [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Thirdly, we have previously observed a similar loss-of-ACV phenotype resulted from dFoxO expression driven by <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 driver [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In support of the assumption, we found that loss-of-<italic>pll</italic> triggered cell death in the wing pouch, as detected by AO staining (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B and 5M</xref>) and cleaved caspase-3 (CC-3) antibody (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5H and 5N</xref>), was notably blocked by RNAi-mediated depletion of <italic>dFoxO</italic>, and in heterozygous or homozygous <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup><bold><italic>Δ94</italic></bold></sup> mutants (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5D–5F and 5J–5N</xref>). Furthermore, depletion of <italic>pll</italic> induced various wing defects are suppressed by loss of <italic>dFoxO</italic>, either by mutation or expression of RNAi (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>; <xref rid="pgen.1005589.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6 Fig</xref>). A <italic>GFP</italic> RNAi was employed as a negative control (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5C and 5I</xref>; <xref rid="pgen.1005589.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7C, 7I and 7O</xref>). The knock-down efficiency of <italic>dFoxO</italic> RNAi lines and the <italic>dFoxO</italic> mRNA level in <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup><bold><italic>Δ94</italic></bold></sup> mutants have been previously verified [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Consistently, expression of dFoxO driven by <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 (<italic>ptc</italic>&gt;dFoxO) recapitulates the loss-of-ACV phenotype in <italic>ptc</italic>&gt;<italic>pll-IR</italic> flies (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S7A Fig</xref>). However, the <italic>ptc</italic>&gt;dFoxO triggered loss-of-ACV phenotype cannot be suppressed by co-expressing Pll (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S7B and S7C Fig</xref>), confirming that dFoxO acts downstream of Pll. Therefore, we conclude that loss of <italic>pll</italic> induces dFoxO-dependent cell death in wing development.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005589.g007" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g007</object-id>
<label>Fig 7</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>dFoxO</italic> is required for loss-of-<italic>pll</italic> induced wing phenotypes.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>-<bold>R</bold>) Light micrographs showing <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings, anterior is to the left and distal up. Compared with controls (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>G</bold> and <bold>M</bold>), the wing phenotypes of <italic>ptc</italic>&gt;<italic>pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (<bold>B</bold>), <italic>Sd&gt;pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (<bold>H</bold>) and <italic>Omb&gt;pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (<bold>N</bold>) flies were suppressed by knocking-down <italic>dFoxO</italic> (<bold>D</bold>, <bold>J</bold> and <bold>P</bold>) or removing one or both copies of <italic>dFoxO</italic> (<bold>E</bold>, <bold>F</bold>, <bold>K</bold>, <bold>L</bold>, <bold>Q</bold> and <bold>R</bold>), but not by expressing a <italic>GFP-IR</italic> (<bold>C</bold>, <bold>I</bold> and <bold>O</bold>). In <bold>A</bold>-<bold>F</bold>, the lower panels are high magnification of the boxed areas in upper panels. (<bold>S</bold>-<bold>U</bold>) Statistical analysis of the ACV phenotype (<bold>S</bold>) and the adult wing size/wild type (WT) (<bold>T</bold> and <bold>U</bold>) as shown in figures <bold>A</bold>-<bold>F</bold>, <bold>G</bold>-<bold>L</bold> and <bold>M</bold>-<bold>R</bold> respectively. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). ns stands for not significant. Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (B) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (C) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS-GFP-IR</italic>/+ (D) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS-dFoxO-IR</italic>/+ (E) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup>Δ94/+</sup> (F) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup>Δ94/Δ94</sup> (G) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (H) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+ (I) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS-GFP-IR</italic>/+ (J) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS-dFoxO-IR</italic>/+ (K) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup>Δ94/+</sup> (L) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup>Δ94/Δ94</sup> (M) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (N) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+ (O) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS-GFP-IR</italic>/+ (P) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS-dFoxO-IR</italic>/+ (Q) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup>Δ94/+</sup> (R) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup>Δ94/Δ94</sup>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>pll</italic> is ubiquitously expressed throughout development [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. To investigate whether Pll modulates dFoxO-dependent cell death in other tissues, we knocked down <italic>pll</italic> in the notum by the <italic>pnr</italic>-Gal4 driver, and observed a loss-of-bristle phenotype in the notum (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8A, 8B and 8H</xref>). This phenotype, most likely caused by cell death as expression of the apoptotic gene <italic>reaper</italic> in the notum produces a similar bristle-ablation phenotype [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], is significantly suppressed by expressing a <italic>dFoxO</italic> RNAi, or deleting one or both copies of endogenous <italic>dFoxO</italic>, or expressing Pll, but not a <italic>GFP</italic> RNAi (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8C–8H</xref>). Thus, Pll negatively regulates dFoxO-dependent cell death in a non-tissue-specific manner.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005589.g008" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g008</object-id>
<label>Fig 8</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>dFoxO</italic> is required for loss-of-<italic>pll</italic> induced bristle phenotype on notum.</title>
<p>(<bold>A-G</bold>) Light micrographs showing bristles on the adult notum. Compared with the <italic>pnr</italic>-Gal4 control (<bold>A</bold>), RNAi-mediated depletion of <italic>pll</italic> in notum resulted in reduced bristle number (<bold>B</bold>), which was suppressed by knocking-down <italic>dFoxO</italic> (<bold>D</bold>), deleting one or both copies of endogenous <italic>dFoxO</italic> (<bold>E</bold> and <bold>F</bold>), or expressing Pll (<bold>G</bold>), but not by expressing a <italic>GFP</italic> RNAi that served as a negative control (<bold>C</bold>). The lower panels show high magnification view of the boxed areas in upper panels. (<bold>H</bold>) Quantification of bristles number in the boxed areas from <bold>A-G</bold>. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001, ** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01). ns stands for not significant. Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>pnr-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (B) <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>pnr-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (C) <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>pnr-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-GFP-IR</italic> (D) <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>pnr-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-dFoxO-IR</italic> (E) <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>pnr-</italic>Gal4/<italic>dFoxO</italic><sup><bold><italic>Δ94</italic></bold></sup> (F) <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>pnr-</italic>Gal4 <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup><bold><italic>Δ94</italic></bold></sup>/<italic>dFoxO</italic><sup><bold><italic>Δ94</italic></bold></sup> (G) <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>pnr-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Pll regulates dFoxO subcellular localization and transcriptional activity</title>
<p>To address how Pll modulates dFoxO activity, we first checked whether Pll regulates dFoxO transcription by executing a real-time qRT-PCR assay. We found that a ubiquitous knockdown of <italic>pll</italic> (<italic>act&gt;pll-IR</italic>) did not affect the mRNA level of <italic>dFoxO</italic>, as compared to the <italic>act</italic>-Gal4 control (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9A</xref>), suggesting that <italic>pll</italic> does not regulate dFoxO transcription. Previous studies indicate that the nuclear localization of dFoxO is regulated by a series of post-translational modifications, including phosphorylation by different kinases [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. To examine whether Pll modulates the nuclear-cytoplasmic shuttling of dFoxO, we checked the sub-cellular localization of a <italic>dFoxO</italic>-GFP fusion protein in the fat body. We found that the nuclear localization of <italic>dFoxO</italic>-GFP was significantly increased when <italic>pll</italic> was knocked down in fat body cells by <italic>Cg</italic>-Gal4 (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9B–9D</xref>), which drives Gal4 expression specifically in fat body and hemocytes under the control of collagen (<italic>Cg25C</italic>) promoter [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. To monitor the dFoxO activity directly, we detected the expression of its well-characterized target gene <italic>Thor/4E-BP</italic> by a <italic>Thor-</italic>LacZ reporter [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. We found that <italic>Thor-</italic>LacZ expression was distinctly induced in the wing pouch by RNAi inactivation of <italic>pll</italic> under the control of <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4 (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9E and 9F</xref>). In addition, qRT-PCR assay confirmed that depletion of <italic>pll</italic> resulted in up-regulated <italic>Thor/4E-BP</italic> transcription (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9G</xref>). Thus, we conclude that Pll regulates dFoxO subcellular localization and transcriptional activity.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005589.g009" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g009</object-id>
<label>Fig 9</label>
<caption>
<title>Loss of <italic>pll</italic> promotes dFoxO nuclear localization and transcriptional activity.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Loss of <italic>pll</italic> does not affect the transcription of <italic>dFoxO</italic>. Histogram showing the levels of <italic>dFoxO</italic> mRNAs measured by quantitative RT-PCR. Total RNA of <italic>Drosophila</italic> third instar larvae were extracted and normalized for cDNA synthesis. Error bars represents standard deviation from three independent experiments. ns stands for not significant. (<bold>B-D</bold>) Loss of <italic>pll</italic> promotes nuclear localization of dFoxO. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification of the nuclear/cytoplasmic ratio of <italic>dFoxO</italic>-GFP fusion protein in the fat body shown in <bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>. <italic>dFoxO</italic>-GFP intensities were measured in pixels using Image J. Error bars showed standard deviation from measurement of at least 15 cells for each genotype. Unpaired t test was used to calculate statistical significance, indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>) Fluorescence micrographs of fat body cells are shown. Compared with the control (<bold>C</bold>), loss of <italic>pll</italic> promotes the translocation of <italic>dFoxO</italic>-GFP from cytoplasm to nucleus (<bold>D</bold>). Nuclei were marked with DAPI (blue), cell membranes were stained by anti-Dlg antibody (red). (<bold>E</bold> and <bold>F</bold>) X-Gal staining of a <italic>Thor</italic>-LacZ reporter in third instar larval wing discs. Compared with the control (<bold>E</bold>), knock-down <italic>pll</italic> in the wing pouch induced <italic>Thor</italic> transcription (<bold>F</bold>). (<bold>G</bold>) Loss of <italic>pll</italic> up-regulated the level of <italic>Thor</italic> mRNA, as measured by quantitative RT-PCR. Total RNA of <italic>Drosophila</italic> third instar larvae were extracted and normalized for cDNA synthesis. Error bars represented standard deviation from three independent experiments. Unpaired t test was used to calculate statistical significance, indicated with asterisks (* <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05). Detailed genotypes: (A) Left: <italic>act</italic>-Gal4/+, Right: <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>act</italic>-Gal4/+ (B) Left: <italic>Cg</italic>-Gal4/+, Right: <italic>Cg-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (C) <italic>Cg-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>dFoxO</italic>-GFP/+ (D) <italic>Cg-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>; <italic>dFoxO</italic>-GFP/+ (E) <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>Thor</italic>-LacZ/+ (F) <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>Thor</italic>-LacZ/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (G) Left: <italic>act</italic>-Gal4/+, Right: <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>act</italic>-Gal4/+.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Pll physically interacts with and phosphorylates dFoxO</title>
<p>To investigate the underlying mechanism by which Pll regulates dFoxO activity, we expressed HA-tagged Pll (HA-Pll) and Flag-tagged dFoxO (Flag-dFoxO) in <italic>Drosophila</italic> S2R+ cells, and examined the phosphorylation of dFoxO through Calf Intestine Phosphatase (CIP) assay. We found that co-expression of Pll resulted in a mobility shift of dFoxO, which was abolished upon CIP treatment (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig 10A</xref>), suggesting that dFoxO could be phosphorylated by Pll. Next, we performed the <italic>in vitro</italic> kinase assay to confirm the phosphorylation of dFoxO by Pll. Since Pll could be auto-phosphorylated (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig 10B</xref>), to better distinguish the phosphorylated dFoxO from auto-phosphorylated Pll, we divided the full-length dFoxO (1-622aa) into two segments: the N-terminal (NT, 1-304aa) and the C-terminal (CT, 305-622aa). Indeed, bacterially purified GST-Pll was able to phosphorylate dFoxO <italic>in vitro</italic>, heavily on the NT and lightly on the CT (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig 10B</xref>), suggesting Pll might phosphorylate dFoxO at multiple sites, most of which are located in the N-terminal half of dFoxO. Furthermore, Co-IP assay demonstrated a physical interaction between HA-Pll and Flag-dFoxO in S2R+ cells (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig 10C</xref>). Finally, we performed the GST-pulldown assay and confirmed a direct binding between Pll and dFoxO (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig 10D</xref>). Together, these data suggest that Pll could phosphorylate dFoxO through direct interaction, thus negatively regulates dFoxO activity by preventing its nuclear translocation.</p>
<fig id="pgen.1005589.g010" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g010</object-id>
<label>Fig 10</label>
<caption>
<title>Pll binds to and phosphorylates dFoxO.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>) Expression of Pll induced mobility shift of dFoxO, which was abolished by CIP treatment. Cell lysis was prepared from S2R+ cells expressing Flag<italic>-</italic>dFoxO alone or with HA<italic>-</italic>Pelle, treated with or without calf intestine phosphatase (CIP), followed by western blotting. (<bold>B)</bold> Kinase assay shows Pll phosphorylates the N- and C- terminal parts of dFoxO. (<bold>C</bold>) Co-immunoprecipitation experiment shows dFoxO interacts with Pelle in S2R+ cells. (<bold>D</bold>) GST pull-down assay shows direct binding between bacterially expressed His–dFoxO and GST–Pll <italic>in vitro</italic>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.g010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p><italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> has emerged as an excellent model organism to study apoptotic cell death and has made significant contribution to understand cell death regulation and its role in development. While mammalian IRAKs function as the mediator of IL-1Rs/TLRs signal transduction in the immune and inflammatory responses [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], Pll, the sole <italic>Drosophila</italic> orthologue of IRAKs, has been implicated as a central regulator of Toll pathway involved in embryonic dorsal/ventral patterning, innate immune response, muscle development and axon guidance. In this work, we identified a Toll pathway independent function of Pll in modulating caspase-mediated cell death in animal development.</p>
<p>Previous studies have suggested that <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing vein formation is a result of cell fate specification regulated by multiple signaling pathways including Notch, Hedgehog, EGF (epidermal growth factor) and BMP (bone morphogenetic proteins) pathways [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. In the present study, we found that knock-down <italic>pll</italic> along the A/P compartment boundary of the developing wing (<italic>ptc&gt;pll-IR</italic>) resulted in extensive cell death in the wing disc (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>) and a loss-of-ACV phenotype in the adult wing (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1C</xref>; <xref rid="pgen.1005589.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1A and S1F Fig</xref>), implying a potential role of cell death in vein patterning. Consistent with this notion, the loss-of-ACV phenotype is rescued by blocking apoptotic cell death (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6C–6E</xref>; <xref rid="pgen.1005589.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5B and S5C Fig</xref>), suggesting cell death is responsible for the loss of ACV. To investigate whether cell death is able to impede vein patterning, we initiated apoptosis by expressing the pro-apoptotic protein Grim under the control of <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4. <italic>ptc</italic>&gt;Grim caused extensive cell death in tissue ablation between L3 and L4 in the adult wing. In most cases, L3 and L4 were fused in the proximal area where ACV is located (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s008" ref-type="supplementary-material">S8A Fig</xref>). To adjust Grim expression and cell death, we added <italic>Tub</italic>-Gal80<sup>ts</sup> that represses Gal4 activity in a temperature sensitive manner. At 25°C, <italic>Tub</italic>-Gal80<sup>ts</sup> partially blocks <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4 activity and allows limited Grim expression and therefore, cell death, between L3 and L4. Intriguingly, under this condition, we observed the loss-of-ACV phenotype accompanied by a slight reduction of area between L3 and L4 (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s008" ref-type="supplementary-material">S8B Fig</xref>), suggesting that both reduced area and loss-of-ACV phenotypes are consequences of cell death. From our experience, the loss-of-ACV phenotype is more sensitive to cell death, since weak cell death is sufficient to generate the phenotype, whereas stronger cell death is required to delete tissue between L3 and L4. Consistent with this notion, while <italic>ptc</italic>&gt;<italic>pll-IR</italic> flies reared at 25°C only displayed the loss-of-ACV phenotype (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1C</xref>), those raised at 29°C also showed reduced area between L3 and L4 (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s008" ref-type="supplementary-material">S8D and S8G Fig</xref>), which was caused by a reduction in cell number, but not cell size (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s008" ref-type="supplementary-material">S8E and S8F Fig</xref>).</p>
<p>We show that Pll regulates caspase activation and cell death through dFoxO. Mechanistically, loss of <italic>pll</italic> promotes the nuclear translocation of dFoxO, which otherwise is retained in the cytoplasm by phosphorylation. A number of kinases, including AKT, IκK and JNK, have been reported to phosphorylate FoxO and regulate its nuclear-cytoplasmic trafficking [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Here we provide evidence that Pll is another dFoxO kinase that phosphorylates dFoxO and inhibits its nuclear localization. Thus, it would be very interesting to check whether a similar interaction is conserved between IRAKs and FoxOs in mammal.</p>
<p>The FoxO family proteins have been implicated in multiple important biological processes, including cell death and tumor suppression. It has been reported that conditional deletion of FoxO1, FoxO3 and FoxO4 simultaneously results in the development of hemangiomas and thymic lymphomas [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], and IκB kinase represses FoxO3a activity to promote human breast tumorigenesis and acute myeloid leukemia (AML) [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. IRAKs also show altered expression level in tumors and surrounding stroma [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], and participate in tumor initiation and progression [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], yet the underlying mechanisms remain poorly understood. Thus, the inhibitory effect of Pll on dFoxO activity in <italic>Drosophila</italic> provides a beneficial framework for a better understanding of mammalian IRAKs’ crucial roles in tumor development.</p>
<p>As the Toll/NF<bold>-</bold>κB pathway is not implicated in loss-of-<italic>pll</italic> triggered dFoxO-dependent cell death, we are curious about what are the pathways or factors act upstream of Pll to regulate its role in cell death? Since dFoxO has been reported as a downstream transcription factor in the JNK and Insulin pathways in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s009" ref-type="supplementary-material">S9P Fig</xref>; <xref rid="pgen.1005589.s010" ref-type="supplementary-material">S10O Fig</xref>) [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], we wondered whether Pll is also involved in these pathways. Activation of JNK signaling between L3 and L4 by expressing Egr (<italic>Drosophila</italic> TNF) or Hep (<italic>Drosophila</italic> JNK Kinase), or depleting <italic>puc</italic> (encoding a JNK inhibitor), produced similar loss-of-ACV and reduced area phenotypes as that of <italic>pll</italic> depletion, yet the phenotypes were not affected by gain or loss of <italic>pll</italic> (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s009" ref-type="supplementary-material">S9 Fig</xref>). Inactivation of the Insulin pathway by expressing a dominant negative form of PI3K, or knocking-down <italic>PI3K</italic> or <italic>Akt</italic>, resulted in diminished area between L3 and L4, which remained unaffected by gain or loss of <italic>pll</italic> (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s010" ref-type="supplementary-material">S10 Fig</xref>). We also examined the Hippo pathway known to play a crucial role in regulating cell death and organ size [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Up-regulation of Hippo pathway in distinct wing areas by different Gal4 drivers led to various small wing or wing tissue ablation phenotypes, which were not altered by changing Pll level (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s011" ref-type="supplementary-material">S11 Fig</xref>). Finally, we checked dMyc, the fly homolog of c-Myc that regulates cell growth and cell death in <italic>Drosophila</italic> [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], and the cell polarity gene <italic>scribble</italic> (<italic>scrib</italic>), whose depletion promotes cell death [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. We found that depletion of <italic>dMyc</italic> triggered wing phenotype and loss of <italic>scrib</italic> induced cell death are both independent of Pll (<xref rid="pgen.1005589.s012" ref-type="supplementary-material">S12 Fig</xref>). Thus, while Pll directly regulates dFoxO-mediated caspase-dependent cell death in development, the upstream factors modulating Pll activity remain unknown, which deserve further investigation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Fly strains</title>
<p>All <italic>Drosophila</italic> stocks were raised on a standard cornmeal and agar media, and crosses were performed at 25°C according to standard protocols unless otherwise indicated. <italic>Drosophila</italic> strains used include: <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4, <italic>Omb</italic>-Gal4, <italic>en</italic>-Gal4, <italic>act-</italic>Gal4, <italic>nub</italic>-Gal4, <italic>Cg</italic>-Gal4 (7011), <italic>Tub</italic>-Gal80<sup>ts</sup> (7017), <italic>UAS</italic>-RFP, <italic>UAS</italic>-LacZ, <italic>UAS</italic>-Dcr2, <italic>UAS</italic>-Toll<sup>10B</sup>, <italic>UAS</italic>-Cactus, <italic>UAS</italic>-DIAP1, <italic>UAS</italic>-dFoxO, <italic>UAS</italic>-Grim<sup>M146</sup>, <italic>UAS</italic>-Hep, <italic>UAS-GFP-IR</italic>, <italic>UAS-Toll-IR</italic> (31044, 31447 and 35628), <italic>UAS-dorsal-IR</italic> (27650, 32934 and 34938), <italic>UAS-Dif-IR</italic> (29514 and 30513), <italic>UAS-dFoxO-IR</italic>, <italic>UAS-puc-IR</italic> (3018), <italic>UAS-PI3K-IR</italic> (27690), <italic>Df(3L)H99</italic>, <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup><bold><italic>Δ94</italic></bold></sup>, <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> (3111), <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup> (3112), <italic>dFoxO</italic>-GFP (37585), <italic>hid</italic>-LacZ, <italic>Thor</italic>-LacZ (9558) and <italic>y w hs</italic>-Flp; <italic>act</italic>&gt;y+&gt;Gal4 <italic>UAS</italic>-GFP were obtained from Bloomington stock center, <italic>UAS-pelle-IR</italic> (2889 and 103774), <italic>UAS-dorsal-IR</italic> (45996 and 45998), <italic>UAS-Dif-IR</italic> (30578 and 30579), <italic>UAS-yki-IR</italic> (40497), <italic>UAS-dMyc-IR</italic> (2948) and <italic>UAS-scrib-IR</italic> (27424) were obtained from Vienna <italic>Drosophila</italic> RNAi Center (VDRC), <italic>UAS-tube-IR</italic> (10520R1 and 10520R3), <italic>UAS-dorsal-IR</italic> (6667R2 and 6667R5), <italic>UAS-cactus-IR</italic> (5848R3) and <italic>UAS-Akt-IR</italic> (4006R1) were obtained from Japanese National Institute of Genetics (NIG), <italic>UAS</italic>-Pelle (201696) was obtained from <italic>Drosophila</italic> Genetic Resource Center (DGRC). <italic>GMR</italic>-Gal4 [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], <italic>pnr-</italic>Gal4 [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4 [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], <italic>UAS-pelle-IR</italic><sup><italic>W</italic></sup> [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>], <italic>UAS</italic>-Dronc<sup>DN</sup> [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], <italic>UAS</italic>-GFP [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], <italic>reaper</italic>-LacZ [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>], <italic>UAS</italic>-Egr<sup>W</sup> [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], <italic>UAS</italic>-PI3K<sup>DN</sup> [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], <italic>UAS</italic>-Warts [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>] and <italic>UAS</italic>-Hippo [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>] were previously described.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Immunohistochemistry</title>
<p>Imaginal wing discs dissected from third instar larvae were collected in cold PBS and fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde. After proper washes, the wing discs were blocked in 10% horse serum, and stained with antibodies. The following antibodies were used: rabbit anti-pH3 (1:200 Cell Signaling Technology), rabbit anti-Cleaved Caspase-3 (1:200 Cell Signaling Technology) and mouse anti-Dlg (1:200). Secondary antibodies were anti-rabbit-Alexa (1:1000 Cell Signaling Technology) and anti-mouse-Cy3 (1:1000, Jackson Immuno Research).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>AO staining</title>
<p>Wing discs were dissected from third instar larvae in PBST and incubated in 1×10<sup>−5</sup> M AO for 5 min at room temperature prior to imaging as described [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>X-Gal staining</title>
<p>Wing discs were dissected from third instar larvae in PBST (1×PBS pH 7.0, 0.1% Triton X-100) and stained for ß-galactosidase activity as described [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>TUNEL staining</title>
<p>The wing discs of wandering third-instar were dissected out in PBS. Wing discs were fixed in 4% Paraformaldehyde for 30 min at room temperature (RT) and washed with PBS-Tx (0.3% Triton100) three times for 30 min. TUNEL staining was performed using the Fluorescein Cell Death Kit produced by Boster Company. Imaging of prepared sample was conducted by a Leica confocal microscope (Leica SP5).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>qRT-PCR</title>
<p>Five third instar larvae of indicated genotypes were collected and total RNA was isolated using TRIzol (Invitrogen). qRT-PCR was performed as previously described [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>] using following primers:</p>
<p specific-use="line">For <italic>rp49</italic> Sense: 5’- TACAGGCCCAAGATCGTGAA-3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">            Antisense: 5’- TCTCCTTGCGCTTCTTGGA-3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">For <italic>pelle</italic> Sense: 5’GTGGTAAGCCGTGCCTCGTCTA-3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">            Antisense: 5’-CTGCCAGGTGAGTGCTGGTAGT-3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">For <italic>dFoxO</italic> Sense: 5’- CAATCTCGAGTGCAATGTCGAGGA -3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">            Antisense: 5’-CCCTGAGCATCAGCAACATTAGCA-3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">For <italic>Thor</italic> Sense: 5’-TCGGAGTTTGGATGCTGGGATCTT-3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">            Antisense: 5’-AGTCACGTCGTCCTCATCGTTGTT-3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">For <italic>hid</italic> Sense: 5’-TGCGAAATACACGGGTTCA-3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">            Antisense: 5’-CCAATATCACCCAGTCCCG-3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">For <italic>rpr</italic> Sense: 5’-GAGCAGAAGGAGCAGACGAT-3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">            Antisense: 5’-CGATATTTGCCGGACTTTCT-3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">For <italic>grim</italic> Sense: 5’-TCGGAGTTTGGATGCTGGGATCTT-3’</p>
<p specific-use="line">            Antisense: 5’-AGTCACGTCGTCCTCATCGTTGTT-3’</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Western blotting, co-immunoprecipitation and phosphatase treatment</title>
<p><italic>Drosophila</italic> S2R+ cells were cultured in Corning Insectagro DS2 with 10% FBS (HyClone). Plasmids pUAST-Flag-dFoxO, pUAST-3HA-Pelle and Actin-GAL4 were used for co-transfection as indicated using Effectene Transfection Reagent (QIAGEN). 48 hours after transfection, cells were lysed in RIPA buffer (CST) with PMSF and proceeded with the standard western blot and co-immunoprecipitation protocols. Proteins were probed or immunoprecipitated with following antibodies: Flag-Tag antibody [3A6] (CMCTAG), HA-Tag (C29F4) Rabbit mAb (CST), Anti dFoxO (Cosmo Bio), Anti-rabbit IgG, HRP-linked Antibody (CST), Anti-mouse IgG, HRP-linked Antibody (CST). For Phosphatase Treatment, cell extracts were incubated with calf intestine phosphatase (CIP) (New England BioLabs) for 40 mins at 37°C.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title><italic>In vitro</italic> kinase assays</title>
<p>The GST-Pelle plasmid is a gift from Dr. Wasserman at UCSD. GST-Pelle protein was induced to express in BL21 cells and purified as described [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] except that cells were lysed by sonication. PCR amplified DNA fragments of dFoxO were constructed into pET.M.3C vector (gift from Dr. Long at Nankai University) for expressing proteins of full-length (1-622aa), N-terminal (1-304aa) and C-terminal (305-622aa) dFoxO, respectively. Each resulting protein contains 6ᵡHis-tag at N termini designed as His-dFoxO, His-dFoxONT or His-dFoxOCT. BL21 cells transformed with the constructs were grown for 15 hours at 16°C following 0.8mM IPTG induction, and 6ᵡHis-tagged proteins were purified as previously described [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>].</p>
<p>The <italic>in vitro</italic> kinase assays were performed as described [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Briefly, GST-Pelle (30 μg) was pre-incubated for 45 mins at 30°C in 1×kinase buffer (10mM ATP, 10mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 50mM β-glycerophosphate, 25mM HEPES, pH6.5) to allow activation by auto-phosphorylation. The activated Pelle (6 μg) was then incubated with recombinant 6ᵡHis-tagged dFoxO/NT/CT (10 μg) in a volume of 40 μl in the presence of [γ-32P]-ATP (5 μ Curie, Perkin Elmer) in 1×kinase buffer. Following reaction for 5 mins at 30°C, samples were mixed with 10 μl 5×SDS loading sample buffer, boiled, and loaded (25 ml) on an 10% SDS protein gel.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019">
<title>GST-pulldown assays</title>
<p>The GST-pulldown assays were performed as previous described [<xref rid="pgen.1005589.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Recombinant GST-Pelle-λPPase and 6ᵡHis-dFoxo proteins were produced in BL21 cells and purified with glutathione-Sepharose 4B (GE Healthcare) or Ni-NTA resin (GE Healthcare) respectively according to standard protocols. 2 μg GST or 10 μg GST-fusion proteins was incubated at 4°C for 5 hours with 10 μg purified 6ᵡHis-dFoxo and 50 μl of glutathione-Sepharose beads. Supernatants were collected as input and the Sepharose beads were then extensively washed 5 times with lysis buffer and resuspended in SDS loading buffer and boiled. A quarter of the sample buffer was loaded in 12% SDS-PAGE for detection with anti-His antibody (Sungene Biotech).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005589.s001" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Depletion of <italic>pll</italic> produces a loss-of-ACV phenotype in adult wings.</title>
<p>(<bold>A-G</bold>) Light micrographs showing <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings. Expression of two additional <italic>pll</italic> RNAi, <italic>pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>W</italic></sup> (<bold>A</bold>) and <italic>pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup> (<bold>F</bold>), driven by <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 generated a loss-of-ACV phenotype, which was rescued by expression of Pll (<bold>G</bold>). Heterozygous for two <italic>pll</italic> mutants, <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> (<bold>D</bold>) and <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup> (<bold>E</bold>), showed no obvious defects, but strongly enhanced <italic>ptc&gt;pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>W</italic></sup> induced loss-of-ACV phenotype (<bold>B</bold> and <bold>C</bold>). The lower panels show high magnification view of the boxed areas in upper panels. (<bold>H</bold>) Statistical analysis of the ACV phenotype shown in figures <bold>A</bold>-<bold>G</bold>. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>W</italic></sup> (B) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>W</italic></sup>; <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>/+ (C) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>W</italic></sup>; <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup>/+ (D) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>/+ (E) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup>/+ (F) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup> (G) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005589.s002" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Verification of RNAi lines for <italic>pll</italic> and Toll pathway components.</title>
<p>(<bold>A-K</bold>) Light micrographs of <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult eyes are shown. Compared with the <italic>GMR-</italic>Gal4 control (<bold>A</bold>), <italic>GMR</italic>&gt;Pll produced a rough eye phenotype (<bold>B</bold>) that was significantly suppressed by three independent <italic>pll</italic> RNAi lines (<bold>C-E</bold>). The rough eye phenotype of <italic>GMR</italic>&gt;Toll<sup>10B</sup> (Tl<sup>10B</sup>) (<bold>F</bold>) was fully suppressed by RNAi down-regulation of Toll pathway components: <italic>Toll</italic>, <italic>tube</italic>, <italic>dorsal</italic> and <italic>Dif</italic>, or ectopic expression of Cactus (<bold>G-K</bold>). (<bold>L</bold>) The knock-down efficacies of <italic>pll</italic> RNAi lines. Expression of three <italic>pll</italic> RNAi, but not LacZ, significantly reduced the level of <italic>pll</italic> mRNA, as measured by quantitative RT-PCR. Total RNA of <italic>Drosophila</italic> third instar larvae were extracted and normalized for cDNA synthesis. Error bars represent standard deviation from three independent experiments. Parison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks. ** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01, ns stands for not significant. Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>GMR</italic>-Gal4/+ (B) <italic>GMR</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll (C) <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>GMR</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll (D) <italic>UAS-pll-IRV</italic><sup><italic>103774</italic></sup>/+; <italic>GMR</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll (E) <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>W</italic></sup>/+; <italic>GMR</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll (F) <italic>UAS</italic>-Toll<sup>10B</sup>/+; <italic>GMR</italic>-Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (G) <italic>UAS</italic>-Toll<sup>10B</sup>/+; <italic>GMR</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-Toll-IR</italic> (H) <italic>UAS</italic>-Toll<sup>10B</sup>/+; <italic>GMR</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-tube-IR</italic> (I) <italic>UAS</italic>-Toll<sup>10B</sup>/<italic>UAS</italic>-Cactus; <italic>GMR</italic>-Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (J) <italic>UAS</italic>-Toll<sup>10B</sup>/+; <italic>GMR</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-dorsal-IR</italic> (K) <italic>UAS</italic>-Toll<sup>10B</sup>/+; <italic>GMR</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-Dif-IR</italic>.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005589.s003" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S3 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Loss of <italic>pll</italic> results in wing tissue ablation.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>-<bold>C</bold>, <bold>E</bold>-<bold>G</bold> and <bold>I</bold>-<bold>K</bold>) Light micrographs of <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings are shown. Compared with controls (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>E</bold> and <bold>I</bold>), expression of <italic>pll</italic> RNAi driven by <italic>Omb</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>B</bold>), <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>F</bold>) or <italic>en</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>J</bold>) resulted in reduced wing sizes, which were suppressed by expressing Pll (<bold>C</bold>, <bold>G</bold> and <bold>K</bold>). Quantifications of adult wing size/wild type (WT) (<bold>D</bold> and <bold>H</bold>) and total size P/A ratio (<bold>L</bold>) are shown for indicated genotypes. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>Omb</italic>-Gal4/+ (B) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>/+ (C) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+ (E) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (F) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>/+ (G) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>/+; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+ (I) <italic>en-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (J) <italic>en-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup> (K) <italic>en-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005589.s004" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S4 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Loss of <italic>pll</italic> elicits apoptotic cell death in wing discs.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>, <bold>K</bold> and <bold>L</bold>) AO staining of third instar larval wing discs. Compared with controls (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>K</bold>), knock down <italic>pll</italic> by <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>B</bold>) or <italic>Omb</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>L</bold>) triggered cell death detected by AO staining. (<bold>C</bold>-<bold>F</bold>) X-Gal staining of a <italic>hid</italic>-LacZ and an <italic>rpr</italic>-LacZ reporters in wing discs. Compared with controls (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>E</bold>), knock down <italic>pll</italic> in the wing pouch induced <italic>hid</italic> (<bold>D</bold>) and <italic>rpr</italic> (<bold>F</bold>) transcription. (<bold>G-J</bold>) TUNEL staining of third instar larval wing discs. Compared with Gal4 controls (<bold>G</bold> and <bold>I</bold>), knock down <italic>pll</italic> by <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>H</bold>) or <italic>Omb</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>J</bold>) induced cell death in the corresponding areas. In all figures, anterior is to the left and dorsal up. (<bold>M</bold>) Loss of <italic>pll</italic> up-regulated the mRNA level of <italic>hid</italic>, <italic>rpr</italic> and <italic>grim</italic>, as measured by quantitative RT-PCR. Total RNA of <italic>Drosophila</italic> third instar larvae were extracted and normalized for cDNA synthesis. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to calculate statistical significance, indicated with asterisks (* <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, ** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01). Error bars represent standard deviation from three independent experiments. Detailed genotypes: (A and G) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (B and H) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>/+ (C) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>hid</italic>-LacZ/+ (D) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>/+; <italic>hid</italic>-LacZ/+ (E) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>rpr</italic>-LacZ/+ (F) <italic>Sd-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>/+; <italic>rpr</italic>-LacZ/+ (I and K) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (J and L) <italic>Omb-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic>; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>/+.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005589.s005" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.s005" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S5 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>Df(3L)H99</italic> suppresses loss-of-<italic>pll</italic> triggered wing phenotypes.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>, <bold>D</bold> and <bold>E</bold>) Light micrographs showing <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings. Wing phenotypes of <italic>ptc&gt;pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (<bold>A</bold>) and <italic>Omb&gt;pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (<bold>D</bold>) were partially suppressed by <italic>Df(3L)H99</italic> that deletes one copy of the apoptotic genes <italic>reaper</italic>, <italic>hid</italic> and <italic>grim</italic> (<bold>B</bold> and <bold>E</bold>). The lower panels show high magnification view of the boxed areas in upper panels (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>). Statistical analysis of the ACV phenotype (<bold>C</bold>) and quantification of adult wing size/WT (<bold>F</bold>) are shown for indicated genotypes. Unpaired t test was used to calculate statistical significance, indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup> (B) <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>; <italic>H99</italic>/+ (D) <italic>Omb</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+ (E) <italic>Omb</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>/+; <italic>H99</italic>/+.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005589.s006" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.s006" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S6 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title><italic>dFoxO</italic> is required for loss-of-<italic>pll</italic> induced wing phenotype.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>-<bold>D</bold>) Light micrographs showing <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings. The loss-of-ACV phenotype in <italic>ptc</italic>&gt;<italic>pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup> flies (<bold>A</bold>) was suppressed by removing one copy of endogenous <italic>dFoxO</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) or expressing a <italic>dFoxO</italic> RNAi (<bold>D</bold>), but not by expressing LacZ (<bold>B</bold>). The lower panels show high magnification view of the boxed areas in upper panels. (<bold>E</bold>) Quantification of the ACV phenotype as shown in figures <bold>A</bold>-<bold>D</bold>. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup> (B) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS</italic>-LacZ/+ (C) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>; <italic>dFoxO</italic><sup><bold><italic>Δ94</italic></bold></sup>/+ (D) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V103774</italic></sup>; <italic>UAS-dFoxO-IR</italic>/+.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005589.s007" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.s007" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S7 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Expression of Pll does not suppress dFoxO-induced wing phenotype.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) Light micrographs of <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings are shown. Expression of dFoxO driven by <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 recapitulated the loss-of-ACV phenotype (<bold>A</bold>), which was not suppressed by the expression of Pll (<bold>B</bold>). (<bold>C</bold>) Statistical analysis of the ACV phenotype shown in figures <bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>. Unpaired t test was used to calculate statistical significance. ns stands for not significant. Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-</italic>dFoxO (B) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-</italic>dFoxO; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005589.s008" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.s008" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S8 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Cell death phenotypes triggered by Grim expression or <italic>pll</italic> depletion.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>-<bold>D</bold>) Light micrographs showing <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings. Compared with the <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 control (<bold>C</bold>), expression of Grim triggered strong cell death that resulted in partially fused L3 and L4 (<bold>A</bold>), while limited Grim expression imposed by <italic>Tub</italic>-Gal80<sup>ts</sup> produced a loss-of-ACV phenotype (<bold>B</bold>). Enhanced expression of a <italic>pll</italic> RNAi (at 29°C) not only abolished ACV, but also diminished the area between L3 and L4 (<bold>D</bold>). (<bold>E</bold>-<bold>G</bold>) Quantifications of cell size (<bold>E</bold>), cell number (<bold>F</bold>) and area size (<bold>G</bold>) of L3-L4/total ratio in <bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold> are shown. While cell size was not affected, both cell number and area size decreased significantly when <italic>pll</italic> was knocked down by <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4. Unpaired t test was used to calculate statistical significance, indicated with asterisks (**<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01, n = 10 in each group). ns stands for not significant. Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS</italic>-Grim (B) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS</italic>-Grim; <italic>Tub-</italic>Gal80<sup>ts</sup>/+ (C) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (D) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-pll-IR</italic><sup><italic>V2889</italic></sup>.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005589.s009" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.s009" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S9 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Pll is not involved in JNK pathway-triggered cell death.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>-<bold>M</bold>) Light micrographs of <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings are shown. Compared with <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 control (<bold>A</bold>), expression of Egr<sup>w</sup> (<bold>B</bold>) or Hep (<bold>F</bold>), or RNAi-mediated down-regulation of <italic>puc</italic> (<bold>J</bold>) along the A/P compartment boundary resulted in a loss-of-ACV phenotype and size reduction between L3 and L4. The phenotypes are not affected by gain- or loss-of-<italic>pll</italic>, or by expression of LacZ (<bold>C</bold>-<bold>E</bold>, <bold>G</bold>-<bold>I</bold> and <bold>K</bold>-<bold>M</bold>). Statistics analysis of area size L3-L4/total ratio (<bold>N</bold>) and the ACV phenotype (<bold>O</bold>) are shown for figures <bold>A</bold>-<bold>M</bold>. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). ns stands for not significant. (<bold>P</bold>) A diagram for the key components of JNK pathway. Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (B) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-</italic>Egr<sup>W</sup> (C) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-</italic>Egr<sup>W</sup>; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+ (D) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-</italic>Egr<sup>W</sup>; <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup>/+ (E) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-</italic>Egr<sup>W</sup>; <italic>UAS-</italic>LacZ/+ (F) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-</italic>Hep (G) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-</italic>Hep; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+ (H) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-</italic>Hep; <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup>/+ (I) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-</italic>Hep; <italic>UAS-</italic>LacZ/+ (J) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-puc-IR</italic> (K) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-puc-IR</italic>; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+ (L) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-puc-IR</italic>; <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup>/+ (M) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-puc-IR</italic>; <italic>UAS-</italic>LacZ/+.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005589.s010" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.s010" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S10 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Pll is not involved in the Insulin signaling.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>-<bold>M</bold>) Light micrographs showing <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings. Compared with <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 control (<bold>A</bold>), expression of a dominant negative form of PI3K (<bold>B</bold>), or RNAi-mediated inactivation of <italic>PI3K</italic> (<bold>F</bold>) or <italic>Akt</italic> (<bold>J</bold>) led to a size reduction between L3 and L4, which was not affected by changing Pll level or expressing LacZ (<bold>C</bold>-<bold>E</bold>, <bold>G</bold>-<bold>I</bold> and <bold>K</bold>-<bold>M</bold>). (<bold>N</bold>) Quantification of adult wing size L3-L4/total ratio as shown in figures <bold>A</bold>-<bold>M.</bold> One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). ns stands for not significant. (<bold>O</bold>) A diagram for the key components of Insulin pathway. Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (B) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>PI3K<sup>DN</sup>/+ (C) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>PI3K<sup>DN</sup>/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll (D) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>PI3K<sup>DN</sup>/<italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup> (E) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>PI3K<sup>DN</sup>/<italic>UAS-</italic>LacZ (F) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-PI3K-IR</italic>/+ (G) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-PI3K-IR</italic>/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll (H) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-PI3K-IR</italic>/<italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup> (I) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-PI3K-IR</italic>/<italic>UAS-</italic>LacZ (J) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-Akt-IR</italic> (K) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-Akt-IR</italic>; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+ (L) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-Akt-IR</italic>; <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup>/+ (M) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-Akt-IR</italic>; <italic>UAS-</italic>LacZ/+.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005589.s011" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.s011" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S11 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Pll is not involved in the Hippo pathway.</title>
<p><bold>(A</bold>-<bold>E, G</bold>-<bold>K, M</bold>-<bold>Q</bold> and <bold>S</bold>-<bold>W)</bold> Light micrographs of <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings are shown. Compared with controls (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>G</bold>, <bold>M</bold> and <bold>S</bold>), up-regulated Hippo signaling by expressing Hippo (Hpo) under the control of <italic>nub</italic>-Gal4 or <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>B</bold> and <bold>H</bold>), or expressing Warts by <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>N</bold>), or knocking-down <italic>yki</italic> by <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 (<bold>T</bold>) resulted in reduced wing tissue in the corresponding areas, which were not altered by changing Pll level or expressing LacZ (<bold>C</bold>-<bold>E</bold>, <bold>I</bold>-<bold>K</bold>, <bold>O</bold>-<bold>Q</bold> and <bold>U</bold>-<bold>W</bold>). (<bold>F</bold>, <bold>L</bold>, <bold>R</bold> and <bold>X</bold>) Quantifications of total wing size/wild type (WT) ratio or wing size L3-L4/total ratio are shown for figures <bold>A</bold>-<bold>E</bold>, <bold>G</bold>-<bold>K</bold>, <bold>M</bold>-<bold>Q</bold> and <bold>S</bold>-<bold>W</bold> respectively (n = 10). One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). ns stands for not significant. (<bold>Y</bold>) A diagram for the key components of Hippo pathway. Detailed genotypes: (A) <italic>nub-</italic>Gal4/<italic>+</italic> (B) <italic>nub-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Hippo/+ (C) <italic>nub-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Hippo/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll (D) <italic>nub-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Hippo/<italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup> (E) <italic>nub-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Hippo/<italic>UAS-</italic>LacZ (G) <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4/+ (H) <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Hippo/+ (I) <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Hippo/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll (J) <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Hippo/<italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup> (K) <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Hippo/<italic>UAS-</italic>LacZ (M) <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4/+ (N) <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Warts/+ (O) <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Warts/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll (P) <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Warts/<italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup> (Q) <italic>Sd</italic>-Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-</italic>Warts/<italic>UAS-</italic>LacZ (S) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+ (T) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-yki-IR</italic>/+ (U) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-yki-IR</italic>/<italic>UAS</italic>-Pll (V) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-yki-IR</italic>/<italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup> (W) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+; <italic>UAS-yki-IR</italic>/<italic>UAS-</italic>LacZ.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1005589.s012" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1005589.s012" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S12 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Loss of <italic>dMyc-</italic> or <italic>scrib</italic>- induced cell death is independent of Pll.</title>
<p>(<bold>A</bold>-<bold>E</bold>) Light micrographs showing <italic>Drosophila</italic> adult wings. Compared with control (<bold>A</bold>), RNAi-mediated depletion of <italic>dMyc</italic> driven by <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 triggered cell death that resulted in reduced wing area between L3 and L4 (<bold>B</bold>), which is independent of Pll or LacZ (<bold>C</bold>-<bold>E</bold>). Fluorescence micrographs of third instar larval wing discs stained with AO (<bold>G-K</bold>) or anti-Cleaved Caspase-3 (CC-3) antibody (<bold>M-Q</bold>) are shown. Compared with controls (<bold>G</bold> and <bold>M</bold>), loss of <italic>scrib</italic> along the A/P boundary resulted in increased cell death (<bold>H</bold>) and caspase activity (<bold>N</bold>), both of which were not suppressed by up/down-regulation of Pll or expression of LacZ (<bold>I</bold>-<bold>K</bold> and <bold>O</bold>-<bold>Q</bold>). <bold>M’</bold>-<bold>Q’</bold> are high magnification of the boxed areas in <bold>M</bold>-<bold>Q</bold>. (<bold>F</bold>, <bold>L</bold> and <bold>R</bold>) Quantifications of adult wing size L3-L4/total ratio (<bold>F</bold>), cell death with AO staining (<bold>L</bold>) and CC-3 antibody staining (<bold>R</bold>) are shown for figures <bold>A-E, G</bold>-<bold>K</bold> and <bold>M-Q</bold> respectively. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni multiple comparison test was used to compute <italic>P</italic>-values, significance is indicated with asterisks (*** <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). ns stands for not significant. Detailed genotypes: (A, G and M) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/+ (B) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-dMyc-IR</italic> (C) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-dMyc-IR</italic>; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+ (D) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-dMyc-IR</italic>; <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup>/+ (E) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-dMyc-IR</italic>; <italic>UAS-</italic>LacZ/+ (H and N) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-scrib-IR</italic> (I and O) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-scrib-IR</italic>; <italic>UAS</italic>-Pll/+ (J and P) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-scrib-IR</italic>; <italic>pll</italic><sup><italic>7</italic></sup>/+ (K and Q) <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4/<italic>UAS-scrib-IR</italic>; <italic>UAS-</italic>LacZ/+.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Dr. Won-Jae Lee, Bloomington, VDRC, DGRC and NIG stock centers for fly stocks, Drs. Huiqiang Lou, Qun He and Yun Quan from China Agricultural University for help in the Kinase assays, Drs. Margaret Ho and Ying Cao for discussion and critical comments.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowie</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The interleukin-1 receptor-associated kinases: Critical regulators of innate immune signalling</article-title>. <source>Biochemical Pharmacology</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>1981</fpage>–<lpage>1991</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bcp.2010.06.020" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.bcp.2010.06.020</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20599782</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssens</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beyaert</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Functional diversity and regulation of different interleukin-1 receptor-associated kinase (IRAK) family members</article-title>. <source>Molecular Cell</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12620219</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gosu</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basith</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durai</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Molecular Evolution and Structural Features of IRAK Family Members</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source> <volume>7</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silverman</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maniatis</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>NF-kappaB signaling pathways in mammalian and insect innate immunity</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2321</fpage>–<lpage>2342</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11562344</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunne</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Neill</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The interleukin-1 receptor/Toll-like receptor superfamily: signal transduction during inflammation and host defense</article-title>. <source>Sci STKE</source> <volume>2003</volume>: <fpage>re3</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12606705</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shelton</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wasserman</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>pelle encodes a protein kinase required to establish dorsoventral polarity in the Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>515</fpage>–<lpage>525</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8440018</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Towb</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wasserman</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Tube Is an IRAK-4 homolog in a Toll pathway adapted for development and immunity</article-title>. <source>J Innate Immun</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1159/000200773" xlink:type="simple">10.1159/000200773</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19498957</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerttula</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>KV</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Zygotic expression and activity of the Drosophila Toll gene, a gene required maternally for embryonic dorsal-ventral pattern formation</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2456252</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valanne</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramet</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Drosophila Toll signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source> <volume>186</volume>: <fpage>649</fpage>–<lpage>656</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1002302" xlink:type="simple">10.4049/jimmunol.1002302</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21209287</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemaitre</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michaut</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reichhart</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The dorsoventral regulatory gene cassette spatzle/Toll/cactus controls the potent antifungal response in Drosophila adults</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>973</fpage>–<lpage>983</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8808632</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halfon</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keshishian</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The Toll pathway is required in the epidermis for muscle development in the Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source> <volume>199</volume>: <fpage>164</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9676200</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mindorff</surname> <given-names>EN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Keefe</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labbe</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A gain-of-function screen for genes that influence axon guidance identifies the NF-kappaB protein dorsal and reveals a requirement for the kinase Pelle in Drosophila photoreceptor axon targeting</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>176</volume>: <fpage>2247</fpage>–<lpage>2263</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17603113</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akira</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>TLR signaling</article-title>. <source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source> <volume>311</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17048703</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutschmann</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silverman</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Role of Drosophila IKK gamma in a toll-independent antibacterial immune response</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>342</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11017107</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silverman</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stoven</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hultmark</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A Drosophila IkappaB kinase complex required for Relish cleavage and antibacterial immunity</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>2461</fpage>–<lpage>2471</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11018014</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Towb</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bergmann</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wasserman</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The protein kinase Pelle mediates feedback regulation in the Drosophila Toll signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>4729</fpage>–<lpage>4736</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11731453</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dick</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Megeney</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Cell death proteins: an evolutionary role in cellular adaptation before the advent of apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Bioessays</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>974</fpage>–<lpage>983</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/bies.201300052" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/bies.201300052</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23943356</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Caspase function in programmed cell death</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17082813</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goyal</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCall</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agapite</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartwieg</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steller</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Induction of apoptosis by Drosophila reaper, hid and grim through inhibition of IAP function</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>597</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10675328</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holley</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colon-Ramos</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kornbluth</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Reaper eliminates IAP proteins through stimulated IAP degradation and generalized translational inhibition</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>444</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12021770</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huh</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muro</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Hid, Rpr and Grim negatively regulate DIAP1 levels through distinct mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>416</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12021767</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goyal</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ditzel</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zachariou</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The DIAP1 RING finger mediates ubiquitination of Dronc and is indispensable for regulating apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>450</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12021771</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hay</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The Drosophila caspase inhibitor DIAP1 is essential for cell survival and is negatively regulated by HID</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10481910</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dorman</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodan</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kenyon</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>daf-16: An HNF-3/forkhead family member that can function to double the life-span of Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>278</volume>: <fpage>1319</fpage>–<lpage>1322</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9360933</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greer</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunet</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>FOXO transcription factors at the interface between longevity and tumor suppression</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>7410</fpage>–<lpage>7425</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16288288</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Junger</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rintelen</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stocker</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wasserman</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vegh</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The Drosophila forkhead transcription factor FOXO mediates the reduction in cell number associated with reduced insulin signaling</article-title>. <source>J Biol</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12908874</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davidge</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lockyer</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staveley</surname> <given-names>BE</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Expression of Drosophila FOXO regulates growth and can phenocopy starvation</article-title>. <source>BMC Dev Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12844367</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puig</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marr</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruhf</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tjian</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Control of cell number by Drosophila FOXO: downstream and feedback regulation of the insulin receptor pathway</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>2006</fpage>–<lpage>2020</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12893776</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brault</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schild</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandri</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>FoxO3 coordinately activates protein degradation by the autophagic/lysosomal and proteasomal pathways in atrophying muscle cells</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>472</fpage>–<lpage>483</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18054316</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Puig</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyun</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohmann</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jasper</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Foxo and Fos regulate the decision between cell death and survival in response to UV irradiation</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>380</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183370</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannakou</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goss</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Junger</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hafen</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leevers</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Long-lived Drosophila with overexpressed dFOXO in adult fat body</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>305</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15192154</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwangbo</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gershman</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatar</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Drosophila dFOXO controls lifespan and regulates insulin signalling in brain and fat body</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>429</volume>: <fpage>562</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15175753</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>FoxO mediates APP-induced AICD-dependent cell death</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Dis</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1233</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/cddis.2014.196" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/cddis.2014.196</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24832605</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>WG</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Applications of post-translational modifications of FoxO family proteins in biological functions</article-title>. <source>J Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jmcb/mjr013" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/jmcb/mjr013</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21669942</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Govind</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steward</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Dorsoventral pattern formation in Drosophila: signal transduction and nuclear targeting</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2068782</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steller</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms and genes of cellular suicide</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>267</volume>: <fpage>1445</fpage>–<lpage>1449</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7878463</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daigneault</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klemetsaune</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wasserman</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The IRAK homolog Pelle is the functional counterpart of IkappaB kinase in the Drosophila Toll pathway</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e75150</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0075150" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0075150</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24086459</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ligoxygakis</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pelte</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leclerc</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duvic</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A serpin mutant links Toll activation to melanization in the host defence of Drosophila</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>6330</fpage>–<lpage>6337</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12456640</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naitza</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosse</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kappler</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Georgel</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belvin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The Drosophila immune defense against gram-negative infection requires the death protein dFADD</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>575</fpage>–<lpage>581</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12433364</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steller</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Regulation of apoptosis in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1132</fpage>–<lpage>1138</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/cdd.2008.50" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/cdd.2008.50</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18437164</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fessler</surname> <given-names>LI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steller</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Programmed cell death during Drosophila embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8223253</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Garijo</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morata</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Apoptosis in Drosophila: compensatory proliferation and undead cells</article-title>. <source>Int J Dev Biol</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>1341</fpage>–<lpage>1347</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1387/ijdb.072447fm" xlink:type="simple">10.1387/ijdb.072447fm</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19247932</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Berriguete</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Espiridion</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cansino</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olmedilla</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Onsurbe</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Clinical significance of both tumor and stromal expression of components of the IL-1 and TNF-alpha signaling pathways in prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Cytokine</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>563</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slack</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giannakou</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foley</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goss</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>dFOXO-independent effects of reduced insulin-like signaling in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Aging Cell</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>748</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1474-9726.2011.00707.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1474-9726.2011.00707.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443682</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nechipurenko</surname> <given-names>IV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broihier</surname> <given-names>HT</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>FoxO limits microtubule stability and is itself negatively regulated by microtubule disruption</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source> <volume>196</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1083/jcb.201105154" xlink:type="simple">10.1083/jcb.201105154</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22312004</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Igaki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanda</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto-Goto</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanuka</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuranaga</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Eiger, a TNF superfamily ligand that triggers the Drosophila JNK pathway</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>3009</fpage>–<lpage>3018</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12065414</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asha</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacs</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stetson</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ando</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Analysis of Ras-induced overproliferation in Drosophila hemocytes</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>163</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12586708</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattila</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kallijarvi</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Puig</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>RNAi screening for kinases and phosphatases identifies FoxO regulators</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>14873</fpage>–<lpage>14878</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0803022105" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0803022105</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18815370</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Obata</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuranaga</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tomioka</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ming</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takeishi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Necrosis-driven systemic immune response alters SAM metabolism through the FOXO-GNMT axis</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>821</fpage>–<lpage>833</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2014.03.046" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.celrep.2014.03.046</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24746817</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortini</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Notch signaling: the core pathway and its posttranslational regulation</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>633</fpage>–<lpage>647</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2009.03.010" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.devcel.2009.03.010</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19460341</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrimon</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pitsouli</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shilo</surname> <given-names>BZ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Signaling mechanisms controlling cell fate and embryonic patterning</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>a005975</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/cshperspect.a005975" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/cshperspect.a005975</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22855721</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Golfman</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ou-Yang</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>IkappaB kinase promotes tumorigenesis through inhibition of forkhead FOXO3a</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15084260</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapuis</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leotoing</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamburini</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verdier</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>IkappaB kinase overcomes PI3K/Akt and ERK/MAPK to control FOXO3a activity in acute myeloid leukemia</article-title>. <source>Blood</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>4240</fpage>–<lpage>4250</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1182/blood-2009-12-260711" xlink:type="simple">10.1182/blood-2009-12-260711</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20671123</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunet</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonni</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zigmond</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>MZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Juo</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Akt promotes cell survival by phosphorylating and inhibiting a Forkhead transcription factor</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>857</fpage>–<lpage>868</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10102273</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paik</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kollipara</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>FoxOs are lineage-restricted redundant tumor suppressors and regulate endothelial cell homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>323</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17254969</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhyasen</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bolanos</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Starczynowski</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Differential IRAK signaling in hematologic malignancies</article-title>. <source>Exp Hematol</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1005</fpage>–<lpage>1007</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.exphem.2013.09.008" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.exphem.2013.09.008</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24084080</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guven</surname> <given-names>Maiorov E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keskin</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gursoy</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nussinov</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The structural network of inflammation and cancer: merits and challenges</article-title>. <source>Semin Cancer Biol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.semcancer.2013.05.003" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.semcancer.2013.05.003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23712403</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Accili</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arden</surname> <given-names>KC</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>FoxOs at the crossroads of cellular metabolism, differentiation, and transformation</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15137936</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Essers</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weijzen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Vries-Smits</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saarloos</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Ruiter</surname> <given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>FOXO transcription factor activation by oxidative stress mediated by the small GTPase Ral and JNK</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>4802</fpage>–<lpage>4812</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15538382</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oldham</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hafen</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Insulin/IGF and target of rapamycin signaling: a TOR de force in growth control</article-title>. <source>Trends Cell Biol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12559758</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grewal</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Insulin/TOR signaling in growth and homeostasis: a view from the fly world</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1006</fpage>–<lpage>1010</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.biocel.2008.10.010" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.biocel.2008.10.010</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18992839</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Hippo signaling: a hub of growth control, tumor suppression and pluripotency maintenance</article-title>. <source>J Genet Genomics</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>481</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jgg.2011.09.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jgg.2011.09.009</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22035868</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prober</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenman</surname> <given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallant</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Drosophila myc regulates cellular growth during development</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>779</fpage>–<lpage>790</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10499795</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marquardt</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bras</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medema</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eilers</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Myc-induced proliferation and transformation require Akt-mediated phosphorylation of FoxO proteins</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2830</fpage>–<lpage>2840</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15241468</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benassayag</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montero</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colombie</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallant</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cribbs</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Human c-Myc isoforms differentially regulate cell growth and apoptosis in Drosophila melanogaster</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>9897</fpage>–<lpage>9909</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16260605</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bilder</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perrimon</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Localization of apical epithelial determinants by the basolateral PDZ protein Scribble</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>403</volume>: <fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>680</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688207</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Igaki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pastor-Pareja</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aonuma</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miura</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Intrinsic tumor suppression and epithelial maintenance by endocytic activation of Eiger/TNF signaling in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>458</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2009.01.002" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.devcel.2009.01.002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19289090</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohsawa</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimura</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takino</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miyawaki</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Elimination of oncogenic neighbors by JNK-mediated engulfment in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2011.02.007" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.devcel.2011.02.007</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21397843</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The canonical Wg signaling modulates Bsk-mediated cell death in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Dis</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1713</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/cddis.2015.85" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/cddis.2015.85</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25855961</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>WZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A broad expression profile of the GMR-GAL4 driver in Drosophila melanogaster</article-title>. <source>Genet Mol Res</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1997</fpage>–<lpage>2002</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4238/2012.August.6.4" xlink:type="simple">10.4238/2012.August.6.4</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22911584</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>dUev1a modulates TNF-JNK mediated tumor progression and cell death in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source> <volume>380</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2013.05.013" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ydbio.2013.05.013</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23726905</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Bendless modulates JNK-mediated cell death and migration in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>415</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/cdd.2013.154" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/cdd.2013.154</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24162658</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Src42A modulates tumor invasion and cell death via Ben/dUev1a-mediated JNK activation in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Dis</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e864</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/cddis.2013.392" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/cddis.2013.392</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24136228</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ha</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seol</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brey</surname> <given-names>PT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>An essential complementary role of NF-kappaB pathway to microbicidal oxidants in Drosophila gut immunity</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>3693</fpage>–<lpage>3701</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16858400</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordstrom</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steller</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Activation of the reaper gene during ectopic cell killing in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source> <volume>180</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8948586</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neufeld</surname> <given-names>TP</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Dietary sugar promotes systemic TOR activation in Drosophila through AKH-dependent selective secretion of Dilp3</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>6846</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ncomms7846" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ncomms7846</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25882208</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Spatial organization of Hippo signaling at the plasma membrane mediated by the tumor suppressor Merlin/NF2</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>154</volume>: <fpage>1342</fpage>–<lpage>1355</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2013.08.025" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2013.08.025</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24012335</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>hippo encodes a Ste-20 family protein kinase that restricts cell proliferation and promotes apoptosis in conjunction with salvador and warts</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12941273</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>NOPO modulates Egr-induced JNK-independent cell death in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Cell Res</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>431</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/cr.2011.135" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/cr.2011.135</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21844890</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noll</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Drosophila female sexual behavior induced by sterile males showing copulation complementation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>3272</fpage>–<lpage>3275</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10725377</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohmann</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jasper</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>JNK signaling confers tolerance to oxidative stress and extends lifespan in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>811</fpage>–<lpage>816</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14602080</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Structural insights into Paf1 complex assembly and histone binding</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>10619</fpage>–<lpage>10629</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkt819" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/nar/gkt819</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24038468</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1005589.ref083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Hypoxia regulates Hippo signalling through the SIAH2 ubiquitin E3 ligase</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ncb3073" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ncb3073</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25438054</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>