<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
    <front>
        <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn><publisher>
                <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
            </publisher></journal-meta>
        <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PLGE-RA-4219R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368</article-id><article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                    <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
                    <subject>Genetics and Genomics/Animal Genetics</subject>
                    <subject>Genetics and Genomics/Complex Traits</subject>
                    <subject>Genetics and Genomics/Gene Discovery</subject>
                    <subject>Genetics and Genomics/Genetics of the Immune System</subject>
                    <subject>Immunology/Genetics of the Immune System</subject>
                    <subject>Immunology/Immune Response</subject>
                    <subject>Immunology/Innate Immunity</subject>
                    <subject>Infectious Diseases/Viral Infections</subject>
                    <subject>Virology/Animal Models of Infection</subject>
                    <subject>Virology/Host Antiviral Responses</subject>
                    <subject>Virology/Mechanisms of Resistance and Susceptibility, including Host
                        Genetics</subject>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories><title-group><article-title>NK Cell Receptor/<italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>–Dependent
                    Host Resistance to Viral Infection Is Quantitatively Modulated by
                        <italic>H2</italic><sup>q</sup> Inhibitory Signals</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">NKC- and MHC-Dependent Response to Viral
                    Infection</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Fodil-Cornu</surname>
                        <given-names>Nassima</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Loredo-Osti</surname>
                        <given-names>J. Concepción</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Vidal</surname>
                        <given-names>Silvia M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Human Genetics and Department of
                    Microbiology and Immunology, McGill University, Life Sciences Complex, Montreal,
                    Canada</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>McGill Centre for the Study of Host
                    Resistance, McGill University, Montreal, Canada</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Mathematics and Statistics,
                    Memorial University of Newfoundland, St. Johns, Canada</addr-line>
            </aff><contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Roopenian</surname>
                        <given-names>Derry C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <role>Editor</role>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">The Jackson Laboratory, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">silvia.vidal@mcgill.ca</email></corresp>
                <fn fn-type="con">
                    <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: NFC SMV. Performed the experiments:
                        NFC. Analyzed the data: NFC JCLO SMV. Wrote the paper: NFC SMV.</p>
                </fn>
            <fn fn-type="conflict">
                <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
            </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>21</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e1001368</elocation-id><history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>24</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>8</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Fodil-Cornu et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under
                the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted
                use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and
                source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
                <p>The cytomegalovirus resistance locus <italic>Cmv3</italic> has been linked to an
                    epistatic interaction between two loci: a Natural Killer (NK) cell receptor gene
                    and the major histocompatibility complex class I (MHC-I) locus. To demonstrate
                    the interaction between <italic>Cmv3</italic> and
                        <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>, we generated double congenic mice between
                    MA/My and BALB.K mice and an F<sub>2</sub> cross between FVB/N
                            (<italic>H-2<sup>q</sup></italic>) and BALB.K
                        (<italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>) mice, two strains susceptible to mouse
                    cytomegalovirus (MCMV). Only mice expressing <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> in
                    conjunction with <italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup></italic> or
                            <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic> were resistant to MCMV infection.
                    Subsequently, an F<sub>3</sub> cross was carried out between transgenic
                            FVB/<italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> and MHC-I deficient mice in which
                    only the progeny expressing <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic> and a single
                            <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> class-I molecule completely controlled
                    MCMV viral loads. This phenotype was shown to be NK cell–dependent and
                    associated with subsequent NK cell proliferation. Finally, we demonstrated that
                    a number of <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> alleles influence the expression
                    level of <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> molecules, but not intrinsic functional
                    properties of NK cells; viral loads, however, were quantitatively proportional
                    to the number of <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> alleles. Our results support a
                    model in which <italic>H-2<sup>q</sup></italic> molecules convey Ly49-dependent
                    inhibitory signals that interfere with the action of
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> on NK cell activation against MCMV
                    infection. Thus, the integration of activating and inhibitory signals emanating
                    from various MHC-I/NK cell receptor interactions regulates NK
                    cell–mediated control of viral load.</p>
            </abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary">
                <title>Author Summary</title>
                <p>Effective natural killer (NK) cell responses against virally infected cells are
                    regulated by NK cell receptors that specifically recognize target cells. In the
                    current study, we validated the specific interaction taking place between NK
                    cell receptors and MHC class I molecules on the surface of infected cells,
                    resulting in resistance to cytomegalovirus. Genetic dissection of this mechanism
                    of interaction revealed that the NK cell response occurs exclusively through the
                    triggering of the activating Ly49P receptor by the MHC class I
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> molecule. We observed, in this context,
                    that NK cells were incapable of clearing the virus when target cells also
                    expressed MHC class I <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> molecules, which strongly
                    and quantitatively inhibit NK cells. Our findings reveal that the interplay
                    between inhibitory and activating NK cell receptors and their MHC class I
                    ligands generate signals that shape the outcome of infection.</p>
            </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by Canadian Institutes of Health Research MOP-7781 and
                    the Canada Research Chairs Program (SMV). The funders had no role in study
                    design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the
                    manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
                <page-count count="13"/>
            </counts></article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec id="s1">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Natural killer (NK) cells play an important role in the innate immune response
                against tumors, MHC-mismatched bone-marrow grafts, and pathogens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Raulet1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Lodoen1">[2]</xref>. These cells
                also contribute to defense against parasites and intracellular bacteria, and they
                are critical for the control of a variety of viral infections <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Guan1">[3]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Ward1">[6]</xref>. NK cell actions are immediate and
                appear to be particularly important during the first few days of infection; they
                involve direct lysis of infected cells and production of proinflammatory cytokines
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Biron1">[7]</xref>. NK cell
                activation is tightly regulated by output signals derived from the engagement of
                inhibitory and activating receptors by their respective ligands on potential targets
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Ortaldo1">[8]</xref>.
                Inhibitory human killer immunoglobulin–like receptors (KIR), mouse killer
                C-type lectin-like receptors family A (KLRA or Ly49), and NKG2A/CD94 receptors
                recognize major histocompatibility (MHC) class I molecules (<italic>H2</italic> in
                mice), thus controlling NK cell reactivity against “self.” As virally
                infected cells downregulate the expression of MHC class I molecules, the lack of
                inhibitory signals stimulates NK cells. This mechanism is described as the
                “missing self” hypothesis, whereby NK cells eliminate targets that lack
                normal levels of self-MHC class I molecules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Karre1">[9]</xref>. In addition, the interaction
                between inhibitory receptors and self MHC-I molecules is the basis of NK cell
                education (also termed licensing), leading to the maturation of functional NK cells
                in homeostatic conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Fernandez1">[10]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Yokoyama2">[17]</xref>. By contrast, several families of activating receptors,
                such as activating KLRA (also known as Ly49) receptors, KLRK1 (NKG2D) and the
                natural cytotoxicity receptor (NCR) NKP46 (NCR1) can induce NK cell activation
                through the recognition of viral ligands or stress-induced molecules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Dokun1">[18]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Arase1">[22]</xref>. Although it is
                clear that NK cell responses are modulated by a balance of opposing signals received
                from self- or nonself-specific ligands, the precise contribution of specific
                inhibitory and activating pathways to the resolution of infection remains to be
                fully understood.</p>
            <p>The genetic dissection of host resistance or susceptibility to mouse cytomegalovirus
                (MCMV) has provided a fresh view of the precise role of activating NK cell receptors
                in the recognition of infected cells and host protection against the infection.
                Using informative crosses between various mouse strain combinations, several
                MCMV-resistance loci have been mapped to the NK cell gene complex (NKC) on mouse
                chromosome 6. The best characterized, <italic>Cmv1</italic> (also known as
                    <italic>Klra8</italic>) and <italic>Cmv3</italic>, are defined by two different
                modes of inheritance, which seem to correlate with two different mechanisms of
                recognition. <italic>Cmv1</italic> is a single dominant locus whose resistance
                allele, described in C57BL/6 (B6) mice, encodes the Ly49H activating receptor. Ly49H
                recognizes MCMV-infected cells through a direct interaction with the viral product
                m157 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Smith1">[21]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Arase1">[22]</xref>. Engagement of Ly49H by m157 elicits NK
                cell–mediated cytotoxicity, cytokine secretion, NK cell proliferation, and
                viral clearance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Dokun1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Bubic1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-FodilCornu1">[24]</xref>. The <italic>Cmv3</italic>
                locus was detected in a cross between resistant MA/My and susceptible BALB/c mice.
                Expression of <italic>Cmv3</italic>-determined resistance accounted for a 100-fold
                decrease in splenic viral load, but it was only observed in mice carrying a specific
                combination of MA/My alleles at the NKC and MHC (<italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>)
                loci. Functional candidate gene testing of Ly49 receptors isolated from MA/My mice
                showed that another DAP12-associated receptor, Ly49P, responded to MCMV-infected
                cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Desrosiers1">[25]</xref>. In
                this case, Ly49P functional recognition of target cells required surface expression
                of both the host <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> molecule and the viral component
                    <italic>m04</italic>/gp34 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Kielczewska1">[26]</xref>. The role of the <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>
                haplotype in MCMV resistance was previously associated with greater survival
                following infection with lethal inoculum doses of MCMV compared to other
                    <italic>H2</italic> haplotypes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Chalmer1">[27]</xref>. In addition, linkage analyses in a cross between
                resistant MA/My and susceptible C57L strains, as well as the generation of congenic
                    C57L.M-<italic>H2</italic><sup>k</sup> mice carrying the
                    <italic>H2</italic><sup>k</sup> allele from MA/My, confirmed a role for
                    <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>-linked resistance to MCMV <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Dighe1">[28]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Xie1">[29]</xref>. Nevertheless, the
                mechanism of resistance regulated by the interaction between NK receptors and MHC
                class I molecule is still unclear.</p>
            <p>In MA/My mice, <italic>Cmv3</italic>-determined MCMV resistance served as a model for
                researchers and allowed them to propose the existence of a functional interaction
                between the activating Ly49P receptor on NK cells and MHC class I
                    <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> molecules. However, the role of a
                    Ly49P-<italic>m04</italic>-<italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> stimulatory axis
                remained to be clarified. In the present study, we sought to replicate
                experimentally the statistical association between the NKC and the MHC-I locus in
                MCMV resistance, to determine the precise molecules involved in MCMV resistance
                    <italic>in vivo</italic>, and to evaluate the impact of MHC-I inhibitory signals
                on the NK cell antiviral response.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2">
            <title>Results</title>
            <sec id="s2a">
                <title>Interaction between NKC alleles and <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> locus is
                    associated with resistance to MCMV</title>
                <p>To validate the epistatic interaction between the NKC and <italic>H2</italic>
                    detected by linkage analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Desrosiers1">[25]</xref>, we used a
                    marker-assisted strategy to construct congenic mouse lines in which a chromosome
                    6 segment (<italic>Cmv3</italic>) from MA/My MCMV-resistant mice was
                    independently introgressed into BALB/c (<italic>H2<sup>d</sup></italic>) and
                    BALB.K (<italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>) susceptible backgrounds. Congenic
                    BALB.K mice have been described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Klein1">[30]</xref>. The correlations between
                    the current physical maps and the genomic region introgressed in the respective
                    single and double congenic strains
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>d</sup></italic> and
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> are shown in
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001368-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
                <fig id="pgen-1001368-g001" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.g001</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 1</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title>Generation, phenotype, and MCMV infection outcome of BALB mice
                            congenic for the natural killer gene complex inherited from MA/My
                            mice.</title>
                        <p>(A) Left, physical map of chromosome 6 markers used to determine the size
                            of the MA/My fragment introgressed into the BALB background. The four
                            versions of chromosome 6 indicate the genotypes of sub-congenic strains
                            produced during the generation of
                                BALB.<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA</sup></italic><sup>/My</sup> congenic mice
                            carrying a 10 Mb segment (between SNPs <italic>rs13479016</italic> and
                                <italic>rs13479061</italic>) spanning the NKC region from parental
                            MA/My mice. Right, physical map of chromosome 17 markers used to
                            characterize the 9.4 Mb segment (between <italic>D17Mit28</italic> and
                                <italic>D17Mit51</italic>) comprising the <italic>H2</italic> region
                            of BALB.K mice (<italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>). (B) NK cell receptor
                            expression in MA/My parental mice and derived
                                    BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>d</sup></italic> and
                                    BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>
                            congenic mice. The receptors (indicated on the bottom of the panel) were
                            gated by FACS on NKp46<sup>+</sup> splenic NK cells; the proportion
                            of expression is indicated in each histogram. (C) Viral load in spleens
                            (left) and livers (right) of mice of the indicated genotypes, as
                            determined by plaque-forming assays 3 days p.i. (D) Spleen size (top)
                            and weight and total cellularity (bottom) determined in MA/My and
                                    BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> mice at
                            7 days p.i. White bar, uninfected mice; black bar, MCMV-infected mice.
                            Data were analyzed using two-way ANOVA analysis and the two-tailed
                            Student's test. Data are presented as mean ± SEM and
                                <italic>P</italic> values of significant differences between groups
                            are indicated. Results shown in panel B are representative of three
                            experiments using 2–3 mice per group; results shown in panels C
                            and D are representative of five independent experiments using 3–8
                            mice per group.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap id="pgen-1001368-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
                        <title>Nomenclature, NKC/<italic>H2</italic> genotype, and MCMV titer of
                            mouse strains used in this paper.</title>
                    </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pgen-1001368-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
                        <colgroup span="1">
                            <col align="left" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        </colgroup>
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard nomenclature</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Abbreviation used in this paper</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NKC genotype</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>H2</italic> genotype</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> transgene</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCMV titer</td>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BALB/c</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BALB</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>H2</italic><sup>d</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">high</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>MA/My</bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>MA/My</bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>H2</italic></bold><bold><sup>k</sup></bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>low</bold></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C.C3-<italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BALB.K</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BALB</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>H2</italic><sup>k</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">high</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>C.MA-Cmv3r.C3-
                                                </bold><bold><italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic></bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>BALB-</bold><bold><italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic></bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>MA/My</bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>H2</italic></bold><bold><sup>k</sup></bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>−</bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>low</bold></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C.MA-Cmv3r.C-<italic>H2<sup>d</sup></italic></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>d</sup></italic></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MA/My</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>H2</italic><sup>d</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">high</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FVB/N</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FVB/N</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>H2</italic><sup>q</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">high</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FVB-Tg(<italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>) (funder
                                    #65864)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FVB/N</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>H2</italic><sup>q</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">high</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>−</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FVB/N</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>H2</italic><sup>q</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">high</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>B6.129P-</bold><bold><italic>H2</italic></bold><bold>-D1<sup>tm1Bpe</sup>
                                    </bold><bold><italic>H2</italic></bold><bold>-K1<sup>tm1Bpe</sup></bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>B6.</bold><bold><italic>H2</italic></bold><bold><sup>0</sup></bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>B6</bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>H2</italic></bold><bold><sup>0</sup>
                                        (MHC-I knock out)</bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>−</bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>low</bold></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(FVB-Tg(<italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>)1Sv x
                                        B6.129P-<italic>H2</italic>-D1<sup>tm1Bpe</sup>
                                    <italic>H2</italic>-K1<sup>tm1Bpe</sup>)F<sub>3</sub></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic></bold><bold>/</bold><bold><italic>H2</italic></bold><bold><sup>0</sup>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                                            (F<sub>3</sub>)</bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>FVB/N</bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>H2</italic></bold><bold><sup>0</sup></bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>+</bold></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>low</bold></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0</sup>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>−</sup>
                                        (F<sub>3</sub>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FVB/N</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>H2</italic><sup>0</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">high</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0/q</sup>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                                        (F<sub>3</sub>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FVB/N</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>H2</italic><sup>0/q</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">high</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0/q</sup>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>−</sup>
                                        (F<sub>3</sub>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FVB/N</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>H2</italic><sup>0/q</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">high</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>q</sup>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                                        (F<sub>3</sub>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FVB/N</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>H2</italic><sup>q</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">high</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
                        <fn id="nt101">
                            <label/>
                            <p>Text in Bold indicates mouse strains whose genotypes correlate with
                                low viral titers.</p>
                        </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
                <p>To examine the effect of the genetic background on the expression of NKC-encoded
                    receptors in the <italic>Cmv3<sup>MA</sup></italic><sup>/My</sup> region, we
                    used a panel of antibodies with known antigen specificities (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s001">Figure S1</xref>)
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Makrigiannis1">[31]</xref>. Though several anti-Ly49 antibodies are cross-reactive
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Makrigiannis1">[31]</xref>, we observed variations among the mouse strains in terms
                    of frequency of Ly49 subpopulations. Compared to
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>d</sup></italic> mice,
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> animals had a
                    significantly increased frequency of NK cells stained with the monoclonal
                    antibodies 12A8 (against Ly49R; <italic>P</italic> = 0.02)
                    and 14B11 (against Ly49I/U; <italic>P</italic> = 0.007)
                        (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g001">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s002">Figure S2</xref>).
                    Notably, 14B11-stained NK cells were also significantly increased in
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> mice compared
                    to MA/My mice (<italic>P</italic> = 0.005). These results
                    demonstrated the influence of <italic>H2</italic> alleles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Johansson1">[32]</xref>, as well as the
                    influence of an additional non-<italic>H2</italic> mechanism, in the formation
                    of the Ly49 repertoire. We also observed a highly significant increase in the
                    frequency of NK cells labeled with 2F1 antibody
                    (<italic>P</italic> = 0.004), which recognizes the
                    maturation marker KLRG1, in
                        BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>d</sup></italic> mice compared to
                    their <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> counterparts. Finally, we observed that NK
                    cells from the three mouse strains that share the
                        <italic>Cmv3<sup>MA</sup></italic><sup>/My</sup> allele lacked expression of
                    NKG2A/C/E and CD94-associated receptors at the protein but not mRNA level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g001">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s003">Figure
                    S3B</xref>). By contrast, there was a normal expression of these receptors in
                    the FVB/N mouse strain, which carries an NKC haplotype similar to that of MA/My
                    mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s003">Figure S3A
                        and S3B</xref>).</p>
                <p>To evaluate the effect of the transferred MA/My chromosome 6
                        (<italic>Cmv3</italic>) segment on the response of MCMV-susceptible BALB/c
                    and BALB.K mice, we infected congenic and parental control mice by
                    intraperitoneal (i.p.) inoculation of MCMV sublethal doses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). By day 3 post-infection (p.i),
                    uncontrolled MCMV replication was observed in the spleen of susceptible BALB/c
                    mice (log<sub>10</sub> plaque-forming units
                    [PFU] = 4.39±0.16), while MCMV-resistant
                    MA/My mice had restricted viral replication, as shown by a &gt;100-fold lower
                    viral titer (log<sub>10</sub> PFU = 1.81±0.05) than
                    that seen in BALB/c mice. Single congenic BALB.K and
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>d</sup></italic> mice had viral
                    titers that were indistinguishable from those observed in BALB/c mice. More
                    importantly, congenic mice with the BALB.K background, which carry only one copy
                    of the MA/My NKC
                        (BALB-NKC<sup>BALB</sup><italic>Cmv3</italic><sup>MA/My</sup>.<italic>H2</italic><sup>k</sup>),
                    were as susceptible to MCMV as BALB/c, BALB.K, and
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>d</sup></italic> mice. By
                    contrast, double congenic
                        BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> mice had restricted
                    virus growth to the same extent as resistant MA/My mice. Viral titers in the
                    liver correlated with those observed in the spleens. Furthermore, by day 7 p.i.,
                    the virus was cleared from the spleen (unpublished data), which had undergone a
                    massive increase in weight and cell number in MA/My and
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g001">Figure 1D</xref>). Collectively,
                    these data demonstrate that the interaction between
                        <italic>Cmv3<sup>MA</sup></italic><sup>/My</sup> and
                        <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> confers MCMV resistance and is sufficient to
                    explain the control of viral load observed in MA/My mice.</p>
                <p>Because we did not have antibodies that specifically recognize Ly49P receptors
                    and to examine a possible role of CD94 heterodimers, we attempted to confirm the
                    results obtained in the congenic mice in a new cross between two strains that
                    independently carried the <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> loci and the Ly49P
                    gene at the NKC. We examined the segregation of MCMV viral load in the spleens
                    of progeny mice from an F<sub>2</sub> cross between the MCMV-susceptible strains
                    FVB/N and BALB.K. Although both parental strains sustained a relatively high
                    viral titer (5.2 log<sub>10</sub> PFU), the 137 F<sub>2</sub> progeny showed a
                    continuous distribution ranging from 2 to 6 log<sub>10</sub> PFU (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). To evaluate the
                    contribution of <italic>H2</italic> and NKC genes to MCMV resistance in this
                    cross, F<sub>2</sub> mice were genotyped and distributed according to their NKC
                        (<italic>Ly49e</italic>) and <italic>H2</italic> (<italic>IAA1</italic>)
                    genotypes. Mice homozygous for <italic>H2<sup>kk</sup></italic> alleles from
                    BALB.K and <italic>NKC<sup>ff</sup></italic> alleles from FVB/N had the lowest
                    viral load (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). The
                    model that best fitted this phenotype/genotype distribution in the analysis of
                    variance had a joint logarithm of odds (LOD) score of 9
                        (<italic>P</italic>&lt;10<sup>−11</sup>) and accounted for
                    29.6% of the phenotypic variation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001368-t002">Table 2</xref>). Thus, there was a highly
                    significant association between NKC/<italic>H2</italic> interaction and control
                    of MCMV infection in this second cross, indicating that <italic>Cmv3</italic>
                    was also present in the FVB/N mouse strain and that its expression in the
                    presence of <italic>H2</italic><sup>k</sup> was necessary and sufficient for
                    viral control. Furthermore, these data suggest that the same gene encodes
                        <italic>Cmv3</italic> in both the MA/My and FVB/N NKC regions.</p>
                <fig id="pgen-1001368-g002" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.g002</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 2</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title>MCMV resistance in FVB/N×BALB.K F<sub>2</sub> progeny dependent
                            on specific combinations between the NKC and
                            <italic>H2</italic>.</title>
                        <p>(A) Genetic analysis of MCMV infection control in FVB/N×BALB.K
                                F<sub>2</sub> progeny. Mice (FVB/N and BALB.K,
                            <italic>n</italic> = 11 per strain;
                            FVB/N×BALB.K F<sub>2</sub>,
                            <italic>n</italic> = 137) were infected with 5,000
                            PFU of MCMV; the spleen viral titers were determined by plaque assay at
                            day 3 p.i. (B) Box plots show the combined effect of the NKC and
                                <italic>H2</italic> loci derived from FVB/N
                                (<italic>H2<sup>qq</sup></italic> and
                                <italic>NKC<sup>ff</sup></italic>) or BALB.K
                                    (<italic>H2<sup>kk</sup></italic> and
                                <italic>NKC<sup>cc</sup></italic>) parental mice on the viral loads
                            in the spleens of the F<sub>2</sub> progeny. The median and
                            interquartile ranges are shown. Solid dots denote outliers. The red box
                            corresponds to the combination of <italic>NKC<sup>ff</sup></italic> and
                                    <italic>H2<sup>kk</sup></italic> loci
                                (<italic>P</italic>&lt;6×10<sup>−11</sup>).</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap id="pgen-1001368-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
                        <title>ANOVA of MCMV load in spleens from (FVB/N×BALB.K) F<sub>2</sub>
                            mice.</title>
                    </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pgen-1001368-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
                        <colgroup span="1">
                            <col align="left" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        </colgroup>
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Locus</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LOD</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">% Variance</td>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;6.0 E−11</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.6</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Ly49e</italic> (NKC)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;4.5 E−5</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.2</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.7</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>IAA1</italic> (<italic>H2</italic>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;6.4 E−5</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.9</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2b">
                <title>Transgenic expression of <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> has a modest
                    effect on MCMV control in the presence of
                    <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic></title>
                <p>Previously, we showed that activation of Ly49P-bearing reporter cells requires
                    the <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> host molecule on MCMV-infected cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Desrosiers1">[25]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Kielczewska1">[26]</xref>. Therefore, to better
                    delineate the role of <italic>H2</italic> in the host response against MCMV, we
                    attempted <italic>in vivo</italic> rescue of the FVB/N susceptible phenotype by
                    genetic transfer of an 11 kb <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> genomic fragment
                    cloned from AKR mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g003">Figure
                        3A</xref>). We monitored for the presence of a diagnostic 300 bp fragment
                    corresponding to exon 3 of the <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> gene to
                    identify transgenic FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup> mice among the
                    founder population (unpublished data). By surface staining of mouse embryo
                    fibroblasts (MEF) from FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup> mice, we observed
                    the normal low levels of <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> expression under
                    regular conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g003">Figure
                        3B</xref>). However, IFN-β treatment up-regulated expression of
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> on MEF cells from either
                        FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup> mice or AKR mice (H2-D<sup>k</sup>
                    transgene donor mouse strain) to the same extent, indicating that the transgene
                    promoter regulatory sequences were intact (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). We also found that the level of
                    expression of <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> in splenocytes from the FVB/N
                    transgenic mice was similar to the natural
                            <italic>H2</italic>-D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic> expression in
                    splenocytes from MA/My or BALB.K strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g003">Figure 3C</xref>). Finally, we investigated the
                    expression of transgenic <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> and endogenous
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<italic><sup>q</sup></italic> molecules in T and B
                    cells isolated from the spleen and observed that the two MHC-I molecules were
                    expressed in FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup> mice at levels similar to
                    those found in <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic>- and
                        <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>-bearing inbred mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s004">Figure S4</xref>).
                    To test whether the <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> transgene is capable of
                    stimulating the Ly49P receptor, we assessed the activation of Ly49P-bearing
                    reporter cells and found that these cells were equally activated by
                    MCMV-infected MEF cells from BALB.K or from
                        FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s005">Figure
                    S5A</xref>). Stimulation of Ly49P reporters was also observed upon challenge by
                    MEFs infected with a mutant virus lacking m157 (the Ly49H ligand). However,
                    Ly49P reporter cell stimulation was lost upon infection of MEF cells with a
                    mutant virus lacking the <italic>m04</italic> gene, indicating that the
                    transgenic H2-D<sup>k</sup> molecule also requires <italic>m04</italic>/gp34 to
                    stimulate Ly49P, as reported (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s005">Figure S5B</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Kielczewska1">[26]</xref>.</p>
                <fig id="pgen-1001368-g003" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.g003</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 3</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title>Functional characterization of <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic>
                            transgenic mice.</title>
                        <p>(A) Schematic representation of the <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic>
                            gene within the 11.5 kb EcoRI genomic DNA fragment from AKR mice used to
                            generate transgenic mice. (B) Expression of
                                <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> on MEFs from FVB/N nontransgenic
                                (FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>−</sup>, transgenic
                                FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>, and AKR
                                    (<italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>) mice. MEFs from
                                FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup> and wild-type littermates
                            were prepared from PCR-typed embryos, untreated or incubated overnight
                            with 100 U/ml IFN-β prior to analysis of
                                <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> expression by FACS. (C)
                                <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> staining on lymphocytes from
                                FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>−</sup> (red peak), BALB.K (dashed
                            peak), MA/My (black peak), and FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                            (dotted peak) mice. Bar graph shows quantification of the percentage of
                                <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> expression from 2–3 mice per
                            group. (D) Splenocytes from B6.<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic> mice or
                                NKC/<italic>H2</italic> histocompatible mice were inoculated into
                            either untreated or asialo-GM1–treated NK cell–depleted
                            hosts. Ratio values indicate the relative survival in the test
                            population (CFSE<sup>high</sup>) compared to the histocompatible control
                            population (CFSE<sup>low</sup>) at 18 hours after injection. Three mice
                            per group were analyzed. Statistical significance between untreated and
                            NK-depleted mice is shown. (E) Viral load in spleens (left) and livers
                            (right) of mice of the indicated genotypes was determined by
                            plaque-forming assays at day 3 p.i. Data were analyzed using two-way
                            ANOVA analysis and the two-tailed Student's test. Data are
                            presented as mean ± SEM and <italic>P</italic> values of
                            significant results between groups are indicated. Results shown are
                            representative of 2–3 independent experiments.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <p>To establish the contribution of <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> to the MCMV
                    response, we first investigated a possible modulation of the Ly49 receptor
                    repertoire. No significant differences were found between transgenic and
                    non-transgenic mice in terms of the frequency of the various NK cell populations
                    tested (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s006">Figure
                        S6</xref>). Since <italic>H2</italic>-D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic> has the
                    potential to influence licensing through its interactions with cognate Ly49
                    inhibitory receptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Kim1">[16]</xref>, we addressed the licensing status of wild-type and
                    transgenic NK cells. To do this, we determined the ability of NK cells to
                    mediate <italic>in vivo</italic> rejection of MHC class I deficient splenocytes
                    isolated from B6.129P-<italic>H2</italic>-D1<sup>tm1Bpe</sup>
                    <italic>H2</italic>-K1<sup>tm1Bpe</sup> (herein
                        B6.<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic>) mice using a quantitative CFSE-based
                    method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Oberg1">[33]</xref>. As
                    previously described, B6.<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic> mice tolerated grafted
                    syngeneic splenocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g003">Figure
                        3D</xref>). By contrast, both FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup> and
                        FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>−</sup> mice rejected
                            B6.<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic> splenocytes with the same efficiency,
                    suggesting that the presence of the
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic> transgene does not alter
                    the licensing status of NK cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). Finally, we monitored early viral replication following
                    MCMV infection in
                            FVB-Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>+</sup></italic>
                    mice, along with single and double
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>d</sup></italic> and
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> congenic mice
                    and parental MA/My mice. We observed that
                            FVB-Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>+</sup></italic>
                    mice had a statistically significant, albeit modest, reduction in MCMV
                    replication in the spleen (but not in the liver) compared to nontrangenic
                    littermates; this reduction represented only a small fraction (1∶7) of the
                    reduction observed in BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>
                    congenic mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g003">Figure 3E</xref>).
                    Collectively, these data demonstrated that the
                            <italic>H2</italic>-D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic> transgene was fully
                    expressed and able to recognize and activate the Ly49P receptor <italic>in
                        vitro</italic>; however, it only provided partial control of MCMV
                    infection.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2c">
                <title>Transgenic expression of <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> has a major effect
                    on MCMV control in the absence of <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic></title>
                <p>Classical MHC class I molecules are the prototype ligands for Ly49 receptors.
                    Reporter cell assays and tetramer binding assays suggest that
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic> molecules elicit both
                    activating signals, through Ly49P, and inhibitory signals, through Ly49I and
                    Ly49V <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Desrosiers1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Makrigiannis1">[31]</xref>. By contrast, <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic>-encoded
                    molecules can elicit strong inhibitory signals through Ly49I or Ly49C, but are
                    inert to Ly49G2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Hanke1">[34]</xref>, as well as to <italic>Cmv3</italic>-encoded
                    activating receptors (Ly49P, Ly49R, and Ly49U) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Desrosiers1">[25]</xref>. Therefore, we
                    hypothesized that the poor MCMV infection control observed in
                        FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup> mice resulted from competition
                    between the inhibitory and activating signals emanating from
                            <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic>- and
                            <italic>H2</italic>-D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>-encoded ligands,
                    respectively. To test this hypothesis, we crossed
                        FVB-Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>+</sup></italic>
                    transgenic mice with B6.<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic> mice, which possess
                    targeted deletions at the <italic>H2-D</italic> and <italic>H2-K</italic> genes.
                    This cross produced F<sub>3</sub> progeny mice homozygous for the FVB/N NKC
                            (<italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>), but with a different assortment
                    of MHC class I alleles. F<sub>3</sub> mice were either (1) deficient in
                    endogenous MHC class I alleles in the presence or absence of the
                            <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> transgene
                        (<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic>/Tg(Dk)<sup>+</sup> or
                            <italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic>/Tg(Dk)<sup>−</sup>), (2)
                    hemizygous for <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> in the presence or absence of the
                            <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> transgene
                        (<italic>H2<sup>0/q</sup></italic>/Tg(Dk)<sup>−</sup> or
                            <italic>H2<sup>0/q</sup></italic>/Tg(Dk)<sup>+</sup>), or (3)
                    homozygous for <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> in the presence of the
                            <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> transgene
                        (<italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic>/Tg(Dk)<sup>+</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g004">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001368-t001">Table 1</xref>). Again, we
                    monitored whether the frequencies of various NK cell populations were affected
                    by the genetic makeup of F<sub>3</sub> mice and detected no major variations in
                    the NK cell populations, the only exception being Ly49G<sup>+</sup> NK
                    cells, which were barely detectable in
                        <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0</sup>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>−</sup>
                    mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s007">Figure
                        S7</xref>). Similarly, the level of <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> and
                        <italic>H2</italic>-K<sup>k</sup> expression on splenocytes was equivalent
                    in transgenic F<sub>3</sub> mice with different <italic>H2</italic> genotypes
                        (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s007">Figure
                        S7</xref>, right panel). By contrast, we noted that levels of
                        H2-D<sup>q</sup> expression on lymphocytes from homozygous
                            <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                    transgenic mice were double those of hemizygous
                        <italic>H2<sup>0/q</sup></italic>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                    transgenic mice (<italic>P</italic> = 0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g004">Figure 4B</xref> and bar graph).
                    Despite this variation in MHC class I expression levels, licensing of NK cells
                    from H2-D<sup>k</sup> transgenic mice carrying no (<italic>0</italic>), one
                        (<italic>0/q</italic>), or two (<italic>q/q</italic>)
                        <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> alleles was equivalent, as shown by their
                    ability to reject CFSE-labeled splenocytes from
                        B6.<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic> mice [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g004">Figure 4C</xref> right]. These results were
                    confirmed using explanted, IL-2-activated NK cells in cytotoxicity assays
                    against MCH class I–deficient RMA/S target cells [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g004">Figure 4C</xref> left],
                    demonstrating that NK cells from transgenic mice with different H2 assortments
                    sense equally the loss of MHC class I expression on target cells and therefore
                    are equally educated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Kim1">[16]</xref>.</p>
                <fig id="pgen-1001368-g004" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.g004</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 4</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title>Functional characterization of F<sub>3</sub> mice carrying the NKC
                            from FVB/N and different assortment of <italic>H2</italic>
                            molecules.</title>
                        <p>(A) Breeding scheme for the generation of F<sub>3</sub> mice carrying the
                            NKC loci from FVB/N parental mice and various combinations of
                                <italic>H2</italic> loci. The NKC, <italic>H2</italic>, and
                                <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> transgenic loci are represented by
                            boxes, as indicated. The parental (P)
                                FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup> and
                                B6.<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic> strains were mated to generate
                            the F<sub>1</sub> generation. Subsequently, F<sub>2</sub> mice carrying
                            an homozygous FVB/N NKC locus and heterozygous for either the
                                <italic>H2</italic> or the <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic>
                            transgene were kept and intercrossed to generate the F<sub>3</sub> mice
                            with different <italic>H2</italic> assortments
                                (<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic>:
                                <italic>H2-K<sup>b</sup></italic><sup>−/−</sup><italic>D<sup>b</sup></italic><sup>−/−</sup>).
                            (B) H2-D<sup>q</sup> staining of lymphocytes from
                                    <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup>/H2<sup>0</sup></italic>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                                    (<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic> red peak),
                                    <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup>/H2<sup>0/q</sup></italic>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                                    (<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic><sup>/q</sup>, dot peak), and
                                    <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup>/H2<sup>q/q</sup></italic>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                            mice (<italic>H2<sup>q/q</sup></italic>, dashed peak). Histograms on the
                            right represent the quantification of the level of
                                <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>q</sup> expression analyzed in three mice
                            per group. (C) Rejection of B6 MHC class I–deficient cells
                                <italic>in vivo</italic> by the indicated hosts was assessed as in
                                <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g003">Figure 3</xref>, and
                            statistically significant differences are shown. IL-2–derived NK
                            cells from the indicated mouse strains were co-cultured with
                            CFSE-labeled RMA/S cells. Specific lysis at the indicated
                            effector/target ratios was assessed by staining with 7-AAD and analyzed
                            by FACS. Values represent the mean of 2–3 mice per group. (D)
                            Viral loads in spleens (left) and livers (right) of parental and
                                F<sub>3</sub> mice of the indicated genotypes were determined by
                            plaque assay at day 3 p.i. Results shown represent five pooled
                            experiments. Data were analyzed using two-way ANOVA analysis and the
                            two-tailed Student's test. Significant <italic>P</italic> values
                            for differences between groups are indicated.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <p>To determine the influence of the various MHC class I molecules on the NK cell
                    immune response to MCMV infection, we examined F<sub>3</sub> mice and parental
                    controls at early time points, particularly on day 3 p.i., when
                    receptor-specific NK cell responses are established <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Dokun1">[18]</xref>. On day 3, the
                    post-infection viral titers in the spleens and livers of
                            <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2<sup>0/q</sup></italic>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                    and
                        <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0</sup>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>−</sup>
                    mice were indistinguishable, demonstrating that the presence of
                            <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> dampens the effect of
                            <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> on
                    the containment of virus replication (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g004">Figure 4D</xref>). By contrast, the presence of the
                    transgene had a significant effect in the absence of endogenous class I
                    molecules, as
                        <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0</sup>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                    mice had close to 30-fold lower viral titers compared to
                            <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2<sup>0/q</sup></italic>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>−</sup>
                    mice. In parallel, B6.<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic> control mice, which
                    express Ly49H, also cleared the virus load despite lacking MHC-I molecules
                        (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g004">Figure 4D</xref>). To
                    investigate the role of NK cells in limiting viral spread, we found that, as in
                    MA/My mice, the control of virus load was abrogated in
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> and
                            <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0</sup>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                    mice if treated with anti-asialo GM1 antibody prior to MCMV infection,
                    demonstrating that the resistance phenotype is NK cell-dependent (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s008">Figure
                    S8A</xref>). Indeed, we observed uncontrolled virus growth not only when MA/My
                    mice were pretreated with anti-asialo GM1 and anti-NK1.1 antibodies, but also
                    after they were pretreated with YE1/48 (anti-Ly49PRTV), 12A8 (anti-Ly49R), or
                    4D11 (anti-Ly49GT) antibodies, indicating an overlap in Ly49 receptor expression
                    on NK cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s009">Figure S9</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Desrosiers1">[25]</xref>. At day 6 p.i., a time characterized by robust
                    proliferation of receptor-specific NK cell populations responding to the virus
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Dokun1">[18]</xref>, we
                    found that mice expressing <italic>Cmv3</italic> resistance (MA/My,
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>, and
                            <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0</sup>/Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>+</sup></italic>)
                    had cleared MCMV from the spleen (unpublished data). Furthermore, spleen cell
                    numbers were increased 2–6-fold in these mice and BrdU uptake indicated a
                    robust NK cell proliferation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s008">Figure S8B</xref>). Together, our results indicate
                    that expression of <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> can rescue
                        <italic>Cmv3</italic>-determined MCMV resistance in the absence of
                    endogenous <italic>H2</italic><sup>q</sup> molecules and that
                            <italic>Cmv3/H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic>-mediated resistance is associated
                    with the expansion of NK cells in response to infection.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2d">
                <title>Host <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> inhibitory signals quantitatively
                    modulate MCMV resistance and restrict NK cell–specific proliferation upon
                    MCMV challenge</title>
                <p>To better define the role of <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> alleles, we compared
                    the kinetics of viral replication in
                        <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                    transgenic mice carrying no, one, or two <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic>
                    alleles. We observed that the number of <italic>H2</italic> alleles correlated
                    with a quantitative increase in viral load, as early as 36 hours p.i.. On days 3
                    and 5 p.i., differences in viral containment among mice of the three genotypes
                    were significant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g005">Figure
                    5A</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="pgen-1001368-g005" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.g005</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 5</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title><italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> expression interferes with NK cell
                            antiviral responses.</title>
                        <p>(A) MCMV viral load in the spleens of F<sub>3</sub> transgenic mice at
                            the indicated time-points was determined by plaque assay and
                                <italic>P</italic> values of significant results between groups are
                            indicated. (B) BrdU incorporation in NKp46-gated splenocytes stained
                            with anti-BrdU and 4D5 antibodies. Splenoytes were isolated from mice of
                            the indicated genotypes 5 days p.i. Graph bar represents the proportions
                            of NK cells incorporating BrdU in total splenic leukocytes with standard
                            deviations, using three mice per group. (C) Enriched NK cells from
                                    <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup>/H2<sup>0</sup></italic>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                            mice were labeled with CFSE then adoptively transferred into
                                    <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup>/H2<sup>0</sup></italic>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                            and
                                <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup>/H2<sup>0/q</sup></italic>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                            recipients 24 hours before infection with MCMV for 5 days. Analysis of
                            CFSE dilution in NK cells from the spleens of infected (dashed peaks) or
                            uninfected (solid peaks) mice. NK cell proliferation index (number of
                            divisions of CFSE-labeled NK cells) in
                                    <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup>/H2<sup>0</sup></italic>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                            and
                                <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup>/H2<sup>0/q</sup></italic>/Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                            mice. Statistically significant differences between groups are
                            indicated. Three mice per group were analyzed and results shown are
                            representative of two experiments. Data were analyzed using two-way
                            ANOVA analysis and the two-tailed Student's test. Significant
                                <italic>P</italic> values for differences between groups are
                            indicated.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <p>To investigate the effect of <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> molecules on NK cell
                    specific responses against MCMV, we monitored BrdU incorporation on NK cells
                    after MCMV infection in FVB/N WT and F<sub>3</sub> mice carrying no, one, or two
                    copies of <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> alleles. After 5 days p.i., NK cells
                    were stained with the anti-Ly49ORV (4E5) monoclonal antibody, which stained
                    around 50% of NK cells in these strains (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s006">Figure S6</xref>
                    and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s007">Figure
                        S7</xref>), and with the anti-BrdU monoclonal antibody. In all mice, we
                    observed that NK cells that incorporated BrdU were negative for the Ly49ORV
                    antibody staining. Furthermore, the increase in BrdU incorporation was inversely
                    proportional to the number of <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> alleles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). This result
                    suggests that there is a dose-dependent inhibition of NK cell proliferation by
                            <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> alleles in response to MCMV infection.
                    Finally, to investigate whether host MHC-I molecules affect NK cell activity
                    upon MCMV infection, we adoptively transferred CFSE-labeled NK cells enriched
                    from
                            <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0</sup>/Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<sup>+</sup>
                    donor mice into
                        <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0</sup>/Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<sup>+</sup>
                    or
                            <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0/q</sup>/Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<sup>+</sup>
                    recipients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g005">Figure 5C</xref>).
                    After 5 days p.i., donor NK cells had undergone more rounds of division in the
                            <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0</sup>/Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<sup>+</sup>
                    recipients than the NK cells that were transferred into
                            <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2</italic><sup>0/q</sup>/Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<sup>+</sup>
                    mice; this indicated that <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> alleles limited NK
                    cell proliferation induced by MCMV infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g006">Figure 6C</xref> bar graph). Thus, NK cells carrying
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> as the sole MHC class I molecule were
                    impaired in their ability to proliferate if the recipient mice carried
                            <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> alleles. Collectively, these results
                    suggest that expression of host <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> molecules
                    dampens the capacity of NK cells to protect against MCMV.</p>
                <fig id="pgen-1001368-g006" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.g006</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 6</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title>Model of <italic>H2</italic>-dependent,
                            <italic>Cmv3</italic>-determined NK response against MCMV
                            infection.</title>
                        <p>The strength of Ly49 inhibitory signals and the presence of
                                <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>-mediated activating signals
                            modulate the NK cell response against virus infection. Our set of NKC
                            congenic mice bore different assortments of Ly49 receptors, but carried
                            an identical <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> resistance haplotype. (A)
                            NK cells from BALB.K mice had a high frequency and strong binding of
                            inhibitory Ly49 receptors, which rendered BALB.K mice most susceptible
                            to MCMV infection. (B) NK cells from congenic
                                    BALB.<italic>Cmv3<sup>het</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> mice
                            carried one copy of the activating <italic>Ly49p</italic> gene, which
                            can activate the
                                Ly49P/<italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>/<italic>m04</italic> axis,
                            allowing for intermediate viral loads in heterozygous mice. (C) NK cells
                            from BALB.<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> mice had
                            the lowest frequency (and/or weakest binding) of inhibitory Ly49
                            receptors for <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> molecules and the highest
                            frequency of activating Ly49P<sup>+</sup> NK cells, resulting in
                            strong control of MCMV infection. Our set of F<sub>3</sub> mice carried
                            different MHC-I components, but an identical
                            <italic>Cmv3</italic>-resistance haplotype, encoding seven inhibitory
                            and three activating Ly49 receptors, including Ly49P. (D) Engagement of
                            inhibitory receptors in
                                    FVB-Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>−</sup></italic>
                            mice resulted in inhibition of the NK cell response against MCMV. (E) In
                                    FVB-Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>+</sup></italic>
                            mice, activating signals mediated by the engagement of Ly49P by
                                <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>/<italic>m04</italic>, in the
                            presence of inhibitory signals elicited by
                                <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> molecules, provided a marginal
                            enhancement of the NK cell response, and intermediate virus control. (F)
                            In the absence of inhibitory <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> signals,
                                <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>-dependent activation of NK cells
                            was more efficient, which resulted in strong control of MCMV infection
                            in
                                    <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic>/Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>+</sup></italic>
                            mice.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>In this study, we examined the combined contribution of the NKC and
                    <italic>H2</italic> loci to the NK cell response against MCMV infection. We
                report that MCMV resistance was recapitulated in double-congenic mice and in an
                independent F<sub>2</sub> cross that reconstituted the combination of
                    <italic>Cmv3</italic> resistance alleles and <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>.
                Furthermore, we established that the <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> molecule is
                essential to the resistance phenotype, because genetically susceptible mice bearing
                    <italic>Cmv3</italic> were rendered resistant by acquisition of an
                    <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> transgene. However, efficient virus control
                was observed only in the absence of endogenous <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic>
                molecules, whose inhibitory input quantitatively modulated virus control. Thus, MHC
                class I molecules play antagonistic roles in the NK response against viral
                infection.</p>
            <sec id="s3a">
                <title>Combined effect of the NKC and MHC loci on NK cell antiviral
                    responses</title>
                <p>The role of the MHC has been studied using panels of congenic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Chalmer1">[27]</xref>,
                    sub-congenic, and transgenic mice or F<sub>2</sub> crosses with the same NKC
                    haplotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Dighe1">[28]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Xie1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Xie2">[35]</xref>. To the best of our knowledge, the present study is
                    the first to provide formal proof of the impact of both NKC and MHC haplotypes
                    on NK cell antiviral activities <italic>in vivo</italic>. Our study, through the
                    use of single- and double-congenic mice, minimized differences in non-NKC or
                    non-MHC genes. Thus, we established that the joint action of specific alleles at
                    these two regions accounted for most of the overall phenotypic differences
                    between the MCMV-susceptible BALB/c and MCMV-resistant MA/My mouse strains.
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> mice were
                    indistinguishable from MA/My mice in terms of initial control of infection and
                    late NK cell responses.</p>
                <p>Although the MA/My NKC region in congenic mice encompasses more than just
                        <italic>Ly49</italic> genes, our data indicates that the influence of MHC
                    alleles on MCMV-resistance stems from the capacity of MHC class I molecules to
                    serve as ligands for Ly49 receptors. In support of this hypothesis, the
                        F<sub>2</sub> cross between the MCMV-susceptible FVB/N
                            (<italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic>) and BALB.K
                        (<italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>) mouse strains demonstrated that FVB/N mice
                    carried a <italic>Cmv3</italic> resistance allele that was conditional to
                            <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> and overridden by the
                            <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> susceptibility allele. Within the
                        <italic>Cmv3</italic> region, Ly49 receptors were responsive to MHC class I
                    ligands. On the one hand, we noticed that none of the available anti-NKG2 or
                    anti-CD94 antibodies recognized MA/My mouse NK cells, in contrast to NK cell
                    recognition in FVB/N mice. Nevertheless, we observed that F<sub>2</sub> mice of
                    the combined <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic>
                    genotype restrained viral replication to an extent similar to that seen in MA/My
                    mice. On the other hand, our haplotype studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Desrosiers1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Webb1">[36]</xref> and new public data
                        (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phenome.jax.org" xlink:type="simple">http://phenome.jax.org</ext-link>) indicate that FVB/N and MA/My share the
                    same <italic>Ly49</italic> gene repertoire, including Ly49P. Consequently, it
                    seems that NK cell responsiveness during MCMV infection varies with different
                    NKC-MHC combinations and is optimal only with a precise combination of Ly49
                    receptors inherited from MA/My (or FVB/N) mice and MHC class I
                        <italic>H2</italic><sup>k</sup> molecules.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3b">
                <title>Role of the MHC class I molecule H2-D<sup>k</sup></title>
                <p>Our results confirmed that the <italic>H2</italic> effect was due to the MHC
                    class 1 molecule <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>. Using an 11 kb genomic
                    fragment containing a functional <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> gene, we
                    achieved a phenotypic rescue, although the rescue was incomplete if combined
                    with <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> alleles. The complete protective effect of
                            <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> was restored in F<sub>3</sub> mice
                    lacking endogenous <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> molecules. Although
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> also affects the adaptive immune response,
                    early containment of viral replication, massive NK cell proliferation, and
                    reversal of the resistance phenotype by depletion of NK cells in
                            FVB-<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic>-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup>
                    clearly support a mechanism at the level of NK cells. Because of the presence of
                    both inhibitory and activating Ly49 receptors, several nonexclusive scenarios
                    could account for the precise mode of action of the combined MHC class I
                            <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> and <italic>Ly49</italic> genotypes on
                    the NK cell response against MCMV: (1)low threshold of NK cell activation
                    through weak <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>/Ly49 inhibitory signals, (2)
                    effective NK cell activation through <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>/Ly49
                    activating signals, and (3) interplay between
                    <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>/Ly49 activating and inhibitory signals.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3c">
                <title>Inhibitory signals</title>
                <p>One possibility is that MHC class I/inhibitory Ly49 signals have a negative
                    impact on the NK cell response to MCMV. In our study, mature NK cells in BALB.K
                    mice (which are the most susceptible to MCMV infection) express three inhibitory
                    receptors: Ly49A, Ly49C, and Ly49G2, which all bind to MHC-I
                            <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> molecules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Makrigiannis1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Hanke1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Jonsson2">[37]</xref>. Thus, the
                    majority of NK cells from BALB.K mice should be inhibited by a receptor for a
                    self-ligand. Indeed, we have recently shown that deletion of the
                        <italic>m04</italic> gene renders BALB.K mice resistant to MCMV infection,
                    as the protein it encodes abolishes NK cell activation via the
                    “missing-self” recognition mechanism (Babic et al., 2010) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Babic1">[56]</xref>. The
                        <italic>m04</italic>/gp34 protein escorts MHC class I molecules to the
                    surface of infected cells, thus maintaining a level of surface MHC expression
                    sufficient enough to trigger inhibitory NK cell receptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Kavanagh1">[38]</xref>. Thus, with only three
                    (Ly49V, Ly49I, and Ly49G2) out of seven Ly49 inhibitory receptors able to
                    recognize <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> molecules, NK cells from
                            BALB.<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup> H2<sup>k</sup></italic> mice should be
                    less susceptible to inhibition by <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> binding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g006">Figure 6A–6C</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3d">
                <title>Activating signals</title>
                <p>The existence of an <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>–mediated activating
                    axis to MCMV resistance is supported by the gain-of-function phenotype of
                        FVB-<italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> transgenic mice, which presented
                    itself despite their Ly49 repertoire that is virtually identical to that of
                    their non-transgenic littermates (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s006">Figure S6A and S6B</xref>). Furthermore, the absence
                    of NK cell triggering through inhibitory Ly49 receptors was not sufficient to
                    allow efficient control of MCMV replication, as demonstrated by the
                        F<sub>3</sub>
                    <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic> MHC class I–deficient mice. Most NK
                    cells that develop in MHC class I–deficient hosts are unable to respond to
                    MHC class I–deficient targets. However, a recent study demonstrated that,
                    in the context of MCMV infection, NK cells eliminate virally infected cells in
                    MHC class I–negative hosts, in addition to regaining the ability to
                    eliminate MHC class I–deficient hematopoietic host cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Sun1">[39]</xref>. This
                    mechanism seems to be triggered by the inflammatory milieu induced by MCMV
                    infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Sun1">[39]</xref>.
                    These observations suggest that the susceptibility of
                        <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic> MHC class I–deficient
                        F<sub>3</sub> animals to MCMV infection is not due to a defect in education
                    but to the absence of an activation axis, which is provided by
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3e">
                <title>Interplay of inhibitory and activating signals</title>
                <p>Activating signals, mediated by the engagement of Ly49P by
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>/<italic>m04</italic>, provided only a
                    marginal enhancement of the NK cell response in the presence of
                            <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic>. Interestingly, we observed a gene
                    dosage effect in the inhibitory action of <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> that
                    correlated with the level of surface expression of this MHC class I molecule.
                    However, <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> copy number did not affect the ability
                    of NK cells from <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> transgenic mice (FVB or F3)
                    to eliminate MHC class I deficient target cells; this indicates that
                            <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> gene dosage does not alter
                    education/licensing of NK cells. By contrast, adoptive transfer experiments
                    demonstrated that <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> alleles expressed on host
                    cells limit the ability of NK cells to respond to MCMV infection, indicating
                    that the <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> effect influences NK cell recognition
                    of class I ligands on target cells. This suggests that
                        <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> inhibitory signals dominate over
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>-dependent activating
                    signals emanating from MCMV-infected cells. One possibility is that
                            <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> inhibitory signals are stronger and/or
                    more frequent than <italic>H2</italic><sup>k</sup>-dependent activating signals.
                    Indeed, it has been shown that both the density and the avidity of inhibitory
                    Ly49-ligand pairs determine the strength of inhibition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Chalifour1">[40]</xref>. Alternatively,
                            <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> MHC class I molecules could compete with
                        H2-D<sup>k</sup> for binding with the <italic>m04</italic> protein and thus
                    blunt the <italic>m04</italic>/H2-D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>-Ly49P
                    activating axis. We have noted that Ly49P reporter cells are equally stimulated
                    by MCMV-infected MEFs of <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> or
                            <italic>H2<sup>k</sup></italic><sup>/q</sup> genotype, which may
                    indicate otherwise (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001368.s005">Figure S5</xref>). However, these results might not
                    reflect the effect of H2<italic><sup>q</sup></italic> molecules on the
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>/<italic>m04</italic>
                    complex under physiological conditions. While the molecular details of
                            <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic> inhibition of NK cell function remain
                    unclear, our results suggest a model in which two antagonistic mechanisms are at
                    play in NKC-<italic>H2</italic>-determined resistance to virus infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001368-g006">Figure 6</xref>). One involves
                    enhanced NK cell responses through <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>-mediated
                    activating signals. The other involves dampened NK cell responses through
                    inhibitory Ly49 receptors stimulated by class I <italic>H2<sup>q</sup></italic>
                    (or <italic>H2<sup>d</sup></italic>) molecules, which override the effect of the
                        <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> construct.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3f">
                <title>Conclusion</title>
                <p>It is puzzling that Ly49 receptors can sense MHC class I molecules on infected
                    cells despite immune-evasion mechanisms elaborated by MCMV that downregulate
                    surface expression of MHC class I molecules. Indeed, mouse strain–specific
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Hasan1">[41]</xref> and
                    cell type–specific <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-LoPiccolo1">[42]</xref> differences have been reported in the ability of
                    immunoevasins to inhibit lysis of infected cells by CTLs, indicating that the
                    efficiency of MHC class I downregulation during MCMV infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Pinto1">[43]</xref> is context
                    dependent. <italic>In vivo</italic> MCMV replication occurs in a multitude of
                    cell types, and perhaps the ability of the virus to achieve immune avoidance
                    selectively might contribute to the delicate equilibrium of coexistence it has
                    established with the host.</p>
                <p>The striking similarities between Ly49 and KIR interactions with their respective
                    MHC-I ligands and how they both affect NK cell function prompted us and other
                    researchers to use the mouse as a model to study NK cell antiviral responses.
                    Our results lend support to clinical and epidemiological studies implicating
                    KIR-HLA interactions of different strengths in determining a hierarchy of NK
                    cell activation with varied effects on the host response against herpersviruses
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Gazit2">[44]</xref>, HCV
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Khakoo1">[45]</xref>, and
                    HIV <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Carrington1">[46]</xref>.
                    Our work also highlights the ability of inhibitory signals to overcome NK cell
                    activation. These regulatory mechanisms would be relevant in conditions where NK
                    cell activation is undesirable during infection or immune disease. For example,
                    activating KIR genotypes have been found to predispose to reactivation of
                    quiescent, opportunistic infections associated with herpesvirus infections in
                    HIV patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Price1">[47]</xref>), and to fatal outcome following Ebola virus
                    infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Wauquier1">[48]</xref>; furthermore, they may constitute a risk factor for
                    susceptibility to autoimmunity and certain cancers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Nelson1">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Baessler1">[50]</xref>. Ultimately, our data
                    indicate that, as has been proposed for cancer and autoimmunity, manipulating
                    the balance between inhibitory and activating NK receptor signals represents a
                    possible avenue to harness the therapeutic potential of NK cells against virus
                    infections.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
            <title>Materials and Methods</title>
            <sec id="s4a">
                <title>Ethics statement</title>
                <p>The animal protocols and experiments were approved by the Canadian Council on
                    Animal Care (CCAC) and the McGill University Animal Resources Center.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4b">
                <title>Animals</title>
                <p>MA/My, BALB.K, BALB/c, C57Bl/6 (B6), DBA/J, and AKR mice were purchased from The
                    Jackson Laboratory. FVB/N mice were purchased from Charles Rivers Laboratories.
                    The B6 mice deficient for
                        <italic>H2</italic>-<italic>D<sup>b</sup>K<sup>b</sup></italic>
                        (B6.<italic>H2</italic><sup>0</sup>) were kindly provided by Hidde L. Ploegh
                    (Cambridge, Massachusetts).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4c">
                <title>Generation and genetic characterization of congenic mice</title>
                <p>BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> and
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>d</sup></italic> were generated
                    by backcrossing the (MA/MyXBALB.K) F1 or (MA/MyXBALB/c) F1 into BALB.K or
                    BALB/c, respectively, for at least ten generations. At each backcross,
                    inheritance of the NKC from parental MA/My mice was genotyped using either the
                        <italic>Ly49e</italic> marker or the <italic>D6mit135</italic> marker <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-FodilCornu2">[51]</xref>. In the
                    progeny, the introgressed portion from parental MA/My mice, which included the
                    NKC, was analyzed using microsatellite markers or by detecting known SNPs. Once
                    the genetic region was reduced from 34 Mb (between <italic>D6MIT36</italic> and
                        <italic>D6MIT59</italic>) to 10 Mb (between <italic>rs13479016</italic> and
                        <italic>rs13479061</italic> SNPs), heterozygous mice were intercrossed to
                    generate the homozygous congenic lines.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4d">
                <title>Generation of FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>) transgenic mice and derived F<sub>3</sub>
                    strains</title>
                <p>The <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> genomic fragment cloned into the PBR22
                    plasmid was kindly provided by Bernd Arnold (Deutsches Krebsforschungszentrum
                    [DKFZ], Heidelberg, Germany). The 11.5 kb fragment encompassing the
                        D<sup>k</sup> gene was subsequently purified and injected into fertilized
                    FVB/N mouse eggs. Transgenesis was performed at the Quebec Transgenesis Research
                    Network (QTRN). Transgenic founders were screened by PCR with the primers
                        <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-cacacgatccagcggctgt-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-ggcccggtctctctctgcag-3′</named-content>,
                    specific for <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> exon 3. They were then bred to
                    FVB/N WT mice. To generate F<sub>3</sub> mice, FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>) and
                        B6.<italic>H2</italic><sup>0</sup> mice were bred to produce F<sub>1</sub>
                    and F<sub>2</sub> progeny. To discriminate between the NKC and
                        <italic>H2</italic> regions inherited from the parental strains, the
                        F<sub>2</sub> mice were genotyped at the NKC region with the
                        <italic>D6Mit61</italic> and <italic>D6Mit52</italic> markers and at the
                        <italic>H2</italic> region with the <italic>D17Mit51</italic> marker; they
                    were also genotyped for the presence or absence of the
                        <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> transgene. Only the mice homozygous for
                    the FVB/N NKC and heterozygous for either the <italic>H2</italic> or the
                            <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> transgene were kept to generate the
                        F<sub>3</sub> progeny, as listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001368-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4e">
                <title>Antibodies and flow cytometry</title>
                <p>To prepare splenic leukocytes, spleens were removed aseptically then gently
                    mashed through a 70 µm nylon mesh (BD Bioscience). Red blood cells were
                    lysed with ammonium chloride (Sigma). To isolate lymphocytes from mouse blood,
                    mice were bled from the cheek; blood was collected in RPMI medium containing 15
                    mM EDTA. Lymphocytes were collected after gradient centrifugation using
                    Histopaque-1077 (Sigma). Fc receptors were blocked with 2.4G2 antibody prior to
                    staining with specific monoclonal antibodies. NK cells were incubated with NKp46
                    (conjugated to phycoerythrin [PE] or fluorescein isothiocyanate
                    [FITC]) and specific monoclonal antibodies against Ly49A-Biot (YE148),
                    Ly49A/D (12A8), Ly49CIH (14B11), Ly49D (4E5), Ly49G2 (4D11 or AT8), NKG2A/C/E
                    (20d5) or NKG2A/B6 (16A11), CD94 (18D3), or KLRG1 (2F1). NK cells were also
                    incubated with the following isotype control monoclonal antibodies:
                    PE-conjugated golden syrian hamster IgG, FITC- or PE-conjugated mouse IgG2a K,
                    or FITC-conjugated rat IgG2a K (e-Bioscience). <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>
                    and -D<sup>q</sup> products were detected by
                        anti-<italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> antibody (15-5-5) from BioLegend and
                        anti-<italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>q</sup> antibody (KH117) from e-Bioscience.
                    To detect incorporated BrdU on NK cells, mice were scarified 5 or 6 days after
                    MCMV infection; cells were first stained for surface antigens (anti-NKp46 and/or
                    anti-Ly49 receptors) and then fixed, permeabilized, treated with DNase I, and
                    stained with FITC- or allophycocyanin (APC)-conjugated anti-BrdU antibody (clone
                    3D4; BD Biosciences), according to the manufacturer's protocol. Flow
                    cytometry analysis was performed with a FACSCalibur flow cytometer (BD
                    Biosciences) and data were analyzed using CellQuest (BD Biosciences) or FlowJo
                    (Tree Star). To assess NK cell proliferation <italic>in vivo</italic>, NK cells
                    from the spleen were first enriched by negative selection (Miltenyi Biotec),
                    then incubated with 5 µM CFSE for 15 minutes, washed, and resuspended in
                    PBS. The purity of the NK cells (55%–70%) was evaluated by
                    FACS using anti-NKP46 antibody; 2 million NK cells were then injected
                    intravenously into recipient mice 24 hours before infection with MCMV. The
                    proliferation index, indicating the number of divisions of CFSE-labelled NK
                    cells, was determined using the FlowJo software.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4f">
                <title>Viruses and infections</title>
                <p>Stock MCMV from mouse salivary glands was prepared by passaging the virus (Smith
                    strain ATCC VR-1399, lot 1698918) twice in BALB/c mice. The virus was prepared
                    from a homogenate of salivary glands 21 days p.i.. Mice aged between 7 and 9
                    weeks were infected intraperitoneally with 2,000 PFUs of MCMV. The tissue
                    culture-grown viruses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Brune1">[52]</xref>
                    <italic>Δm157</italic> MCMV, which lacks the m157 open reading frame (ORF),
                    and <italic>Δm04</italic> MCMV, which lacks the <italic>m04</italic> ORF,
                    have been previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Bubic1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Wagner1">[53]</xref> and were kindly donated by Ulrich H. Koszinowski (Max
                    von Pettenkofer Institute, Munich, Germany) and Stepan Jonjic (Rijeka
                    University, Rijeka, Croatia). Viral titers of the stock virus or mouse organs
                    (spleen and liver) were evaluated <italic>in vitro</italic> by standard plaque
                    assays on a confluent BALB/c MEF monolayer, as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Depatie1">[54]</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4g">
                <title>MEFs: MCMV infection and reporter cell assay</title>
                <p>The MEFs used in this work were generated as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Brune1">[52]</xref>, except for
                        FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup> transgenic and nontransgenic MEF
                    cells, which were generated from individuals embryos from the progeny of
                        FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)×FVB wild-type mouse crosses and then genotyped
                    for the presence of the <italic>H2-D<sup>k</sup></italic> transgene. 2B4
                    reporter cells expressing Ly49H, Ly49P, Ly49C, or Ly49I were generated as
                    previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Arase1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Desrosiers1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Kielczewska2">[55]</xref>. MEF cultures from
                    AKR, FVB/N <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> transgenic, FVB/N wild-type, and
                    BALB.K mice were infected with MCMV (Smith strain) or <italic>Δm157</italic>
                    or <italic>Δm04</italic> deletion viruses at a multiplicity of infection
                    (MOI) of 1.0 for 24 hours; they were used to stimulate 2B4 reporter cells as
                    previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Desrosiers1">[25]</xref>. GFP was detected by flow cytometry and analyzed
                    using the FlowJo software.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4h">
                <title><italic>In vivo</italic> killing of CFSE-labeled MHC class I–deficient
                    cells</title>
                <p>Splenocytes from B6.<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic> mice were labeled with 0.4 mM
                    CFSE (CFSE low) in RPMI medium containing 5% FCS; splenocytes from
                    recipient mice were labeled with 4 mM CFSE (CFSE high) in RPMI containing
                    10% FCS. The splenocytes were then incubated at 37°C for 10 minutes
                    before being washed three times in RPMI containing 10% FCS. Cells
                        (5×10<sup>6</sup>) of each type were mixed, and the mixture (200
                    µl) was injected intravenously into recipient mice. After 18 hours,
                    spleens were harvested and red blood cells were lysed. The relative percentage
                    of cells in each CFSE population was measured by FACS as previously described
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Oberg1">[33]</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4i">
                <title><italic>In vitro</italic> killing of CFSE-labeled RMA/S cells</title>
                <p>NK cells from the spleen were expanded for 5 days in RPMI medium supplemented
                    with 1,000 U/ml human IL-2 (NCI Preclinical Repository). Cells were washed in
                    RPMI and stained with NKp46 antibody to determine the purity of NK cells and to
                    adjust the number of NK cells among strains. RMA/S cells were labeled with 0.4
                    mM CFSE in RPMI medium containing 5% FCS for 15 minutes at 37°C and
                    washed three times. CFSE-RMA/S and NK cells were cocultured at effector/target
                    ratios of 2∶1, 4∶1, 8∶1, 16∶1, and 32∶1 for 4
                    hours at 37°C. Specific lysis was determined by the measure of
                    7-aminoactinomycin D (7-AAD) incorporation (BD) in CFSE-RMA/S cells by flow
                    cytometry, as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Babic1">[56]</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4j">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>For the 137 (FVB/N×BALB/c) F<sub>2</sub> mice, the contribution of the
                        <italic>NKC</italic> and <italic>H2</italic> loci to the segregation of the
                    phenotype was estimated with the linear model
                        phenotype = <italic>m</italic>+NKC+<italic>H2</italic>+NKC:<italic>H2</italic>+<italic>e</italic>,
                    where NKC and <italic>H2</italic> represent factors that depend on the mode of
                    inheritance proposed, <italic>m</italic> is the common mean value,
                        NKC:<italic>H2</italic> is an interaction term, and <italic>e</italic> is
                    the independent, normally distributed random deviations. For the additive mode
                    of inheritance, the NKC and <italic>H2</italic> represent the number of
                    FVB/N/BALB.K alleles at each locus. For the recessive mode of inheritance, the
                    NKC and <italic>H2</italic> are indicator variables of the homozygous FVB/N and
                    BALB.K backgrounds, respectively. The four possible additive-recessive
                    combinations of <italic>H2</italic>-NKC models, with and without an interaction
                    term, were fitted. We assessed the magnitude of the contribution for each term
                    in the model by its <italic>P</italic> value, obtained by 1 million bootstrapped
                    samples, and partial η<sup>2</sup>. Partial η<sup>2</sup> was computed
                    as
                        η<sup>2</sup> = SS<sub>factor</sub>/(SS<sub>factor</sub>+SS<sub>error</sub>),
                    where SS<sub>factor</sub> is the type 3 associated sum of squares with the
                    factor in the analysis of variance (ANOVA) table, and SS<sub>error</sub> is the
                    sum of squares corresponding to the residual variation. We carried out
                    statistical and graphical analyses using R software. For other statistical
                    analyses in this work, differences between groups were calculated with two-way
                    ANOVA analysis, followed by Bonferroni after tests. For some of the analyses,
                    unpaired, two-tailed Student's <italic>t</italic>-tests were conducted.
                    Results with a <italic>P</italic> value of &lt;0.05 were considered to be
                    statistically significant.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s5">
            <title>Supporting Information</title>
            <supplementary-material id="pgen.1001368.s001" mimetype="application/postscript" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.s001" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S1</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Binding of Ly49-specific monoclonal antibody to MA/My activating receptors.
                        cDNAs encoding MA/My Ly49P, Ly49R and Ly49U receptors were expressed in
                        NFAT-GFP 2B4 T-cell hybridomas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Desrosiers1">[25]</xref>. Expression of the
                        three receptors was detected by the anti-Flag M2 monoclonal antibody.
                        Binding of the isotype control monoclonal antibody (red histogram) or the
                        indicated Ly49-specific monoclonal antibody (black histogram) to Ly49P,
                        Ly49R, and Ly49U receptors was assessed by flow cytometry and analyzed using
                        Flowjo software. The percentage of binding is indicated in each
                        histogram.</p>
                    <p>(1.19 MB EPS)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pgen.1001368.s002" mimetype="application/postscript" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.s002" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S2</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Frequencies of Ly49+ and KLRG1+NK cells in double congenic mice.
                        Quantification of expression frequency of indicated NK receptors in the
                        parental MA/My strain and
                            BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> and
                                BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>d</sup></italic> congenic
                        mice. Data are presented as mean ± SEM and <italic>P</italic> values
                        of significant differences between groups are indicated.</p>
                    <p>(0.89 MB EPS)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pgen.1001368.s003" mimetype="application/postscript" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.s003" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S3</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Lack of NKG2A/C/E and CD94 antibody staining on NK cells from MA/My mice. (A)
                        NKG2A/C/E and CD94 expression on NKp46+ NK cells from MA/My, FVB/N, and
                        DBA/2J (as they carry a NKG2/CD94 deficiency <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001368-Vance1">[57]</xref>) mice was determined by
                        flow cytometry using the indicated monoclonal antibodies. (B) CD94 and NKG2A
                        RNA expression in enriched NK cells from the indicated mice strains was
                        analyzed by RT-PCR. β-actin was used as an internal control.</p>
                    <p>(0.87 MB EPS)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pgen.1001368.s004" mimetype="application/postscript" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.s004" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S4</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Ly49P+2B4 reporter cell stimulation by MCMV-infected MEF cells produced
                        from FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup> mice. (A) Stimulation of Ly49P
                        reporter cells by co-culture with MEF cells from the indicated backgrounds
                        that were uninfected (black histograms) or MCMV infected at an MOI of 1 for
                        24 h (grey histograms). Ly49P-specific activation was detected by NFAT-GFP
                        expression using flow cytometry. (B) Stimulation of Ly49P or Ly49H reporter
                        cells by co-culture with
                                FVB-Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>+</sup></italic>
                        MEF cells that were uninfected (left) or infected with
                            <italic>Δm157</italic> (middle) or <italic>Δm04</italic> (right)
                        MCMV deletion mutants. Reporter cell stimulation was detected by monitoring
                        expression of GFP by flow cytometry. The percentage of positive cells in
                        each gated population is indicated.</p>
                    <p>(0.87 MB EPS)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pgen.1001368.s005" mimetype="application/postscript" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.s005" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S5</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Co-expression of H2-D<sup>q</sup> and H2-D<sup>k</sup> in
                            FVB-Tg(D<sup>k</sup>)<sup>+</sup> mice. Endogenous
                            <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>q</sup> (bottom) and transgenic
                            <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup> (top) expression in splenic T and B
                        cells from
                            FVB-Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>+</sup></italic>
                        transgenic (black peak) or nontransgenic (black peak) littermates was
                        determined by flow cytometry.</p>
                    <p>(0.57 MB EPS)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pgen.1001368.s006" mimetype="application/postscript" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.s006" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S6</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Ly49 receptor expression on NK cells from FVB H2-D<sup>k</sup> transgenic and
                        nontransgenic mice. (A) The indicated Ly49 specific monoclonal antibodies
                        (black peak) or isotype controls (red peak) were gated on NKp46+
                        splenic NK cells from
                            FVB-Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<sup>−</sup> and
                                FVB-Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>+</sup></italic>
                        mice and analyzed by FACS. The proportion of Ly49 receptor expression is
                        indicated in each histogram. (B) Quantification of expression frequency of
                        the indicated NK receptors in
                                FVB-Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>−</sup></italic>
                        and FVB-Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>+</sup></italic>
                        mice.</p>
                    <p>(1.81 MB EPS)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pgen.1001368.s007" mimetype="application/postscript" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.s007" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S7</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Ly49 receptor and MHC class I expression on NK cells from F3 mice. The
                        indicated Ly49-specific monoclonal antibodies were gated on NKp46+
                        splenic NK cells from F3 mice and the proportion of expression is indicated
                        in each histogram. Right panels: expression of MHC-I
                            <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>q</sup> and <italic>H2</italic>-D<sup>k</sup>
                        molecules on total splenocytes was determined. 2–3 mice per genotype
                        were analyzed. We found that the expression of the activating and the
                        inhibitory receptors were almost comparable between strains for the
                        exception of Ly49G which was barely detectable in the
                                <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup>/H2<sup>0</sup></italic>/Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>−</sup></italic>
                        mice using both anti- Ly49G antibodies (LGL-1 and AT8 (data not shown)).
                        This receptor is perfectly expressed in the
                            B6.<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic> parental strain (data not shown) and
                        doesn't seem to be correlated with a defect of NK maturation since the
                        Killer cell lectin-like receptor G1 (KLRG1) is equally expressed between the
                                <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic>/Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>+</sup></italic>
                        and the
                                <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup></italic>/<italic>H2<sup>0</sup></italic>/Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>−</sup></italic>
                        mice.</p>
                    <p>(1.37 MB EPS)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pgen.1001368.s008" mimetype="application/postscript" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.s008" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S8</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>NK cell–dependent MCMV infection control in congenic and F3 mice. (A)
                        Viral loads in spleens (top) and livers (bottom) 3 d post-infection in
                        MCMV-resistant MA/My progenitor,
                                BALB-<italic>Cmv3<sup>MA/My</sup>H2<sup>k</sup></italic> congenic,
                        and
                                <italic>Cmv3<sup>FVB</sup>/H2<sup>0</sup></italic>/Tg(D<italic><sup>k</sup></italic>)<italic><sup>+</sup></italic>
                        transgenic mice that were NK cell depleted (white squares) or not (black
                        circles) with anti-asialo GM1 antibody. (B) Number of NK cells per spleen
                        (top) and BrdU incorporation (bottom) at 7 d post-MCMV infection in
                        MCMV-resistant mice of the indicated genotypes. For the number of NK cells,
                        data are presented as mean ± SEM and statistically significant
                        differences between groups are indicated. For BrdU incorporation data are
                        represented by fold increase between noninfected and infected animals.
                        Results shown are representative of 1–2 experiments.</p>
                    <p>(1.56 MB EPS)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pgen.1001368.s009" mimetype="application/postscript" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001368.s009" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S9</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Effect of Ly49-specifc monoclonal antibody depletion in MA/My mice during the
                        course of MCMV infection. MCMV viral load was assessed in untreated MA/My
                        mice (mock) or treated with the indicated monoclonal antibody prior to MCMV
                        infection. Viral load in spleen was determined by plaque assay after 3 d of
                        infection.</p>
                    <p>(1.47 MB EPS)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <p>We thank Patricia D'Arcy and Chantal Lacroix for excellent help with animal
                experiments and maintenance, H. Ploegh (Harvard University) for MHC class
                I–deficient mice, as well as Seung-Hwan Lee (Brown University) and Michal
                Pyzik (McGill University) for their critical review of this manuscript. We also
                thank Kira Heller and Eve-Marie Gendron Pont-Briand for editorial and proofreading
                services.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Raulet1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Raulet</surname>
                            <given-names>DH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Guerra</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Oncogenic stress sensed by the immune system: role of natural
                        killer cell receptors.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source>
                    <volume>9</volume>
                    <fpage>568</fpage>
                    <lpage>580</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Lodoen1">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lodoen</surname>
                            <given-names>MB</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lanier</surname>
                            <given-names>LL</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Natural killer cells as an initial defense against
                        pathogens.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Opin Immunol</source>
                    <volume>18</volume>
                    <fpage>391</fpage>
                    <lpage>398</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Guan1">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Guan</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Moretto</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bzik</surname>
                            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gigley</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Khan</surname>
                            <given-names>IA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>NK cells enhance dendritic cell response against parasite
                        antigens via NKG2D pathway.</article-title>
                    <source>J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>179</volume>
                    <fpage>590</fpage>
                    <lpage>596</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Vankayalapati1">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vankayalapati</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Garg</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Porgador</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Griffith</surname>
                            <given-names>DE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Klucar</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Role of NK cell-activating receptors and their ligands in the
                        lysis of mononuclear phagocytes infected with an intracellular
                        bacterium.</article-title>
                    <source>J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>175</volume>
                    <fpage>4611</fpage>
                    <lpage>4617</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Gonzalez1">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gonzalez</surname>
                            <given-names>VD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Landay</surname>
                            <given-names>AL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sandberg</surname>
                            <given-names>JK</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>Innate immunity and chronic immune activation in HCV/HIV-1
                        co-infection.</article-title>
                    <source>Clin Immunol</source>
                    <volume>135</volume>
                    <fpage>12</fpage>
                    <lpage>25</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Ward1">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ward</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Barker</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Role of natural killer cells in HIV pathogenesis.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr HIV/AIDS Rep</source>
                    <volume>5</volume>
                    <fpage>44</fpage>
                    <lpage>50</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Biron1">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Biron</surname>
                            <given-names>CA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
                            <given-names>KB</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pien</surname>
                            <given-names>GC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Cousens</surname>
                            <given-names>LP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Salazar-Mather</surname>
                            <given-names>TP</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Natural killer cells in antiviral defense: function and
                        regulation by innate cytokines.</article-title>
                    <source>Annu Rev Immunol</source>
                    <volume>17</volume>
                    <fpage>189</fpage>
                    <lpage>220</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Ortaldo1">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ortaldo</surname>
                            <given-names>JR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Young</surname>
                            <given-names>HA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Mouse Ly49 NK receptors: balancing activation and
                        inhibition.</article-title>
                    <source>Mol Immunol</source>
                    <volume>42</volume>
                    <fpage>445</fpage>
                    <lpage>450</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Karre1">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Karre</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1991</year>
                    <article-title>MHC gene control of the natural killer system at the level of the
                        target and the host.</article-title>
                    <source>Semin Cancer Biol</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <fpage>295</fpage>
                    <lpage>309</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Fernandez1">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Fernandez</surname>
                            <given-names>NC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Treiner</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vance</surname>
                            <given-names>RE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jamieson</surname>
                            <given-names>AM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lemieux</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>A subset of natural killer cells achieves self-tolerance without
                        expressing inhibitory receptors specific for self-MHC
                        molecules.</article-title>
                    <source>Blood</source>
                    <volume>105</volume>
                    <fpage>4416</fpage>
                    <lpage>4423</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Yokoyama1">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yokoyama</surname>
                            <given-names>WM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kim</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>How do natural killer cells find self to achieve
                        tolerance?</article-title>
                    <source>Immunity</source>
                    <volume>24</volume>
                    <fpage>249</fpage>
                    <lpage>257</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Anfossi1">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Anfossi</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Andre</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Guia</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Falk</surname>
                            <given-names>CS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Roetynck</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Human NK cell education by inhibitory receptors for MHC class
                        I.</article-title>
                    <source>Immunity</source>
                    <volume>25</volume>
                    <fpage>331</fpage>
                    <lpage>342</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Jonsson1">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jonsson</surname>
                            <given-names>AH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yang</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kim</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Taffner</surname>
                            <given-names>SM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yokoyama</surname>
                            <given-names>WM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>Effects of MHC class I alleles on licensing of Ly49A+ NK
                        cells.</article-title>
                    <source>J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>184</volume>
                    <fpage>3424</fpage>
                    <lpage>3432</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Raulet2">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Raulet</surname>
                            <given-names>DH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Held</surname>
                            <given-names>W</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Correa</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Dorfman</surname>
                            <given-names>JR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wu</surname>
                            <given-names>MF</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <article-title>Specificity, tolerance and developmental regulation of natural
                        killer cells defined by expression of class I-specific Ly49
                        receptors.</article-title>
                    <source>Immunol Rev</source>
                    <volume>155</volume>
                    <fpage>41</fpage>
                    <lpage>52</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Raulet3">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Raulet</surname>
                            <given-names>DH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vance</surname>
                            <given-names>RE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>McMahon</surname>
                            <given-names>CW</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Regulation of the natural killer cell receptor
                        repertoire.</article-title>
                    <source>Annu Rev Immunol</source>
                    <volume>19</volume>
                    <fpage>291</fpage>
                    <lpage>330</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Kim1">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kim</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Poursine-Laurent</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Truscott</surname>
                            <given-names>SM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lybarger</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Song</surname>
                            <given-names>YJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Licensing of natural killer cells by host major
                        histocompatibility complex class I molecules.</article-title>
                    <source>Nature</source>
                    <volume>436</volume>
                    <fpage>709</fpage>
                    <lpage>713</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Yokoyama2">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yokoyama</surname>
                            <given-names>WM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kim</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Licensing of natural killer cells by self-major
                        histocompatibility complex class I.</article-title>
                    <source>Immunol Rev</source>
                    <volume>214</volume>
                    <fpage>143</fpage>
                    <lpage>154</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Dokun1">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Dokun</surname>
                            <given-names>AO</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kim</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Smith</surname>
                            <given-names>HR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kang</surname>
                            <given-names>HS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Chu</surname>
                            <given-names>DT</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Specific and nonspecific NK cell activation during virus
                        infection.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Immunol</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <fpage>951</fpage>
                    <lpage>956</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Gazit1">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gazit</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gruda</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Elboim</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Arnon</surname>
                            <given-names>TI</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Katz</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Lethal influenza infection in the absence of the natural killer
                        cell receptor gene Ncr1.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Immunol</source>
                    <volume>7</volume>
                    <fpage>517</fpage>
                    <lpage>523</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Diefenbach1">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Diefenbach</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jamieson</surname>
                            <given-names>AM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Liu</surname>
                            <given-names>SD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Shastri</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Raulet</surname>
                            <given-names>DH</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Ligands for the murine NKG2D receptor: expression by tumor cells
                        and activation of NK cells and macrophages.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Immunol</source>
                    <volume>1</volume>
                    <fpage>119</fpage>
                    <lpage>126</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Smith1">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Smith</surname>
                            <given-names>HR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Heusel</surname>
                            <given-names>JW</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mehta</surname>
                            <given-names>IK</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kim</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Dorner</surname>
                            <given-names>BG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Recognition of a virus-encoded ligand by a natural killer cell
                        activation receptor.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>99</volume>
                    <fpage>8826</fpage>
                    <lpage>8831</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Arase1">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Arase</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mocarski</surname>
                            <given-names>ES</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Campbell</surname>
                            <given-names>AE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hill</surname>
                            <given-names>AB</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lanier</surname>
                            <given-names>LL</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Direct recognition of cytomegalovirus by activating and
                        inhibitory NK cell receptors.</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>296</volume>
                    <fpage>1323</fpage>
                    <lpage>1326</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Bubic1">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bubic</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wagner</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Krmpotic</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Saulig</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kim</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Gain of virulence caused by loss of a gene in murine
                        cytomegalovirus.</article-title>
                    <source>J Virol</source>
                    <volume>78</volume>
                    <fpage>7536</fpage>
                    <lpage>7544</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-FodilCornu1">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Fodil-Cornu</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lee</surname>
                            <given-names>SH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Belanger</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Makrigiannis</surname>
                            <given-names>AP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Biron</surname>
                            <given-names>CA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Ly49h-deficient C57BL/6 mice: a new mouse
                        cytomegalovirus-susceptible model remains resistant to unrelated pathogens
                        controlled by the NK gene complex.</article-title>
                    <source>J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>181</volume>
                    <fpage>6394</fpage>
                    <lpage>6405</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Desrosiers1">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Desrosiers</surname>
                            <given-names>MP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kielczewska</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Loredo-Osti</surname>
                            <given-names>JC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Adam</surname>
                            <given-names>SG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Makrigiannis</surname>
                            <given-names>AP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Epistasis between mouse Klra and major histocompatibility complex
                        class I loci is associated with a new mechanism of natural killer
                        cell-mediated innate resistance to cytomegalovirus
                        infection.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Genet</source>
                    <volume>37</volume>
                    <fpage>593</fpage>
                    <lpage>599</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Kielczewska1">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kielczewska</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pyzik</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sun</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Krmpotic</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lodoen</surname>
                            <given-names>MB</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Ly49P recognition of cytomegalovirus-infected cells expressing
                        H2-Dk and CMV-encoded m04 correlates with the NK cell antiviral
                        response.</article-title>
                    <source>J Exp Med</source>
                    <volume>206</volume>
                    <fpage>515</fpage>
                    <lpage>523</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Chalmer1">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Chalmer</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mackenzie</surname>
                            <given-names>JS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Stanley</surname>
                            <given-names>NF</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1977</year>
                    <article-title>Resistance to murine cytomegalovirus linked to the major
                        histocompatibility complex of the mouse.</article-title>
                    <source>J Gen Virol</source>
                    <volume>37</volume>
                    <fpage>107</fpage>
                    <lpage>114</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Dighe1">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Dighe</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sabastian</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Xie</surname>
                            <given-names>X</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>McVoy</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Requisite H2k role in NK cell-mediated resistance in acute murine
                        cytomegalovirus-infected MA/My mice.</article-title>
                    <source>J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>175</volume>
                    <fpage>6820</fpage>
                    <lpage>6828</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Xie1">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Xie</surname>
                            <given-names>X</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Dighe</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Clark</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sabastian</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Buss</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Deficient major histocompatibility complex-linked innate murine
                        cytomegalovirus immunity in MA/My.L-H2b mice and viral downregulation of
                        H-2k class I proteins.</article-title>
                    <source>J Virol</source>
                    <volume>81</volume>
                    <fpage>229</fpage>
                    <lpage>236</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Klein1">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Klein</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1973</year>
                    <article-title>List of congenic lines of mice. I. Lines with differences at
                        alloantigen loci.</article-title>
                    <source>Transplantation</source>
                    <volume>15</volume>
                    <fpage>137</fpage>
                    <lpage>153</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Makrigiannis1">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Makrigiannis</surname>
                            <given-names>AP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pau</surname>
                            <given-names>AT</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Saleh</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Winkler-Pickett</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ortaldo</surname>
                            <given-names>JR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Class I MHC-binding characteristics of the 129/J Ly49
                        repertoire.</article-title>
                    <source>J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>166</volume>
                    <fpage>5034</fpage>
                    <lpage>5043</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Johansson1">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Johansson</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Salmon-Divon</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Johansson</surname>
                            <given-names>MH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pickman</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brodin</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Probing natural killer cell education by Ly49 receptor expression
                        analysis and computational modelling in single MHC class I
                        mice.</article-title>
                    <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                    <volume>4</volume>
                    <fpage>e6046</fpage>
                    <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0006046" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0006046</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Oberg1">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Oberg</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Johansson</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Michaelsson</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Tomasello</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vivier</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Loss or mismatch of MHC class I is sufficient to trigger NK
                        cell-mediated rejection of resting lymphocytes in vivo - role of
                        KARAP/DAP12-dependent and -independent pathways.</article-title>
                    <source>Eur J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>34</volume>
                    <fpage>1646</fpage>
                    <lpage>1653</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Hanke1">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hanke</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Takizawa</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>McMahon</surname>
                            <given-names>CW</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Busch</surname>
                            <given-names>DH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pamer</surname>
                            <given-names>EG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Direct assessment of MHC class I binding by seven Ly49 inhibitory
                        NK cell receptors.</article-title>
                    <source>Immunity</source>
                    <volume>11</volume>
                    <fpage>67</fpage>
                    <lpage>77</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Xie2">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Xie</surname>
                            <given-names>X</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Stadnisky</surname>
                            <given-names>MD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Coats</surname>
                            <given-names>ER</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ahmed Rahim</surname>
                            <given-names>MM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lundgren</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>MHC class I D(k) expression in hematopoietic and nonhematopoietic
                        cells confers natural killer cell resistance to murine
                        cytomegalovirus.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>107</volume>
                    <fpage>8754</fpage>
                    <lpage>8759</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Webb1">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Webb</surname>
                            <given-names>JR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lee</surname>
                            <given-names>SH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vidal</surname>
                            <given-names>SM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Genetic control of innate immune responses against
                        cytomegalovirus: MCMV meets its match.</article-title>
                    <source>Genes Immun</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>250</fpage>
                    <lpage>262</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Jonsson2">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jonsson</surname>
                            <given-names>AH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yang</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kim</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Taffner</surname>
                            <given-names>SM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yokoyama</surname>
                            <given-names>WM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Effects of MHC class I alleles on licensing of Ly49A+ NK
                        cells.</article-title>
                    <source>J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>184</volume>
                    <fpage>3424</fpage>
                    <lpage>3432</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Kavanagh1">
                <label>38</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kavanagh</surname>
                            <given-names>DG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gold</surname>
                            <given-names>MC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wagner</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Koszinowski</surname>
                            <given-names>UH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hill</surname>
                            <given-names>AB</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>The multiple immune-evasion genes of murine cytomegalovirus are
                        not redundant: m4 and m152 inhibit antigen presentation in a complementary
                        and cooperative fashion.</article-title>
                    <source>J Exp Med</source>
                    <volume>194</volume>
                    <fpage>967</fpage>
                    <lpage>978</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Sun1">
                <label>39</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sun</surname>
                            <given-names>JC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lanier</surname>
                            <given-names>LL</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Cutting edge: viral infection breaks NK cell tolerance to
                        “missing self”.</article-title>
                    <source>J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>181</volume>
                    <fpage>7453</fpage>
                    <lpage>7457</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Chalifour1">
                <label>40</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Chalifour</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Roger</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lemieux</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Duplay</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Receptor/ligand avidity determines the capacity of Ly49
                        inhibitory receptors to interfere with T-cell receptor-mediated
                        activation.</article-title>
                    <source>Immunology</source>
                    <volume>109</volume>
                    <fpage>58</fpage>
                    <lpage>67</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Hasan1">
                <label>41</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hasan</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Krmpotic</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ruzsics</surname>
                            <given-names>Z</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bubic</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lenac</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Selective down-regulation of the NKG2D ligand H60 by mouse
                        cytomegalovirus m155 glycoprotein.</article-title>
                    <source>J Virol</source>
                    <volume>79</volume>
                    <fpage>2920</fpage>
                    <lpage>2930</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-LoPiccolo1">
                <label>42</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>LoPiccolo</surname>
                            <given-names>DM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gold</surname>
                            <given-names>MC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kavanagh</surname>
                            <given-names>DG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wagner</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Koszinowski</surname>
                            <given-names>UH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Effective inhibition of K(b)- and D(b)-restricted antigen
                        presentation in primary macrophages by murine
                        cytomegalovirus.</article-title>
                    <source>J Virol</source>
                    <volume>77</volume>
                    <fpage>301</fpage>
                    <lpage>308</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Pinto1">
                <label>43</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pinto</surname>
                            <given-names>AK</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Munks</surname>
                            <given-names>MW</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Koszinowski</surname>
                            <given-names>UH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hill</surname>
                            <given-names>AB</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Coordinated function of murine cytomegalovirus genes completely
                        inhibits CTL lysis.</article-title>
                    <source>J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>177</volume>
                    <fpage>3225</fpage>
                    <lpage>3234</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Gazit2">
                <label>44</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gazit</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Garty</surname>
                            <given-names>BZ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Monselise</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hoffer</surname>
                            <given-names>V</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Finkelstein</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Expression of KIR2DL1 on the entire NK cell population: a
                        possible novel immunodeficiency syndrome.</article-title>
                    <source>Blood</source>
                    <volume>103</volume>
                    <fpage>1965</fpage>
                    <lpage>1966</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Khakoo1">
                <label>45</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Khakoo</surname>
                            <given-names>SI</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Thio</surname>
                            <given-names>CL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Martin</surname>
                            <given-names>MP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brooks</surname>
                            <given-names>CR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gao</surname>
                            <given-names>X</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>HLA and NK cell inhibitory receptor genes in resolving hepatitis
                        C virus infection.</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>305</volume>
                    <fpage>872</fpage>
                    <lpage>874</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Carrington1">
                <label>46</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Carrington</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Martin</surname>
                            <given-names>MP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>van Bergen</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>KIR-HLA intercourse in HIV disease.</article-title>
                    <source>Trends Microbiol</source>
                    <volume>16</volume>
                    <fpage>620</fpage>
                    <lpage>627</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Price1">
                <label>47</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Price</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Witt</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>de Santis</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>French</surname>
                            <given-names>MA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Killer immunoglobulin-like receptor genotype may distinguish
                        immunodeficient HIV-infected patients resistant to immune restoration
                        diseases associated with herpes virus infections.</article-title>
                    <source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source>
                    <volume>45</volume>
                    <fpage>359</fpage>
                    <lpage>361</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Wauquier1">
                <label>48</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wauquier</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Padilla</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Becquart</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Leroy</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vieillard</surname>
                            <given-names>V</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>Association of KIR2DS1 and KIR2DS3 with fatal outcome in Ebola
                        virus infection.</article-title>
                    <source>Immunogenetics</source>
                    <volume>62</volume>
                    <fpage>767</fpage>
                    <lpage>771</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Nelson1">
                <label>49</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nelson</surname>
                            <given-names>GW</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Martin</surname>
                            <given-names>MP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gladman</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wade</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Trowsdale</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Cutting edge: heterozygote advantage in autoimmune disease:
                        hierarchy of protection/susceptibility conferred by HLA and killer Ig-like
                        receptor combinations in psoriatic arthritis.</article-title>
                    <source>J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>173</volume>
                    <fpage>4273</fpage>
                    <lpage>4276</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Baessler1">
                <label>50</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Baessler</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Charton</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Schmiedel</surname>
                            <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Grunebach</surname>
                            <given-names>F</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Krusch</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>CD137 ligand mediates opposite effects in human and mouse NK
                        cells and impairs NK-cell reactivity against human acute myeloid leukemia
                        cells.</article-title>
                    <source>Blood</source>
                    <volume>115</volume>
                    <fpage>3058</fpage>
                    <lpage>3069</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-FodilCornu2">
                <label>51</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Fodil-Cornu</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pyzik</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vidal</surname>
                            <given-names>SM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>Use of inbred mouse strains to map recognition receptors of MCMV
                        infected cells in the NK cell gene locus.</article-title>
                    <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>
                    <volume>612</volume>
                    <fpage>393</fpage>
                    <lpage>409</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Brune1">
                <label>52</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brune</surname>
                            <given-names>W</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hengel</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Koszinowski</surname>
                            <given-names>UH</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>A mouse model for cytomegalovirus infection.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Protoc Immunol Chapter</source>
                    <volume>19</volume>
                    <fpage>Unit 19 17</fpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Wagner1">
                <label>53</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wagner</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gutermann</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Podlech</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Reddehase</surname>
                            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Koszinowski</surname>
                            <given-names>UH</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Major histocompatibility complex class I allele-specific
                        cooperative and competitive interactions between immune evasion proteins of
                        cytomegalovirus.</article-title>
                    <source>J Exp Med</source>
                    <volume>196</volume>
                    <fpage>805</fpage>
                    <lpage>816</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Depatie1">
                <label>54</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Depatie</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Chalifour</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pare</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lee</surname>
                            <given-names>SH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vidal</surname>
                            <given-names>SM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Assessment of Cmv1 candidates by genetic mapping and in vivo
                        antibody depletion of NK cell subsets.</article-title>
                    <source>Int Immunol</source>
                    <volume>11</volume>
                    <fpage>1541</fpage>
                    <lpage>1551</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Kielczewska2">
                <label>55</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kielczewska</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kim</surname>
                            <given-names>HS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lanier</surname>
                            <given-names>LL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Dimasi</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vidal</surname>
                            <given-names>SM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Critical residues at the Ly49 natural killer receptor's
                        homodimer interface determine functional recognition of m157, a mouse
                        cytomegalovirus MHC class I-like protein.</article-title>
                    <source>J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>178</volume>
                    <fpage>369</fpage>
                    <lpage>377</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Babic1">
                <label>56</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Babic</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pyzik</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Zafirova</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mitrovic</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Butorac</surname>
                            <given-names>V</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>Cytomegalovirus immunoevasin reveals the physiological role of
                        “missing self” recognition in natural killer cell dependent
                        virus control in vivo.</article-title>
                    <source>J Exp Med</source>
                    <volume>207</volume>
                    <fpage>2663</fpage>
                    <lpage>2673</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pgen.1001368-Vance1">
                <label>57</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vance</surname>
                            <given-names>RE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jamieson</surname>
                            <given-names>AM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Cado</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Raulet</surname>
                            <given-names>DH</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Implications of CD94 deficiency and monoallelic NKG2A expression
                        for natural killer cell development and repertoire
                        formation.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>99</volume>
                    <fpage>868</fpage>
                    <lpage>873</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
        
    </back>
</article>