<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">pgen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="allenpress-id">plge</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">06-PLGE-RA-0365R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="sici">plge-03-06-02</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Mathematics</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy">
          <subject>Homo (human)</subject>
          <subject>None</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Localizing Recent Adaptive Evolution in the Human Genome</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Selective Sweeps in the Human Genome</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Williamson</surname>
            <given-names>Scott H</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hubisz</surname>
            <given-names>Melissa J</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="fn" rid="n104">
            <sup>¤a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Clark</surname>
            <given-names>Andrew G</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Payseur</surname>
            <given-names>Bret A</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="fn" rid="n105">
            <sup>¤b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bustamante</surname>
            <given-names>Carlos D</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Nielsen</surname>
            <given-names>Rasmus</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line> Department of Biological Statistics and Computational Biology, Cornell
          University, Ithaca, New York, United States of America </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line> Department of Molecular Biology and Genetics, Cornell University, Ithaca, New
          York, United States of America </addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line> Center for Bioinformatics and Department of Biology, University of Copenhagen,
          Copenhagen, Denmark </addr-line>
      </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>McVean</surname>
            <given-names>Gil</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Oxford, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="ack1">
          <p>SHW, MJH, and BP analyzed the data. SHW wrote the first draft of the manuscript. All
            authors contributed to conceiving the idea and editing the manuscript.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="n104">
          <p>¤a Current address: Department of Human Genetics, University of Chicago, Chicago,
            Illinoins, United States of America,</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="n105">
          <p>¤b Current address: Laboratory of Genetics, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin,
            United States of America</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor1">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">sw292@cornell.edu</email></corresp>
      <fn fn-type="conflict" id="ack3">
        <p> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epreprint">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e90</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Williamson et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the
        terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
        distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are
        credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>Identifying genomic locations that have experienced selective sweeps is an important
          first step toward understanding the molecular basis of adaptive evolution. Using
          statistical methods that account for the confounding effects of population demography,
          recombination rate variation, and single-nucleotide polymorphism ascertainment, while also
          providing fine-scale estimates of the position of the selected site, we analyzed a genomic
          dataset of 1.2 million human single-nucleotide polymorphisms genotyped in
          African-American, European-American, and Chinese samples. We identify 101 regions of the
          human genome with very strong evidence (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 10<sup>−5</sup>) of a
          recent selective sweep and where our estimate of the position of the selective sweep falls
          within 100 kb of a known gene. Within these regions, genes of biological interest include
          genes in pigmentation pathways, components of the dystrophin protein complex, clusters of
          olfactory receptors, genes involved in nervous system development and function, immune
          system genes, and heat shock genes. We also observe consistent evidence of selective
          sweeps in centromeric regions. In general, we find that recent adaptation is strikingly
          pervasive in the human genome, with as much as 10% of the genome affected by linkage to a
          selective sweep.</p>
      </abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary">
        <title>Author Summary</title>
        <sec id="st1">
          <title/>
          <p>A selective sweep is a single realization of adaptive evolution at the molecular level.
            When a selective sweep occurs, it leaves a characteristic signal in patterns of
            variation in genomic regions linked to the selected site; therefore, recently released
            population genomic datasets can be used to search for instances of molecular adaptation.
            Here, we present a comprehensive scan for complete selective sweeps in the human genome.
            Our analysis is complementary to several recent analyses that focused on partial
            selective sweeps, in which the adaptive mutation still segregates at intermediate
            frequency in the population. Consequently, our analysis identifies many genomic regions
            that were not previously known to have experienced natural selection, including
            consistent evidence of selection in centromeric regions, which is possibly the result of
            meiotic drive. Genes within selected regions include pigmentation candidate genes, genes
            of the dystrophin protein complex, and olfactory receptors. Extensive testing
            demonstrates that the method we use to detect selective sweeps is strikingly robust to
            both alternative demographic scenarios and recombination rate variation. Furthermore,
            the method we use provides precise estimates of the genomic position of the selected
            site, which greatly facilitates the fine-scale mapping of functionally significant
            variation in human populations.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Supported by an National Institutes of Health grant (1R01HG003229) to AGC, CDB, RN, and
          T. Mattisse, and an NSF grant (Nsg00319553) to CDB, RN, S. McCouch, and M. Purugganan
          (co-principal investigators).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="15"/>
      </counts><!--===== Restructure custom-meta-wrap to custom-meta-group =====--><custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>citation</meta-name>
          <meta-value>Williamson SH, Hubisz MJ, Clark AG, Payseur BA, Bustamante CD, et al. (2007)
            Localizing recent adaptive evolution in the human genome. PLoS Genet 3(6): e90.
              doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090</ext-link></meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Describing how natural selection shapes patterns of genetic variation within and between
        species is critical to a general understanding of evolution. With the advent of comparative
        genomic data, considerable progress has been made toward quantifying the effect of adaptive
        evolution on genome-wide patterns of variation between species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b001">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b005">5</xref>],
        and the effect of weak negative selection against deleterious mutations on patterns of
        variation within species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b001">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b005">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b006">6</xref>]. However, relatively little is known about the degree to
        which adaptive evolution affects DNA sequence polymorphism within species and what types of
        selection are most prevalent across the genome. Of particular interest is the effect of very
        recent adaptive evolution in humans. If one can localize adaptive events in the genome, then
        this information, along with functional knowledge of the region, speaks to the selective
        environment experienced by recent human populations. Another reason for the interest in
        genomic patterns of selection is that recent studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b003">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b005">5</xref>]
        have suggested a link between selected genes and factors causing inherited disease;
        furthermore, several established cases of recent adaptive evolution in the human genome
        involve mutations that confer resistance to infectious disease (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b007">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b008">8</xref>]).
        Therefore, knowledge of the location of selected genes could aid in the effort to identify
        genetic variation underlying genetic diseases and infectious disease resistance. From a
        theoretical perspective, both the relative rate of adaptive evolution at the molecular level
        and the degree to which natural selection maintains polymorphism have been the subjects of
        intense debate in population genetics and molecular evolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b009">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b012">12</xref>].
        With genome-scale polymorphism data becoming available, it is now possible to address these
        decades-old problems directly.</p>
      <p>Adaptive events alter patterns of DNA polymorphism in the genomic region surrounding a
        beneficial allele, so population genetic methods can be used to infer selection by searching
        for their effects in genomic single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) data. Several recent
        studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b013">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b016">16</xref>] have taken this approach to scan the human genome for
        evidence of recent adaptation. These studies identify several regions of the genome that
        have recently experienced selection, and they suggest that adaptation is a surprisingly
        pervasive force in recent human evolution. However, the results of these analyses can only
        be considered preliminary. All of these studies have focused on the empirical distribution
        of a given test statistic, reasoning that loci with extreme values will be the most likely
        candidates for selective sweeps. This approach provides a sensible way to rank loci
        according to their signal of recent adaptation, but because we do not know how common
        selection is in the genome, the “empirical <italic>p</italic> value” approach does not
        directly test the hypothesis of selection for any individual locus, and it provides no means
        for quantifying how common selection is across the genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b017">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b018">18</xref>]. For instance, the null hypothesis of selective neutrality could be true for the
        entire genome, in which case even the most extreme values would carry no information
        regarding selection. Also, there are no a priori criteria available for deciding how extreme
        a region needs to be in order to identify selection. In short, these previous studies do not
        estimate their uncertainty in identifying selection. Another concern is that the statistical
        properties of previous methods have only been explored under the very simplest evolutionary
        models. Complex factors such as demographic events in the history of the population,
        recombination rate variation, and the biasing effects of SNP ascertainment protocols all
        have the potential to systematically cause false signals of natural selection, yet previous
        methods for identifying recent adaptation have not been thoroughly tested for their
        robustness to these complicating factors.</p>
      <p>In this paper, we present a full statistical analysis of evidence for selective sweeps in
        the human genome using a method for detecting sweeps that has been thoroughly tested for
        robustness to demography and recombination rate variation, and that explicitly incorporates
        SNP ascertainment protocols. We apply this approach to dense genomic polymorphism data
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b019">19</xref>] with uniform SNP discovery
        protocols. A recent selective sweep (a bout of adaptive evolution that fixes a beneficial
        mutation) alters patterns of allele frequency at linked sites, eliminating variation at
        tightly linked loci and creating a relative excess of alleles at very low and very high
        frequencies at more distant loci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b020">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b022">22</xref>]. Because the effect of
        a selective sweep will depend on the genomic distance away from the beneficial mutation, we
        use a statistical method (test 2 in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b022">22</xref>]) that searches for the unique spatial pattern of allele frequencies along a
        chromosome that is found after a selective sweep. Essentially, the test uses a composite
        likelihood ratio (CLR) to compare a neutral model for the evolution of a genomic window with
        a selective sweep model. In the neutral null model, allele frequency probabilities are drawn
        from the background pattern of variation in the rest of the genome. In the selective sweep
        model, allele frequency probabilities are calculated using a model of a selective sweep that
        conditions on the background pattern of variation. Allele frequency probabilities also
        depend on two parameters: the genomic position of the selective sweep (<italic>ψ</italic>),
        and a compound parameter (<italic>α</italic>) that measures the combined effects of the
        strength of selection and the recombination rate between a SNP and the selected site.</p>
      <p>Extensive simulations under a variety of evolutionary models indicate that this CLR
        approach is not misled by demographic events in the population's history, such as population
        size changes, divergence, subdivision, or migration. Furthermore, simulations indicate that
        this is the only available method for detecting sweeps that is not highly sensitive to
        assumptions about the underlying recombination rate or recombination hotspots. This lack of
        dependence on demography and recombination allows us to calculate <italic>p</italic> values
        for individual loci that are consistent across a wide range of selectively neutral null
        models. Hence, we can reliably measure our uncertainty in identifying selective sweeps, and
        we can obtain rough estimates of the prevalence of recent adaptation across the genome.
        Also, the present analysis is one of the first to fully correct for the bias introduced by
        SNP discovery protocols, and we account for the effects of multiple hypothesis testing using
        a false discovery rate approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b023">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b024">24</xref>]. The method we use
        provides an accurate estimate of the genomic location of the selected allele, a feature that
        greatly facilitates mapping of the genomic targets of natural selection. A final important
        difference between our analysis and previous work is that the method we use searches for the
        signature of “complete” selective sweeps (i.e., adaptation where the beneficial mutation has
        recently attained a frequency of ~100% in the population). In contrast, methods based on
        extended haplotype length and high linkage disequilibrium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b014">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b016">16</xref>]
        have the most power to detect “partial” selective sweeps [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b015">15</xref>] (i.e., where the beneficial mutation has not yet spread
        throughout the entire population). Therefore, the two approaches are complementary, and most
        loci where we discover evidence for recent adaptation were not detected by previous
        genome-wide scans for selection or targeted candidate gene approaches.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030090-t001">Table 1</xref> lists the 101 genomic
        locations that show very strong evidence for a recent, complete selective sweep (CLR
          <italic>p</italic> &lt; 10<sup>−5</sup>), excluding locations where the estimate of sweep
        position was greater than 100 kb from a known gene, and excluding centromeric regions.
        Genomic locations with very strong evidence for a selective sweep, but not within 100 kb of
        a known gene, are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030090-st001">Table S1</xref>, and application of the CLR test via sliding window analyses of all
        autosomes are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030090-st002">Table S2</xref>. Under the model of a recent and strong selective sweep, the composite
        likelihood estimate of the position of the selective sweep is very accurate (to within ~20
        kb in regions with typical recombination rates; see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b022">22</xref>]), so the gene nearest the estimate of sweep position is
        generally the best candidate as the target of selection. However, we cannot rule out the
        possibility that unknown functional elements or, in very gene-dense or low-recombination
        regions, another nearby gene might be the true target of selection.</p>
      <table-wrap content-type="1col" id="pgen-0030090-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
          <p>The 101 Regions of the Human Genome with the Strongest Evidence (<italic>p</italic>
            &lt; 0.00001, CLR Test) for a Recent Selective Sweep from a Sliding Window Analysis of
            the Combined, African-American, European-American, and Chinese Samples</p>
        </caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup><col id="tb1col1" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb1col2" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb1col3" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb1col4" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb1col5" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb1col6" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left"><hr/>Sample</td><td valign="top"><hr/>Chr.</td><td valign="middle"><hr/>CMLE Position<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top"><hr/>CLR</td><td valign="top"><hr/>Genes (Distance in kb)<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top"><hr/>Notes</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>African-American</bold></td><td>1</td><td>13427120</td><td>29.024</td><td><italic>PRDM2</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>1</td><td>195876600</td><td>41.904</td><td><italic>PTPRC</italic> (19 kb), <italic>ATP6V1G3</italic> (78 kb)</td><td><italic>PTPRC</italic> encodes a leukocyte cell-surface molecule and contains suceptibility alleles for multiple sclerosis</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>4</td><td>177391500</td><td>29.622</td><td><italic>GPM6A</italic> (0)</td><td><italic>GPM6A</italic> is a neuronal membrane glycoprotein</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>5</td><td>29062440</td><td>59.662</td><td><italic>LOC340211</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>6</td><td>66157130</td><td>59.88</td><td><italic>EGFL11</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>4886706</td><td>40.618</td><td><italic>CSMD1</italic> (47 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>10</td><td>38121540</td><td>42.777</td><td><italic>ZNF248</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>11</td><td>55171790</td><td>48.233</td><td><italic>OR4P4</italic> (9 kb)</td><td>Position estimate is within a cluster of olfactory receptor genes; six <italic>OR</italic> genes within 100 kb</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>15</td><td>89572970</td><td>35.422</td><td><italic>SV2B</italic> (4 kb)</td><td><italic>SV2B</italic> is synaptic vesicle glycoprotein 2B, which is expressed primarily in the cerebral cortex</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>20</td><td>20149280</td><td>43.999</td><td><italic>C20orf26</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td><bold>European- American</bold></td><td>1</td><td>52897800</td><td>42.055</td><td><italic>SCP2</italic> (11 kb)</td><td><italic>SCP2</italic> plays a role in the intracellular movement of cholesterol</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>2</td><td>158371000</td><td>41.014</td><td><italic>KIAA1189</italic> (0), <italic>PSCDBP</italic> (100 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>144901300</td><td>44.16</td><td><italic>SLC9A9</italic> (13 kb)</td><td><italic>SLC9A9</italic> is a sodium/hydrogen exchanger with a suggestive association with ADHD</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>189987700</td><td>33.127</td><td><italic>LPP</italic> (70 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>5</td><td>110427700</td><td>37.645</td><td><italic>TSLP</italic> (55 kb), <italic>WDR36</italic> (76 kb)</td><td><italic>TSLP</italic> is part of a family of B cell&ndash;stimulating factors</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>5</td><td>133570600</td><td>37.535</td><td><italic>SKP1A</italic> (0), <italic>TCF7</italic> (11 kb)</td><td><italic>SKP1A</italic> is a transcription regulator with a suggested involvement with nervous/sensory development, especially the inner ear</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>6</td><td>105777300</td><td>32.39</td><td><italic>PREP</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>7</td><td>136657300</td><td>35.646</td><td><italic>DGKI</italic> (0)</td><td>Mutations in <italic>Drosophila DGKI</italic> causes degeneration of photoreceptor cells</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>35614900</td><td>38.744</td><td><italic>UNC5D</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>10</td><td>21268430</td><td>32.164</td><td><italic>NEBL</italic> (0)</td><td><italic>NEBL</italic> encodes an actin-binding protein, and mutations in NEBL have been shown to cause nemaline myopathy, which causes several problems including decreased muscle density and problems with reflexes</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>10</td><td>22739870</td><td>44.449</td><td><italic>SPAG6</italic> (29 kb), <italic>PIP5K2A</italic> (90 kb)</td><td>Mutations in mouse <italic>SPAG6</italic> are known to cause sperm motility problems</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>10</td><td>74357920</td><td>37.558</td><td><italic>TTC18</italic> (0), <italic>MRPS16</italic> (1 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>11</td><td>36601700</td><td>33.082</td><td><italic>LOC119710</italic> (0), <italic>RAG2</italic> (18 kb), <italic>RAG1</italic> (37 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>12</td><td>42894650</td><td>47.363</td><td><italic>DKFZp434K2435</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>12</td><td>99399670</td><td>37.529</td><td><italic>NR1H4</italic> (0), <italic>GAS2L3</italic> (70 kb), <italic>SLC17A8</italic> (82 kb)</td><td><italic>NR1H4</italic> is a nuclear hormone receptor relating to phenotypes of serum cholesterol, bile acid, lipoprotein, and triglycerides</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>15</td><td>26994330</td><td>39.48</td><td><italic>APBA2</italic> (0)</td><td>The <italic>APBA2</italic> protein binds the amyloid-beta (A4) precursor, and is a candidate gene for Alzheimer disease</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>15</td><td>27655440</td><td>32.385</td><td><italic>TJP1</italic> (53 kb)</td><td>The tight-junction protein 1 (TJP1) associates with a protein (CagA) injected into gastric epithelial cells by <named-content content-type="genus-species">H. pylori</named-content></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>15</td><td>86739850</td><td>35.154</td><td><italic>MRPS11</italic> (0), <italic>MRPL46</italic> (0), <italic>DET1</italic> (45 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>17</td><td>59013260</td><td>32.4</td><td><italic>APPBP2</italic> (0)</td><td>The APPPBP2 protein binds the amyloid (beta-A4) precursor, and is a candidate gene for Alzheimer disease</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>17</td><td>59681810</td><td>39.782</td><td><italic>BCAS3</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>18</td><td>28723870</td><td>50.461</td><td><italic>C18orf34</italic> (46 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>18</td><td>30398320</td><td>51.283</td><td><italic>DTNA</italic> (0)</td><td><italic>DTNA</italic> is dystrobrevin-alpha, a component of the dystrophin protein complex</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>18</td><td>44260350</td><td>39.481</td><td><italic>KIAA0427</italic> (57 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>18</td><td>64896900</td><td>44.055</td><td><italic>C18orf14</italic> (26 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>18</td><td>65739330</td><td>37.6</td><td><italic>CD226</italic> (0)</td><td>The CD226 protein is involved in T cell and natural killer cell cytotoxicity</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>19</td><td>47672850</td><td>32.195</td><td><italic>CEACAM1</italic> (30 kb), <italic>UNQ473</italic> (34 kb), <italic>LIPE</italic> (50 kb), <italic>CNFN</italic> (87 kb), <italic>SBP1</italic> (98 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td><bold>Chinese</bold></td><td>1</td><td>57813740</td><td>33.199</td><td><italic>DAB1</italic> (0)</td><td><italic>DAB1</italic> plays a role in establishing the laminar organization of the cerebral cortex</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>1</td><td>66817090</td><td>30.064</td><td><italic>MI-ER1</italic> (0), <italic>SLC35D1</italic> (23 kb), <italic>FLJ23129</italic> (56 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>1</td><td>103041700</td><td>40.208</td><td><italic>COL11A1</italic> (5 kb)</td><td><italic>COL11A1</italic> is a collagen associated with two disorders: (1) Stickler syndrome, which is characterized by progressive myopia and retinal detachment; and (2) Marshall's syndrome, which causes abnormalities in facial development</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>1</td><td>158541900</td><td>33.019</td><td><italic>SDHC</italic> (0), <italic>LOC257177</italic> (9 kb), <italic>MPZ</italic> (45 kb)</td><td><italic>SDHC</italic> is associated with hereditary paragangliomas, which involves nonmalignant tumors in vascular tissue</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>2</td><td>109198300</td><td>40.035</td><td><italic>EDAR</italic> (0)</td><td><italic>EDAR</italic> is associated with ectodermal dysplasia, and it is involved in hair follicle, sweat gland, and tooth development</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>2</td><td>189810100</td><td>54.195</td><td><italic>DIRC1</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>2</td><td>216482300</td><td>29.141</td><td><italic>FN1</italic> (0), <italic>ATIC</italic> (65 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>17387700</td><td>43.978</td><td><italic>TBC1D5</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>115642400</td><td>31.113</td><td><italic>ZBTB20</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>144899200</td><td>38.179</td><td><italic>SLC9A9</italic> (11 kb)</td><td>See entry for <italic>SLC9A9</italic> in the European-American sample</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>4</td><td>6024760</td><td>47.629</td><td><italic>FLJ46481</italic> (0), <italic>CRMP1</italic> (66 kb), <italic>MARLIN1</italic> (95 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>4</td><td>13404330</td><td>31.993</td><td><italic>FAM44A</italic> (23 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>4</td><td>41912200</td><td>57.385</td><td><italic>SLC30A9</italic> (0), <italic>TMEM33</italic> (39 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>4</td><td>106988000</td><td>36.517</td><td><italic>FLJ20184</italic> (0), <italic>LOC57117</italic> (74 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>5</td><td>42060400</td><td>33.69</td><td><italic>FBXO4</italic> (73 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>6</td><td>12902840</td><td>30.008</td><td><italic>PHACTR1</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>6</td><td>26350950</td><td>44.027</td><td><italic>HIST1H4F</italic> (2 kb)</td><td>Position estimate is in a large cluster of histone-1 genes, 20 of which are within 100 kb</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>6</td><td>54864430</td><td>40.376</td><td><italic>C6orf143</italic> (10 kb),</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>6</td><td>158234200</td><td>36.574</td><td><italic>SNX9</italic> (0), <italic>SYNJ2</italic> (78 kb)</td><td><italic>SNX9</italic> is an intracellular trafficking protein that regulates the degradation of ectodermal growth factor receptor</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>7</td><td>100731700</td><td>51.119</td><td><italic>EMID2</italic> (0), <italic>MYLC2PL</italic> (85 kb)</td><td><italic>EMID2</italic> is a collagen expressed in the testis and ovary, and the protein is found in the extracellular matrix</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>7</td><td>136674800</td><td>31.625</td><td><italic>DGKI</italic> (0)</td><td>See entry for <italic>DGKI</italic> in the European-American sample</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>50815690</td><td>38.22</td><td><italic>SNTG1</italic> (58 kb)</td><td><italic>SNTG1</italic> is a subunit of the dystrophin protein complex</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>66983090</td><td>29.969</td><td><italic>DNAJC5B</italic> (1 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>98234550</td><td>29.599</td><td><italic>TSPYL5</italic> (5 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>106772400</td><td>38.378</td><td><italic>ZFPM2</italic> (0)</td><td><italic>ZFPM2</italic> is a transcription factor with an important role in heart development</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>136395000</td><td>36.856</td><td><italic>KHDRBS3</italic> (45 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>9</td><td>74370350</td><td>37.428</td><td><italic>RFK</italic> (87 kb)</td><td><italic>RFK</italic> plays a role in metabolizing riboflavin</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>9</td><td>102273200</td><td>37.709</td><td><italic>SMC2L1</italic> (0)</td><td><italic>SMC2L1</italic> is involved in the maintenance and segregation of chromosomes during cell division</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>10</td><td>22732610</td><td>37.798</td><td><italic>SPAG6</italic> (22 kb), <italic>PIP5K2A</italic> (97 kb)</td><td>See entry for <italic>SPAG6</italic> in the European-American sample</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>10</td><td>45409270</td><td>42.153</td><td><italic>ANUBL1</italic> (0), <italic>MARCH8</italic> (35 kb), <italic>FAM21C</italic> (98 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>10</td><td>55292980</td><td>41.377</td><td><italic>PCDH15</italic> (0)</td><td><italic>PCDH15</italic> is involved in morphogeneisis of stereocilia in the inner ear</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>10</td><td>81881400</td><td>42.407</td><td><italic>TSPAN14</italic> (0), <italic>C10orf58</italic> (24 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>11</td><td>36610870</td><td>33.832</td><td><italic>LOC119710</italic> (0), <italic>RAG2</italic> (27 kb), <italic>RAG1</italic> (46 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>11</td><td>60688890</td><td>29.627</td><td><italic>VPS37C</italic> (0), <italic>CD5</italic> (18 kb), <italic>PGA5</italic> (95 kb)</td><td><italic>VPS37C</italic> is part of the endosomal sorting complex, which is recruited for viral budding</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>12</td><td>24305690</td><td>29.76</td><td><italic>SOX5</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>12</td><td>34031300</td><td>39.953</td><td><italic>ALG10</italic> (35 kb)</td><td><italic>ALG10</italic> is a regulator of potassium channels</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>12</td><td>53770680</td><td>41.792</td><td><italic>OR9K2</italic> (38 kb)*, <italic>NEUROD4</italic> (64 kb)</td><td>*Estimate is at the edge of a cluster of <italic>OR</italic> genes</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>12</td><td>84651660</td><td>54.887</td><td><italic>PAMCI</italic> (49 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>12</td><td>91589690</td><td>37.412</td><td><italic>FLJ46688</italic> (42 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>13</td><td>18052490</td><td>38.147</td><td><italic>PSPC1</italic> (0), HSMPP8 (47 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>14</td><td>21862100</td><td>29.019</td><td><italic>MYH6</italic> (0), <italic>MYH7</italic> (10 kb), <italic>CKLFSF5</italic> (23 kb), <italic>IL17E</italic> (27 kb), <italic>EFS</italic> (37 kb), <italic>SLC22A17</italic> (51 kb), <italic>PABPN1</italic> (77 kb), <italic>BCL2L2</italic> (91 kb)</td><td>Both <italic>MYH6</italic> and <italic>MYH7</italic> have been associated with cardiac myopathy</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>14</td><td>43313740</td><td>36.514</td><td><italic>C14orf28</italic> (42 kb), <italic>BTBD5</italic> (74 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>14</td><td>75923480</td><td>33.061</td><td><italic>AHSA1</italic> (0), <italic>THSD3</italic> (7 kb)</td><td><italic>AHSA1</italic> activates the heat shock protein hsp90, and is involved in stress response</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>15</td><td>29051590</td><td>29.039</td><td><italic>TRPM1</italic> (0), <italic>MTMR10</italic> (53 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>15</td><td>61878600</td><td>42.35</td><td><italic>DAPK2</italic> (36 kb), <italic>HERC1</italic> (37 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>15</td><td>86742750</td><td>40.079</td><td><italic>MRPS11</italic> (0), <italic>MRPL46</italic> (3 kb), <italic>DET1</italic> (42 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>17</td><td>44236980</td><td>45.792</td><td><italic>FLJ25168</italic> (42 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>17</td><td>44710400</td><td>29.86</td><td><italic>LOC284058</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>17</td><td>59681810</td><td>29.413</td><td><italic>BCAS3</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>17</td><td>64527940</td><td>39.821</td><td><italic>MGC33887</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>18</td><td>14001290</td><td>32.131</td><td><italic>ZNF519</italic> (93 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>18</td><td>28715730</td><td>45.289</td><td><italic>C18orf34</italic> (53 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>18</td><td>30406890</td><td>62.627</td><td><italic>DTNA</italic> (0)</td><td>See entry for <italic>DTNA</italic> in the European-American sample</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>18</td><td>44351560</td><td>32.265</td><td><italic>KIAA0427</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>20</td><td>3532485</td><td>33.116</td><td><italic>ATRN</italic> (0)</td><td><italic>ATRN</italic> is homologous to the mouse <italic>mohogany</italic> gene, and it plays a role in several processes in mouse, including pigmentation, adaptive immunity, and obesity</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>20</td><td>31004100</td><td>31.003</td><td><italic>BCL2L1</italic> (0), <italic>COX4I2</italic> (26 kb), <italic>ID1</italic> (65 kb), <italic>TPX2</italic> (68 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>21</td><td>16307440</td><td>29.563</td><td><italic>C21orf34</italic> (57 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td><bold>Combined</bold></td><td>1</td><td>113016400</td><td>23.963</td><td><italic>LRIG2</italic> (50 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>1</td><td>154941000</td><td>24.15</td><td><italic>FCRL2</italic> (0), <italic>FCRL1</italic> (40 kb), <italic>FCRL3</italic> (54 kb)</td><td>CMLE for position in the middle of a cluster of <italic>FCRL</italic> genes, which are thought to play a role in B cell development</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>1</td><td>211644800</td><td>47.46</td><td><italic>PTPN14</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>2</td><td>141425500</td><td>44.172</td><td><italic>LRP1B</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>2</td><td>202042300</td><td>26.795</td><td><italic>MGC39518</italic> (3 kb), <italic>ORC2L</italic> (12 kb), <italic>NIF3L1</italic> (72 kb), <italic>PPIL3</italic> (86 kb), <italic>NDUFB3</italic> (96 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>29922840</td><td>25.623</td><td><italic>RBMS3</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>43323910</td><td>27.861</td><td><italic>SNRK</italic> (0), <italic>FLJ10375</italic> (44 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>3</td><td>144913600</td><td>23.908</td><td><italic>SLC9A9</italic> (26 kb), <italic>MGC33365</italic> (93 kb)</td><td>See entry for <italic>SLC9A9</italic> in the European-American sample</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>4</td><td>71991670</td><td>27.388</td><td><italic>IGJ</italic> (0), <italic>ENAM</italic> (13 kb), <italic>SAS10</italic> (28 kb), <italic>RIPX</italic> (62 kb)</td><td><italic>IGJ</italic> is an immunoglobulin with two known functions: linking immunoglobulin monomers and binding these immunoglobulins to secretory component</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>4</td><td>169845700</td><td>24.098</td><td><italic>FLJ20035</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>5</td><td>15527500</td><td>41.987</td><td><italic>FBXL7</italic> (26 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>6</td><td>128601800</td><td>33.418</td><td><italic>PTPRK</italic> (0)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>8</td><td>57052930</td><td>25.735</td><td><italic>RPS20</italic> (16 kb), <italic>MOS</italic> (22 kb), <italic>PLAG1</italic> (70 kb), <italic>LYN</italic> (80 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>10</td><td>45462260</td><td>26.114</td><td><italic>ANUBL1</italic> (10 kb), <italic>FAM21C</italic> (44 kb)</td><td>See entry for <italic>ANUBL1</italic> in the Chinese sample</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>12</td><td>81503770</td><td>24.547</td><td><italic>DKFZp762A217</italic> (79 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>13</td><td>36706830</td><td>29.695</td><td><italic>UFM1</italic> (15 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>15</td><td>37567860</td><td>35.829</td><td><italic>THBS1</italic> (21 kb), <italic>FSIP1</italic> (40 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>15</td><td>89573760</td><td>39.016</td><td><italic>SV2B</italic> (5 kb)</td><td>See entry for <italic>SV2B</italic> in the African-American sample</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>16</td><td>81827590</td><td>24.175</td><td><italic>HSPC105</italic> (3 kb), <italic>HSD17B2</italic> (20 kb)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>18</td><td>30386860</td><td>42.249</td><td><italic>DTNA</italic> (0)</td><td>See entry for <italic>DTNA</italic> in the European-American sample</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>18</td><td>44272270</td><td>25.806</td><td><italic>KIAA0427</italic> (45 kb)</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table> --><!-- <table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>Also shown are all known genes within 100 kb of the estimate of the position of the selective sweep. The 65 genomic regions which exhibited very strong evidence for a recent selective sweep that is more than 100 kb from a known gene are not shown.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><p><sup>a</sup>Physical map estimate of the location of the sweep for the window with the highest local test statistic.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><p><sup>b</sup>Lists all refseq genes within 100 kb of the estimate of sweep position.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot> --></table-wrap>
      <p>The genomic region with the strongest evidence for a recent selective sweep is in the
          <italic>DTNA</italic> gene on Chromosome 18; this location shows very strong evidence for
        selection in the Chinese, European-American, and combined samples. In the Chinese sample,
        the observed CLR statistic in this region is 62.63. In contrast, the highest CLR statistic
        for the Chinese population over 100,000 selectively neutral simulations is 24.34, and the
        95th percentile of the simulated neutral datasets is 9.57. These simulations were performed
        with population bottleneck parameters that have been fit to human data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b025">25</xref>] and with a recombination rate that is
        slightly less than that of the <italic>DTNA</italic> region. <italic>DTNA</italic> encodes
        the dystrobrevin protein, a component of the dystrophin protein complex (DPC). Aside from
          <italic>DTNA</italic>, several other genes that contribute to the DPC show evidence for
        recent selective sweeps (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030090-st003">Table S3</xref>), including several syntrophin and sarcoglycan genes. The DPC primarily
        functions as a key structural component in the architecture of muscle tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b026">26</xref>], suggesting that the selective sweeps
        at DPC genes may involve a muscle-related phenotype. Furthermore, several other
        muscle-related genes show very strong evidence for recent selective sweeps, including
          <italic>NEBL</italic> and two tightly linked, cardiac-specific myosin heavy-chain genes
          <italic>(MYH6</italic> and <italic>MYH7).</italic></p>
      <p>One of the most conspicuous features of our genomic scan is that several centromeric
        regions have extreme spatial patterns of allele frequency consistent with recent selective
        sweeps. For instance, the region spanning the centromere of Chromosome 16 shows strong
        evidence of recent selection. The size of the affected area is remarkable: the combined,
        European-American, and Chinese samples exhibit skewed frequency spectra and very low
          <italic>p</italic> values by the CLR test over 16 Mb. Of the 17 autosomes for which we
        have data spanning the centromere, we observe evidence of selective sweeps in centromeric
        regions of Chromosomes 1, 3, 8, 11, 12, 16, 18, and 20 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030090-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Because the CLR test is not very sensitive to
        the underlying recombination rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b022">22</xref>],
        it is unlikely that this signal is an artifact of reduced recombination rates in centromeric
        regions. The large genomic distance over which the signature of selection extends in many of
        these regions complicates the identification of the selected target. However, the consistent
        signal of selective sweeps and the paucity of known genes in centromeric regions suggest the
        hypothesis that the centromeres themselves may be the functional genomic elements targeted
        by selection. One interesting possibility in this regard is that selection in centromeric
        regions may be the result of meiotic drive [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b027">27</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b029">29</xref>] (e.g., during female
        meiosis, any variant which even slightly decreases the probability that a chromosome
        segregates to a polar body will carry a huge selective advantage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b030">30</xref>]). Also, centromeres are strong candidates for regions
        affecting chromosomal segregation.</p>
      <fig id="pgen-0030090-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Evidence for Selective Sweeps in Centromeric Regions of Several Chromosomes, as
            Measured by the <italic>p</italic> Value of the CLR Test in Three Human
            Populations</title>
          <p>Vertical dashed lines indicate the positions of the centromere, and <italic>p</italic>
            values are plotted on a log scale.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Because of the time scale in which the CLR test has power to detect a selective sweep
        (within the last ~200,000 y), it is useful for identifying selected changes that occurred in
        one or more populations since the time of population divergence (the continental populations
        represented by the samples probably diverged within the last 100,000 years). Such
        population-specific selective sweeps should be evident in our analysis as a high CLR
        statistic and low CLR <italic>p</italic> value in only one of the continental groups that
        was sampled. Along these lines, Jablonski and Chaplin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b031">31</xref>] suggested that global variation in skin pigmentation is
        due to adaptation to local environments, noting that skin pigmentation in indigenous human
        populations correlates very strongly with the local average intensity of UV radiation. To
        investigate the role of local adaptation in shaping global patterns of human skin
        pigmentation, we interrogate pigmentation candidate genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030090-t002">Table 2</xref>) for evidence of population-specific selective
        sweeps. <italic>KITLG,</italic> which encodes a signaling molecule that stimulates
        melanocyte proliferation, growth, and dendricity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b032">32</xref>], shows strong evidence for selective sweeps in the
        European-American and Chinese samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030090-g002">Figure
          2</xref>). Notably, the coding sequence of <italic>KITLG</italic> is 218 kb away from our
        estimate of the sweep position, whereas the next-nearest gene is 550 kb away, indicating
        that <italic>KITLG</italic> is the likely target of selection. Furthermore, the distance
        between our estimate of the sweep position and the <italic>KITLG</italic> coding sequence
        suggests the hypothesis that the selected mutation may be regulatory in nature. The presence
        of a selective sweep or sweeps at <italic>KITLG,</italic> along with experimental phenotypic
        effects of the gene, suggests that <italic>KITLG</italic> may be an important quantitative
        trait locus underlying variation in human skin pigmentation.</p>
      <table-wrap content-type="1col" id="pgen-0030090-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
          <p>Candidate Genes for Variation in Human Skin Pigmentation and Evidence of
            Population-Specific Selective Sweeps</p>
        </caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup><col id="tb2col1" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col2" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col3" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col4" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col5" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col6" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><hr/>Gene</td><td valign="bottom"><hr/>Chr</td><td valign="bottom"><hr/>Position (Mb)</td><td><hr/>CLR <italic>p</italic> Value, African-American</td><td><hr/>CLR <italic>p</italic> Value, European-American</td><td><hr/>CLR <italic>p</italic> Value, Chinese</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>POMC</italic></td><td valign="bottom">2</td><td valign="bottom">25.36</td><td valign="bottom">0.654 (0.433)</td><td valign="bottom">0.295</td><td valign="bottom">0.150</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>MITF</italic></td><td valign="bottom">3</td><td valign="bottom">69.83</td><td valign="bottom">0.181</td><td valign="bottom">0.254 (0.182)</td><td valign="bottom">0.658 (0.627)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>KIT</italic></td><td valign="bottom">4</td><td valign="bottom">55.48</td><td valign="bottom">0.828 (0.813)</td><td valign="bottom">0.618</td><td valign="bottom">0.301</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>F2r11</italic></td><td valign="bottom">5</td><td valign="bottom">76.21</td><td valign="bottom">0.808</td><td valign="bottom">0.870</td><td valign="bottom">0.933</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>MATP</italic></td><td valign="bottom">5</td><td valign="bottom">34.01</td><td valign="bottom">0.976</td><td valign="bottom"><bold>0.00014</bold></td><td valign="bottom">0.658</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>DTNBP1</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td valign="bottom">6</td><td valign="bottom">15.70</td><td valign="bottom">0.913 (0.416)</td><td valign="bottom">0.644 (0.599)</td><td valign="bottom">0.037</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>TYRP1</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td valign="bottom">9</td><td valign="bottom">12.69</td><td valign="bottom">0.652</td><td valign="bottom">0.326</td><td valign="bottom">0.421</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>TYR</italic></td><td valign="bottom">11</td><td valign="bottom">88.66</td><td valign="bottom">0.746 (0.725)</td><td valign="bottom">0.145 (0.117)</td><td valign="bottom">0.221 (0.209)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>SILV</italic></td><td valign="bottom">12</td><td valign="bottom">54.64</td><td valign="bottom">0.092</td><td valign="bottom">0.050</td><td valign="bottom"><bold>0.007</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>KITLG</italic></td><td valign="bottom">12</td><td valign="bottom">87.44</td><td valign="bottom"><bold>0.014</bold></td><td valign="bottom"><bold>0.000007</bold></td><td valign="bottom"><bold>0.00002</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>DCT</italic></td><td valign="bottom">13</td><td valign="bottom">92.81</td><td valign="bottom">0.812 (0.796)</td><td valign="bottom">0.335</td><td valign="bottom">0.305</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>OCA2</italic> <sup>a</sup></td><td valign="bottom">15</td><td valign="bottom">25.77</td><td valign="bottom">0.400 <bold>(0.046)</bold></td><td valign="bottom">0.140 (0.055)</td><td valign="bottom"><bold>0.020</bold> <bold>(0.0023)</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>TRPM1</italic></td><td valign="bottom">15</td><td valign="bottom">29.04</td><td valign="bottom">0.992</td><td valign="bottom">0.707 (0.689)</td><td valign="bottom"><bold>0.00004</bold> <bold>(0.00002)</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>SLC24A5</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td valign="bottom">15</td><td valign="bottom">46.14</td><td valign="bottom">0.287</td><td valign="bottom"><bold>0.0008</bold></td><td valign="bottom">0.868</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>MYO5A</italic><sup>a</sup></td><td valign="bottom">15</td><td valign="bottom">50.43</td><td valign="bottom">0.382</td><td valign="bottom">0.492 (0.454)</td><td valign="bottom">0.398</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>RAB27A</italic></td><td valign="bottom">15</td><td valign="bottom">53.23</td><td valign="bottom">0.885 (0.814)</td><td valign="bottom"><bold>0.0025</bold></td><td valign="bottom"><bold>0.00020</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>MC1R</italic></td><td valign="bottom">16</td><td valign="bottom">89.73</td><td valign="bottom">0.274</td><td valign="bottom">0.556</td><td valign="bottom">0.405</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>MC2R</italic></td><td valign="bottom">18</td><td valign="bottom">13.88</td><td valign="bottom">0.839</td><td valign="bottom">0.125</td><td valign="bottom"><bold>0.0005</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>ATRN</italic></td><td valign="bottom">20</td><td valign="bottom">35.19</td><td valign="bottom">0.613</td><td valign="bottom">0.608 (0.582)</td><td valign="bottom"><bold>0.00020</bold> <bold>(0.00006)</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom"><italic>ASIP</italic></td><td valign="bottom">20</td><td valign="bottom">33.57</td><td valign="bottom">0.518</td><td valign="bottom">0.749</td><td valign="bottom">0.375</td></tr></tbody></table> --><!-- <table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt201"><p>Reported <italic>p</italic> values are from the genomic window with a midpoint nearest the midpoint of the gene.</p></fn><fn id="nt202"><p>Values in parentheses indicate the minimum <italic>p</italic> value of windows with a center between the start and stop codon of the gene, which is reported only if it is different from the midpoint <italic>p</italic> value. Bold typeface indicates <italic>p</italic> values with nominal significance below 5&percnt;.</p></fn><fn id="nt203"><p><sup>a</sup>Genes previously identified as experiencing partial selective sweeps in the European population &lsqb;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b015">15</xref>&rsqb;.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot> --></table-wrap>
      <fig id="pgen-0030090-g002" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Sliding Window Analysis of the <italic>KITLG</italic> Region of Chromosome 12,
            Along with Gene Models of All refseq Genes in the Region</title>
          <p>The horizontal dashed line represents the <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 critical value
            of the population-specific CLR tests generated using a conservative estimate of the
            average recombination rate in the region.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Other pigmentation candidate genes with strong evidence of population-specific selective
        sweeps include <italic>RAB27A, MATP, MC2R, ATRN, TRPM1,</italic> and <italic>SLC24A5.
          SILV</italic> and <italic>OCA2</italic> show marginally significant evidence for
        population-specific sweeps. Mouse orthologs of most of these genes carry coat color
        phenotypes, and <italic>SLC24A5</italic> was recently shown to contain a common mutation
        affecting skin pigmentation in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b033">33</xref>]. Considered as a whole, pigmentation candidate genes are enriched for
        significant CLR tests. For instance, in the genome scan of the Chinese sample, pigmentation
        genes contain more than twice as many significant CLR tests (at the <italic>p &lt;</italic>
        0.01 level) compared with the expectation from the rest of the genome; this enrichment is
        marginally significant (χ<sup>2</sup><sub>(1)</sub> = 6.04, <italic>p =</italic> 0.007).
        Using a more stringent significance level for the CLR test, the enrichment of pigmentation
        genes becomes more pronounced (i.e., at the <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 level), and
        pigmentation genes are more than 5-fold enriched for significant tests, compared with the
        genomic expectation (χ<sup>2</sup><sub>(1)</sub> = 17.3948, <italic>p =</italic> 1.5 ×
          10<sup>−5</sup>). A similar pattern emerges in the European-American sample: at the CLR
          <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 level, we observe twice as many significant pigmentation
        genes as expected (χ<sup>2</sup><sub>(1)</sub> = 2.6297, <italic>p =</italic> 0.052), and at
        the <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 level, we observe a nearly 5-fold enrichment
          (χ<sup>2</sup><sub>(1)</sub> = 9.057, <italic>p =</italic> 0.0013). In a similar analysis,
        Voight and coworkers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b015">15</xref>] identified a
        signal of partial selective sweeps in the European population for <italic>OCA2, MYO5A,
          DTNBP1, TYRP1,</italic> and <italic>SLC24A5,</italic> all of which are pigmentation
        candidate genes. Likewise, Izagirre and coworkers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b034">34</xref>] found evidence of a partial selective sweep at
          <italic>TP53B1</italic> and <italic>RAD50</italic> in African populations, and at
          <italic>TYRP1</italic> and <italic>SLC24A5</italic> in European populations. A partial
        sweep occurs when the beneficial mutation has not spread throughout the entire population,
        whereas the CLR test is designed to detect beneficial mutations that have recently reached a
        frequency of 100% (complete sweeps). Thus, the two analyses should be complementary, and
        there is little overlap between the analyses in terms of which pigmentation genes are
        identified as selected in which populations. Taken together, these results indicate that
        population-specific selective sweeps, both partial and complete, have been common in genes
        in skin pigmentation pathways, suggesting that adaptation to local environments has driven
        the evolution of human skin pigmentation.</p>
      <p>Several other gene categories and pathways show a striking pattern of recent adaptation.
        For instance, we observe evidence for a selective sweep mainly in the African-American
        sample in a region surrounding a cluster of olfactory receptor <italic>(OR)</italic> genes
        on Chromosome 11. Recent adaptive evolution appears to be a pervasive force among
          <italic>OR</italic> genes. Among 29 autosomal clusters of <italic>OR</italic> genes, 16
        clusters show evidence of a selective sweep (CLR <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in at least
        one of the populations. These findings corroborate work on adaptation in <italic>OR</italic>
        genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b035">35</xref>], and suggest that many
        changes in the human olfactory repertoire may have occurred very recently. Similarly,
        candidate genes for hair morphology show consistent signals of recent adaptation.
        Keratin-associated proteins (KRTAPs) are thought to play an important role in the shape of
        hair follicles, and we observe evidence for recent adaptation at four out of five clusters
        of <italic>KRTAP</italic> genes, mostly in the European-American sample. Perhaps the most
        surprising category of genes that show consistent evidence of recent adaptation is heat
        shock proteins (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030090-st004">Table
          S4</xref>). Among 56 unlinked heat shock genes, 28 showed evidence of a recent selective
        sweep in at least one population at the <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 level. Several genes
        with functional roles in the development and function of the nervous system show very strong
        evidence (CLR <italic>p</italic> &lt; 10<sup>−5</sup>) for a recent selective sweep. For
        example, <italic>SV2B,</italic> a gene encoding a synaptic vesicle protein with highest
        expression during brain development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b036">36</xref>], exhibits strong evidence for a selective sweep in the African-American sample.
        Likewise, the protein encoded by <italic>DAB1</italic> plays a developmental role in the
        layering of neurons in the cerebral cortex and cerebellum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b037">37</xref>], and exhibits strong evidence for a selective sweep in
        the Asian sample. Other nervous system genes with strong evidence for a selective sweep
        include two candidate genes for Alzheimer disease <italic>(APPBP2</italic> and
          <italic>APBA2)</italic> that bind the amyloid-beta precursor protein, two genes
          <italic>(SKP1A</italic> and <italic>PCDH15)</italic> with a role in sensory development,
        and several others with various roles in nervous system development and function
          <italic>(PHACTR1, ALG10, PREP, GPM6A,</italic> and <italic>DGKI).</italic></p>
      <p>Several analyses (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b003">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b005">5</xref>]) suggest genes that play a role in
        immunity and pathogen response are among the most common targets of adaptive evolution.
        Consistent with these results, we observe very strong evidence of recent adaptation (CLR
          <italic>p</italic> &lt; 10<sup>−5</sup>) within or very close to several immune system
        genes. These include: (1) two genes thought to play a role B-cell development
          <italic>(FCRL2</italic> and <italic>TSLP)</italic>; (2) two somatic
        recombination-activating genes <italic>(RAG1</italic> and <italic>RAG2),</italic> which help
        generate the diversity of immunoglobulins and T cell receptors; (3) <italic>CD226,</italic>
        a <italic>trans</italic>-membrane protein involved in the cytotoxicity of natural killer
        cells and T cells; and (4) <italic>IGJ,</italic> an immunoglobulin responsible for linking
        other immunoglobulins to each other and to the secretory component. In addition, two genes
        that are not part of the immune system, but which might play an important role in pathogen
        interactions, also show very strong evidence of a recent sweep; these are
          <italic>TJP1</italic> and <italic>VPS37C.</italic> The TJP1 protein associates with the
        CagA protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b038">38</xref>], which is
        translocated into gastric epithelial cells by the human pathogen <italic>Helicobacter
          pylori.</italic> The <italic>TJP1</italic>–CagA interaction is thought to play a role in
        the pathogenicity of <italic>H. pylori,</italic> and the selective sweep in the
          <italic>TJP1</italic> region suggests the hypothesis that the selected variation may have
        affected the pathogenic effects of <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">H. pylori</named-content> infection. The VPS37C protein is a subunit
        of the endosomal sorting complex, which is recruited by HIV and other viruses to promote
        viral budding from infected cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b039">39</xref>].</p>
      <p>Several loci in the human genome have been previously identified as targets of recent
        adaptive evolution. Because these loci were identified using independent data and different
        statistical methods, they are to some extent positive controls (i.e., if selection is truly
        operating in these regions and if the CLR test has sufficient power, then we should observe
        evidence for selective sweeps at many of these loci using our approach). One such locus is
        the <italic>LCT</italic> gene on Chromosome 2. Numerous studies have identified evidence for
        one or more functional polymorphsims in <italic>LCT</italic> that affect lactose metabolism
        in adults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b040">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b041">41</xref>], and Bersaglieri and coworkers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b042">42</xref>] found that very recent positive selection in European
        populations has strongly affected the frequency of this polymorphism. Concordantly, we
        observe evidence for a selective sweep in the European-American sample (CLR
          <italic>p</italic> = 0.012), but not the other samples. Notably, the proposed beneficial
        mutation in <italic>LCT,</italic> the lactase persistence allele, is not completely fixed in
        European populations; rather, its frequency is 77% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b042">42</xref>]. Even though the CLR test considers a model of a
        complete selective sweep in which the beneficial allele reaches a frequency of 100%, the
        significant result at <italic>LCT</italic> suggests that the CLR test has at least some
        power to detect recent adaptive events that deviate from the assumptions of the complete
        sweep model. The <italic>HFE</italic> gene on Chromosome 6 is another locus for which
        previous work suggests a selective sweep [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b043">43</xref>]. For the genomic window centered on <italic>HFE,</italic> we find significant
        evidence for a selective sweep in the vicinity of <italic>HFE</italic> in the Chinese
          (<italic>p</italic> = 0.00006), European-American (<italic>p</italic> = 0.002), and
        combined (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0006) samples. <italic>HFE</italic> contains a relatively
        high-frequency recessive mutation, C282Y, which causes hereditary hemochromatosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b044">44</xref>], an iron-overload disorder. Although
        positive selection is thought to operate somewhere in the vicinity of <italic>HFE,</italic>
        it is unknown whether the C282Y mutation attained high frequency through selection directly
        (positive selection on C282Y itself) or indirectly (positive selection on a nearby
        beneficial mutation associated with C282Y). Our composite likelihood estimate of the
        position of the selective sweep is within a cluster of histone genes, 150 kb away from
          <italic>HFE,</italic> suggesting that C282Y may have attained high frequency through
        association with a nearby beneficial allele. If this hypothesis of C282Y rising to high
        frequency indirectly is correct, then it carries the interesting implication that
        populations experiencing selective sweeps may sometimes incur indirect costs: occasionally,
        selective sweeps may carry tightly linked, initially rare, deleterious, and potentially
        disease-causing variation to relatively high frequencies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b045">45</xref>]. Essentially, a recent selective sweep may have a
        localized effect in the genome similar to a population bottleneck (i.e., a sweep is somewhat
        analogous to a genomically localized reduction in effective population size), and
        deleterious disease alleles in these regions may obtain observable frequency by chance in
        this situation. Other regions where previous research has suggested positive selection, and
        the signal is confirmed by our analysis, include the cluster of <italic>ADH</italic> genes
        on Chromosome 4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b046">46</xref>], which show
        evidence for a recent sweep only in the Chinese sample (CLR <italic>p</italic> = 0.00015),
        and the opioid receptor <italic>PDYN</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b047">47</xref>], which also shows evidence of a selective sweep only in the Chinese sample
        (CLR <italic>p</italic> = 0.002). Loci that have been previously identified as targets of
        recent or ongoing selective sweeps, but do not show evidence for a selective sweep in the
        present analysis, include <italic>MMP3</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b048">48</xref>], <italic>CD40LG</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b008">8</xref>], <italic>CCR5</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b007">7</xref>], <italic>ASPM</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b049">49</xref>], and <italic>MCPH</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b050">50</xref>]. Like <italic>LCT,</italic> previous work indicates a
        partial selective sweep at these loci, and in all of the above cases, the frequency of the
        putatively beneficial allele is relatively low (between 10% and 70%). Because these loci are
        thought to deviate more strongly from the complete sweep model, the CLR test probably does
        not have adequate power to detect selection at these loci.</p>
      <p>Another means of validation for our genomic scan is to compare the spatial distribution of
        evidence for selection along chromosomes with the distribution of known functional elements
        in the genome (i.e., if a large proportion of positive tests are false positives, then one
        would not expect positive tests to be associated with functional elements). For example,
        Voight and coworkers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b015">15</xref>] found that
        genic regions of chromosomes are strongly enriched for extreme values of the integrated
        extended haplotype homozygosity statistic, an observation that is not readily explainable by
        factors that can cause a false signal of selection, such as demography or ascertainment
        bias. Using a similar approach, we tested regions surrounding known genes for an enrichment
        of significant CLR tests. We used a contingency table approach to test for enrichment (i.e.,
        we compared the proportion of significant tests in windows nearest the center of known genes
        to the proportion of significant tests in the remainder of the genome). The results of these
        analyses are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030090-st005">Table
          S5</xref>. Notably, in the European-American and Chinese samples, we observe a strong
        excess of significant tests in genic regions, and this signal becomes stronger as the
        significance level applied to the CLR test becomes more stringent. For example, in the
        European-American sample at a significance level of <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001, we
        observe 40% more significant tests than expected at gene centers, based on the total number
        of significant tests and the total number of windows at gene centers. Because centromeric
        regions have strong evidence of selection and low gene density, this signal becomes even
        stronger if centromeric regions are excluded. We conclude, therefore, that extreme values of
        the CLR statistic are strongly associated with genic regions of chromosomes, and this
        association has two important implications. First, it further corroborates the results of
        our genomic scan for selective sweeps, as this association is not predicted if a high
        proportion of significant tests are false positives. Second, the association between genes
        and selection in this paper and in the Voight et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b015">15</xref>] study suggests that the empirical follow-up to genomic
        scans for selection will be at least somewhat experimentally tractable. Identifying
        beneficial mutations and determining their phenotypic effects will be much easier if the
        beneficial mutation is within a known gene.</p>
      <p>Another interesting comparison is the contrast between our analysis and previously
        published genomic scans for selective sweeps. This comparison does not necessarily provide a
        means of validating ours or previous analyses, as the statistics used in the different
        genomic scans may be correlated even under selective neutrality, and the statistics have
        power to detect different types of selective sweeps. However, the comparison does provide a
        general sense of the consistency of population genetic methods for identifying selective
        sweeps from genomic variation data. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030090-st006">Table S6</xref> gives the CLR statistics and <italic>p</italic>
        values for the most extreme regions of the genome identified in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b016">16</xref>] using two different approaches: population
        differentiation (Table 9 in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b016">16</xref>]) and
        extended haplotype homozygosity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b008">8</xref>]
        (Table 10 in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b016">16</xref>]). In the Chinese
        sample, genes containing nonsynonymous SNPs that exhibit high levels of population
        differentiation in the Hapmap data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b016">16</xref>]
        are enriched for CLR tests significant at the <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 level
          (χ<sup>2</sup><sub>(1)</sub> = 10.6; <italic>p</italic> = 0.0011). Similarly, genomic
        regions with the most extreme patterns of extended haplotype homozygosity in the Hapmap data
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b016">16</xref>] also have more significant CLR
        tests than would be expected if the two statistics were statistically independent. However,
        even among the most extreme regions of the genome in the Hapmap analysis, the CLR analysis
        does not always show evidence of a selective sweep. This inconsistency is likely the result
        of differential power of the alternative approaches in detecting different types of
        selection. For example, considering that extended haplotype approaches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b008">8</xref>] have the most power to detect partial
        selective sweeps [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b015">15</xref>], it would not be
        surprising if the most extreme regions of the genome by these approaches were the result of
        a partial sweep. Furthermore, the CLR approach probably has limited power to detect this
        type of selection because it does not leave a population genetic signature similar to that
        of a complete sweep. In conclusion, it is encouraging that the CLR test is not independent
        of other statistics, which suggests some consistency among genomic scans for selective
        sweeps. However, it is also encouraging that the CLR test is not completely correlated with
        other approaches; if it were, then we would not have uncovered any previously unknown
        selective sweeps in this analysis.</p>
      <p>In addition to the statistical exploration of the CLR test by Nielsen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b022">22</xref>], we performed extensive neutral
        simulations to determine how robust the CLR approach is to both recombination rate variation
        and complex demography. Recent work suggests that recombination rate variation is a
        pervasive feature of the human genome, and most recombination events occur in recombination
        hotspots [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b051">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b052">52</xref>]. To investigate how recombination rate variation might
        affect our analysis, we performed coalescent simulations with recombination hotspots, as
        well as SNP ascertainment, missing data, and different demographic scenarios. Recombination
        hotspots were represented as randomly spaced 5 kb fragments with an average distance between
        hotspots of 50 kb, and within the hotspot, the recombination rate was assumed to be 8-fold
        higher than the background rate. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030090-g003">Figure
          3</xref> shows a comparison of <italic>p</italic> values calculated from a constant
        recombination model and a hotspot model with an equal average recombination rate.
        Recombination rate variation appears to have no effect on the null distribution of the CLR
        statistic, and <italic>p</italic> values calculated under the hotspot and constant
        recombination models are strikingly consistent. We observe some minor differences in
          <italic>p</italic> values calculated for very extreme test statistics (<italic>p
          &lt;</italic> 10<sup>−4</sup>), but these differences are readily explainable by Monte
        Carlo error in the estimation of <italic>p</italic> values via simulation.</p>
      <fig id="pgen-0030090-g003" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.g003</object-id>
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>A Comparison of <italic>p</italic> Values of the CLR Test, Calculated from
            Simulations of Models Assuming a Constant Recombination Rate and Models That Include
            Recombination Hotspots</title>
          <p>(A) The combined sample.</p>
          <p>(B) The African-American sample.</p>
          <p>(C) The European-American sample.</p>
          <p>(D) The Chinese sample.</p>
          <p><italic>p</italic> Values are highly consistent between constant recombination and
            hotspot models, indicating that the CLR test is robust to recombination rate variation.
            Note that both axes are on a log scale.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>We also performed simulations under a variety of demographic models beyond those considered
        by Nielsen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b022">22</xref>] in order to more
        fully explore the robustness of the CLR test to complex population demography. In
        particular, we investigated how the strength of the population bottlenecks experienced by
        non-African populations affects the null distribution of the CLR statistic. We simulated
        data under population bottlenecks with a constant duration and varying severity, with the
        temporary reduction in population size ranging from 50% to 99% only for non-African
        populations. Surprisingly, the null distribution of the CLR statistic is shifted toward
        lower values under the strong bottleneck model (99% reduction) compared with the equilibrium
        model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030090-g004">Figure 4</xref>), and the variance in
        the CLR statistic is much lower. This result indicates that, if the strong bottleneck model
        accurately reflects history, but we use the equilibrium model (random mating, constant
        population size) to obtain <italic>p</italic> values of the CLR test, our results will be
        strongly conservative. These surprising results for the strong bottleneck model can be
        explained by a coalescent argument: with a strong and recent bottleneck, the vast majority
        of the coalescences and the most recent common ancestor of the sample typically occur during
        the bottleneck, which reduces the stochasticity due to the ancestral process. This reduced
        stochasticity results in less variation in the site-frequency spectrum (SFS) across the
        genome and, consequently, less extreme CLR statistics. Under a weak bottleneck (50%
        reduction), the null distribution of the CLR statistic is nearly unaffected.
        Intermediate-strength bottlenecks (90%–95% reduction) cause the most problems: compared with
        the equilibrium model, the CLR statistic shows slightly more variation under intermediate
        bottlenecks, and the upper tail of the null distribution is slightly heavier. Similar to the
        case of an intermediate bottleneck model, the complex model approximated by Schaffner et al.
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b053">53</xref>] results in slightly more
        variation in the CLR statistic with a heavier upper tail. Therefore, the equilibrium neutral
        model will be somewhat anticonservative when applied to a population that has experienced an
        intermediate bottleneck or multiple weak bottlenecks, as in the case of the Schaffner et al.
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b052">52</xref>] model. However, compared with
        the effect of demography on standard methods for detecting selection, the CLR approach is
        very robust to even the most extreme demographic effects. The robustness of the CLR approach
        to demographic effects is reflected in the general consistency of <italic>p</italic> values
        obtained under alternative demographic models (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030090-sg001">Figure S1</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="pgen-0030090-g004" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.g004</object-id>
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <title>The Null Distribution of the CLR Statistic in a Non-African Population for
            Non-African Bottleneck Models of Varying Strength, As Well As the Complex Schaffner
            Model</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>False discovery rate (FDR) methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b023">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b024">24</xref>] use the distribution
        of <italic>p</italic> values among tests to correct for multiple hypothesis testing,
        providing an estimate of the probability that the null hypothesis is true for any particular
        test (the <italic>q</italic> value). The distribution of <italic>p</italic> values for the
        different windows is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030090-g005">Figure 5</xref>.
        In the Chinese and European-American samples, the distribution shows a strong excess of
        tests with very low <italic>p</italic> values from the CLR test, suggesting that the null
        hypothesis is false for many of these windows. In addition to correcting for multiple
        testing, FDR methods estimate the number of tests in which the null hypothesis is false
            (<italic>m<sub>1</sub></italic>). In the case of genomic scans for natural selection,
            <italic>m<sub>1</sub></italic> is itself a parameter of interest, because it provides a
        rough indication of what proportion of the genome is affected by selective sweeps at linked
        sites. FDR estimates of the proportion of tests where the null hypothesis is false
            (<italic>m<sub>1</sub>/m</italic>) is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030090-g006">Figure 6</xref>, using several alternative demographic models to
        obtain <italic>p</italic> values. All alternative models indicate that recent selective
        sweeps have been a pervasive force in the human genome, with ~10% of the genome affected by
        selective sweeps in the European-American and Chinese samples, ~1% in the African-American
        sample, and ~5% in the combined sample.</p>
      <fig id="pgen-0030090-g005" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.g005</object-id>
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <title>The Distribution of <italic>p</italic> Values for the CLR Test of a Selective
            Sweep</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="pgen-0030090-g006" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.g006</object-id>
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <title>The Fraction of Tests for Which the Null Hypothesis Is False, Estimated Using a FDR
            Procedure and Shown for Four Alternative Evolutionary Models</title>
          <p>(1) The equilibrium, random mating, neutral model. (2) The Marth et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b025">25</xref>] bottleneck and growth model. (3)
            The most conservative non-African bottleneck model. (4) The complex demographic and
            recombination model calibrated by Schaffner et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b050">50</xref>].</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The FDR estimates of <italic>m<sub>1</sub></italic> suggest that recent adaptation has had
        a strong effect on genome-wide patterns of nucleotide variation, to the point that a
        considerable fraction of the genome is evolving nonneutrally. However, this conclusion
        should be considered preliminary: <italic>m<sub>1</sub></italic> is a very rough measure of
        the pervasiveness of selective sweeps, and estimates of the proportion of the genome
        affected by a sweep will of course depend strongly on what is meant by “affected.” In our
        case, this means that selection has altered patterns of variation in the window sufficiently
        to drive the <italic>p</italic> value of the CLR test below ~0.05. The ability of selection
        to alter variation in a window will depend very much on the strength of selection, the
        genomic distance away from the beneficial mutation, the age of the selective event, and the
        type of selection. Fully describing the genomic effects of linked selection and estimating
        the number of selective events will require fitting a model of multiple selective events to
        the entire genome (perhaps including complete selective sweeps of varying age, different
        types of balancing selection, partial selective sweeps, and “soft” sweeps starting from
        standing variation), rather than fitting a model of a single selective sweep to a small
        window of the genome for a number of different windows. The primary utility of the present
        analysis lies in the fine-scale identification of individual loci that have experienced
        selection, which greatly facilitates the investigation of what human phenotypes have been
        affected by adaptation, and what forces in the environment have driven recent human
        evolution.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Here we have presented a comprehensive scan for selective sweeps across the human genome.
        Several general patterns emerge from the analysis. We find much more evidence for selective
        sweeps in Chinese and European-American populations than in the African-American population.
        This result is consistent with the hypothesis that, as anatomically modern humans migrated
        out of sub-Saharan Africa, the novel environments they encountered imposed new selective
        pressures, which in turn led to an increased rate of population-specific selective sweeps
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b054">54</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b056">56</xref>]. However, a caveat should be considered when
        interpreting the differences between African-American and non-African populations: the
        statistical power to detect selective sweeps is likely to be much lower in the
        African-American sample. Because the CLR test is based on a complete sweep model, the recent
        admixture of African and European lineages in the African-American population probably
        weakens the signal of Africa-specific selective sweeps. If a complete selective sweep
        occurred in African populations after the divergence of European populations, then the
        beneficial allele, and corresponding haplotypes, would not be fixed in the African-American
        sample. In other words, admixture is expected to fundamentally alter the molecular signature
        of a selective sweep, and it is therefore unsurprising that our results for the
        African-American sample are distinctly different from those of the European-American and
        Chinese samples. Another factor to consider is the extensive subdivision among African
        populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b057">57</xref>]. Subdivision within
        Africa may have allowed, or may have been driven by, adaptation to local environments within
        Africa. This sort of selection may not be evident in the African-American sample, which
        represents a nonrandom, continent-wide sampling of African lineages with some admixture of
        European lineages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b058">58</xref>]. Subdivision
        within Africa may add further complications to the effect of admixture on the power of the
        CLR test (i.e., perhaps the proper demographic history of the African-American population
        includes the admixture of several diverged African populations), followed by large-scale
        (20%, from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b059">59</xref>]) admixture with
        European populations. For example, in this demographic scenario, if a selective sweep
        occurred within Africa in a source population for the African-American population, the
        molecular signature of this sweep would be obscured by the admixture among African
        populations during the founding of the African-American population, and the signature would
        further be eroded by subsequent admixture with the European population. Considering that
        numerous factors suggest that selective sweeps will be much more difficult to detect in the
        African-American sample, compared with the non-African populations, it is premature to
        conclude that the rate of adaptation has increased in non-African populations.</p>
      <p>Another general pattern that emerges from our analysis is that we observe more evidence for
        selective sweeps within subpopulations, compared with the cosmopolitan sample. This result
        suggests that adaptation to local environments has been an important force in recent human
        evolution. The relevance of local adaptation might be predicted considering the extensive
        range expansions in recent human history, and the tremendous diversity of environments
        inhabited by indigenous human populations. However, the notable discrepancy between local
        and cosmopolitan sweeps is also difficult to interpret due to potential differences in the
        statistical power to detect different types of selective events. For example, if the power
        to detect sweeps were much greater in the local samples compared with the cosmopolitan
        sample, then one would expect to observe results similar to ours, even if the true number of
        local and cosmopolitan sweeps were equal. Fully evaluating the relative importance of
        localized and worldwide selective sweeps will require a detailed study of the statistical
        power to detect these types of sweeps under reasonable models of human demographic
        history.</p>
      <p>In order to correct for the confounding effects of demographic history, we use a test
          [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b022">22</xref>] that compares allele frequencies
        in regions of the genome to the background pattern of variation. Simulations of a number of
        demographic models indicate that the methods are fairly robust to a wide variety of
        demographic histories; therefore, complex demography should not increase the rate of false
        positives, but we cannot rule out the possibility that some complicated demographic
        scenarios could lead to an aberrant signal of selection. Even so, if selective sweeps have
        affected some regions of the human genome, we feel that the regions that we have identified
        with extreme frequency spectra are the best candidates for future studies. Another
        alternative explanation of the results of the CLR test is that weak negative selection
        operating on the SNPs themselves could locally skew allele frequencies toward rare alleles
        in a manner that could mimic a selective sweep. Although we cannot rule out this
        explanation, several factors suggest that localized weak selection does not have a
        systematic effect on our results. First, the vast majority of SNPs are in genomic regions
        with no known function (99.2% are noncoding). Second, in most of the regions where we
        identify selective sweeps, the sweep is population-specific, an observation that is
        difficult to explain with weak negative selection. And third, we observe greater evidence
        for selective sweeps in non-African populations than in the African-American sample. If weak
        negative selection were the root cause for these deviations from neutrality, then one would
        expect a greater signal in the African-American sample because of the larger effective
        population size in African populations.</p>
      <p>The approach we have taken here—detecting complete selective sweeps by their effects on
        variation at linked sites—is complementary to previous divergence-based approaches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b001">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b005">5</xref>] characterizing adaptive evolution across the human
        genome. For instance, divergence-based approaches have been limited to detecting adaptive
        changes that have occurred via recurrent amino acid substitutions within a gene, whereas the
        present approach is capable of detecting adaptive changes at all functional genomic
        categories. The two approaches also differ in the time scale over which selection is
        detectable. Divergence-based approaches detect molecular adaptation that has occurred at any
        time on the lineage separating humans and chimps. Linked selection approaches, in contrast,
        are time-specific, detecting ongoing or very recent (within the last ~200,000 years)
        selection. Linked selection approaches are also much more amenable to investigating the
        adaptation of subpopulations to local environments at the molecular level. Given the
        complementary nature of divergence-based and linked selection methods, the present analysis
        fills in some of the gaps in our knowledge of human adaptive evolution. The challenge now is
        to use information about the genomic location of selective sweeps, in combination with the
        tools of functional genomics and knowledge of human ecology, to identify the traits that
        have been affected by recent adaptation and the selective forces that have shaped human
        populations.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Statistics.</title>
        <p>To correct for the confounding effect of demography, the CLR test of a selective sweep
          compares the SFS of a small region of the genome (a “window”) to the SFS of the rest of
          the genome. The CLR test calculates the composite likelihood of the data in a window for
          two models: (1) a model which predicts the probability of SNP frequencies using the
          genomic background SFS; and (2) a model of a very recent selective sweep. The composite
          likelihood in the sweep model is independent of demography because the SNP frequencies
          among lineages that were present before the sweep are predicted using the genomic
          background SFS. In essence, the CLR test works by considering the spatial pattern of
          allele frequencies along the genomic sequence, as predicted by a selective sweep model
          given the background pattern of variation. In an investigation of the statistical
          properties of methods for detecting selective sweeps, Nielsen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b022">22</xref>] demonstrate that, among several
          statistical tests for detecting selective sweeps, the CLR test is the most powerful and is
          the most robust to demography and the underlying recombination rate. The CLR test can be
          applied to either the SFS of the entire sample or to population-specific subsets of the
          data, enabling the detection of geographically restricted selective sweeps and balancing
          selection. For population-specific tests, we incorporate SNPs that are variable in the
          combined sample, but invariable within the subpopulation (i.e., the SFS describes the
          number of SNPs with minor allele counts of <italic>I =</italic>
          0,1,2…<italic>n</italic>/2). The inclusion of invariable SNPs may significantly increase
          power to detect selective sweeps because, if a population-specific sweep has occurred
          recently, then one expects a strong excess of invariable SNPs within the population. By
          using SNPs that are invariable within a subpopulation, but variable in the combined
          sample, our methods should be robust to mutation rate heterogeneity across the genome,
          which would not be true if we included all invariable sites. A full description of the
          tests and an exploration of their statistical properties can be found in Nielsen et al.
            [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b022">22</xref>].</p>
        <p>Because allele frequencies of linked SNPs are not statistically independent, we determine
          the null (selectively neutral) distributions of all test statistics using coalescent
          simulations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b060">60</xref>]. For data analysis,
          we define genomic windows based on the number of SNPs in the window; therefore, we
          condition on an equal number of SNPs being present in our simulated datasets. Defining
          windows based on the number of SNPs makes the procedure robust to both mutation rate
          heterogeneity and the increased variance in regional nucleotide diversity caused by
          nonstandard demographies such as bottlenecks (K. Thornton, personal communication). To
          address the effect of SNP ascertainment, we incorporate the ascertainment scheme into our
          simulations by simulating the genealogy of both the genotyping sample and the sample in
          which the SNP was discovered, and keeping only those SNPs that are variable in the
          discovery sample. For each SNP, the discovery sample size was determined by a random draw
          from the empirical distribution of discovery sample sizes, which was provided by Perlegen
          Sciences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.perlegen.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.perlegen.com</ext-link>). We incorporate ascertainment
          into the simulations, rather than applying an explicit ascertainment correction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b061">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b062">62</xref>], because the cosmopolitan discovery sample is
          computationally expensive to correct for in population-specific genotyping samples. The
          Monte Carlo approach to correcting for SNP ascertainment is greatly simplified by the
          uniform SNP discovery protocol used by Perlegen; for datasets with variable SNP
          ascertainment, such as the hapmap SNPs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b016">16</xref>], it would be necessary to also model the autocorrelation of ascertainment
          along the chromosomes. Each iteration consisted of simulating a sample with a fixed number
          of ascertained SNPs, dividing the sample into African-American, European-American, and
          Chinese samples, then calculating the combined and population-specific CLR statistics.
          This procedure was repeated 10<sup>5</sup> times. Nielsen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b022">22</xref>] found that, among a variety of demographic models
          that have been fitted to human data, the equilibrium neutral model (random mating,
          constant population size) provides the most conservative critical values for the CLR test;
          therefore, all reported <italic>p</italic> values are from simulations of the standard
          neutral model. Finally, we incorporate SNPs with missing data by calculating the tests
          using SNP allele frequencies from a subsample of the data, summing over all possible
          allele frequencies in the subsample [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b025">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b062">62</xref>]. For the
          population-specific tests, the subsample size was set to <italic>n</italic> = 44
          chromosomes, and for the combined test, it was set to <italic>n</italic> = 132. SNPs that
          did not have at least 44 chromosomes successfully genotyped in the African-American,
          European-American, and Chinese samples were excluded from further analysis. The correction
          for missing data was incorporated into the simulations of the CLR null distribution, and
          data was missing in the simulated data sets by randomly drawing the sample size for each
          SNP according to the empirical distribution of sample sizes.</p>
        <p>The CLR statistic is weakly dependent on the underlying recombination rate: the test
          becomes somewhat more conservative if the assumed recombination rate is less than the true
          rate, and slightly anticonservative if the assumed rate is greater than the true rate. It
          is necessary to account for this weak dependence because: (1) recombination rates are
          known to vary considerably across the genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b063">63</xref>]; and (2) we base the size of our genomic windows on a
          fixed number of contiguous SNPs, so that the size of the window in base pairs will vary
          with SNP density. To address these issues, we estimate the recombination rate for each
          window of the genome based on the size of the window and genetic map estimates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b063">63</xref>] of the local recombination rate.
          Then, to make the tests more conservative, we downwardly bias our estimates by a factor of
          five. We have simulated the null distributions of all test statistics for regional
          recombination rates of <italic>r</italic> = 0, 10<sup>−5</sup>, 3 × 10<sup>−5</sup>,
            10<sup>−4</sup>, 3 × 10<sup>−4</sup>, and 10<sup>−3</sup>. To estimate the
            <italic>p</italic> value for each genomic window, we use our downwardly biased estimates
          of <italic>r</italic> to interpolate between <italic>p</italic> values calculated from the
          simulated null distributions with different <italic>r</italic>.</p>
        <p>To account for multiple hypothesis testing, we apply FDR methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b023">23</xref>] that are specifically designed for genomic analyses
            [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b024">24</xref>]. FDR methods use the
          distribution of <italic>p</italic> values to estimate the number of tests in which the
          null hypothesis is false (<italic>m<sub>1</sub></italic>), and the probability that the
          null hypothesis is true for any particular test (the <italic>q</italic> value). One
          modification to the approach outlined by Storey and Tishirani [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b024">24</xref>] is the method we use for selecting the tuning
          parameter, <italic>λ</italic>. First, we represent the distribution of <italic>p</italic>
          values using a histogram of 500 bins. Next, we smooth the distribution by calculating the
          average density of the distribution in a window surrounding a particular
            <italic>p</italic> value. Let <italic>b</italic> be the number of bins in the window,
            <italic>a</italic>(<italic>P</italic>) be the average density around <italic>P</italic>,
          and <italic>w</italic> be the width of the bins. Then we select the tuning parameter
            <italic>λ</italic> as the minimum <italic>P</italic> for which the following relation
          holds: [<italic>a</italic>(<italic>P</italic>) − <italic>a</italic>(<italic>P</italic> +
            <italic>wb</italic>)] / <italic>a</italic>(<italic>P</italic> + <italic>wb</italic>) ≤
          ε. For the CLR test, <italic>b</italic> was set to 12, and <italic>ε</italic> was set to
          0.1. In essence, we use this procedure to estimate the point at which the distribution of
            <italic>p</italic> values flattens out. The procedure was used because the CLR test was
          designed to be conservative; therefore, one expects the distribution of <italic>p</italic>
          values to be skewed somewhat toward <italic>p</italic> = 1. Standard methods, such as
          splines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b026">26</xref>], assume the distribution
          of <italic>p</italic> values is flat near <italic>p</italic> = 1.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Data.</title>
        <p>We obtained allele frequency data for the Perlegen SNPs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b019">19</xref>] from the Perlegen genotype browser website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.perlegen.com/browser/download.html" xlink:type="simple">http://genome.perlegen.com/browser/download.html</ext-link>), and
          ascertainment information was obtained directly from Perlegen Sciences. We limited the
          analysis to those SNPs that were discovered by Perlegen's chip-based resequencing in a
          worldwide sample of 24 individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b064">64</xref>], including African-Americans, European-Americans, Native-Americans, and
          Asian-Americans. For analysis, we take a sliding window approach to scan the entire genome
          for evidence of selective sweeps and balancing selection. For a genomic window of 200
          contiguous SNPs (on average ~500 kb), we perform the CLR test on the SFS of the combined
          sample (African-American + European-American + Chinese) and on the SFS of each of the
          individual populations. The values of all test statistics, corresponding significance
          levels, maximum likelihood estimates of the position of the sweep, and an estimate of the
          composite parameter <italic>α</italic> are then recorded along with the genomic position
          of the center of the window. We repeat this procedure for every tenth window of 200 SNPs
          across all autosomes. Chromosomal positions of genes and genetic map estimates of local
          recombination rates were retrieved using the July 2003 build of the human genome on the
          University of California Santa Cruz (UCSC) table browser [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030090-b065">65</xref>]. A list of refseq genes mapped on to the same genomic
          build as the Perlegen SNPs is available either from the UCSC table browser or by request
          from the corresponding author.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pgen-0030090-sg001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.sg001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>A Comparison of <italic>p</italic> Values Calculated from the Equilibrium Neutral
            Model with <italic>p</italic> Values Calculated from Alternative Neutral Null
            Models</title>
          <p>Curves above the diagonal dashed lines indicate that the equilibrium model is
            anticonservative relative to the alternative null, and curves below the dashed line
            indicate that the equilibrium model conservatively identifies selection. The close
            correspondence between the curves and the diagonal dashed lines indicates that
              <italic>p</italic> values are largely consistent across alternative neutral null
            models, and demographic history does not systematically mislead the CLR approach.</p>
          <p>(47 KB PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pgen-0030090-st001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.st001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>The 63 Genomic Regions with Strong Evidence for a Recent Selective Sweep
              (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.00001, CLR test), but where the Estimate of the Position of
            the Beneficial Allele Is Not within 100 kb of the Coding Sequence of a Known
            Gene</title>
          <p>(111 KB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pgen-0030090-st002" mimetype="text/plain" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.st002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>A Genomic Scan for Selective Sweeps Using the CLR Test and a Sliding Window
            Approach</title>
          <p>Each row contains the results of the CLR test for a 200 SNP window of the genome.
            Columns represent (1) chromosome; (2) position of the center of the window; (3) CLR
            statistic for the combined sample; (4) maximum composite likelihood estimate of sweep
            position in the combined sample; (5) CLR <italic>p</italic> value for the combined
            sample; (6) CLR statistic for the African-American sample; (7) maximum composite
            likelihood estimate of sweep position in the African-American sample; (8) CLR
              <italic>p</italic> value for the African-American sample; (9) CLR statistic for the
            European-American sample; (10) maximum composite likelihood estimate of sweep position
            in the European-American sample; (11) CLR <italic>p</italic> value for the
            European-American sample; (12) CLR statistic for the Chinese sample; (13) maximum
            composite likelihood estimate of sweep position in the Chinese sample; (14) CLR
              <italic>p</italic> value for the Chinese sample.</p>
          <p>(12 MB TXT)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pgen-0030090-st003" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.st003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Evidence of Selective Sweeps at Genes Involved in the Dystrophin Protein
            Complex</title>
          <p><italic>p</italic> values are from the test of the genomic window nearest the midpoint
            of the gene, and values in parentheses represent the minimum <italic>p</italic> value
            for all windows within the gene, which is reported if different from the midpoint
              <italic>p</italic> value.</p>
          <p>(71 KB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pgen-0030090-st004" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.st004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Evidence of Selective Sweeps at Heat Shock Genes</title>
          <p><italic>p</italic> values are from the test of the genomic window nearest the midpoint
            of the gene.</p>
          <p>(147 KB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pgen-0030090-st005" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.st005" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S5</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Contingency Table Analyses for Enrichment of Significant Results in Windows Nearest
            the Midpoint of Known Genes, Compared with the Remainder of the Genome</title>
          <p>Different rows repeat the analysis for different CLR test significance levels
            (indicated in parentheses) and for different population samples. For the CLR test in the
            European-American and Chinese samples, we observe a highly significant enrichment of CLR
            tests that reject the null at gene centers, and this signal becomes stronger with more
            stringent significance levels.</p>
          <p>(74 KB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pgen-0030090-st006" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030090.st006" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S6</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Evidence of a Selective Sweep by the CLR Test in the Most Extreme Genomic Regions
            Identified by Other Methods in the Hapmap Analysis</title>
          <p>Values in parentheses indicate <italic>p</italic> values of the CLR statistic.</p>
          <p>(99 KB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This work benefited from many helpful suggestions from A. Andres and K. Thornton.</p>
    </ack>
    
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>CLR</term>
          <def>
            <p>composite likelihood ratio</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>DPC</term>
          <def>
            <p>dystrophin protein complex</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>FDR</term>
          <def>
            <p>false discovery rate</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>
            <italic>OR</italic>
          </term>
          <def>
            <p>olfactory receptor gene</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>SFS</term>
          <def>
            <p>site-frequency spectrum</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>SNP</term>
          <def>
            <p>single-nucleotide polymorphism</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b001">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Fay</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Wyckoff</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>CI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>Positive and negative selection on the human genome.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>158</volume>
          <fpage>1227</fpage>
          <lpage>1234</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b002">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>NGC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Eyre-Walker</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Adaptive protein evolution in <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>415</volume>
          <fpage>1022</fpage>
          <lpage>1024</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b003">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Glanowski</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kejariwal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Inferring nonneutral evolution from human-chimp-mouse orthologous gene
            trios.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>302</volume>
          <fpage>1960</fpage>
          <lpage>1963</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b004">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Bustamante</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Glanowski</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Sackton</surname>
              <given-names>TB</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>A scan for positively selected genes in the genomes of humans and
            chimpanzees.</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Biol</source>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <elocation-id>e170.</elocation-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b005">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Bustamante</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Fledel-Alon</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Williamson</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hubisz</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Natural selection on protein-coding genes in the human
            genome.</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>437</volume>
          <fpage>1153</fpage>
          <lpage>1157</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b006">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Williamson</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hernandez</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Fledel-Alon</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Simultaneous inference of selection and population growth from patterns of
            variation in the human genome.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>7882</fpage>
          <lpage>7887</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b007">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Stephens</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Reich</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Goldstein</surname>
              <given-names>DB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>HD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>MW</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>1998</year>
          <article-title>Dating the origin of the CCR5-Δ32 AIDS-resistance allele by the coalescence
            of haplotypes.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <fpage>1507</fpage>
          <lpage>1515</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b008">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Sabeti</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Reich</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Higgins</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Levine</surname>
              <given-names>HZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Richter</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Detecting recent positive selection in the human genome from haplotype
            structure.</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>419</volume>
          <fpage>832</fpage>
          <lpage>837</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b009">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Dobzhansky</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1955</year>
          <article-title>A review of some fundamental concepts and problems of population
            genetics.</article-title>
          <source>Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol</source>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b010">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Lewontin</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1974</year>
          <source>The genetic basis of evolutionary change</source>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
          <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">346</size>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b011">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kimura</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1983</year>
          <source>The neutral theory of molecular evolution</source>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
          <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">367</size>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b012">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Gillespie</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1991</year>
          <source>The causes of molecular evolution</source>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
          <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">336</size>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b013">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Carlson</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Eberle</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Swanson</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Livingston</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Genomic regions exhibiting positive selection identified from dense
            genotype data.</article-title>
          <source>Genome Res</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>1553</fpage>
          <lpage>1565</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b014">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>ET</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kodama</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Baldi</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Moyzis</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Global landscape of recent inferred Darwinian selection for <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Homo
            sapiens</named-content>.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>140</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b015">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Voight</surname>
              <given-names>BF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kudaravalli</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Wen</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Pritchard</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>A map of recent positive selection in the human genome.</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Biol</source>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <elocation-id>e72.</elocation-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b016">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <collab xlink:type="simple">The International HapMap Consortium</collab>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>A haplotype map of the human genome.</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>437</volume>
          <fpage>1299</fpage>
          <lpage>1320</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b017">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Teshima</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Coop</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Przeworski</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>How reliable are empirical genomic scans for selective
            sweeps?</article-title>
          <source>Genome Res</source>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>702</fpage>
          <lpage>712</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b018">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kelley</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Madeoy</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Calhoun</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Swanson</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Akey</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Genomic signatures of positive selection in humans and the limits of
            outlier approaches.</article-title>
          <source>Genome Res</source>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>980</fpage>
          <lpage>989</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b019">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hinds</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Stuve</surname>
              <given-names>LL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nilsen</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Halperin</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Eskin</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Whole-genome patterns of common DNA variation in three human
            populations.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>1072</fpage>
          <lpage>1079</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b020">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Fay</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>CI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>Hitchhiking under positive Darwinian selection.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>155</volume>
          <fpage>1405</fpage>
          <lpage>1413</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b021">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Stephan</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Detecting a local signature of genetic hitchhiking along a recombining
            chromosome.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>160</volume>
          <fpage>765</fpage>
          <lpage>777</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b022">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Williamson</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hubisz</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Genomic scans for natural selection using ascertained SNP
            data.</article-title>
          <source>Genome Res</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>1566</fpage>
          <lpage>1575</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b023">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Benjamini</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hochberg</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1995</year>
          <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: A practical and powerful approach to
            multiple testing.</article-title>
          <source>J R Stat Soc B</source>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <fpage>289</fpage>
          <lpage>300</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b024">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Storey</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Tibshirani</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Statistical significance for genome-wide studies.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>9440</fpage>
          <lpage>9445</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b025">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Marth</surname>
              <given-names>GT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Czabarka</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Murvai</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Sherry</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>The allele frequency spectrum in genome-wide human variation data reveals
            signals of differential demographic history in three large world
            populations.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>166</volume>
          <fpage>351</fpage>
          <lpage>372</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b026">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Ehmsen</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Poon</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Davies</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>The dystrophin-associated protein complex.</article-title>
          <source>J Cell Sci</source>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>2801</fpage>
          <lpage>2803</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b027">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Malik</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Henikoff</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Conflict begets complexity: The evolution of centromeres.</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>711</fpage>
          <lpage>718</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b028">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Malik</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Bayes</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>Genetic conflicts during meiosis and the evolutionary origins of centromere
            complexity.</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Soc Trans</source>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>569</fpage>
          <lpage>573</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b029">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Pardo-Manuel de Villena</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Sapienza</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2001</year>
          <article-title>Female meiosis drives karyotypic evolution in mammals.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>159</volume>
          <fpage>1179</fpage>
          <lpage>1189</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b030">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Chevin</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hospital</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>The hitchiking effect of an autosomal meiotic drive gene.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>173</volume>
          <fpage>1829</fpage>
          <lpage>1832</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b031">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Jablonski</surname>
              <given-names>NG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Chaplin</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2000</year>
          <article-title>The evolution of human skin coloration.</article-title>
          <source>J Hum Evol</source>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>106</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b032">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Grichnik</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Burch</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Burchette</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Shea</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1998</year>
          <article-title>The SCF/KIT pathway plays a critical role in the control of normal human
            melanocyte homeostasis.</article-title>
          <source>J Invest Dermatol</source>
          <volume>111</volume>
          <fpage>233</fpage>
          <lpage>238</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b033">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Lamason</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Mohideen</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Mest</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Norton</surname>
              <given-names>HL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>SLC24A5, a putative cation exchanger, affects pigmentation in zebrafish and
            humans.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>310</volume>
          <fpage>1782</fpage>
          <lpage>1786</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b034">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Izagirre</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Garcia</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Junquera</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>de la Rua</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Alonso</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2006</year>
          <article-title>A scan for signatures of positive selection in candidate loci for skin
            pigmentation in humans.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>1697</fpage>
          <lpage>1706</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b035">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Gilad</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Bustamante</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Lancet</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Pääbo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Natural selection on the olfactory receptor gene family in humans and
            chimpanzees.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>489</fpage>
          <lpage>501</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b036">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Bajjalieh</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Peterson</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Linial</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Scheller</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1994</year>
          <article-title>Brain contains two forms of synaptic vesicle protein 2.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Nat Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <fpage>2150</fpage>
          <lpage>2154</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b037">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Howell</surname>
              <given-names>BW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hawkes</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Soriano</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1997</year>
          <article-title>Neuronal position in the developing brain is regulated by mouse
            disabled-1.</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>389</volume>
          <fpage>733</fpage>
          <lpage>737</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b038">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Amieva</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Vogelmann</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Covacci</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Tompkins</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Disruption of the epithelial apical-junctional complex by <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Helicobacter pylori</named-content>
            CagA.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>300</volume>
          <fpage>1430</fpage>
          <lpage>1434</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b039">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Stuchell</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Garrus</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Muller</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Stray</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Ghaffarian</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>The human endosomal sorting complex required for transport (ESCRT-I) and
            its role in HIV-1 budding.</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <volume>279</volume>
          <fpage>36059</fpage>
          <lpage>36071</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b040">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Cavalli-Sforza</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1973</year>
          <article-title>Analytic review: Some current problems of population
            genetics.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>82</fpage>
          <lpage>104</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b041">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Enattah</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Sahi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Savilahti</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Terwilliger</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Peltonen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Identification of a variant associated with adult-type
            hypolactasia.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>233</fpage>
          <lpage>237</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b042">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Bersaglieri</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Sabeti</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Patterson</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Vanderploeg</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Schaffner</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Genetic signatures of strong recent positive selection at the lactase
            gene.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>1111</fpage>
          <lpage>1120</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b043">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Toomajian</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Ajioka</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Jorde</surname>
              <given-names>LB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kushner</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kreitman</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>A method for detecting recent selection in the human genome from allele age
            estimates.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>165</volume>
          <fpage>287</fpage>
          <lpage>297</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b044">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Feder</surname>
              <given-names>JN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Gnirke</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Tsuchihashi</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Ruddy</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>1996</year>
          <article-title>A novel MHC class I-like gene is mutated in patients with hereditary
            haemochromatosis.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>399</fpage>
          <lpage>408</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b045">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Peck</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1994</year>
          <article-title>A ruby in the rubbish: Beneficial mutations, deleterious mutations and the
            evolution of sex.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>137</volume>
          <fpage>597</fpage>
          <lpage>606</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b046">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Osier</surname>
              <given-names>MV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Pakstis</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Soodyall</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Comas</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Goldman</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>A global perspective on genetic variation at the <italic>ADH</italic> genes
            reveals unusual patterns of linkage disequilibrium and diversity.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <fpage>84</fpage>
          <lpage>99</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b047">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Rockman</surname>
              <given-names>MV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hahn</surname>
              <given-names>MW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Soranzo</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Zimprich</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Goldstein</surname>
              <given-names>DB</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Ancient and recent positive selection transformed opioid
              <italic>cis</italic>-regulation in humans.</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Biol</source>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <elocation-id>e387.</elocation-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b048">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Rockman</surname>
              <given-names>MV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hahn</surname>
              <given-names>MW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Soranzo</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Loisel</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Goldstein</surname>
              <given-names>DB</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Positive selection on MMP3 regulation has shaped heart disease
            risk.</article-title>
          <source>Curr Biol</source>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>1531</fpage>
          <lpage>1539</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b049">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Mekel-Bobrov</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Gilbert</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Evans</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Vallender</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Ongoing adaptive evolution of <italic>ASPM,</italic> a brain size
            determinant in <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Homo
              sapiens</named-content>.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>309</volume>
          <fpage>1720</fpage>
          <lpage>1722</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b050">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Evans</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Gilbert</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Mekel-Bobrov</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Vallender</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title><italic>Microcephalin,</italic> a gene regulating brain size, continues to
            evolve adaptively in humans.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>309</volume>
          <fpage>1717</fpage>
          <lpage>1720</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b051">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>McVean</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Myers</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hunt</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Deloukas</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Bentley</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>The fine-scale structure of recombination rate variation in the human
            genome.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>304</volume>
          <fpage>581</fpage>
          <lpage>584</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b052">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Myers</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Bottolo</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Freeman</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>McVean</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Donnelly</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>A fine-scale map of recombination rates and hotspots across the human
            genome.</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>310</volume>
          <fpage>321</fpage>
          <lpage>324</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b053">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Schaffner</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Foo</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Gabriel</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Reich</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Daly</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Calibrating a coalescent simulation.</article-title>
          <source>Genome Res</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>1576</fpage>
          <lpage>1583</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b054">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kayser</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Brauer</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Stoneking</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>A genome scan to detect candidate regions influenced by local natural
            selection in human populations.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>893</fpage>
          <lpage>900</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b055">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Storz</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Payseur</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nachman</surname>
              <given-names>MW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Genome scans of DNA variability in humans reveal evidence for selective
            sweeps outside of Africa.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>1800</fpage>
          <lpage>1811</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b056">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Stajich</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hahn</surname>
              <given-names>MW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Disentangling the effects of demography and selection in human
            history.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>63</fpage>
          <lpage>73</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b057">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Tishkoff</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Genetic analysis of African populations: Human evolution and complex
            disease.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>611</fpage>
          <lpage>621</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b058">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Dodson</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Diouf</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <source>In motion: The African-American migration experience</source>
          <publisher-loc>Washington (D. C.)</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>National Geographic</publisher-name>
          <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">224</size>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b059">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Parra</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Marcini</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Akey</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Martinson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Batzer</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>1998</year>
          <article-title>Estimating African American admixture proportions by use of
            population-specific alleles.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>1839</fpage>
          <lpage>1851</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b060">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hudson</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>Generating samples under a Wright-Fisher neutral model of genetic
            variation.</article-title>
          <source>Bioinformatics</source>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>337</fpage>
          <lpage>338</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b061">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hubisz</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Bustamante</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Williamson</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2005</year>
          <article-title>Ascertainment bias in studies of human genome-wide
            polymorphism.</article-title>
          <source>Genome Res</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>1496</fpage>
          <lpage>1502</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b062">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hubisz</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>Reconstituting the frequency spectrum of ascertained single-nucleotide
            polymorphism data.</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <volume>168</volume>
          <fpage>2373</fpage>
          <lpage>2382</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b063">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kong</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Gudbjartsson</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Sainz</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Jonsdottir</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Gudjonsson</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2002</year>
          <article-title>A high-resolution recombination map of the human genome.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>241</fpage>
          <lpage>247</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b064">
        <label>64</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Collins</surname>
              <given-names>FS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Brooks</surname>
              <given-names>LD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Chakravarti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1998</year>
          <article-title>A DNA polymorphism discovery resource for research on human genetic
            variation.</article-title>
          <source>Genome Res</source>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>1229</fpage>
          <lpage>1231</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen-0030090-b065">
        <label>65</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Karolchik</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Hinrichs</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Furey</surname>
              <given-names>TS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Roskin</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Sugnet</surname>
              <given-names>CW</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <year>2004</year>
          <article-title>The UCSC Table Browser data retrieval tool.</article-title>
          <source>Nuc Acids Res</source>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
          <fpage>D493</fpage>
          <lpage>D496</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>