<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PGENETICS-D-12-02742</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Behavioral neuroscience</subject><subject>Developmental neuroscience</subject><subject>Molecular neuroscience</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>EGL-13/SoxD Specifies Distinct O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> Sensory Neuron Fates in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">A Sox Factor Specifies Gas-Sensing Neurons</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gramstrup Petersen</surname><given-names>Jakob</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rojo Romanos</surname><given-names>Teresa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Juozaityte</surname><given-names>Vaida</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Redo Riveiro</surname><given-names>Alba</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hums</surname><given-names>Ingrid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Traunmüller</surname><given-names>Lisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>Manuel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>Roger</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Biotech Research and Innovation Centre, University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Research Institute of Molecular Pathology, Vienna, Austria</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mango</surname><given-names>Susan E.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Harvard University, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">roger.pocock@bric.ku.dk</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JGP TRR VJ ARR IH LT MZ RP. Performed the experiments: JGP TRR VJ ARR IH LT MZ RP. Analyzed the data: JGP TRR VJ ARR IH LT MZ RP. Wrote the paper: RP.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e1003511</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Gramstrup Petersen et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract><sec>
<title/>
<p>Animals harbor specialized neuronal systems that are used for sensing and coordinating responses to changes in oxygen (O<sub>2</sub>) and carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>). In <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>, the O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub> sensory system comprises functionally and morphologically distinct sensory neurons that mediate rapid behavioral responses to exquisite changes in O<sub>2</sub> or CO<sub>2</sub> levels via different sensory receptors. How the diversification of the O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons is established is poorly understood. We show here that the molecular identity of both the BAG (O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing) and the URX (O<sub>2</sub>-sensing) neurons is controlled by the phylogenetically conserved SoxD transcription factor homolog EGL-13. <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant animals fail to fully express the distinct terminal gene batteries of the BAG and URX neurons and, as such, are unable to mount behavioral responses to changes in O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>. We found that the expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> is regulated in the BAG and URX neurons by two conserved transcription factors—ETS-5(Ets factor) in the BAG neurons and AHR-1(bHLH factor) in the URX neurons. In addition, we found that EGL-13 acts in partially parallel pathways with both ETS-5 and AHR-1 to direct BAG and URX neuronal fate respectively. Finally, we found that EGL-13 is sufficient to induce O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing cell fates in some cellular contexts. Thus, the same core regulatory factor, <italic>egl-13</italic>, is required and sufficient to specify the distinct fates of O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons in <italic>C. elegans</italic>. These findings extend our understanding of mechanisms of neuronal diversification and the regulation of molecular factors that may be conserved in higher organisms.</p>
</sec></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>During the development of an organism, certain neurons are programmed to perform specific tasks. For example, motor neurons coordinate locomotion and sensory neurons recognize specific environmental cues. The molecular mechanisms that generate specific neuronal classes are not fully understood. We investigated mechanisms that control the development of two distinct classes of neurons that are required for the nematode <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> to sense the respiratory gases O<sub>2</sub> or CO<sub>2</sub>. In this study, we identified and characterized a conserved transcription factor, <italic>egl-13</italic>, that is required for the development of both of these classes of neurons. <italic>egl-13</italic> is related to the SoxD family of transcription factor proteins in vertebrates. We found that <italic>egl-13</italic> controls the production of specific proteins that provide these cells with the ability to sense both O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>. Further, we found that <italic>egl-13</italic> works in conjunction with two additional factors, <italic>ahr-1</italic> and <italic>ets-5</italic>, to regulate this developmental decision. This work provides new insight into how transcriptional regulatory networks specify different but related neuronal identities and provides a platform for future studies to understand how neuronal diversity is generated.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by a grant from the Lundbeck Foundation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lundbeckfonden.dk" xlink:type="simple">www.lundbeckfonden.dk</ext-link>) (grant number R93-A8391) and by an ERC Starting Grant (281869—elegansNeurocircuits). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The capacity of the nervous system to sense and respond to fluctuations in the external and internal environment is essential for homeostasis and survival. Neuronally controlled homeostatic buffering is delivered through cellular and systemic physiological adjustments and by seeking optimal environmental conditions through behavioral strategies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Prahlad1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Bretscher1">[4]</xref>. A crucial homeostatic capacity of animals is the ability to sense and respond to changes in concentration of the respiratory gases oxygen (O<sub>2</sub>) and carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Semenza1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Sharabi1">[6]</xref>. O<sub>2</sub> is essential for the generation of energy in the form of adenosine triphosphate (ATP); however, O<sub>2</sub> also exerts toxicity through the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Prahlad1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Bretscher1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Kaelin1">[7]</xref>. CO<sub>2</sub> is a by-product of oxidative metabolism and prolonged exposure leads to acidosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Semenza1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Sharabi1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Guais1">[8]</xref>. CO<sub>2</sub> is also an environmental cue used in host- and mate- finding and can initiate both aversive or attractive behaviors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Suh1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Hallem1">[11]</xref>. The evolution of mechanisms required to sense and respond to O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> is therefore paramount for survival.</p>
<p>In <italic>Drosophila</italic>, specific sensory systems respond to external O<sub>2</sub> levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Prahlad1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Kaelin1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Wingrove1">[12]</xref>. In addition, <italic>Drosophila</italic> uses specialized olfactory and gustatory neurons to detect CO<sub>2</sub> changes via specialized chemosensory receptors called Gr21a/Gr63a <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Suh1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Jones1">[13]</xref>. In humans, O<sub>2</sub>, CO<sub>2</sub> and pH levels are monitored by specific regions of the brainstem and by specialized neurosecretory glomus cells of the carotid body <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-LpezBarneo1">[14]</xref>, whereas in non-human mammals CO<sub>2</sub> is also sensed by specific olfactory neurons that target the necklace glomeruli in the olfactory bulb via the guanylyl cyclase GC-D <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Hu1">[15]</xref>. It is poorly understood how the specification of such specialized sensory neurons is regulated. However, recent work in <italic>Drosophila</italic> has shown that epigenetic mechanisms play an important role <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Sim1">[16]</xref>.</p>
<p>Respiratory gas sensing is a crucial modality for <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> whose natural environment, such as rotting fruit and compost, can have wide ranges of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Sylvia1">[17]</xref>. Previous work has shown that in the laboratory, worms have a behavioral preference for 5%–10% O<sub>2</sub> and are exquisitely sensitive to minor changes in O<sub>2</sub> concentration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Gray1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Cheung1">[19]</xref>. In addition, worms mount avoidance responses to CO<sub>2</sub> levels above 0.5% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Bretscher1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Hallem1">[11]</xref>. Of the 302 neurons in the C. <italic>elegans</italic> nervous system, at least six neurons are specifically dedicated to the detection and response to changes in O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> levels. These include the BAGL/R, URXL/R, AQR and PQR neurons. The BAG neurons are the primary CO<sub>2</sub> sensors and they also respond to decrease in O<sub>2</sub> concentration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Hallem1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Zimmer1">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Bretscher2">[22]</xref>. The URX, AQR and PQR neurons are specialized for responding to increasing O<sub>2</sub> concentrations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Zimmer1">[20]</xref>. In <italic>C. elegans</italic>, members of the guanylyl cyclase family of proteins are crucial factors required for O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> sensing. Pioneering work revealed that the soluble guanylyl cyclases (sGCs) GCY-35 and GCY-36 mediate high O<sub>2</sub> avoidance behavior via the URX, AQR and PQR neurons and that GCY-35 directly binds to molecular O<sub>2</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Gray1">[18]</xref>. In contrast, the sGCs, GCY-31 and GCY-33 function in the BAG neurons to sense decreases in O<sub>2</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Zimmer1">[20]</xref>. Recent work found that the membrane-bound receptor-type guanylyl cyclase GCY-9 acts specifically in the BAG neurons to mediate CO<sub>2</sub> avoidance behavior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Hallem2">[21]</xref>. Other molecules such as the Phe-Met-Arg-Phe-NH<sub>2</sub> (FMRF-amide)-related peptides (FLP-8, FLP-13, FLP-17 and FLP-19) are expressed in either a subset or all of the O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons; however their precise molecular functions in O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> sensing are not known <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Ortiz1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Kim1">[24]</xref>.</p>
<p>Neuronal specialization within the O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing system in <italic>C. elegans</italic> is an excellent model to study the control of neuron diversity. The O<sub>2</sub>-sensing (URX, AQR and PQR) and O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing (BAG) neurons have overlapping and non-overlapping patterns of guanylyl cyclase and neuropeptide expression, which are reflected in their related, albeit distinct functionalities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Zimmer1">[20]</xref>. At present, it is unclear how the expression of these molecules is restricted to certain parts of the O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing nervous system, and how such restrictions coordinate neuronal fate and function.</p>
<p>Here, we have identified the Sox transcription factor EGL-13 as an important regulator of the O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron cell fate decision. EGL-13 is required for the expression of distinct proteins required for sensing both O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> and as such, <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant animals are unable to mount behavioral responses to changes in O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>. We found that the expression of EGL-13 is controlled by ETS-5 in the BAG neurons and by AHR-1 in the URX neurons, and acts in partially parallel pathways with these factors to drive neuronal fate. Finally, we found that EGL-13 is sufficient to drive O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing cell fates in certain cellular contexts. Therefore, EGL-13 is a core regulatory factor that is both required and sufficient to drive O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron specification in <italic>C. elegans</italic>. As EGL-13 is a member of the SoxD family of transcription factors, we anticipate that the regulatory relationships described here will provide a paradigm for the control of neuronal fate specification by Sox proteins in other cellular contexts.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results/Discussion</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>The SoxD transcription factor <italic>egl-13</italic> specifies distinct O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons</title>
<p>In order to identify molecules and pathways important for O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron specification, we have taken a forward genetics approach in <italic>C. elegans</italic>. We isolated four independent allelic mutations (<italic>rp14</italic>, <italic>rp22</italic>, <italic>rp23</italic> and <italic>rp26</italic>) that affect the expression of terminal differentiation markers in the O<sub>2</sub> and/or CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s006">Table S1</xref>) Mutant hermaphrodites of each of these alleles are severely egg-laying defective (Egl) and form a bag-of-worms where embryos hatch inside the mother (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s001">Figure S1</xref>). We investigated their vulval phenotype and found that the anchor cell fails to fuse with the uterine seam cell, causing a blockage of the uterus and the resultant Egl phenotype (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s001">Figure S1</xref>). This anchor cell fusion defect is reminiscent of that observed in <italic>egl-13(ku194</italic>) mutant animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-HannaRose1">[25]</xref> which we found to also exhibit defects in O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> reporter expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s001">Figure S1</xref>). Subsequent Sanger sequencing of <italic>rp14</italic>, <italic>rp22</italic>, <italic>rp23</italic> and <italic>rp26</italic> revealed genetic lesions in the <italic>egl-13</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). <italic>egl-13</italic> encodes the <italic>C. elegans</italic> ortholog of the HMG-domain-containing SoxD family of transcription factors that has no previously reported role in the worm nervous system.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003511-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title><italic>egl-13</italic> is required for O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron specification.</title>
<p>(A) Molecular identity of mutant alleles obtained from the forward genetic screens. <italic>egl-13</italic> alleles first described in this article are shown in black (<italic>rp14</italic>, <italic>22</italic>, <italic>23</italic>, and <italic>26</italic>) and the previously described <italic>ku194</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-HannaRose1">[25]</xref> is shown in red. The nature of the molecular lesions is as follows: <italic>rp14</italic> is a splice acceptor mutation between exons 8 and 9, causing a premature termination codon within the HMG domain. <italic>rp22</italic> is an out-of-frame 317 bp deletion between exons 6 and 7 that leads to a predicted premature STOP codon in the EGL-13 protein that lacks the HMG domain. The <italic>rp23</italic> allele is a promoter deletion, removing 1128 bp between −1700 and −572 upstream of the ATG codon. <italic>rp26</italic> is a G-to-A transition that converts a highly conserved glycine to a glutamic acid in the HMG domain. The isolated <italic>egl-13</italic> mutants are therefore predicted to either abrogate DNA binding (<italic>rp14</italic>, <italic>rp22</italic> and <italic>rp26</italic>) or reduce/eliminate expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> transcript (<italic>rp23</italic>). (B) Schematic of the O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing system. Anterior to the left. (C) Fluorescence reporter expression of the O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron terminal gene batteries in wild-type (left) and <italic>egl-13(ku194</italic>) mutant (right) at the young adult stage. Quantification of data and information on reporter strains is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s006">Table S1</xref>. Neuron positions are marked with dashed circles: BAG(red), URX(blue), AQR(yellow) and PQR(green). Fluorescent cells not marked with circles are non-O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons in the respective strains and their expression is unaffected by loss of <italic>egl-13</italic>. Scale bar, 20 µm. Anterior to the left.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Loss of <italic>egl-13</italic> affects terminal fate of O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons</title>
<p>The BAG, URX, AQR and PQR neurons in <italic>C. elegans</italic> are required for sensing and responding to fluctuations of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> levels in the environment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Hallem1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Gray1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Cheung1">[19]</xref>. Distinct batteries of genes are expressed in these neurons that are predicted to provide the optimal functionality required for O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> sensing, however the role of only a subset of these genes has been analyzed in detail <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Zimmer1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Hallem2">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Brandt1">[26]</xref>. We used fluorescent reporter constructs to monitor expression of these gene batteries to understand how <italic>egl-13</italic> controls O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron cell fate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g001">Figure 1</xref>). We analyzed the expression of guanylyl cyclases (<italic>gcy-9</italic>, <italic>gcy-31</italic>, <italic>gcy-33</italic>, <italic>gcy-35</italic> and <italic>gcy-36</italic>) and Phe-Met-Arg-Phe-NH<sub>2</sub> (FMRF-amide)-related peptides (<italic>flp-8</italic>, <italic>flp-13</italic>, <italic>flp-17</italic> and <italic>flp-19</italic>) that are all terminal differentiation genes expressed in all or a subset of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Gray1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Cheung1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Hallem2">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Kim1">[24]</xref>. We crossed these reporter transgenes into <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant animals (<italic>ku194</italic> allele) and found that none of the reporters were properly expressed in <italic>egl-13</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s006">Table S1</xref>). We also found similar effects in the four <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant alleles we isolated (<italic>rp14</italic>, <italic>rp22</italic>, <italic>rp23</italic> and <italic>rp26</italic>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s001">Figure S1C</xref>). We noticed that some of the reporters were exquisitely sensitive to <italic>egl-13</italic> loss whereas others exhibited partially penetrant defects (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s006">Table S1</xref>). This suggests that the expression of some terminal differentiation factors are under the collaborative control of additional factors that are able to compensate for the loss of <italic>egl-13</italic>.</p>
<p>The BAG and URX neurons are derived from the AB lineage and are posterior sisters of other neurons that have distinct fates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Sulston1">[27]</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s002">Figure S2</xref>). We therefore asked whether <italic>egl-13</italic> is also required for the specification of the sister cells of BAG or URX. We crossed <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant animals into fluorescent reporter strains for the SMDV, <italic>zfIs2 (lgc-55::mCherry)</italic> and CEPD, <italic>vtIs1</italic> (<italic>dat-1::gfp</italic>), sister cells for BAG and URX neurons respectively. We found that the expression of these reporters were unaffected by loss of <italic>egl-13</italic> suggesting a specific role for <italic>egl-13</italic> in the posterior branch of these lineages (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s006">Table S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s002">Figure S2</xref>). Taken together, we conclude that <italic>egl-13</italic> controls the expression of the distinct O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron terminal gene batteries that distinguish them from lineage-related neurons.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title><italic>egl-13</italic> acts cell-autonomously in O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons</title>
<p>To monitor <italic>egl-13</italic> expression, we generated two promoter-driven fluorescent reporters (<italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup>::mCherry</italic> and <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup>::gfp</italic>) that contain 3.5 kb of <italic>egl-13</italic> upstream sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g002">Figure 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s003">Figure S3</xref>). Expression is first detected in 4 neuronal cells at around 350 min post-fertilization, which is the time at which the BAG and URX neurons are born (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s003">Figure S3</xref>). Expression is restricted to these 4 neurons during embryogenesis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s003">Figure S3</xref>). At the first larval stage, <italic>egl-13</italic> expression is observed in the BAG and URX neurons plus occasionally in a small number of unidentified cells in the head and tail (including the AQR and PQR neurons) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s003">Figure S3</xref>). Later during larval development, <italic>egl-13</italic> expression is observed in body wall muscle and vulval cells (data not shown). Neuronal expression is restricted to the O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons in the adult (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Using the 3.5 kb <italic>egl-13</italic> promoter (<italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup></italic>) we transgenically expressed <italic>egl-13<sup>isoformA</sup></italic>cDNA in <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant animals and were able to rescue both the defect in O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate marker expression and the Egl phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g002">Figure 2B–2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s004">Figure S4</xref> and data not shown). To confirm that <italic>egl-13</italic> acts cell autonomously to control O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate, we used neuron-specific promoters to drive <italic>egl-13<sup>isoformA</sup></italic>cDNA expression in the BAG or URX neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g002">Figure 2D</xref>). We found that indeed neuron-specific expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> rescued the O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate defect of <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g002">Figure 2D</xref>). Therefore, we conclude that <italic>egl-13</italic> acts autonomously in the BAG and URX neurons to direct their fate.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003511-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title><italic>egl-13</italic> functions cell autonomously to drive O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron cell fate.</title>
<p>(A) Dorsal view of a young adult hermaphrodite expressing an <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup>::mCherry</italic> transcriptional reporter transgene (top panels), a <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic> translational reporter marking BAGL/R, URXL/R, AQR and PQR (center panels) and a merge of the two pictures showing co-localization in the O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons (bottom panels). Left hand panels show the head region and right hand panels the tail region. We also observed expression of <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup>::mCherry</italic> in muscle and vulval cells (not shown). A: anterior, L: left. The scale bar in lower panel is 20 µm. The <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup>::mCherry</italic> transgene is <italic>rpEx272</italic> and the <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::GCY-33::gfp</italic> transgene is <italic>rpIs7</italic>. (B) Fluorescence micrographs of <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic> expression in a wild-type animal (top panels), an <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant animal (center panels) and an <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant animal rescued by transgenic expression of <italic>egl-13<sup>isoformA</sup>cDNA</italic> driven by the endogenous 3.5 kb <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup></italic> (bottom panels). Left hand panels show the head region and right hand panels the tail region. (C) Transgenic expression of <italic>egl-13<sup>isoformA</sup>cDNA</italic> under the control of <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup></italic> rescues <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant neuronal phenotypes, in the <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic> strain. n = 52–55. ***P&lt;0.001. Lines 1–3 = independent transgenic rescue lines. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">materials and methods</xref> for neuronal scoring criteria used. (D) Transgenic expression of <italic>egl-13<sup>isoformA</sup>cDNA</italic> under the control of the <italic>gcy-33<sup>1kb</sup></italic> (BAG-specific) or <italic>unc-86<sup>(700bp)</sup></italic> (URX-specific) promoters rescues <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant neuronal phenotypes in the <italic>flp-19<sup>prom</sup>::gfp</italic> (BAG) and <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic> (URX) strains. n = 39–55. ***P&lt;0.001. Lines 1–2 = independent transgenic rescue lines. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">materials and methods</xref> for neuronal scoring criteria used. (E) Transgenic expression of <italic>sox-2</italic> cDNA under the control of <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup></italic> is unable to rescue <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant neuronal phenotypes, in the <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic> strain. n = 56–60. (n.s.) indicates no significant difference from non transgenic <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant animals. Lines 1–2 = independent transgenic rescue lines. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">materials and methods</xref> for neuronal scoring criteria used.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The <italic>egl-13</italic> gene has 4 predicted isoforms, all of which contain the same HMG DNA/protein binding domain, however they each have varying lengths of amino terminal tail. Such tails in SoxD proteins can cooperate with other factors to control gene expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Lefebvre1">[28]</xref>. We therefore tested whether the long N-terminal region of EGL-13<sup>isoformA</sup> is required for its rescuing ability. We used <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup></italic> to drive EGL-13<sup>isoformD</sup> (lacking 157 amino acids of the N-terminal tail of isoformA) in <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> animals and found that it fully rescued the defect in O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate marker expression and the Egl phenotype (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s004">Figure S4</xref> and data not shown). Thus, the EGL-13 N-terminal region is not required for its roles in vulval cell nor O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron specification. We next asked whether SoxD proteins play specific roles in these decisions by attempting to rescue the <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant defects with the SoxB family member, <italic>sox-2</italic>. We expressed <italic>sox-2</italic> cDNA under the control of <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup></italic> in <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant animals. We found that <italic>sox-2</italic> is unable to rescue O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate marker expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g002">Figure 2E</xref>). These data indicate that the SoxD HMG domain plays a specific role in the specification of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title><italic>egl-13</italic> is required and sufficient to induce O<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate</title>
<p>We have shown that <italic>egl-13</italic> is expressed throughout the life of the worm in the O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons; and is required to induce terminal differentiation features. To ask whether <italic>egl-13</italic> is required continuously to maintain the expression of the terminal gene battery of these neurons, we sought to postdevelopmentally remove <italic>egl-13</italic> gene activity. <italic>egl-13</italic> gene activity could not be removed by RNA-mediated interference in an RNAi sensitized background (data not shown) and there are no temperature-sensitive alleles of <italic>egl-13</italic> available. Instead, we generated animals that lack endogenous EGL-13 protein but express heat-shock inducible <italic>egl-13</italic> cDNA from an extrachromosomal array under the control of the <italic>hsp-16.2</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g003">Figure 3</xref>). We focused our analysis on the URX neurons and found that the loss of <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic> reporter expression in <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> worms could be rescued through heat-shock induction of <italic>egl-13</italic> during mid-larval stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). This indicates that O<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons generated during embryogenesis persist in an <italic>egl-13</italic>-responsive state. These neurons are, therefore, not converted into another fate when <italic>egl-13</italic> is lost; however, they do not acquire the terminal O<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron differentiation program. When <italic>egl-13</italic> activity was supplied transiently, through removal of heat-shock stimulus, we observed a gradual loss of reporter expression during adulthood in the URX neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Therefore, <italic>egl-13</italic> gene activity is continuously required to maintain URX cell fate. To ask whether misexpression of <italic>egl-13</italic> in other neurons is sufficient to induce O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> terminal fate we expressed <italic>egl-13</italic> under the control of an early neuronal promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). We found that <italic>egl-13</italic> is indeed sufficient to induce expression of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> terminal fate markers in some cellular contexts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). This suggests that <italic>egl-13</italic> is not only required but also sufficient to induce O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate in specific contexts, which is similar to previous studies of terminal selector genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Satterlee1">[29]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Tursun1">[31]</xref>. The restricted induction we observed may be dependent on the embryonic time-point of induction or the expression of other unknown co-factors that are required for induction of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003511-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title><italic>egl-13</italic> is required and sufficient to induce O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate.</title>
<p>(A) <italic>egl-13</italic> is required to maintain O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate. Induction of <italic>egl-13</italic> expression via transient heat-shock at the L2/3 stage restores <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic> expression in the URX neurons of <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant animals. A schematic describing the heat-shock protocol is shown at the top left. The number of positive neurons was assessed one day after heat-shock (L2/3+1 day). No increase in the number of positive neurons was observed in <italic>egl-13(ku194); gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic>; Ex<italic>[hsp-16.2::egl-13]</italic> animals in the absence of heat shock. A significant decrease in the number of positive neurons was observed in <italic>egl-13(ku194); gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic>; Ex<italic>[hsp-16.2::egl-13]</italic> animals 3 days after heat shock with growth at 15°C (L4+3 days) when compared to one day after heat shock (L4+1 day). Quantification of the number of <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic> positive neurons is shown at the indicated time points. Error bars represent the standard error of the mean (SEM). Statistical model applied is a one-way ANOVA with Newman-Keuls multiple comparison test **P&lt;0.05, ***P&lt;0.005. Representative fluorescent micrographs on the right indicate the continual requirement for <italic>egl-13</italic> to maintain O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate. Neuron positions are marked with dashed circles: BAG(red), URX(blue). Two different extrachromosomal lines were analyzed for this experiment and showed similar effects (only one is shown). 53–113 animals were used per time point per genotype. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">materials and methods</xref> section for heat shock protocol and for neuronal scoring criteria used. Scale bar, 20 µm. Anterior to the left. (B) <italic>egl-13</italic> is sufficient to induce O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing cell fate markers. An <italic>unc-86</italic> promoter was used to drive broad neuronal expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> cDNA in a wild-type background. Graph indicates the percentage of animals that exhibit ectopic expression O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing cell fate marker (+ array = transgenic animals expressing <italic>unc-86<sup>prom</sup>::egl-13cDNA</italic> array; − array = transgenic siblings not expressing the array). Representative fluorescent micrographs of ectopic expression of three O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing cell fate markers: <italic>flp-8<sup>prom</sup>::gfp</italic>, <italic>flp-19<sup>prom</sup>::gfp</italic> and <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic>. Neuron positions are marked with dashed circles: BAG(red), URX(blue) and ectopic expression of each reporter is marked with arrowheads. Scale bar, 20 µm. Anterior to the left.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e">
<title><italic>egl-13</italic> mutants are defective in O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> sensing</title>
<p>The crucial role for <italic>egl-13</italic> in O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate determination suggested that <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant animals would be defective in O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> sensing. We applied three behavioral paradigms that have been previously reported to be specific to either one of these neuron classes: BAG neurons modulate the animals' locomotion speed in response to an oxygen downshift from 21% O<sub>2</sub> towards 10% O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g004">Figure 4A, 4E</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Zimmer1">[20]</xref>. In addition, BAG neurons detect increases in CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations, which trigger reorientation movements (omega turns) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g004">Figure 4G</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Hallem1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Hallem2">[21]</xref>. URX neurons modulate the animals' locomotion speed in response to O<sub>2</sub> upshifts towards 21% O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g004">Figure 4A, 4F</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Zimmer1">[20]</xref>. We applied these behavioral assays to test how BAG and URX neurons are functionally affected in <italic>egl-13</italic> mutants. We tracked animals in a chamber without food, in an air-flow that switched between 21% O<sub>2</sub> and 10% O<sub>2</sub>, or between 0% CO<sub>2</sub> and 1% CO<sub>2</sub>. In contrast to wild-type animals, <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant animals do not slow their locomotion in response to O<sub>2</sub> upshift or downshift (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g004">Figure 4A, 4C, 4E, 4F</xref>). We found that <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutants are also defective in CO<sub>2</sub> sensing since they fail to slow or perform omega turns in response to CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g004">Figure 4G</xref>). O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> behavioral defects of <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutants are fully rescued when <italic>egl-13</italic> cDNA is resupplied under the control of <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g004">Figure 4D–4G</xref>). These data confirm that <italic>egl-13</italic> is crucial for the specification and function of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing system in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003511-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title><italic>egl-13</italic> is essential for locomotion responses to O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> concentration shifts.</title>
<p>(A-D) Locomotion speed of <italic>C. elegans</italic> during O<sub>2</sub> concentration shifts. Traces show average forward speed and dark shading indicates standard error of the mean (SEM). O<sub>2</sub> concentrations were switched between 21% and 10%. Shading represents intervals at 21%. (A) Wild-type animals. (B) <italic>egl-13(rp23)</italic> mutants. (C) <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutants. (D) Rescue of <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant phenotype by transgenic expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> cDNA under control of its own promoter. Transgene <italic>rpEx401</italic>. Note the respective reduction of speed levels in N2 after up- and downshift, which are abolished in <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> and restored in the transgenic line. <italic>egl-13(rp23)</italic> animals are affected mostly in their response to O<sub>2</sub> upshift. (E, F) Quantification of data in A–D. Average speed changes in percent from basal speed to O<sub>2</sub> downshift (E) and upshift (F) of animals with indicated genotypes. Transgenic rescue lines are significantly different from <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant animals. (G) Average changes in omega turn frequency of animals with indicated genotypes, in response to 1% CO<sub>2</sub>. The defect in omega turn responses seen in <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> animals is restored in the transgenic lines (<italic>rpEx399</italic> and <italic>rpEx401</italic>). <italic>egl-13(rp23)</italic> animals only exhibit a partial defect. Error bars = SEM. Symbols indicate all significant differences one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni's Multiple Comparison Test (*/◊ p = 0.01–0.05, **/◊◊ p = 0.001–0.01, ***/◊◊◊ p&lt;0.001). Asterisks indicate significant difference compared to wild-type, while diamonds indicate significant difference compared to <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutants. Data were calculated from n = 3 independent experiments for each mutant and transgenic rescue strain, and n = 6 independent experiments for wild-type. Each individual experiment was performed on 60–70 animals.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>The <italic>egl-13</italic> promoter contains neuron-specific regulatory modules</title>
<p>One of the <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant alleles retrieved from our screen was a promoter deletion mutant (<italic>rp23</italic>). The <italic>rp23</italic> deletion removes 1128 bp of <italic>egl-13</italic> promoter from −1700 to −572 upstream of the translational start site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g001">Figure 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). Intriguingly, the <italic>rp23</italic> mutation affects terminal marker expression in the URX but not BAG sensory neurons and is mostly defective in URX and less affected in BAG regulated behaviors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g004">Figure 4B, 4E–4G</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s004">Figure S4C</xref>; and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s006">Table S1</xref>). This suggests that the <italic>rp23</italic> promoter deletion removes element(s) required to drive <italic>egl-13</italic> in the URX neurons while leaving the BAG-specific element(s) intact. To identify which upstream factors drive expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> in the molecularly and functionally distinct BAG and URX neurons we performed promoter deletion analysis, using the 3.5 kb upstream element (<italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup></italic>) as a template. We generated transgenic worms expressing truncated versions of <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup></italic> driving <italic>mCherry</italic> or <italic>gfp</italic> protein and focused our expression analysis on BAG and URX regulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). A 900 bp fragment (<italic>egl-13<sup>prom3</sup></italic>), which includes 360 bp corresponding to the 3′ end of the <italic>rp23</italic> deletion, drove expression in BAG and URX. However, a 691 bp fragment (<italic>egl-13<sup>prom4</sup></italic>), which lacks the missing region in the <italic>rp23</italic> deletion, only drove expression in the BAG neurons. Therefore, an important element required for <italic>egl-13</italic> expression specifically in the URX neurons lies within the 200 bp region included in <italic>egl-13<sup>prom3</sup></italic>. Bioinformatic analysis of this region revealed that there are two conserved motifs that are potential binding sites for EGL-13/SOX5 itself and AHR-1, an aryl hydrocarbon receptor bHLH protein. Interestingly, <italic>ahr-1</italic> was previously shown to be required for the expression of some URX terminal fate markers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Qin1">[32]</xref>. Site-directed mutagenesis of the predicted AHR-1 binding site significantly reduced <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup>::mCherry</italic> expression and a subsequent mutation in the putative EGL-13 binding site further reduced expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). This suggests that both AHR-1 and EGL-13 regulate egl-13 expression. To test this, we crossed <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup>mCherry/gfp</italic>-expressing animals into <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> and <italic>ahr-1(ia3)</italic> mutants and found that URX expression was reduced in both cases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). Therefore, AHR-1 and EGL-13 both contribute to the control of <italic>egl-13</italic> expression in the URX neurons.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003511-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Independent regulatory modules drive <italic>egl-13</italic> expression in O<sub>2</sub> versus O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons.</title>
<p>(A) <italic>egl-13</italic> promoter analysis. Schematic representation of the <italic>egl-13</italic> locus with its 3.5 kb upstream region. The ATG codon is marked with an arrow and the exons are represented as black blocks. The upstream region deleted in the <italic>rp23</italic> allele is indicated with a blue horizontal line and a grey dashed vertical line. Below is a representation of cloned and injected constructs, and their expression pattern in the URX and BAG neurons. Black lines denote the promoter fragment placed in front of mCherry fluorescent protein (red boxes). Orange, blue and green crosses represent mutated Sox5, AHR-1 and ETS binding sites respectively. “+” indicates consistent reporter expression in at least 50% of animals in all lines. “+/−” indicates less than 50% of animals expressing the reporter in all lines. “−” indicates loss of expression. Three independent transgenic lines were analyzed for each promoter as indicated. (B) Expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ets-5</italic> reporter transgenes in the BAG neurons in the reciprocal mutant backgrounds (left). <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> and <italic>ets-5(tm1734)</italic> alleles were used. Expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ahr-1</italic> reporter transgenes in the URX neurons in the reciprocal mutant backgrounds (right). <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> and <italic>ahr-1(ia3)</italic> alleles were used. n&gt;50 per strain. Error bars represent the standard error of the mean (SEM) **P&lt;0.05, ***P&lt;0.005. (n.s.) indicates no significant difference from wild-type. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">materials and methods</xref> for neuronal scoring criteria used. (C) In the BAG neurons (left), the ETS transcription factor, ETS-5 regulates the expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> in the BAG neurons via conserved ETS binding sites located in the <italic>egl-13</italic> promoter. In addition, <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ets-5</italic> autoregulate in the BAG neurons to generate BAG fate. In the URX neurons (right), <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ahr-1</italic> autoregulate, in addition to regulating the expression of each other. Other unknown factors act in parallel to and in combination with these factors to drive BAG and URX neuronal fate.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>To identify the regulatory module(s) that control <italic>egl-13</italic> expression in the BAG neurons, we continued to dissect the <italic>egl-13</italic> promoter. We identified a 432 bp region (<italic>egl-13<sup>prom5.1</sup></italic>), immediately upstream of the ATG codon, which is sufficient to drive expression in the BAG neurons. Intriguingly, we found two conserved ETS-5/Pet1 binding sites in this region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Previous work identified ETS-5 as a crucial factor required for the specification of the BAG neurons, suggesting that ETS-5 may regulate <italic>egl-13</italic> expression in these neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Brandt1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Guillermin1">[33]</xref>. We used site-directed mutagenesis to eliminate the ETS-5/Pet1 binding sites individually and in combination, and found that when both ETS-5/Pet1 binding sites are mutated the expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> is abrogated in the BAG neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). This suggests that ETS-5 directly regulates the expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> in the BAG neurons via conserved binding sites. We crossed the <italic>ets-5(tm1734)</italic> mutant into the <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup>::mCherry</italic> strain and indeed found that BAG expression was affected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). In addition, we found that <italic>egl-13</italic> can regulate its own expression in the BAG neurons independently of <italic>ets-5</italic> via an, as yet, unidentified mechanism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5B</xref>).</p>
<p>Taken together, these data indicate that control of <italic>egl-13</italic> expression is coordinated by two independent regulatory mechanisms. In the O<sub>2</sub>-sensing URX neurons, <italic>egl-13</italic> expression is predominantly regulated by AHR-1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). In contrast, an independent promoter module controlled by ETS-5 regulates <italic>egl-13</italic> expression in the O<sub>2</sub>/CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing BAG neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). In addition, <italic>egl-13</italic> is able to autoregulate in both the URX and BAG neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5C</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2g">
<title><italic>egl-13</italic> acts in partially parallel pathways with <italic>ets-5</italic> and <italic>ahr-1</italic></title>
<p>Previous work has identified <italic>ets-5</italic> and <italic>ahr-1</italic> as regulators of BAG and URX specification respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Brandt1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Qin1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Guillermin1">[33]</xref> and we have shown that these factors are predominantly required to drive <italic>egl-13</italic> expression in these cells. To understand how these factors function together to coordinate BAG and URX specification, we analyzed the expression of terminal fate markers in single and double mutant combinations, where appropriate. We analyzed three URX markers (<italic>flp-8::gfp</italic>, <italic>flp-19::gfp</italic> and <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic>) and six BAG markers (<italic>flp-13::gfp</italic>, <italic>flp-17::gfp</italic>, <italic>flp-19::gfp</italic>, <italic>gcy-9::gfp</italic>, <italic>gcy-31::gfp</italic> and <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic>) and compared the effect of the individual loss of <italic>egl-13</italic>, <italic>ets-5</italic> and <italic>ahr-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s005">Figure S5</xref>).</p>
<p>The first observation from this analysis was that the expression of a subset of terminal differentiation markers is completely dependent on <italic>egl-13</italic> and one of the other factors acting in a linear pathway. For example, we find that BAG expression of <italic>flp-13::gfp</italic> and <italic>flp-19::gfp</italic> is almost 100% affected in both the <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ets-5</italic> single mutants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s005">Figure S5</xref>). This suggests that for these markers <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ets-5</italic> act in the same pathway to drive marker expression. In contrast, expression of <italic>gcy-9::mCherry</italic> is completely dependent on <italic>ets-5</italic> with <italic>egl-13</italic> playing a minor role in its regulation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s005">Figure S5</xref>). At the other end of the spectrum, <italic>ets-5</italic> and <italic>egl-13</italic> are minimally required to drive <italic>gcy-31::mCherry</italic> expression in the BAG neurons suggesting other factor(s) control the expression of this terminal fate marker (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s005">Figure S5</xref>). Taken together, these data indicate that <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ets-5</italic> act in partially parallel pathways to drive BAG cell fate and that other unknown factors possibly act in a combinatorial manner to drive specific aspects of BAG fate.</p>
<p>We also observed differential effects of <italic>egl-13</italic> loss with URX terminal fate markers. Expression of the <italic>flp-8::gfp</italic> reporter is partially affected by single loss of <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ahr-1</italic>, whereas loss of both genes totally abrogates expression, suggesting that <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ahr-1</italic> act in parallel pathways to regulate <italic>flp-8::gfp</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s005">Figure S5</xref>). However, in the case of <italic>flp-19::gfp</italic>, loss of <italic>egl-13</italic> causes complete loss of expression and <italic>ahr-1</italic> plays a minor role in its regulation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s005">Figure S5</xref>).</p>
<p>To further investigate the regulatory relationship between <italic>egl-13</italic>, <italic>ets-5</italic> and <italic>ahr-1</italic> we analyzed how they affect the expression of each other. We have already shown that <italic>ets-5</italic> positively regulates the expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> in the BAG neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). In a reciprocal experiment, we found that <italic>ets-5::gfp</italic> expression is unaffected in <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). These data and other work <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Brandt1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Guillermin1">[33]</xref> suggest that <italic>ets-5</italic> acts upstream and in parallel to <italic>egl-13</italic> to direct BAG cell fate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). In addition, we found that <italic>egl-13</italic> is able to regulate its own expression in the BAG neurons, in parallel to <italic>ets-5</italic>; however, the mechanistic basis of this regulation is unclear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). In the URX neurons, we found that <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ahr-1</italic> regulate the expression of each other in addition to having autoregulatory capabilities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5B,C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s005">Figure S5</xref>).</p>
<p>Our studies have elucidated a novel function for <italic>egl-13</italic>, the SoxD homolog, in the specification of distinct classes of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> sensory neurons in <italic>C. elegans</italic>. We show that <italic>egl-13</italic> is expressed in the O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons and acts cell-autonomously to regulate their distinct cell fates. We further show that <italic>egl-13</italic> is continuously expressed in the O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing system to maintain the expression of terminal features of these neurons. In certain cellular contexts, <italic>egl-13</italic> is also sufficient to induce O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron cell fate. We found that the regulatory inputs controlling the expression of <italic>egl-13</italic> in the O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing system are mechanistically distinct. Independent regulatory modules control <italic>egl-13</italic> expression in the BAG neurons (CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> downshift sensors) versus the URX neurons (O<sub>2</sub> upshift sensors). Interestingly, we found that <italic>egl-13</italic> expression in the BAG neurons is controlled by the ETS-5 transcription factor via conserved ETS binding sites. In contrast, in the URX neurons, <italic>egl-</italic>13 expression is controlled by the bHLH transcription factor AHR-1 via a conserved AHR1 binding site.</p>
<p>The influence EGL-13 exerts on the expression of the terminal gene batteries of the distinct O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neurons is diverse. Particular factors are exquisitely sensitive to loss of <italic>egl-13</italic>, whereas others are only partially affected. These findings suggest that alternative unknown modes of regulation are in place to ensure that particular molecules are faithfully expressed in the O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> sensory neurons, which work in conjunction with and/or in parallel to <italic>egl-13</italic>.</p>
<p>Sox transcription factors have diverse functions during development and play crucial roles in regulating neuronal fate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Azim1">[34]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Pevny1">[37]</xref>. In addition, Sox proteins act at different levels to preselect neuronal genes in embryonic stem cells and to direct the activation of these genes in neuronal precursors and fully differentiated neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Bergsland1">[38]</xref>. Here we describe a novel role for EGL-13, the SoxD transcription factor in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, in driving the specification of different but related sensory neuron identities. Closely related orthologs of EGL-13 are found in vertebrates, some of which are expressed in sensory neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Morales1">[39]</xref>, therefore; SoxD proteins may have a previously unrecognized conserved function in the specification of gas-sensing neurons in higher organisms.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Strains used in this study</title>
<p>Strains were grown using standard growth conditions on NGM agar at 20°C on <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> OP50 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Guais1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Brenner1">[40]</xref>. Transgenic animals were created according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Mello1">[41]</xref>. Strain information is detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s007">Table S2</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Forward genetic screening approaches</title>
<p>In all screens, animals were mutagenized with EMS (ethyl methanesulfonate) according to standard protocols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Flibotte1">[42]</xref>. Worms were incubated at 25°C at all times. In the manual screens, 5 parental (P0) mutagenized animals were placed in each of 10 founder plates. Three days later, 400 F1 progeny of the mutagenized P0 animals were singled. Their ensuing F2 progeny were screened under a fluorescence stereomicroscope.</p>
<p>In the automated worm sorter screen, around 100,000 synchronized larval stage L4 animals were mutagenized with EMS, the following day the P0 young adult animals were bleached and their F1 progeny synchronized at larval stage L1 by starvation (approximately 1,000,000 animals). F1 animals were grown to the young adult stage, bleached and their F2 progeny synchronized at larval stage L1 by starvation (approximately 10,000,000 animals). The F2 progeny were grown until larval stage L4 and 10% of the population (approximately 1,000,000) was passed through a COPAS biosorter (Karolinska Institute, Stockholm, Sweden).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title><italic>C. elegans</italic> expression constructs and generation of transgenic worms</title>
<p>Reporter gene constructs were generated by PCR amplifying promoter elements and cloning into the pPD95.75-mCherry and gfp vectors (Fire Vector Kit). Mutagenesis was performed using the QuikChange II XL Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (Stratagene). Rescue constructs were generated by cloning promoter and cDNA sequences into the pPD49.26 expression vector (Fire Vector Kit). Constructs were injected into young adult hermaphrodites as either simple arrays (<italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic> (50 ng ul<sup>−1</sup>) and pRF4 (50 ng ul<sup>−1</sup>) as injection markers) or as complex arrays using 1–10 ng ul<sup>−1</sup> of linearized plasmid, 150 ng ul<sup>−1</sup> of <italic>PvuII</italic>-digested bacterial genomic DNA and <italic>myo-2<sup>prom</sup>::dsRed</italic> (3–5 ng ul<sup>−1</sup>), <italic>elt-2<sup>prom</sup>::gfp</italic> (3–15 ng ul<sup>−1</sup>) as injection markers.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Behavioral assays</title>
<p>Animals were transferred without food to 14 cm NGM assay plates containing a cut out arena of Whatman filter paper soaked in 20 mM CuCl<sub>2</sub> to prevent them from leaving a 56 mm×56 mm center area. Sixty to seventy animals were used in a single experiment and starved for one hour prior to examination. Each experiment was carried out three times, except for wild-type, which was performed six times. A custom-made transparent plexiglass device with a flow arena of 60 mm×60 mm×0.7 mm was placed onto the assay arena and animals were accustomed to a gas flow of 100 ml/min containing 21% (v/v) oxygen for 5 minutes. During the assays animals were exposed for 6 minutes to 21% O<sub>2</sub> before and after a 6 minute stimulus interval of either 10% O<sub>2</sub> or 1% CO<sub>2</sub> (+21% O<sub>2</sub>). All gas mixtures were balanced with N<sub>2</sub>. Gases were mixed with a static mixing element connected to mass flow controllers (Vögtlin Instruments) that were operated by LabView software. Recordings of freely behaving animals illuminated with flat red LED lights were made at 3 fps on a 4 megapixel CCD camera (Jai) using Streampix software (Norpix). Movies were analyzed by MatLab-based image processing and tracking scripts as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Ramot1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003511-Tsunozaki1">[44]</xref>. The resulting trajectories were used to calculate instantaneous speed during continuous forward movements (1 second binning). Omega turns were detected based on characteristic changes in object eccentricity and their frequency was calculated in 15 second bins. For quantifications, relative speed changes were calculated between representative intervals of 120 seconds before (basal level) and 4 seconds after the stimulus, capturing the minimum speed levels (4–8 seconds post stimulus). Data were normalized to the basal level. Changes in omega turn frequency were calculated between representative intervals of 180 seconds before (basal level) and 60 seconds after the stimulus, to capture the maximum rise phase (55–115 seconds post stimulus).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Heat-shock experiments</title>
<p>Two transgenic lines for <italic>hsp-16.2::egl-13</italic> were used for the heat-shock experiments. For the rescue and maintenance experiments, third larval stage (L3) worms were heat shocked at 37°C two times for 30 min. After heat shock, worms were kept at 25°C overnight and then transferred to 15°C for 2 days.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3f">
<title>Microscopy</title>
<p>Worms were mounted on 5% agarose on glass slides and images were taken using an automated fluorescence microscope (Zeiss, AXIO Imager M2) and MicroManager software (version 3.1).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3g">
<title>Neuronal scoring</title>
<p>Neurons were given a numerical value according to their expression levels. Wild-type expression scored 1, decreased expression scored 0.5 and abolished expression scored 0. Percentage of GFP expressing animals was then correlated to the theoretical maximum score using the equation below.<disp-formula id="pgen.1003511.e001"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula></p>
</sec><sec id="s3h">
<title>Bioinformatic analysis</title>
<p>The Jaspar program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jaspar.genereg.net/" xlink:type="simple">http://jaspar.genereg.net/</ext-link>) was used to predict the transcription factor binding sites in the <italic>egl-13</italic> upstream regulatory sequence.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3i">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Statistical analysis was performed in GraphPad Prism 5 using one-way ANOVA with Newman-Keuls Multiple Comparison Test. Values are expressed as mean ± s.d. Differences with a <italic>P</italic> value&lt;0.05 were considered significant. For the behavioral assays statistical significance was determined using one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni's Multiple Comparison Test.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1003511.s001" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><italic>egl-13</italic> mutants have anchor cell fusion defects. (A) <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant hermaphrodites are severely egg-laying defective due to a defect in anchor cell fusion (right, compared to the wild-type adult on the left). (B) <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant alleles isolated from our forward genetic screens (<italic>rp14</italic>, <italic>22</italic>, <italic>23</italic> and <italic>26</italic>) all have anchor cell fusion defects comparable to the <italic>ku194</italic> allele. In the wild-type vulva, the anchor cell fuses to the utse cells to form the mature uterine-vulval connection (green arrowhead, top left). In <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant animals, the anchor cell fails to fuse to the utse (red arrowheads) and blocks egg-laying. (C) Scoring of neuronal phenotypes in <italic>egl-13</italic> mutants. <italic>rp13</italic> was isolated with the BAG marker, <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gfp. rp22</italic> and <italic>rp23</italic> were isolated with the URX marker, <italic>flp-8<sup>prom</sup>::GFP</italic> and <italic>rp26</italic> was isolated with the BAG, URX, AQR and PQR marker, <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::GCY-33::gfp</italic>. Expression of each marker in wild-type animals is stated with a +. Scorings were conducted as stated in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">materials and methods</xref> section.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1003511.s002" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p>BAG and URX lineages. Lineage diagrams of the BAG and URX neurons. Neurons whose fate are affected in <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutants are indicated in red, unaffected in green and untested in black. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003511.s007">Table S2</xref> for fate markers used.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1003511.s003" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><italic>egl-13</italic> expression pattern. Expression pattern of <italic>egl-13</italic> at different stages (330–360 mins, 550 mins and L1 larva), using the <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup>::gfp</italic> reporter transgene. Fluorescence micrographs (right) and differential interference contrast (DIC) microscopy images (left). Scale bar, 10 µm.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1003511.s004" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p><italic>egl-13</italic> acts cell autonomously to control O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron fate. (A) Protein domain structure of EGL-13 isoforms A+D. (B) Extrachromosomal transgenic rescue of <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant phenotypes, in the <italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gcy-33::gfp</italic> strain, using <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup></italic>-driven <italic>egl-13<sup>isoformA</sup>cDNA</italic> (left) and <italic>egl-13<sup>isoformD</sup>cDNA</italic> (right). Both isoforms equally rescue the <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant phenotype. n = 46–61. *P&lt;0.05, ***P&lt;0.001 indicates significant difference from non-transgenic <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant animals. (C) Transgenic lines expressing <italic>egl-13</italic> cDNA under the control of <italic>egl-13<sup>prom1</sup></italic> rescues all the <italic>egl-13</italic> alleles retrieved from the genetic screens. Rescue of <italic>rp14</italic> in BAG (<italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::gfp), rp22</italic> in URX (<italic>flp-8<sup>prom</sup>::gfp</italic>), <italic>rp23</italic> in URX (<italic>flp-8<sup>prom</sup>::gfp</italic>) and <italic>rp26</italic> in BAG, URX, AQR and PQR (<italic>gcy-33<sup>prom</sup>::GCY-33::gfp</italic>). n = 47–87. **P&lt;0.01, ***P&lt;0.001 indicates significant difference from non-transgenic <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant animals. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">materials and methods</xref> for neuronal scoring criteria used.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1003511.s005" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S5</label><caption>
<p>Differential regulation of O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron terminal differentiation markers by <italic>egl-13</italic>, <italic>ets-5</italic>, and <italic>ahr-1</italic>. (A) Requirement of <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ets-5</italic> for the expression of BAG terminal differentiation markers: <italic>flp-13</italic>, <italic>flp-17, flp-19</italic>, <italic>gcy-9, gcy-31</italic> and <italic>gcy-33. egl-13</italic> and <italic>ets-5</italic> are both absolutely required for the expression of <italic>flp-13</italic> and <italic>flp-19</italic> suggesting that they act in a common pathway. <italic>gcy-9</italic> is predominantly regulated by <italic>ets-5</italic> with <italic>egl-13</italic> playing a lesser role. <italic>flp-17</italic> is regulated by both <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ets-5</italic> acting in parallel pathways. Finally, <italic>gcy-31</italic> and <italic>gcy-33</italic> expression is predominantly regulated by <italic>egl-13</italic>. + = wt, red bars = mutant backgrounds. (B) Requirement of <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ahr-1</italic> for the expression of URX terminal differentiation markers: <italic>flp-8</italic>, <italic>flp-19</italic> and <italic>gcy-33</italic>. <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ahr-1</italic> act in parallel pathways to regulate <italic>flp-8</italic> expression. <italic>egl-13</italic> is absolutely required for the expression of <italic>flp-19</italic> whereas <italic>ahr-1</italic> is less important. <italic>egl-13</italic> and <italic>ahr-1</italic> are both required for <italic>gcy-33</italic> expression, probably via the same pathway. + = wt, blue bars = mutant backgrounds. Statistical model applied is a one-way ANOVA with Newman-Keuls multiple comparison test **P&lt;0.05, ***P&lt;0.005. Statistical model applied is a one-way ANOVA with Newman-Keuls multiple comparison test **P&lt;0.05, ***P&lt;0.005. Alleles used in this analysis <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic>, <italic>ets-5(tm1734)</italic> and <italic>ahr-1(ia03)</italic>. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">materials and methods</xref> for neuronal scoring criteria used.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1003511.s006" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p>Expression of the O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron terminal gene battery is affected in <italic>egl-13</italic> mutant animals. (A) Effects in the expression of O<sub>2</sub>- and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensing neuron reporters in <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant animals differ from gene to gene and from cell to cell. For example, <italic>flp-19</italic> expression is strongly affected in both URX and BAG neurons, whereas <italic>gcy-33</italic> expression is more strongly affected in the URX neurons than BAG neurons. Fluorescent reporters for the sister cells of the URX (CEPD) and BAG (SMDV) neurons are unaffected in <italic>egl-13(ku194)</italic> mutant animals. (B) The deletion in the <italic>egl-13</italic> locus of <italic>rp23</italic> leaves the BAG-element intact (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003511-g005">Figure 5</xref>). As a result, BAG terminal fate marker expression is not significantly affected in <italic>egl-13(rp23)</italic> mutant animals. In both tables, quantification indicates the percentage of animals in which fluorescence was observed (ON), not observed (OFF) or asymmetrically affected left expressed (L ON) or right expressed (R ON). “−” indicates that the reporter is not expressed in those neurons. Animals were scored at the young adult stage. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">materials and methods</xref> for neuronal scoring criteria used.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1003511.s007" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003511.s007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p>Strains used in this study.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank members of the Pocock Laboratory and Oliver Hobert, Baris Tursun, and Iva Greenwald for comments on the manuscript; we thank the following people for strains and reagents: Oliver Hobert (Columbia University), Cornelia Bargmann (Rockefeller University), Mark Alkema (University of Massachusetts Medical School). Some strains were provided by the CGC and by Shohei Mitani at the National Bioresource Project (Japan). We also thank Thomas Burglin and Peter Swoboda at the Karolinska Institue for use of their COPAS Biosorter facility, under the <italic>C. elegans</italic> Nordforsk Researcher Network of Shared Technology Platforms.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Prahlad1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prahlad</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Regulation of the cellular heat shock response in Caenorhabditis elegans by thermosensory neurons</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>320</volume>: <fpage>811</fpage>–<lpage>814</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1156093" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1156093</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Pocock1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hobert</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Hypoxia activates a latent circuit for processing gustatory information in C. elegans</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>610</fpage>–<lpage>614</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nn.2537" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nn.2537</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Chang1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bargmann</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Hypoxia and the HIF-1 transcriptional pathway reorganize a neuronal circuit for oxygen-dependent behavior in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>7321</fpage>–<lpage>7326</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0802164105" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0802164105</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Bretscher1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bretscher</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Bono</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A carbon dioxide avoidance behavior is integrated with responses to ambient oxygen and food in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>8044</fpage>–<lpage>8049</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0707607105" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0707607105</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Semenza1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semenza</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Hypoxia-inducible factors in physiology and medicine</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2012.01.021" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2012.01.021</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Sharabi1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharabi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lecuona</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helenius</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beitel</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sznajder</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Sensing, physiological effects and molecular response to elevated CO2 levels in eukaryotes</article-title>. <source>J Cell Mol Med</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>4304</fpage>–<lpage>4318</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1582-4934.2009.00952.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1582-4934.2009.00952.x</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Kaelin1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaelin</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ratcliffe</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Oxygen sensing by metazoans: the central role of the HIF hydroxylase pathway</article-title>. <source>Molecular Cell</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2008.04.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.molcel.2008.04.009</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Guais1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guais</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacquot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karrer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dukan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Toxicity of carbon dioxide: a review</article-title>. <source>Chem Res Toxicol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>2061</fpage>–<lpage>2070</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/tx200220r" xlink:type="simple">10.1021/tx200220r</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Suh1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>GSB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hergarden</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A single population of olfactory sensory neurons mediates an innate avoidance behaviour in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>431</volume>: <fpage>854</fpage>–<lpage>859</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature02980" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature02980</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Munger1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Munger</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leinders-Zufall</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDougall</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cockerham</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>An olfactory subsystem that detects carbon disulfide and mediates food-related social learning</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1438</fpage>–<lpage>1444</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2010.06.021" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cub.2010.06.021</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Hallem1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallem</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Acute carbon dioxide avoidance in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>8038</fpage>–<lpage>8043</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0707469105" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0707469105</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Wingrove1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wingrove</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Farrell</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Nitric oxide contributes to behavioral, cellular, and developmental responses to low oxygen in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80610-8" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80610-8</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Jones1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cayirlioglu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kadow</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Two chemosensory receptors together mediate carbon dioxide detection in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>445</volume>: <fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature05466" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature05466</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-LpezBarneo1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>López-Barneo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega-Sáenz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pardal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piruat</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Oxygen sensing in the carotid body</article-title>. <source>Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences</source> <volume>1177</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>131</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.05033.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.05033.x</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Hu1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Detection of near-atmospheric concentrations of CO2 by an olfactory subsystem in the mouse</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>317</volume>: <fpage>953</fpage>–<lpage>957</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1144233" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1144233</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Sim1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tharadra</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lipsick</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Epigenetic regulation of olfactory receptor gene expression by the Myb-MuvB/dREAM complex</article-title>. <source>Genes &amp; Development</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>2483</fpage>–<lpage>2498</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gad.201665.112" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/gad.201665.112</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Sylvia1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sylvia DM, Fuhrmann JJ, Hartel PG, Zuberer DA (2004) Principles and Applications of Soil Microbiology (2nd Edition). 2nd ed. Prentice Hall. 1 pp.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Gray1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karow</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Oxygen sensation and social feeding mediated by a C. elegans guanylate cyclase homologue</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>430</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature02714" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature02714</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Cheung1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>BHH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Albayram</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Bono</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Experience-Dependent Modulation of C. elegans Behavior by Ambient Oxygen</article-title>. <source>Current Biology</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>905</fpage>–<lpage>917</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2005.04.017" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cub.2005.04.017</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Zimmer1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pokala</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karow</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Neurons detect increases and decreases in oxygen levels using distinct guanylate cyclases</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>865</fpage>–<lpage>879</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2009.02.013" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.neuron.2009.02.013</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Hallem2"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallem</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McWhirter</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henz</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Receptor-type guanylate cyclase is required for carbon dioxide sensation by Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>254</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1017354108" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1017354108</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Bretscher2"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bretscher</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kodama-Namba</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soltesz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Temperature, oxygen, and salt-sensing neurons in C. elegans are carbon dioxide sensors that control avoidance behavior</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1099</fpage>–<lpage>1113</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2011.02.023" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.neuron.2011.02.023</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Ortiz1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Searching for Neuronal Left/Right Asymmetry: Genomewide Analysis of Nematode Receptor-Type Guanylyl Cyclases</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>173</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1534/genetics.106.055749" xlink:type="simple">10.1534/genetics.106.055749</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Kim1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Expression and regulation of an FMRFamide-related neuropeptide gene family inCaenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>J Comp Neurol</source> <volume>475</volume>: <fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>550</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/cne.20189" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/cne.20189</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-HannaRose1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanna-Rose</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>COG-2, a sox domain protein necessary for establishing a functional vulval-uterine connection in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Brandt1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz-Zaman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Juozaityte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Velazquez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A single gene target of an ETS-family transcription factor determines neuronal CO2-chemosensitivity</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e34014</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0034014" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0034014</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Sulston1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sulston</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schierenberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>The embryonic cell lineage of the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Developmental Biology</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Lefebvre1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Crombrugghe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>A new long form of Sox5 (L-Sox5), Sox6 and Sox9 are coexpressed in chondrogenesis and cooperatively activate the type II collagen gene</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>5718</fpage>–<lpage>5733</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/emboj/17.19.5718" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/emboj/17.19.5718</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Satterlee1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Satterlee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasakura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berkeley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Specification of thermosensory neuron fate in C. elegans requires ttx-1, a homolog of otd/Otx</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>943</fpage>–<lpage>956</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Flames1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flames</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hobert</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Gene regulatory logic of dopamine neuron differentiation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>458</volume>: <fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>889</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature07929" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature07929</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Tursun1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tursun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kratsios</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hobert</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Direct conversion of C. elegans germ cells into specific neuron types</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>331</volume>: <fpage>304</fpage>–<lpage>308</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1199082" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1199082</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Qin1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powell-Coffman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The Caenorhabditis elegans AHR-1 transcription complex controls expression of soluble guanylate cyclase genes in the URX neurons and regulates aggregation behavior</article-title>. <source>Developmental Biology</source> <volume>298</volume>: <fpage>606</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2006.07.017" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ydbio.2006.07.017</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Guillermin1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillermin</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castelletto</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hallem</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Differentiation of carbon dioxide-sensing neurons in Caenorhabditis elegans requires the ETS-5 transcription factor</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>189</volume>: <fpage>1327</fpage>–<lpage>1339</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1534/genetics.111.133835" xlink:type="simple">10.1534/genetics.111.133835</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Azim1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Azim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jabaudon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fame</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macklis</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>SOX6 controls dorsal progenitor identity and interneuron diversity during neocortical development</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1238</fpage>–<lpage>1247</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nn.2387" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nn.2387</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Lai1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jabaudon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molyneaux</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arlotta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>SOX5 controls the sequential generation of distinct corticofugal neuron subtypes</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>232</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2007.12.023" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.neuron.2007.12.023</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Scott1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wynn</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sesay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>SOX9 induces and maintains neural stem cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1181</fpage>–<lpage>1189</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nn.2646" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nn.2646</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Pevny1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pevny</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Placzek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>SOX genes and neural progenitor identity</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Neurobiology</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.conb.2005.01.016" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.conb.2005.01.016</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Bergsland1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergsland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramsköld</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zaouter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Sequentially acting Sox transcription factors in neural lineage development</article-title>. <source>Genes &amp; Development</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2453</fpage>–<lpage>2464</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gad.176008.111" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/gad.176008.111</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Morales1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Alcala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barbas</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Dynamic Sox5 protein expression during cranial ganglia development</article-title>. <source>Dev Dyn</source> <volume>236</volume>: <fpage>2702</fpage>–<lpage>2707</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/dvdy.21282" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/dvdy.21282</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Brenner1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>The genetics of Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Mello1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stinchcomb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ambros</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Efficient gene transfer in C.elegans: extrachromosomal maintenance and integration of transforming sequences</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>3959</fpage>–<lpage>3970</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Flibotte1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flibotte</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edgley</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neil</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Whole-genome profiling of mutagenesis in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>185</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>441</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1534/genetics.110.116616" xlink:type="simple">10.1534/genetics.110.116616</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Ramot1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carnell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The Parallel Worm Tracker: a platform for measuring average speed and drug-induced paralysis in nematodes</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e2208</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0002208" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0002208</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003511-Tsunozaki1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsunozaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chalasani</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bargmann</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A behavioral switch: cGMP and PKC signaling in olfactory neurons reverses odor preference in C. elegans</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>959</fpage>–<lpage>971</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2008.07.038" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.neuron.2008.07.038</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>