<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PGENETICS-D-12-00364</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002623</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Perspective</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Obstetrics and gynecology</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Oncology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cancers and neoplasms</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Oncology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Too Much Cleavage of Cyclin E Promotes Breast Tumorigenesis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Loeb</surname>
            <given-names>Keith R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Xueyan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Laboratory Medicine, University of Washington School of Medicine, Seattle, Washington, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Pathology, University of Washington School of Medicine, Seattle, Washington, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Division of Clinical Research, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, Washington, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Horwitz</surname>
            <given-names>Marshall S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Washington, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">kloeb@fhcrc.org</email></corresp>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e1002623</elocation-id><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Loeb, Chen</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article ext-link-type="uri" id="RA1" related-article-type="companion" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002538" xlink:type="simple"> <article-title>LMW-Cyclin E/CDK2 Deregulates Acinar Morphogenesis, Induces Tumorigenesis and Associates with Activated b-Raf-ERK1/2-mTOR Pathway in Breast Cancer</article-title></related-article><funding-group><funding-statement>The authors received no specific funding for this article.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="3"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title/>
      <p>Cyclin E, together with cyclin-dependent kinase 2 (CDK2), functions as a gatekeeper to promote G1/S transitions and the initiation of DNA replication. In normal cells, cyclin E–associated kinase activity is exquisitely regulated, with activity being limited to a brief time interval between late G1 and early S phase. Human cancers frequently exhibit deregulated cyclin E–associated kinase activity resulting from overexpression of cyclin E and loss of cyclin-dependent kinase inhibition (via p53 mutations) promoting genetic instability and cell proliferation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Hwang1">[1]</xref>. Increased levels of cyclin E correlate with tumorigenesis and are a poor prognostic indicator independent of proliferation rate, suggesting that cyclin E's role in tumorigenesis is not limited to promoting increased cell proliferation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Keyomarsi1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Porter1">[3]</xref>. By eliminating regulatory constraints using p53 null cells, we and others have shown that overexpression or endogenous expression of stabilizing mutant forms of cyclin E can lead to hyperproliferation, genetic instability, and malignancy in cell culture and murine models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Loeb1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Minella1">[5]</xref>. Normal cells suppress the effects of excess/stabilized cyclin E via the G1/S checkpoint involving the p53/p21 pathway.</p>
      <p>Five isoforms of cyclin E, ranging in size from 33 to 44 kDa, have been identified in tumors over-expressing cyclin E. These low molecular weight forms of cyclin E (LMW-E) are generated through post-translational cleavage of full-length cyclin E by the elastase family of serine proteases in tumor cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Harwell1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Porter2">[7]</xref>. In comparison to full-length cyclin E (50 kDa), LMW-E forms are uniquely expressed in tumor cells, exhibit enhanced CDK2-associated kinase activity, have increased affinity for CDK2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Porter2">[7]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Wingate1">[9]</xref>, and exhibit decreased inhibition by CDK2 inhibitors, p21 and p27 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002623-g001">Figure 1</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Akli1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Wingate2">[11]</xref>. Ectopic expression of LMW-E isoforms promotes cell proliferation, genetic instability, centrosome amplification, and malignancy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Akli2">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-BagheriYarmand1">[13]</xref>. In addition, clinical studies have shown that high LMW-E is strongly associated with poor survival in breast cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Keyomarsi1">[2]</xref>, colorectal cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Zhou1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Corin1">[15]</xref>, ovarian cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Davidson1">[16]</xref>, and melanomas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Bales1">[17]</xref>. Given its unique properties and distinct function in human cancers, targeting LMW-E could have important therapeutic implications.</p>
      <fig id="pgen-1002623-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002623.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Low molecular weight cyclin E promotes tumorigenesis.</title>
          <p>In normal cells, cyclin E/CDK2 is tightly regulated and triggers the onset of S phase. In tumors, cyclin E undergoes proteolytic processing generating low molecular weight species that exhibit increased kinase activity and resistance to inhibition by cyclin kinase inhibitors p21/p27. The expression of LMW-E promotes aberrant acinar morphogenesis, centrosome amplification, and tumors associated with activation of the bRaf/ERK/mTOR pathway. LMW-E, low molecular weight cyclin E.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002623.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The study by Duong et al. in this issue of <italic>PLoS Genetics</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Duong1">[18]</xref> convincingly uncovers the tumorigenic potential of LMW-E. The authors used three different model systems—3D acinar cultures, xenograft transplantation, and transgenic mice—to show that overexpression of LMW-E is sufficient to induce aberrant acinar morphogenesis in culture and mammary tumors in mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002623-g001">Figure 1</xref>). When grown on Matrigel, immortalized human mammary epithelial cells (hMECs) expressing LMW-E exhibit large misshapen multiacinar structures resulting from defective growth arrest and apoptosis that mimic morphologic features of breast carcinomas. Further, ectopic expression of LMW-E in immortalized hMECs promotes tumorigenesis in xenografts and transgenic mice to a much greater extent than full-length cyclin E. Consistent with the reports by Akli et al. and Nanos-Webb et al., tumorigenesis associated with LMW-E is dependent on CDK2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Akli3">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-NanosWebb1">[20]</xref>. Furthermore, in vivo passaging of tumor cells increases the expression of LMW-E, suggesting that LMW-E provides a selective growth advantage to the tumor. Duong et al. also took advantage of a proteomic analysis termed reverse-phase protein array assay (RPPA) to examine protein expression patterns in cultured tumor cells and in breast tumors expressing high LMW-E levels. Their analyses revealed that multiple components of the b-RAF-ERK1/2-mTOR pathway are elevated in these cells. Activation of the b-RAF-ERK1/2-mTOR pathway normally promotes cell division and cell survival. Consistent with this, the authors observed that endogenous cyclin E levels are also increased in cells expressing high LMW-E, indicative of the existence of a positive feedback loop that promotes cell proliferation. Both high LMW-E levels and up-regulation of the b-RAF-ERK1/2-mTOR signaling pathway are associated with poor survival, suggesting functional correlation of these events in aggressive tumors. Importantly, the authors demonstrated that combination therapy targeting LMW-E/CDK2 and the b-RAF-ERK1/2-mTOR pathway has a synergistic effect in abrogating the tumorigenic effect of LMW-E. Thus, the identification of these downstream regulators may provide novel biomarkers and/or potential therapeutic targets for LMW-E–expressing tumors.</p>
      <p>The report that LMW-E potentiates tumorigenesis in three independent model systems associated with activation of the b-RAF-ERK1/2-mTOR pathway is intriguing. However, there are many important questions about the role of LMW-E in tumorigenesis that need to be addressed. 1) What is the functional relationship between LMW-E and full-length cyclin E? In each tumor model reported by Duong et al., the effect was examined by over-expressing LMW-E in a background of endogenous full-length cyclin E. Further, the authors show that ectopic expression of LMW-E in transplanted xenografts triggers tumor evolution and results in increased levels of endogenous cyclin E. Thus, the contribution of endogenous full-length cyclin E in tumorigenesis cannot be excluded. In addition, Spruck et al. reported that the level of LMW-E correlates with full-length cyclin E, suggesting that LMW-E reflects the total cyclin E protein in primary breast tumors, cell lines, and even normal breast tissue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Spruck1">[21]</xref>. To examine the effect of LMW-E in the absence of over-expression, and in the absence of full-length cyclin E, it will be important to use a knock-in model in which expression of LMW-E is driven from the endogenous cyclin E promoter. 2) What is the relationship between LMW-E and the b-Raf-ERK1/2-mTOR signaling pathway? The authors demonstrated that the b-Raf-ERK1/2-mTOR signaling pathway is activated in tumors expressing high levels of LMW-E. The b-Raf-ERK1/2-mTOR pathway may be a downstream signaling pathway deregulated by LMW-E, or it could be a parallel survival pathway selected in LMW-E–expressing tumors. In particular, the fact that only combinational therapy targeting both cyclin E–associated kinase activity and the b-Raf-ERK1/2-mTOR pathway generates an anti-tumor effect argues against a direct cause–effect relationship and is suggestive of a parallel pathway. 3) Is LMW-E expression required for tumor growth and does down-regulation of LMW-E alter tumor growth, invasion, or metastasis? The authors have generated an inducible model that should facilitate these studies. 4) Is the tumor-promoting activity of LMW-E due to enhanced deregulated kinase activity or to alternative target specificity? The LMW-E construct used in these studies has an N-terminal deletion (40 amino acids) that eliminates the proposed nuclear localization signal (NLS) and potentially affects the intracellular localization and substrate specificity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Delk1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Jackman1">[23]</xref>. 5) How is LMW-E generated in tumors, and is it tumor-type specific? It has been proposed and demonstrated by Caruso et al. that many tumors have elevated protease activity and decreased levels of protease inhibitors such as elafin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002623-Caruso1">[24]</xref> that may contribute to the generation of LMW-E. Further characterization of the proteolytic pathways that target cyclin E in tumors may provide alternative therapeutic targets.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Hwang1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clurman</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Cyclin E in normal and neoplastic cell cycles.</article-title>             <source>Oncogene</source>             <volume>24</volume>             <fpage>2776</fpage>             <lpage>2786</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Keyomarsi1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyomarsi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchholz</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Cyclin E and survival in patients with breast cancer.</article-title>             <source>N Engl J Med</source>             <volume>347</volume>             <fpage>1566</fpage>             <lpage>1575</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Porter1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heagerty</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gatti</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Expression of cell-cycle regulators p27Kip1 and cyclin E, alone and in combination, correlate with survival in young breast cancer patients.</article-title>             <source>Nat Med</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>222</fpage>             <lpage>225</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Loeb1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Firpo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norwood</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>A mouse model for cyclin E-dependent genetic instability and tumorigenesis.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Cell</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>35</fpage>             <lpage>47</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Minella1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Minella</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swanger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welcker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>p53 and p21 form an inducible barrier that protects cells against cyclin E-cdk2 deregulation.</article-title>             <source>Curr Biol</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>1817</fpage>             <lpage>1827</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Harwell1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harwell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyomarsi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Processing of cyclin E differs between normal and tumor breast cells.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Res</source>             <volume>60</volume>             <fpage>481</fpage>             <lpage>489</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Porter2">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGahren</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harwell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Tumor-specific proteolytic processing of cyclin E generates hyperactive lower-molecular-weight forms.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>6254</fpage>             <lpage>6269</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Harwell2">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harwell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mull</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyomarsi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Activation of cyclin-dependent kinase 2 by full length and low molecular weight forms of cyclin E in breast cancer cells.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>279</volume>             <fpage>12695</fpage>             <lpage>12705</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Wingate1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wingate</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puskas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Low molecular weight cyclin E is specific in breast cancer and is associated with mechanisms of tumor progression.</article-title>             <source>Cell Cycle</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>1062</fpage>             <lpage>1068</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Akli1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Multani</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wingate</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Tumor-specific low molecular weight forms of cyclin E induce genomic instability and resistance to p21, p27, and antiestrogens in breast cancer.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Res</source>             <volume>64</volume>             <fpage>3198</fpage>             <lpage>3208</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Wingate2">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wingate</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGarhen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedrosian</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>The tumor-specific hyperactive forms of cyclin E are resistant to inhibition by p21 and p27.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>280</volume>             <fpage>15148</fpage>             <lpage>15157</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Akli2">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Pelt</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Multani</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Overexpression of the low molecular weight cyclin E in transgenic mice induces metastatic mammary carcinomas through the disruption of the ARF-p53 pathway.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Res</source>             <volume>67</volume>             <fpage>7212</fpage>             <lpage>7222</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-BagheriYarmand1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagheri-Yarmand</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biernacka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyomarsi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Low molecular weight cyclin E overexpression shortens mitosis, leading to chromosome missegregation and centrosome amplification.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Res</source>             <volume>70</volume>             <fpage>5074</fpage>             <lpage>5084</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Zhou1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Overexpression of cyclin E isoforms correlates with poor prognosis in rectal cancer.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Surg Oncol</source>             <volume>37</volume>             <fpage>1078</fpage>             <lpage>1084</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Corin1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Giacomo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lastella</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagnulo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guanti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Tumor-specific hyperactive low-molecular-weight cyclin E isoforms detection and characterization in non-metastatic colorectal tumors.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Biol Ther</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>198</fpage>             <lpage>203</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Davidson1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skrede</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silins</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shih Ie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trope</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Low-molecular weight forms of cyclin E differentiate ovarian carcinoma from cells of mesothelial origin and are associated with poor survival in ovarian carcinoma.</article-title>             <source>Cancer</source>             <volume>110</volume>             <fpage>1264</fpage>             <lpage>1271</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Bales1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bales</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGahren-Murray</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>The low molecular weight cyclin E isoforms augment angiogenesis and metastasis of human melanoma cells in vivo.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Res</source>             <volume>65</volume>             <fpage>692</fpage>             <lpage>697</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Duong1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duong</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wingate</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2012</year>             <article-title>LMW-E/CDK2 deregulates acinar morphogenesis, induces tumorigenesis and associates with the activated b-Raf-ERK1/2-mTOR pathway in breast cancer patients.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Genet</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>e1002538</fpage>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002538" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002538</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Akli3">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Pelt</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyomarsi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Cdk2 is required for breast cancer mediated by the low-molecular-weight isoform of cyclin E.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Res</source>             <volume>71</volume>             <fpage>3377</fpage>             <lpage>3386</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-NanosWebb1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nanos-Webb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jabbour</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Multani</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wingate</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oumata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Targeting low molecular weight cyclin E (LMW-E) in breast cancer.</article-title>             <source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source>             <comment>E-pub ahead of print 22 June 2011</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Spruck1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spruck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiegl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller-Holzner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Detection of low molecular weight derivatives of cyclin E1 is a function of cyclin E1 protein levels in breast cancer.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Res</source>             <volume>66</volume>             <fpage>7355</fpage>             <lpage>7360</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Delk1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delk</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyomarsi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Altered subcellular localization of tumor-specific cyclin E isoforms affects cyclin-dependent kinase 2 complex formation and proteasomal regulation.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Res</source>             <volume>69</volume>             <fpage>2817</fpage>             <lpage>2825</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Jackman1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>den Elzen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagting</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pines</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Cyclin A- and cyclin E-Cdk complexes shuttle between the nucleus and the cytoplasm.</article-title>             <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>1030</fpage>             <lpage>1045</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002623-Caruso1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caruso</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyomarsi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>The neutrophil elastase inhibitor elafin triggers rb-mediated growth arrest and caspase-dependent apoptosis in breast cancer.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Res</source>             <volume>70</volume>             <fpage>7125</fpage>             <lpage>7136</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>