<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn><publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PLGE-RA-3967R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Chromosome Biology</subject><subject>Molecular Biology/DNA Repair</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>SUMO-Targeted Ubiquitin Ligase, Rad60, and Nse2 SUMO Ligase Suppress Spontaneous Top1–Mediated DNA Damage and Genome Instability</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">STUbL and Rad60 Facilitate Genome Lesion Repair</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heideker</surname><given-names>Johanna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prudden</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>J. Jefferson P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tainer</surname><given-names>John A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>Michael N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Molecular Biology, The Scripps Research Institute, La Jolla, California, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>School of Biotechnology, Amrita Vishwa Vidya Peetham, Amritapuri, Kerala, India</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Life Sciences Division, Department of Molecular Biology, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, California, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heyer</surname><given-names>Wolf-Dietrich</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of California Davis, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">nboddy@scripps.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JH JP JJPP JAT MNB. Performed the experiments: JH JP MNB. Analyzed the data: JH JP MNB. Wrote the paper: JH JP JJPP JAT MNB.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e1001320</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Heideker et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
<p>Through as yet undefined proteins and pathways, the SUMO-targeted ubiquitin ligase (STUbL) suppresses genomic instability by ubiquitinating SUMO conjugated proteins and driving their proteasomal destruction. Here, we identify a critical function for fission yeast STUbL in suppressing spontaneous and chemically induced topoisomerase I (Top1)–mediated DNA damage. Strikingly, cells with reduced STUbL activity are dependent on tyrosyl–DNA phosphodiesterase 1 (Tdp1). This is notable, as cells lacking Tdp1 are largely aphenotypic in the vegetative cell cycle due to the existence of alternative pathways for the removal of covalent Top1–DNA adducts (Top1cc). We further identify Rad60, a SUMO mimetic and STUbL-interacting protein, and the SUMO E3 ligase Nse2 as critical Top1cc repair factors in cells lacking Tdp1. Detection of Top1ccs using chromatin immunoprecipitation and quantitative PCR shows that they are elevated in cells lacking Tdp1 and STUbL, Rad60, or Nse2 SUMO ligase activity. These unrepaired Top1ccs are shown to cause DNA damage, hyper-recombination, and checkpoint-mediated cell cycle arrest. We further determine that Tdp1 and the nucleotide excision repair endonuclease Rad16-Swi10 initiate the major Top1cc repair pathways of fission yeast. Tdp1-based repair is the predominant activity outside S phase, likely acting on transcription-coupled Top1cc. Epistasis analyses suggest that STUbL, Rad60, and Nse2 facilitate the Rad16-Swi10 pathway, parallel to Tdp1. Collectively, these results reveal a unified role for STUbL, Rad60, and Nse2 in protecting genome stability against spontaneous Top1-mediated DNA damage.</p>
</abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>The failure of cellular DNA repair mechanisms can lead to cancer, neurodegeneration, or premature aging. Although much is known about specific DNA repair mechanisms, an understanding of how these processes are critically orchestrated by post-translational modifiers such as SUMO and ubiquitin is in its infancy. We identified an intriguing family of E3 ubiquitin ligases called STUbLs that act at the interface between the SUMO and ubiquitin pathways, and through undefined proteins and pathways maintain genome stability. Here we show that dysfunction of STUbL, an associated SUMO-like protein called Rad60, or the Nse2 SUMO E3 ligase converts the normally benign topoisomerase I (Top1) activity into a genome destabilizing genotoxin. Normally, Top1 transiently introduces a break in one strand of the DNA duplex allowing DNA to unwind. However, these transient breaks are converted into recombinogenic DNA lesions when STUbL, Rad60, Nse2, and parallel pathways that we identify are compromised. This study reveals important regulatory circuits reliant on STUbL, Rad60, and Nse2 that insulate the genome from the potentially harmful effects of Top1, which may otherwise promote cancer or neurodegeneration. Furthermore, Top1 is a major chemotherapeutic target, and so our findings may aid in the development of more efficacious Top1-based therapies.</p>
</abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was funded by the National Institutes of Health (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nih.gov/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nih.gov/</ext-link>) grants GM068608 and GM081840 awarded to MNB, who is supported by a Scholar Award from The Leukemia &amp; Lymphoma Society (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.leukemia-lymphoma.org/hm_lls" xlink:type="simple">http://www.leukemia-lymphoma.org/hm_lls</ext-link>). JH is supported by a predoctoral fellowship from Boehringer Ingelheim Fonds (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bifonds.de/cgi-bin/index.pl" xlink:type="simple">http://www.bifonds.de/cgi-bin/index.pl</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Efficient DNA repair suppresses spontaneous genetic alterations that otherwise lead to cell death or transformation. Posttranslational modifications (PTMs) can enhance the efficiency of individual repair processes and proteins and/or channel repair through appropriate pathways (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Schleker1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Ulrich1">[2]</xref>). Among these PTMs, the small proteins ubiquitin and SUMO have gained increasing recognition as key guardians of chromosomal integrity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Schleker1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Kerscher1">[3]</xref>. Related enzymatic cascades covalently attach either SUMO or ubiquitin to lysine residues within target proteins to modulate their stability, activity and localization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Kerscher1">[3]</xref>. Each cascade employs dedicated E1 activating enzymes, E2 conjugating enzymes and E3 ligases that contribute to substrate selection and transfer of the modifier from the E2 to the target protein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Kerscher1">[3]</xref>. In contrast to the numerous ubiquitin E3 ligases, there are apparently two major SUMO E3 ligases in fission yeast called Pli1 and Nse2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Watts1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Xhemalce1">[5]</xref>.</p>
<p>Novel crosstalk between the SUMO and ubiquitin pathways is provided by the recently discovered SUMO-targeted ubiquitin E3 ligases (STUbLs), which ubiquitinate and thereby target SUMO-modified proteins to the proteasome for degradation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Geoffroy1">[6]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Hunter1">[8]</xref>. Through this novel activity, STUbLs play key but largely enigmatic roles in maintaining genome stability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Nagai1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Burgess1">[15]</xref>. Fission yeast STUbL was recently shown to physically interact with Nse5/6 and Rad60, providing a potential link between STUbL activity and DNA repair <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden1">[12]</xref>. Nse5/6 are subunits of the Smc5/6 genome stability complex that is architecturally related to the Cohesin and Condensin complexes, but interestingly, contains the SUMO E3 ligase Nse2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Lee1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pebernard1">[17]</xref>.</p>
<p>Mimicry of SUMO was recently discovered as a function of members of the Rad60 DNA repair protein family, which contain two SUMO-like domains (SLDs) at their C-termini <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Boddy1">[18]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Novatchkova1">[20]</xref>. We recently determined that Rad60 SLD2 mimics SUMO by interacting non-covalently with the SUMO E2 conjugating enzyme Ubc9 at the same interface bound by SUMO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden2">[21]</xref>. Disruption of the Rad60∶Ubc9 interface via a single Rad60 glutamate 380 to arginine mutation (<italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup></italic>) causes genome instability and phenotypes associated with dysfunction of the SUMO pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden2">[21]</xref>. Interestingly, <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup></italic> cells, like STUbL mutant cells, are dependent on both the Holliday junction (HJ) endonuclease Mus81-Eme1 and the RecA recombinase Rhp51 (Rad51) for viability in the absence of exogenous stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden2">[21]</xref>. Given the specific role of Mus81-Eme1 in replication fork restart <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Roseaulin1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Boddy2">[23]</xref>, this suggests that for as yet undefined reasons, replication forks are prone to collapse in Rad60 and STUbL mutant cells. A potential source of fork collapse in these mutant cells are stalled covalent topoisomerase I (Top1)-DNA adducts that are encountered during replication <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pommier1">[24]</xref>. In budding yeast, covalent Top1-DNA adducts called Top1 cleavage complexes (Top1cc) are efficiently removed by several repair factors acting in parallel, including tyrosyl-DNA phosphodiesterase (Tdp1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pommier1">[24]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Caldecott1">[26]</xref>). The corresponding fission yeast pathways and their relative contributions to Top1cc repair have not been defined. However, fission yeast Tdp1 was found to process Top1-independent lesions arising from oxidative stress in quiescent fission yeast <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-BenHassine1">[27]</xref>. In budding yeast, Tdp1 also affects Top1-independent repair processes, such as enhancing the fidelity of non-homologous end-joining by producing a 3′-phosphate at the exposed ends of DNA double strand breaks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Bahmed1">[28]</xref>.</p>
<p>Here, we determine that STUbL, together with the physically associated DNA repair protein Rad60 and the Nse2 SUMO E3 ligase, suppresses spontaneous Top1-induced DNA damage. When STUbL, Rad60 or Nse2 functions are compromised, cells require Tdp1 to repair both spontaneous and induced Top1-dependent DNA damage, which otherwise results in genomic instability, cell cycle checkpoint activation and/or cell death. This is a striking result because Tdp1 mutant fission yeast cells are weakly sensitive to the Top1 poison camptothecin (CPT), due to redundancy with as yet unknown factors (our results and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-BenHassine1">[27]</xref>). This primary finding provides mechanistic insight on how STUbL, Rad60 and Nse2 dysfunction can negatively impact genome stability. In addition, we show that Tdp1 is redundant with the fission yeast Ercc1-Xpf homologs, Rad16-Swi10, and that the absence of both pathways is lethal due to an inability to repair spontaneous Top1cc. Epistasis analysis suggests that STUbL acts in the Rad16-Swi10-initiated pathway for Top1cc repair. Furthermore, we find that Tdp1 predominates in the repair of replication-independent Top1cc lesions. Collectively, our data support a function for the evolutionarily conserved STUbL, Rad60 and Nse2 proteins in mitigating DNA damage caused by covalent Top1-DNA complexes, which arise as byproducts of normal cellular metabolism.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>STUbL and Tdp1 Define Parallel Pathways for the Repair of Top1cc</title>
<p>To probe the cause of replication fork collapse identified in STUbL mutant fission yeast <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden1">[12]</xref>, we constructed a double mutant between the hypomorphic STUbL allele, <italic>slx8-1</italic>, and <italic>tdp1Δ</italic>, and analyzed their sensitivity to CPT. The <italic>slx8-1</italic> allele contains a mutation of a non-conserved cysteine residue (C218) to tyrosine, which is within the RING finger domain but is not expected to affect zinc coordination <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Saurin1">[29]</xref>. Phenotypes of <italic>slx8-1</italic> are normally only apparent at the restrictive temperature of 35.5°C <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden1">[12]</xref>. Tdp1 is an enzyme largely dedicated to the removal of stalled Top1cc <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pouliot1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Caldecott1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pommier2">[30]</xref>. Whereas either single mutant exhibited wild-type sensitivity, <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells were synergistically sensitive to CPT, even at the <italic>slx8-1</italic> permissive temperature of 25°C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). This result indicates that STUbL and Tdp1 define parallel or non-overlapping pathways for the repair of Top1cc. Importantly, <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells were as sensitive to the replication fork stalling agent hydroxyurea (HU) as the <italic>slx8-1</italic> single mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g001">Figure 1A</xref>), indicating that the genetic interdependency of <italic>slx8-1</italic> and <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> is specific to Top1-dependent lesions.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1001320-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>STUbL mutant <italic>tdp1</italic> <italic>Δ</italic> cells are synergistically sensitive to CPT and have increased spontaneous Top1cc levels.</title>
<p>(A) Serial dilutions of the indicated strains were spotted onto media with or without the indicated drugs. (B) ChIP-qPCR assays of an <italic>nmt41</italic>-inducible Top1-FLAG in the indicated strains, at the subtelomeres of Chr 2 (<italic>telo2R</italic>), the centromeric inner repeats of Chr 2 (<italic>cnt2</italic>), the rDNA (<italic>rDNA2</italic>), and upstream of <italic>mes1</italic> on Chr 1. The data represents the average DNA recovery compared to the input DNA samples with standard deviations from four independent experiments. ChIP-qPCR data of <italic>nmt41</italic>-Top1-FLAG <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells grown in repressing media (+B1) acts as a negative control. Cells were grown at 25°C.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g001" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>To distinguish between stabilization of Top1ccs or a repair defect downstream of Top1 removal in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells, we utilized chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) of Top1 in the absence of formaldehyde crosslinking, followed by quantitative PCR (qPCR) to specifically detect Top1cc. To avoid propagating the sick <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells and possible selection of suppressors, we placed Top1 under the repressible <italic>nmt41</italic> promoter at its endogenous locus and included the FLAG epitope for ChIP analyses. With Top1 expression induced, a significant elevation of Top1cc was detected in the <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant at 3 out of 4 loci tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). As ChIP-qPCR in the absence of formaldehyde crosslinking is a novel application for high-sensitivity detection of Top1cc, we performed key controls to verify its utility. First, the low background signal under conditions that repress Top1 expression support the specificity of the assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g001">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s001">Figure S1A</xref>). Furthermore, to control for the contribution of non-catalytic Top1 DNA-binding to the ChIP-qPCR signal, we generated and expressed a Top1 catalytic mutant (Top1 Tyrosine 773 mutated to Phenylalanine, Top1<sup>Y773F</sup>) to compare with the otherwise identical wild-type FLAG-Top1 allele. Despite equivalent levels of protein expression, Top1<sup>Y773F</sup> generated a weak ChIP-qPCR signal, significantly below that observed for wild-type Top1 in a wild-type background (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s001">Figure S1B and S1C</xref>). Importantly, the Top1<sup>Y773F</sup> ChIP-qPCR signal did not change, irrespective of the genetic background e.g. <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s001">Figure S1B</xref>). In addition, <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ top1<sup>Y773F</sup></italic> triple mutant cells were as insensitive to CPT treatment as <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ top1Δ</italic> triple mutant cells, demonstrating the specificity of the <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> genetic interaction for Top1cc (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s001">Figure S1D and S1E</xref>). Finally, because CPT-induced Top1cc would be expected to reverse rapidly under our assay conditions, we measured Top1cc in the presence or absence of CPT. As expected for reversible CPT-induced Top1cc, we did not detect a significant difference in ChIP-qPCR signal between the CPT treated or control samples (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s001">Figure S1F</xref>). Thus, our controls confirm that in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> double mutants there are increased spontaneous covalent Top1-DNA adducts and furthermore, reveal that these Top1cc are not readily reversible, unlike those induced by CPT.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Top1-Dependent DNA Damage Checkpoint Activation in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> Cells</title>
<p>Next, we wanted to determine whether STUbL activity was also required to prevent Top1cc-dependent DNA damage during unchallenged growth in Tdp1-deficient cells. Whereas single <italic>slx8-1</italic> and <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> mutants exhibit near wild-type growth, the <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant cells are synthetically sick and highly elongated even at the permissive temperature for <italic>slx8-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Strikingly, an <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ top1Δ</italic> triple mutant is wild-type in appearance, demonstrating that the sickness of <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells is Top1-mediated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Consistent with the evolutionary conservation of STUbL function, expression of the human STUbL RNF4 suppresses the <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> phenotype to a similar extent observed with fission yeast Slx8 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s002">Figure S2</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden1">[12]</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pgen-1001320-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>STUbL mutant <italic>tdp1</italic> <italic>Δ</italic> cells activate the DNA damage checkpoint in a Top1-dependent manner.</title>
<p>(A) Upper: graph depicting the average cell length of the indicated strains grown in liquid media at 25°C. The error bars represent 95% confidence intervals between three independent experiments. Lower: representative images of the indicated genotypes are shown. (B) Western blot analysis of whole cell lysates from the indicated strains expressing HA-tagged Chk1 from the endogenous locus (long and short exposures are shown). The uppermost bands (asterisk) in the top panel are phosphorylated Chk1. Ponceau is shown as a loading control.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g002" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The elongated phenotype of <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells is reminiscent of fission yeast following exposure to genotoxic agents, activation of the DNA damage checkpoint and consequent delay in cell cycle progression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Rhind1">[31]</xref>. We therefore assessed checkpoint activation in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells by monitoring Chk1 phosphorylation and also, abrogated the checkpoint by deleting Chk1. Western analysis of Chk1 revealed no detectable checkpoint activation in <italic>slx8-1</italic> single mutant cells, low level activation in <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells and an apparent increase in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). Deleting Chk1 in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells dramatically reduced their length, similar to the effect of deleting Top1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Deletion of an upstream activator of Chk1, Rad3 (ATR), in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells also suppressed cell elongation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). The highly elongated cell phenotype of <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells is thus due to activation of the DNA damage checkpoint, indicating the presence of spontaneous DNA lesions in these cells.</p>
<p>As STUbL degrades certain SUMO conjugated proteins and the <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> phenotype is Top1-dependent, we tested whether STUbL regulates Top1 itself. We first determined that Top1 is sumoylated in a manner dependent on the major E3 SUMO ligase Pli1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s003">Figure S3</xref>). We then assayed Top1 sumoylation in <italic>slx8-1</italic>, <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> and <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells versus wild-type at the permissive temperature, or in <italic>slx8-1</italic> cells at the restrictive temperature. No detectable change in the sumoylation status of Top1 was observed under any of the conditions tested (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s003">Figure S3</xref>). However, we cannot exclude deregulation of a minor fraction of sumoylated Top1, such as that on chromatin in the form of Top1cc.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Spontaneous Top1-Dependent DNA Damage in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> Cells</title>
<p>To assay the presence of DNA damage in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells, we analyzed Rad52 (<italic>S. pombe</italic> Rad22) and RPA (<italic>S. pombe</italic> Rad11) DNA repair foci by live cell fluorescence microscopy in strains that either express YFP-tagged Rad22 or Rad11 from their endogenous loci. Compared to wild-type, both <italic>slx8-1</italic> and <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> exhibited elevated levels of repair foci (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Strikingly, greater than 60% of <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant cells contained Rad22-YFP foci (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). As activation of the G2 DNA damage checkpoint in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> double mutants is Top1-dependent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g002">Figure 2A</xref>) we analyzed the effect of deleting Top1 on the observed DNA repair foci. Cells deleted for Top1 have a characteristic increase in double Rad22-YFP foci that are associated with nucleoli and likely represent the rDNA loci (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Double mutant <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells that exhibit a profound cell cycle delay have elevated levels of large single Rad22-YFP foci as compared to wild-type and the single mutants, which exhibit no checkpoint-dependent delay in cell cycle progression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Notably, <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ top1Δ</italic> triple mutant cells have a similar spectrum of Rad22-YFP foci as the <italic>top1Δ</italic> single mutant and consistently, show no cell cycle delay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g002">Figure 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). This observation suggests that the excess of large single DNA repair foci evident in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells is responsible for checkpoint activation. Furthermore, these results demonstrate that Top1 causes physical DNA damage in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells. The number and type of Rad22-YFP foci in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> was not affected in the <italic>chk1Δ</italic> background (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g003">Figure 3A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pgen-1001320-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>STUbL mutant <italic>tdp1</italic> <italic>Δ</italic> cells exhibit elevated Top1-dependent DNA damage and spontaneous genomic instability.</title>
<p>(A) Upper left: live cell images of the indicated strains expressing Rad22-YFP (Rad52). Upper right: graph depicting the percentage of nuclei containing one, two, or multiple Rad22-YFP foci using live-cell microscopy in the indicated genotypes. Error bars represent the standard deviations from three independent experiments. Base: Table depicting the percentage of nuclei containing one or more Rad22-YFP or Rad11-YFP (RPA) foci in the indicated genotypes. Standard deviations are derived from three independent experiments. (B) Log phase cultures of <italic>slx8-1</italic> and wildtype cells were treated with 40 µM CPT or 0.008% MMS. G2 checkpoint arrest and recovery was monitored through determining the percentage of septated cells at the indicated times. (C) Table depicting frequency of spontaneous mitotic recombination between tandem adenine heteroalleles in the indicated strains. Rates represent the mean of the means, between at least three independent assays per strain. All experiments were incubated at 25°C.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g003" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The hyper-elongated phenotype of <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells may reflect a role for Slx8 (STUbL) in normal resumption of the cell cycle following checkpoint activation. However, when challenged with the DNA damaging agents CPT or methyl methanesulfonate (MMS), <italic>slx8-1</italic> cells showed a wild-type profile of cell cycle arrest (checkpoint activation) and release (checkpoint inactivation; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g003">Figure 3B</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Top1cc Stimulates Recombination in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> Cells</title>
<p>When STUbL activity is attenuated and Tdp1-based repair is absent, our data indicate that spontaneously occurring Top1cc's generate DNA damage and activate the DNA structure checkpoints. Such DNA damage would be anticipated to be recombinogenic. Therefore, we measured recombination rates in the <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant versus the single mutants using an <italic>ade6</italic> heteroallele system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Osman1">[32]</xref>. We observed a 12-fold increase in recombination in the <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant versus 1.5 and 5-fold for <italic>slx8-1</italic> and <italic>tdp1Δ</italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g003">Figure 3C</xref>). Notably, the increased recombination rate in the <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant is Top1-dependent, consistent with the Top1-dependency of excess DNA repair foci in these cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g003">Figure 3A, 3C</xref>). In addition, we found that <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells depend on the major HR factor Rad51 (Rhp51) for viability (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001320-t001">Table 1</xref>). Thus, consistent with the accumulation of HR foci and elevated spontaneous recombination in <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g003">Figure 3A, 3C</xref>), unrepaired Top1cc generates a recombinogenic substrate that requires Rhp51-dependent HR repair.</p>
<table-wrap id="pgen-1001320-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Summary of genetic interactions of <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pgen-1001320-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Strain</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Genetic interaction with <italic>tdp1Δ</italic></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lethal*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>slx8-1</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Synthetic sick*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>swi10Δ</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lethal*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>rhp51Δ</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None (additive upon CPT treatment)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>rhp51Δ slx8-1</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Synthetic lethal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>rad32Δ</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None (additive upon CPT treatment)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>mus81Δ</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None (additive upon CPT treatment)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>rad13Δ</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>uve1Δ</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>uve1Δ rad13Δ</italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Interactions were analyzed by tetrad dissection and/or random spore analysis. Where tested, asterisks denote phenotypes suppressed by <italic>top1Δ</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Functional Intersection of DNA Repair Protein Rad60 with STUbL</title>
<p>We have previously shown that Rad60 physically interacts with STUbL and shares several mutant phenotypes with the STUbL <italic>slx8-1</italic> allele <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden2">[21]</xref>. In particular, a Rad60 mutant unable to interact with the SUMO E2 Ubc9, <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup></italic> makes cells prone to replication fork collapse <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden2">[21]</xref>. Thus, we also tested the dependency of <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup></italic> cells on Tdp1, and found that the <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup></italic> mutation is synthetically lethal with Tdp1 deletion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). Consistent with Top1cc being the major target of Tdp1, the lethality of <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> tdp1Δ</italic> double mutants is suppressed by concomitant deletion of Top1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). We extended this tetrad analysis using a random spore approach that allows many meiotic progeny to be analyzed in one experiment. The genotypes of more than 1000 progeny from a cross between <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> top1Δ</italic> and <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> were analyzed. Importantly, the single mutants, the <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> top1Δ</italic> and <italic>top1Δ tdp1Δ</italic> double mutants, and the <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> tdp1Δ top1Δ</italic> triple mutant were all readily recovered. However, no <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> tdp1Δ</italic> double mutants were identified indicating that <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup></italic> cells require Tdp1 for viability as observed in our tetrad analysis. To further analyze this phenomenon, we used the <italic>nmt41-</italic>Top1 system to regulate Top1 levels, and constructed an <italic>nmt41-top1 rad60<sup>E380R</sup> tdp1Δ</italic> strain under conditions that repress Top1 expression. With Top1 expression repressed, <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> tdp1Δ</italic>, <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup></italic> and <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> strains all grew similarly in the absence or presence of a low dose of CPT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). Notably however, upon induction of Top1, <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> tdp1Δ</italic> cells grew poorly as compared to either single mutant and exhibited synergistic hypersensitivity to CPT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). These data indicate that in either single mutant Top1cc repair is relatively efficient compared to the <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant and that the lethality of <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> tdp1Δ</italic> cells is due to Top1 activity.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1001320-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>The Rad60∶Ubc9 complex and the Nse2 SUMO E3 ligase are essential to protect <italic>tdp1</italic> <italic>Δ</italic> cells from Top1-induced DNA damage.</title>
<p>(A) A representative tetrad dissection is shown from a cross between <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup></italic> and <italic>top1Δ tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant cells. The key depicts the genotypes present, which are denoted by various shapes placed around each colony. Wildtype cells do not have a shape placed around them. (B) Serial dilutions of the indicated strains expressing Top1 under a thiamine repressible promoter were spotted onto control or CPT containing media with (+B1) or without (-B1) thiamine to repress or induce Top1 expression, respectively. All strains were incubated at 32°C. (C) ChIP-qPCR assays of an <italic>nmt41-</italic>inducible Top1-FLAG in the indicated strains at the subtelomeres of Chr 2 (<italic>telo2R</italic>), the centromeric inner repeats of Chr 2 (<italic>cnt2</italic>), the rDNA (<italic>rDNA2</italic>), and upstream of <italic>mes1</italic> on Chr 1. The data represents the average DNA recovery compared to the input DNA samples with standard deviations from at least three independent experiments. ChIP-qPCR data of <italic>nmt41-</italic>Top1-FLAG <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> tdp1Δ</italic> grown in repressed media (+B1) is shown as a negative control. Cells were grown at 25°C. (D) ChIP qPCR assays of the indicated strains as in (C). (E) Cells of the indicated genotype were restruck directly from tetrad dissection plates onto YES media. Cells were incubated at 32°C.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g004" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Increased Top1cc in <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> tdp1Δ</italic> Double Mutant Cells</title>
<p>We next applied the Top1cc ChIP-qPCR assay as for <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells, and detected low levels of Top1cc at the tested loci in wild-type, <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup></italic> and <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> single mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g004">Figure 4C</xref>). Consistent with a defect in the processive repair of Top1cc in the <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant, there was a significant increase in Top1cc at 3 out of the 4 loci tested in these cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g004">Figure 4C</xref>). Specificity of the assay for Top1cc was again confirmed by performing ChIP-qPCR on <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> tdp1Δ</italic> cells in which either the expression of Top1 was repressed, or the catalytic mutant Top1<sup>Y773F</sup> was expressed instead (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g004">Figure 4C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s001">Figure S1B-S1D</xref>). Western analysis shows equal expression of Top1 in these strain backgrounds and the absence of detectable Top1 in the repressed control strain (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s001">Figure S1B-S1D and S1G</xref>). Thus, like STUbL, the Rad60∶Ubc9 complex constitutes a key activity in the mitigation of Top1-mediated DNA damage in a pathway distinct from that initiated by Tdp1.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2g">
<title>Increased Top1cc in Cells Lacking Nse2 SUMO E3 Ligase Activity and Tdp1</title>
<p>Rad60 and STUbL both physically and functionally interact with the Smc5/6 complex, which contains the Nse2 SUMO E3 ligase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Morishita1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden2">[21]</xref>. Given the intimate association of STUbL and Rad60 function with the SUMO pathway, we tested the potential role of Nse2-dependent sumoylation in supporting Top1cc repair in <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells. To do this we combined the SUMO ligase defective Nse2 mutant, <italic>nse2-SA</italic>, with a Tdp1 deletion. Using ChIP-qPCR with <italic>nmt41-</italic>Top1, we detected significantly elevated Top1cc that were specific to the <italic>nse2-SA tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant background (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g004">Figure 4D</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s001">Figure S1B-S1D and S1H</xref>). Furthermore, <italic>nse2-SA tdp1Δ</italic> cells were poorly viable and their growth defects were rescued by deletion of Top1 or expression of the catalytic mutant Top1<sup>Y773F</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g004">Figure 4E</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s001">Figure S1B-S1D</xref>). We did not observe any growth defect of cells lacking both Tdp1 and the SUMO E3 ligase Pli1 (not shown). Thus, a functionally related “hub” of proteins, including STUbL, Rad60 and the SUMO E3 ligase Nse2, is required to suppress Top1-dependent DNA damage when Tdp1 activity is compromised.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2h">
<title>Top1cc Repair Requires Either the Tdp1 or Rad16-Swi10 Pathway</title>
<p>The synthetic sickness and synergistic sensitivity to CPT observed for <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup></italic> or <italic>slx8-1</italic> with <italic>tdp1Δ</italic>, indicates that these factors act in non-redundant pathways for the repair of spontaneous and induced Top1cc. In budding yeast, the Xpf-Ercc1 family endonuclease Rad1-Rad10 initiates a major pathway parallel to Tdp1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Liu1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Vance1">[34]</xref>. We therefore tested the contribution of the fission yeast Xpf-Ercc1 family endonuclease Rad16-Swi10 to the repair of spontaneous Top1cc in the absence of Tdp1. Strikingly, tetrad analyses demonstrated that the <italic>tdp1Δ swi10Δ</italic> double mutant is inviable due to the presence of irreparable Top1-dependent lesions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). This function of Rad16-Swi10 is independent of its nucleotide excision repair (NER) roles as deletion of another component of NER, Rad13 (XPG) shows no genetic interaction with <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001320-t001">Table 1</xref>). Similarly, deletion of the Uve1 DNA repair endonuclease, which incises 5′ to several DNA lesions, is not synthetic sick with <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001320-t001">Table 1</xref>). Hence, the role of Rad16-Swi10 in repairing/preventing Top1-induced DNA-damage is likely attributable to its 3′-flap endonuclease activity as concluded in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Liu1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Vance1">[34]</xref>. It should be noted, in budding yeast there is apparently additional redundancy in the repair of Top1cc over fission yeast, as cells lacking both Tdp1 and the Rad16-Swi10 homologues Rad1-Rad10 are viable, but exhibit a Top1-dependent growth defect <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Vance1">[34]</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1001320-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Tdp1-deficient cells depend on Swi10, but not on homologous recombination repair factors, to prevent Top1-induced cell death.</title>
<p>(A) A representative tetrad dissection is shown of a cross between <italic>swi10Δ</italic> and the <italic>top1Δ tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant. The key depicts the genotypes present, which are denoted by various shapes placed around each colony. Wildtype cells do not have a shape placed around them. (B) Serial dilutions of the indicated strains expressing Top1 under a thiamine repressible promoter were spotted onto control or CPT containing media with (+B1) or without (-B1) thiamine to repress or induce Top1 expression, respectively. (C) Five fold serial dilutions of the indicated strains were spotted onto rich media that contained either no drug (YES), or camptothecin (CPT). Plates were incubated at 32°C.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g005" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>To examine the parallel functions of Tdp1 and Rad16-Swi10 in fission yeast, we employed our <italic>nmt41-</italic>Top1-Flag system to generate a viable <italic>tdp1Δ swi10Δ</italic> double mutant. When Top1 expression was repressed, the <italic>tdp1Δ swi10Δ</italic> double mutant grew slightly slower than either single mutant, likely due to the inability to completely shut off the <italic>nmt41</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). Strikingly, even under Top1-repressed conditions the <italic>tdp1Δ swi10Δ</italic> double mutant was exquisitely sensitive to CPT, whereas the growth of either single mutant was unaffected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g005">Figure 5B</xref>, upper panels). Furthermore, induction of Top1 expression in the absence or presence of CPT rapidly killed the <italic>tdp1Δ swi10Δ</italic> double mutant, but neither single mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g005">Figure 5B</xref>, lower panels). Consistently, elevated Top1cc were detected by ChIP-qPCR in the <italic>swi10Δ tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant versus the single mutants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s004">Figure S4A and S4B</xref>). As expected, the toxicity of Top1 in <italic>tdp1Δ swi10Δ</italic> cells depends on Top1 catalytic activity, as the double mutant is refractory to expression of the Top1<sup>Y773F</sup> mutant (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s004">Figure S4C</xref>). Collectively, these data indicate that Tdp1 and Rad16-Swi10 define the predominant pathways for the initiation of the repair of spontaneous and induced Top1cc.</p>
<p>The fission yeast Rad32 (Mre11)-Rad50-Nbs1 (MRN) complex, which is a central HR factor, has also been implicated in the direct removal of Top1cc <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Hartsuiker1">[35]</xref>. In light of the finding that Tdp1 and Rad16-Swi10 define the essential parallel pathways for Top1cc removal, we believe it is likely that MRN functions mainly downstream of Top1cc removal in its well-defined HR role. Consistent with this hypothesis and distinct from the synthetic lethality/sickness of <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup></italic>, <italic>slx8-1</italic>, <italic>nse2-SA</italic> or <italic>swi10Δ</italic> in combination with <italic>tdp1Δ</italic>, the <italic>rad32Δ tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant grows comparably to the <italic>rad32Δ</italic> single mutant (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001320-t001">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). Similarly, the <italic>rhp51Δ tdp1Δ</italic> and <italic>mus81Δ tdp1Δ</italic> double mutants grow as well as the <italic>rhp51Δ</italic> and <italic>mus81Δ</italic> single mutants, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001320-t001">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). Thus, HR factors including MRN are not essential for the response to spontaneous Top1cc in <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells. We also tested the CPT sensitivity of <italic>rad32Δ tdp1Δ</italic>, <italic>rhp51Δ tdp1Δ</italic> and <italic>mus81Δ tdp1Δ</italic>, which all exhibited a similar degree of additivity over the respective single HR mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). These data are consistent with partially non-overlapping roles of Tdp1 and the HR machinery in CPT-induced Top1cc repair. This could indicate that either Rad51, Mus81 and Rad32 can directly remove Top1cc, or as we suggest, the delayed removal of Top1cc in <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells causes fork collapse, which then engages the HR-dependent replication restart pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Roseaulin1">[22]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2i">
<title>Tdp1 Pathway Protects Cells from Replication-Independent Top1cc Lesions</title>
<p>The preferred pathways for the removal of Top1cc during either transcription or replication are poorly defined <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pommier2">[30]</xref>. In wild-type fission yeast, CPT induces cell cycle arrest at the G2/M boundary in a replication-dependent manner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Wan1">[36]</xref>. This data indicates that the generation of DNA damage checkpoint-visible lesions requires replication forks to collide with Top1ccs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pommier2">[30]</xref>. Interestingly, while testing the acute response of cells lacking either Tdp1 or the Rad16-Swi10 pathways to CPT treatment, we detected a striking difference in growth inhibition of each mutant. The addition of CPT to asynchronous cultures resulted in a rapid growth arrest of <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> but not wild-type or <italic>swi10Δ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). This phenomenon was dependent on both Top1 and the G2/M checkpoint kinase Chk1 (not shown). Both wild-type and <italic>swi10Δ</italic> cells arrested with kinetics consistent with passage through S phase and arrest in the subsequent G2 phase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). Although the growth of unchallenged <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells is indistinguishable from wild-type (our unpublished observations and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-BenHassine1">[27]</xref>), we considered the possibility that <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells may exhibit delayed completion of S phase and thus, addition of CPT would cause first cycle replication-coupled DNA damage and G2/M checkpoint activation. Therefore, we treated asynchronous <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> and wild-type cells with the replication-blocking agent hydroxyurea (HU) and monitored growth. As anticipated, <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> and wild-type cells arrested with the same kinetics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g006">Figure 6B</xref>), which is consistent with the known requirement for passage into S phase for the action of HU in fission yeast <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Boddy3">[37]</xref>. To confirm that Tdp1 mediates replication-independent Top1cc DNA damage repair, we co-treated wild-type and <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells with both HU and CPT and scored growth. Again, <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> but not wild-type cells arrested first-cycle, demonstrating that this is a replication-independent phenomenon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g006">Figure 6C</xref>). Top1 is a known SUMO substrate in several species; however, the role of SUMO modification is unknown. As described earlier, Top1 is SUMO-modified in a manner solely dependent on Pli1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s003">Figure S3</xref>). It has been suggested that sumoylation of Top1 might be a repair response <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Mao1">[38]</xref>, or required for efficient Top1cc formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Horie1">[39]</xref>. Either of these responses might modulate the rapid arrest kinetics of <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells treated with CPT. However, <italic>pli1Δ tdp1Δ</italic> double mutant cells that lack Top1 sumoylation arrest with the same rapid kinetics of <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g006">Figure 6D</xref>), whereas <italic>pli1Δ</italic> cells arrest with wild-type kinetics (data not shown). Overall, these data reveal a previously undefined dominant role for fission yeast Tdp1 in suppressing replication-independent Top1-induced DNA damage.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1001320-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>STUbL facilitates Top1cc repair in the Rad16-Swi10 pathway.</title>
<p>(A) Log phase cultures of the indicated strains were treated with 40 µM CPT and checkpoint arrest and recovery was monitored through determining the percentage of septated cells at the indicated times. (B) As for (A), except cultures were treated with 15 mM HU. (C) As for (B), except cultures were co-treated with 15 mM HU and 40 µM CPT. (D) The indicated strains were treated with CPT and checkpoint arrest and recovery were monitored as in (A-C). In all of these graphs, the asynchronous septation index was set at 100% for that observed at time zero in each strain studied. (E) The indicated strains were serially diluted and spotted on drug-free or CPT rich media, or were UV-irradiated at the indicated dose, and incubated at 25°C.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g006" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2j">
<title>A Potential Role for STUbL in Rad16-Swi10 Initiated Top1cc Repair</title>
<p>Given that STUbL is critical in the absence of Tdp1, we tested whether it acts in the Rad16-Swi10 initiated pathway by generating an <italic>slx8-1 swi10Δ</italic> double mutant and comparing it to either single mutant. In stark contrast to <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic>, the <italic>slx8-1 swi10Δ</italic> double mutant did not exhibit synthetic sickness and was no more sensitive to CPT than the <italic>swi10Δ</italic> single mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g006">Figure 6E</xref>). In keeping with a key role in nucleotide excision repair, Swi10 mutant cells were hypersensitive to UV irradiation, whereas <italic>slx8-1</italic> cells were insensitive to this agent as expected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g006">Figure 6E</xref>). The absence of synergistic CPT sensitivity in <italic>slx8-1 swi10Δ</italic> double mutant cells, coupled with the fact that Tdp1 and Rad16-Swi10 initiate the critical Top1cc repair pathways, is consistent with STUbL facilitating the Rad16-Swi10-dependent pathway. Due to the sickness of <italic>swi10Δ tdp1Δ</italic>, it was not possible to generate a triple mutant with <italic>slx8-1</italic> to perform additional confirmatory epistasis analyses. Further supporting their overlapping functions parallel to those of Tdp1, both <italic>slx8-1</italic> and <italic>swi10Δ</italic> cells arrest with similar delayed (wild-type) kinetics in response to CPT treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g003">Figure 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g006">Figure 6A</xref>).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Suppression and efficient repair of spontaneous DNA damage is crucial to limit genetic changes that can cause cell death, transformation, or accelerate the aging process. Understanding the molecular basis for these defenses is thus vital to improve our current models of disease and aid novel chemotherapeutic strategies. Our collective results show that STUbL, the STUbL-interacting Rad60∶Ubc9 complex, and the Nse2 SUMO E3 ligase are critical for responding to spontaneous Top1cc-mediated DNA lesions.</p>
<p>Detection of Top1cc in <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells that are also hypomorphic for STUbL, Rad60 or Nse2 by ChIP-qPCR reveals important information about the nature of these lesions. Top1cc induced by CPT are normally readily reversible upon drug removal, due to completion of the Top1 catalytic cycle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pommier1">[24]</xref>. This raises the question: why are the Top1cc we detect in the absence of crosslinking or denaturing conditions stable? The answer likely lies in the propensity for Top1 to become irreversibly trapped at lesions in DNA, such as nicks or larger gaps, which are potentially common due to failed or stalled base excision repair (BER) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Lebedeva1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Lebedeva2">[41]</xref>. In addition to our ChIP-qPCR data, our genetic analyses provide strong support for the formation of spontaneous and intrinsically stable Top1ccs. For example, deleting Top1 or mutating the Top1 catalytic site suppresses the synthetic lethality of <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> and <italic>swi10Δ</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g005">Figure 5A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s004">Figure S4C</xref>). Therefore, even in the absence of exogenous agents, Top1 can form stable Top1ccs that require either Tdp1 or Rad16-Swi10-mediated removal to prevent cell death. Thus, ChIP-qPCR is a valuable novel application for the identification of a subset of Top1ccs.</p>
<p>In contrast to budding yeast, we determined that fission yeast lacking both Tdp1 and Rad16-Swi10 (<italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Rad1-Rad10) are inviable due to their inability to repair spontaneous Top1-dependent DNA damage. In budding yeast, Tdp1 or multiple redundant activities, including Rad1-Rad10, initiate Top1cc repair <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Liu1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Vance1">[34]</xref>. Thus, the genetic dependency of fission yeast <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells on Rad60, STUbL and Nse2 indicates that this group of SUMO pathway regulators may facilitate Top1cc processing by Rad16-Swi10.</p>
<p>We showed that the human STUbL, RNF4, is able to functionally substitute the Slx8-based fission yeast STUbL in Top1cc repair. Further supporting evolutionary conservation of the STUbL-dependent Top1cc repair pathway, the strongest negative genetic interactors of <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> in budding yeast are the non-essential STUbL components <italic>slx5Δ</italic> and <italic>slx8Δ</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Collins1">[42]</xref>. Consistent with redundancy in the processing of spontaneous Top1cc in budding yeast, and in keeping with our findings in fission yeast, Tdp1 mutants show no increased dependency on HR factors during unchallenged growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Liu1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Vance1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Collins1">[42]</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g005">Figure 5C</xref>).</p>
<p>The involvement of STUbL, Rad60 and Nse2 in Top1cc repair is intriguing, as each factor is functionally connected with the SUMO pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Perry1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden2">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Potts1">[43]</xref>, and human Top1 is extensively SUMO-conjugated when stalled in the cleavage complex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Mao1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Horie1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Desai1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Kanagasabai1">[45]</xref>. SUMO conjugation to Top1 may affect many processes including directing Top1 subcellular localization, initiating the repair signal or enhancing Top1cc levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Mao1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Horie1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Desai1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Kanagasabai1">[45]</xref>. The human Top1cc is also subject to ubiquitin-dependent proteasomal degradation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Desai2">[46]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Lin1">[48]</xref>, which may allow subsequent access of DNA repair factors to the otherwise occluded Top1 active site tyrosyl-DNA linkage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Interthal1">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Debethune1">[50]</xref>. A recent mass spectrometric study found that mammalian Top1cc was modified extensively with SUMO-2/3 and ubiquitin following CPT treatment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Kanagasabai1">[45]</xref>. Such modifications are consistent with SUMO-modified human Top1cc being targeted by STUbL-dependent ubiquitination prior to proteasomal degradation (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Geoffroy1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Perry1">[7]</xref>). Unlike human Top1, we find that fission yeast Top1 is not as extensively SUMO modified, and this sumoylation is not increased upon CPT treatment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s003">Figure S3</xref> and data not shown). In addition, we have not detected hyper-sumoylated Top1 in fission yeast STUbL mutants or STUbL <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s003">Figure S3</xref>). However, as such a small proportion of total Top1 is sumoylated, functionally important changes could be masked. Because a single unrepaired Top1cc per cell could account for the checkpoint response and death of <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> cells; STUbL-mediated degradation of Top1cc, stimulated by Rad60∶Ubc9 and Nse2 remains a possibility.</p>
<p>It should be noted that cells lacking the predominant Top1 SUMO E3 ligase Pli1 are not sensitive to CPT, whereas those lacking the Nse2 SUMO E3 ligase are hypersensitive to CPT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Watts1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Andrews1">[51]</xref>. Furthermore, Rad60 and STUbL physically and functionally associate with the Smc5–6 complex, of which Nse2 is a core component <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Boddy1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Morishita1">[19]</xref>. Thus, it is conceivable that an Nse2-dependent sumoylation target other than Top1 is at the hub of this Top1cc repair network. In keeping with this, we find that <italic>nse2-SA tdp1Δ</italic> double mutants accumulate Top1cc that cause the observed severe sickness of these cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g004">Figure 4D and 4E</xref>). Determining whether Top1 or other potential STUbL, Rad60∶Ubc9 or Nse2 targets are responsible for the observed repair defect in <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells will require the development of novel genetic and proteomic approaches, which will be the focus of future endeavors.</p>
<p>Conceptually, either Tdp1 or Rad16-Swi10 could process Top1cc encountered during transcription, initiating single strand break repair to heal the resulting lesion without the involvement of HR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g007">Figure 7</xref>). However, if a replication fork encounters a Top1cc and collapses, HR is required to restart replication. In <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells, the number of lesions encountered during replication may increase due to defective Top1cc removal during transcription, and this could explain the observed additive CPT sensitivity of <italic>tdp1Δ rhp51Δ</italic> (and other HR factor) double mutants. This is supported by our data indicating that in fission yeast, Tdp1 is the predominant replication-independent Top1cc repair activity, most likely acting in a transcription-coupled manner. However, as <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> cells are dependent on Rad16-Swi10, but not HR factors for viability, Rad16-Swi10 must be able to initiate HR-independent Top1cc repair. Supporting replication-independent Tdp1 functions, Tdp1 mutation can cause degeneration of post-mitotic cells such as neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Katyal1">[52]</xref>. In the absence of both Tdp1 and Rad16-Swi10, the burden of unrepaired Top1cc leads to lethality. In this scenario, neither single strand break repair nor HR can proceed. In light of the well-characterized role of Rad16-Swi10 in budding yeast (Rad1-Rad10) as a 3′ flap endonuclease, we propose that in <italic>tdp1Δ swi10Δ</italic> cells HR cannot engage due to the Top1cc blocking the DNA 3′ terminus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001320-g007">Figure 7</xref>). Within our model, STUbL, Rad60∶Ubc9 and Nse2 facilitate Top1cc removal by Rad16-Swi10. Our data does not exclude the possibility that STUbL, Rad60∶Ubc9 and Nse2 may also act to suppress genomic lesions that favor stable Top1cc formation. Other factors may act in the removal of Top1cc from 3′ termini such as MRN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Hartsuiker1">[35]</xref>; however, in light of the synthetic lethality of <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> and <italic>swi10Δ,</italic> as opposed to the observed epistasis between <italic>tdp1Δ</italic> and <italic>rad32Δ</italic> during normal growth, such contributions appear minor.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1001320-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Model depicting the parallel actions of Tdp1 and Rad16-Swi10 in Top1cc removal, potentially facilitated by STUbL, Rad60∶Ubc9, and Nse2.</title>
<p>In wild-type cells, Tdp1 efficiently removes Top1cc (black circle), leaving a substrate for single strand break repair (SSBR) or homologous recombination (HR). In the absence of Tdp1, Top1cc is converted into a checkpoint visible lesion (shaded oval) that arrests cell cycle progression in a Chk1-dependent manner. Top1cc can ultimately be removed by Rad16-Swi10, a process that may be facilitated by STUbL, Rad60∶Ubc9 and Nse2. SSBR or HR can then heal the resulting lesion.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.g007" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>By combining genetic, physical and mutational analyses, we here identify a unifying and critical role for STUbL, Rad60∶Ubc9 and Nse2 in DNA repair. While these factors have additional non-overlapping roles (indicated by the Top1-<italic>independent</italic> lethality of the <italic>rad60<sup>E380R</sup> slx8-1</italic> double mutant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden2">[21]</xref>), they apparently collaborate in processing potentially lethal or genome destabilizing spontaneous Top1cc lesions. High-throughput observations in budding yeast (see above) and the RNF4 rescue-experiment indicate that the pathways we have defined in fission yeast are likely to contribute to Top1cc repair in other species. Top1 is an important chemotherapeutic target but acquired resistance to chemotherapy, via up regulation of repair factors or reduction in Top1 levels, is a common cause of therapeutic failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pommier1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pommier2">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Liu2">[53]</xref> and refs. therein). Thus, our data implicating the evolutionarily conserved STUbL, Nse2 and Rad60∶Ubc9 factors in Top1cc repair may aid therapeutic strategies. Currently, the presented results characterize a critical STUbL-Rad60-Nse2 DNA repair function acting parallel to Tdp1, potentially in a pathway initiated by the Xpf-Ercc1 family DNA endonuclease Rad16-Swi10. More broadly, these STUbL-Rad60-Nse2 results provide key knowledge on how cells deal with the genotoxic effects of spontaneous Top1-induced DNA damage.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>General Yeast Techniques and Drug Treatments</title>
<p>Standard yeast methods were performed as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Moreno1">[54]</xref>. Top1 was N-terminally tagged at its endogenous locus using <italic>nmt41-3FLAG</italic>, as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Noguchi1">[55]</xref>. The Top1 catalytic mutant was generated by site directed mutagenesis (Quikchange; Stratagene). Drugs were obtained from Sigma–Aldrich. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1001320.s005">Table S1</xref> lists the strains used in this study.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Microscopy</title>
<p>Cells were either grown on solid media at 25°C for 3 days and resuspended in 1 x PBS before imaging, or cultured in supplemented minimal media to mid-log phase at 25°C, and analyzed with a Nikon Eclipse E800 microscope equipped with a Photometrics Quantix charge-coupled device camera. Images were analyzed with ImageJ (NIH, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/" xlink:type="simple">http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>). For cell length comparisons at least 100 cells per strain were measured. Data represents the average cell length in units defined by ImageJ with 95% confidence intervals. For indirect fluorescence at least 300 cells were analyzed for each strain. Data represents the average of three independent experiments with standard deviations.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Determination of Septation Index</title>
<p>Log phase cultures (OD<sub>600</sub> of ∼0.3–0.4) were treated with 40 µM CPT, 0.008% MMS, or 15 mM HU. Septation was monitored using a Zeiss Axioscope 20. After 4 h, MMS was washed out and cells were transferred to medium without drug to allow recovery. For comparison between the <italic>slx8-1</italic> and wild type strain a minimum of 175 cells were scored for each data point. Data represents the average of four experiments with standard deviations.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4d">
<title><italic>S. pombe</italic> Protein Lysate Preparation and Immunoblotting</title>
<p>Cultures were grown at the permissive temperature (25°C) for the <italic>slx8-1</italic> allele to mid-log phase for all experiments (except where otherwise indicated). Top1-FLAG cells were cultured overnight in minimal media containing thiamine. Cultures were then washed and diluted into minimal media either with or without thiamine, grown for an additional 48 h and harvested. Cells were lysed in 8 M Urea, 50 mM Tris pH 8, 50 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 300mM NaCl, and Complete Protease Inhibitors EDTA-free (Roche, IN). Chk1-HA cells were grown over night in rich media, lysed in 50 mM Tris pH 8, 150 mM NaCl, 2.5 mM EDTA, 10% glycerol, 0.2% Nonidet P-40, 90 mM NaF, Complete Protease Inhibitors EDTA-free, and 5 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF). Protein samples were separated by SDS-PAGE on 4-20% Tris-glycine gels (Invitrogen, CA) for Top1-FLAG and 8% acrylamide gels (99%) for Chk1-HA. Immunoblotting was performed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Prudden2">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Boddy2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pebernard2">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pebernard3">[57]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4e">
<title>Detection of Sumoylated Top1</title>
<p>Top1-TAP cells were grown over night at either 30°C, or at the permissive temperature (25°C), then cultured at the semi-permissive temperature (30°C) on day two, and shifted to the restrictive temperature (36°C) for 6 h on day three, to inactivate the <italic>slx8-1</italic> allele. Top1-TAP cells were lysed using the buffer described above for Chk1-HA, supplemented with 60 mM <italic>N</italic>-ethyl maleimide (NEM) that lacked glycerol. Protein extracts were incubated with IgG-Sepharose beads (GE healthcare) at 4°C for 2 h, washed and separated by SDS-PAGE on 4-8% Tris-glycine gels (Expedeon, CA) followed by western blotting. For denaturing Nickel pull downs, Top1-Myc and 6His-Pmt3 expressing strains were grown overnight in rich media at the permissive temperature (25°C). Cells were lysed in 8 M Urea buffer described above for Top1-FLAG, supplemented with 60 mM NEM. Equal amounts of total protein per strain were incubated with Ni-NTA Superflow beads (Qiagen) for 1.5 hrs rotating at room temperature. Beads were washed and analyzed by SDS-PAGE on 4–8% Tris-glycine gels followed by anti-Myc western blotting.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4f">
<title>Chromatin Immunoprecipitation</title>
<p>ChIP experiments were essentially performed as published <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Pebernard3">[57]</xref> with minor modifications. In order to capture covalent Top1-DNA complexes, cells were not treated with formaldehyde. 4.5×10<sup>8</sup> cells were lysed by bead beating in buffer L (50 mM HEPES KOH pH 7.4, 140 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 0.1% Triton, 0.1% Na-Deoxycholate, Complete Protease Inhibitors EDTA-free, and 5 mM PMSF). After bead beating the Triton-X concentration of the buffer was brought to 1%. DNA was sonicated to 500–800 bp using the Sonicator 3000 (Misonix, NY) equipped with a cup horn for 3×20 seconds at power level 10, in 1 minute intervals. Protein extracts were normalized to the lowest protein concentration (1–2 mgs final) between strains. Lysates were then incubated with Protein-G Dynabeads (Invitrogen, CA) pre-bound with FLAG antibodies (M2, F1804, Sigma). Following a 2 h pull-down at 4°C, immunocomplexes were washed 3 times in buffer L (1% Triton-X), 2 times in Buffer H (buffer L with 500 mM NaCl), 2 times in buffer D (10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8, 250 mM LiCl, 1 mM EDTA, 0.5% NP40, 0.5% Na-deoxycholate), and one time in 10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8, 1 mM EDTA. The DNA was eluted off the Dynabeads by heating in 10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8, 10 mM EDTA, at 70°C for 15 minutes. The protein was digested with 0.5 mg/ml final concentration Proteinase K (Invitrogen, CA) for 2 h at 50°C. The DNA was purified using the PureLink PCR purification Kit (Invitrogen, CA). For each experiment, the percentage DNA recovery of ChIP samples relative to the DNA amount in the input was averaged over triplicate qPCR measurements. Data represents the average of at least three independent experiments with standard deviations. Primer sequences for <italic>cnt2, telo2R, mes1</italic> and <italic>rDNA2</italic> have been published <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Hayashi1">[58]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Yokobayashi1">[59]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4g">
<title>Determination of spontaneous recombination rates</title>
<p>Spontaneous mitotic recombination rates between Adenine heteroalleles were determined by fluctuation tests as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Osman1">[32]</xref>, using the <italic>ade6-L469/pUC8/ura4<sup>+</sup>/ade6-M375</italic> heteroallele system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1001320-Osman2">[60]</xref>. For each assay, four independent colonies were analyzed. Each assay was repeated independently at least three times. Assays were performed at 25°C.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1001320.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.s001" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p>Top1-FLAG expression and functional analysis of strains used for ChIP-qPCR assays. (A) Western blot analysis of whole cell lysates from the indicated strains immunoblotted with anti-FLAG antiserum. The strains were cultured in supplemented minimal media that either induced (-B1), or repressed (+B1) <italic>nmt41</italic>-Top1-FLAG expression. Cells were induced at 25°C for 48 hours prior to harvesting. Top1-FLAG is similarly expressed in wt, <italic>slx8-1</italic>, and <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> strains. (B) ChIP-qPCR analysis of the indicated strains expressing either <italic>nmt41-</italic>Top1-FLAG (<italic>wildtype</italic>) or a catalytically inactive <italic>nmt41-top1Y773F</italic>-FLAG mutant. The data represents the average DNA recovery compared to the input DNA samples with standard deviations from three independent experiments when <italic>nmt41-</italic>Top1-FLAG is induced. Cells were induced at 25°C for 48 hours prior to harvesting. (C) Western blot analysis of whole cell lysates from the indicated strains immunoblotted with anti-FLAG antiserum. The strains used for the ChIP analysis described in (B) were analysed; each strain shows similar expression of the <italic>top1Y773F</italic> construct compared to wildtype Top1-FLAG. (D) Five fold serial dilutions of the indicated strains were spotted onto media that induced expression of the <italic>nmt</italic> constructs, which contained either no drug, or 150 µM CPT. Plates were incubated at 32°C. (E) Five fold serial dilutions of the indicated strains were spotted onto media that induced expression of the <italic>nmt</italic> constructs, which contained either no drug, or the indicated concentration of CPT. Plates were incubated at 25°C. (F) ChIP-qPCR analysis of Top1-FLAG expressing wildtype cells, either treated or not with 50 µM CPT for 1 hour prior to harvesting. The data represents the average DNA recovery compared to the input DNA samples with standard deviations from three independent experiments when <italic>nmt41-</italic>Top1-FLAG was induced. Cells were induced at 25°C for 48 hours prior CPT treatment and harvesting. (G) and (H) Top1-FLAG expression analysis as described in (A) repeated for the indicated strains, except in (G) an untagged wildtype control is also shown.</p>
<p>(1.08 MB TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1001320.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.s002" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p>Expression of <italic>pSlx8</italic> and Human <italic>pRNF4</italic> suppresses the <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> phenotype. <italic>The slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic>double mutants were transformed with vectors expressing Slx8, human RNF4, or an empty Glutathione-S-transferase (GST) control, and then grown at 25°C, either in inducing conditions (supplemented minimal media without thiamine: left panels) or in rich media to repress expression and allow vector loss (YES: right panels). Cells were cultured for 20 hours until reaching mid-log phase before photographing. The elongated phenotype of <italic>slx8-1 tdp1Δ</italic> is rescued when <italic>pSlx8</italic> and <italic>pRNF4</italic> are present, and induced.</p>
<p>(3.59 MB TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1001320.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.s003" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p>Pli1-dependent Top1 SUMO modification appears unchanged in the <italic>slx8-1</italic> background. (A) Representative anti-TAP western blots are shown following IgG pulldowns from the indicated strains expressing TAP-tagged Top1 from the endogenous locus. The sumoylated forms of Top1-TAP are indicated by asterisks. Left: expression of a vector containing GFP-tagged Pmt3 retards gel migration of the Top1-SUMO species by the amount expected for a monosumoylated Top1-SUMO-GFP. Center: Top1 monosumoylation is undetectable in <italic>pli1Δ</italic> cells. Right: Top1 monosumoylation appears unaffected by STUbL inactivation. All strains in this experiment were incubated at the restrictive temperature for <italic>slx8-1</italic> (36°C). (B) Western blot analysis of whole cell lysates from the indicated strains expressing Top1-Myc ± 6His-Pmt3 from their endogenous loci, after denaturing Ni-NTA pulldowns (long and short exposures are shown). The monosumoylated species of Top1 is indicated (Top1-Pmt3). All experiments were performed at 25°C.</p>
<p>(3.01 MB TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1001320.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.s004" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p><italic>swi10Δ tdp1Δ</italic> have elevated levels of Top1ccs but are not sensitive to oxidative damage caused by H2O2. (A) ChIP-qPCR assay of the indicated strains. The data represents the average DNA recovery compared to the input DNA samples with standard deviations from at least three independent experiments when <italic>nmt41-</italic>Top1-FLAG is induced. ChIP-qPCR data of <italic>nmt41-</italic>Top1-FLAG <italic>swi10Δ tdp1Δ</italic> grown in repressed media (+B1) is shown as a negative control. Cells were induced at 25°C for 48 hours prior to harvesting. (B) Anti-FLAG western blot analysis of the strains used for the ChIP analysis shown in (A). (C) Cells of the indicated genotype were restruck onto plates that either repressed (+B1), or induced expression of the <italic>nmt</italic> promoter in the presence or absence of the indicated concentration of CPT. Cells were cultured at 32°C. (D) Five fold serial dilutions of the indicated strains were spotted onto media, which either contained no drug, H<sub>2</sub>0<sub>2</sub>, or camptothecin (CPT) at the indicated concentrations. Plates were incubated at 32°C. No profound sensitivity of <italic>swi10Δ tdp1Δ top1Δ</italic> cells as compared to wild-type or <italic>spc1Δ</italic> cells was observed. This was anticipated due to the known robust and stress-inducible catalase activity in fission yeast, and the key role of Apn2 phosphodiesterase in processing the 3′ blocked end generated by Nth1-dependent AP site incision e.g. [Hida Y., Ikeda S. (2008) Base excision repair of oxidative DNA damage in a catalase-deficient mutant of schizosaccharomyces pombe. Genes and Environment 30, 86–91. Kanamitsu K., Ikeda S. (2010) Early Steps in the DNA Base Excision Repair Pathway of a Fission Yeast Schizosaccharomyces pombe. J Nucleic Acids 2010].</p>
<p>(5.73 MB TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pgen.1001320.s005" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001320.s005" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><italic>S. pombe</italic> strains used during this study.</p>
<p>(0.08 MB DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Eishi Noguchi for plasmids. We also thank The Scripps Cell Cycle Group for support and encouragement and Paul Russell (TSRI) for yeast strains and use of the qPCR cycler.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Schleker1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schleker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gasser</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Posttranslational modifications of repair factors and histones in the cellular response to stalled replication forks.</article-title>             <source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>1089</fpage>             <lpage>1100</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Ulrich1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ulrich</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Mutual interactions between the SUMO and ubiquitin systems: a plea of no contest.</article-title>             <source>Trends Cell Biol</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>525</fpage>             <lpage>532</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Kerscher1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kerscher</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Felberbaum</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hochstrasser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Modification of proteins by ubiquitin and ubiquitin-like proteins.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>159</fpage>             <lpage>180</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Watts1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Skilton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Trickey</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>The role of Schizosaccharomyces pombe SUMO ligases in genome stability.</article-title>             <source>Biochem Soc Trans</source>             <volume>35</volume>             <fpage>1379</fpage>             <lpage>1384</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Xhemalce1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xhemalce</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Riising</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dejean</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arcangioli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Role of SUMO in the dynamics of telomere maintenance in fission yeast.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>893</fpage>             <lpage>898</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Geoffroy1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Geoffroy</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>An additional role for SUMO in ubiquitin-mediated proteolysis.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>564</fpage>             <lpage>568</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Perry1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tainer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>A SIM-ultaneous role for SUMO and ubiquitin.</article-title>             <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>201</fpage>             <lpage>208</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Hunter1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Crosstalk between the SUMO and ubiquitin pathways.</article-title>             <source>Ernst Schering Found Symp Proc</source>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>16</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Nagai1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dubrana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai-Pflugfelder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Functional targeting of DNA damage to a nuclear pore-associated SUMO-dependent ubiquitin ligase.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>322</volume>             <fpage>597</fpage>             <lpage>602</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Putnam1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Specific pathways prevent duplication-mediated genome rearrangements.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>460</volume>             <fpage>984</fpage>             <lpage>989</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Mullen1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kaliraman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brill</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Requirement for three novel protein complexes in the absence of the Sgs1 DNA helicase in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>157</volume>             <fpage>103</fpage>             <lpage>118</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Prudden1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prudden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pebernard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Raffa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Slavin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>SUMO-targeted ubiquitin ligases in genome stability.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>4089</fpage>             <lpage>4101</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Sun1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Leverson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Conserved function of RNF4 family proteins in eukaryotes: targeting a ubiquitin ligase to SUMOylated proteins.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>4102</fpage>             <lpage>4112</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Zhang1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Suppression of genomic instability by SLX5 and SLX8 in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</article-title>             <source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>336</fpage>             <lpage>346</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Burgess1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lisby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>The Slx5-Slx8 complex affects sumoylation of DNA repair proteins and negatively regulates recombination.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>27</volume>             <fpage>6153</fpage>             <lpage>6162</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Lee1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>A new SUMO ligase in the DNA damage response.</article-title>             <source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>138</fpage>             <lpage>141</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Pebernard1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pebernard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wohlschlegel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>JR</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>The Nse5-Nse6 dimer mediates DNA repair roles of the Smc5-Smc6 complex.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>1617</fpage>             <lpage>1630</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Boddy1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shanahan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Girona</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Replication checkpoint kinase Cds1 regulates recombinational repair protein Rad60.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>5939</fpage>             <lpage>5946</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Morishita1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morishita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tsutsui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shinagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>The Schizosaccharomyces pombe rad60 Gene Is Essential for Repairing Double-Strand DNA Breaks Spontaneously Occurring during Replication and Induced by DNA-Damaging Agents.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>3537</fpage>             <lpage>3548</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Novatchkova1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Novatchkova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bachmair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenhaber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenhaber</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Proteins with two SUMO-like domains in chromatin-associated complexes: the RENi (Rad60-Esc2-NIP45) family.</article-title>             <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>22</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Prudden2"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prudden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arvai</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tainer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Molecular mimicry of SUMO promotes DNA repair.</article-title>             <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>509</fpage>             <lpage>516</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Roseaulin1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roseaulin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tsutsui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Mus81 is essential for sister chromatid recombination at broken replication forks.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>27</volume>             <fpage>1378</fpage>             <lpage>1387</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Boddy2"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Girona</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shanahan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Interthal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Heyer</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Damage tolerance protein Mus81 associates with the FHA1 domain of checkpoint kinase Cds1.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>20</volume>             <fpage>8758</fpage>             <lpage>8766</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Pommier1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pommier</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Topoisomerase I inhibitors: camptothecins and beyond.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>789</fpage>             <lpage>802</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Pouliot1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pouliot</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Yeast gene for a Tyr-DNA phosphodiesterase that repairs topoisomerase I complexes.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>286</volume>             <fpage>552</fpage>             <lpage>555</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Caldecott1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Caldecott</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Single-strand break repair and genetic disease.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>619</fpage>             <lpage>631</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-BenHassine1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Hassine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arcangioli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Tdp1 protects against oxidative DNA damage in non-dividing fission yeast.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>28</volume>             <fpage>632</fpage>             <lpage>640</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Bahmed1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bahmed</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nitiss</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nitiss</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Yeast Tdp1 regulates the fidelity of nonhomologous end joining.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>107</volume>             <fpage>4057</fpage>             <lpage>4062</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Saurin1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saurin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borden</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Freemont</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Does this have a familiar RING?</article-title>             <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>208</fpage>             <lpage>214</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Pommier2"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pommier</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barcelo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sordet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jobson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Repair of topoisomerase I-mediated DNA damage.</article-title>             <source>Prog Nucleic Acid Res Mol Biol</source>             <volume>81</volume>             <fpage>179</fpage>             <lpage>229</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Rhind1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rhind</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Chk1 and Cds1: linchpins of the DNA damage and replication checkpoint pathways.</article-title>             <source>J Cell Sci</source>             <volume>113</volume>             <issue>Pt 22</issue>             <fpage>3889</fpage>             <lpage>3896</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Osman1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Adriance</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McCready</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>The genetic control of spontaneous and UV-induced mitotic intrachromosomal recombination in the fission yeast Schizosaccharomyces pombe.</article-title>             <source>Curr Genet</source>             <volume>38</volume>             <fpage>113</fpage>             <lpage>125</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Liu1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pouliot</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Repair of topoisomerase I covalent complexes in the absence of the tyrosyl-DNA phosphodiesterase Tdp1.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>99</volume>             <fpage>14970</fpage>             <lpage>14975</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Vance1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Yeast Tdp1 and Rad1-Rad10 function as redundant pathways for repairing Top1 replicative damage.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>99</volume>             <fpage>13669</fpage>             <lpage>13674</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Hartsuiker1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hartsuiker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Distinct requirements for the Rad32(Mre11) nuclease and Ctp1(CtIP) in the removal of covalently bound topoisomerase I and II from DNA.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>117</fpage>             <lpage>123</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Wan1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Capasso</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Walworth</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>The topoisomerase I poison camptothecin generates a Chk1-dependent DNA damage checkpoint signal in fission yeast.</article-title>             <source>Yeast</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>821</fpage>             <lpage>828</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Boddy3"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Furnari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mondesert</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Replication checkpoint enforced by kinases Cds1 and Chk1.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>280</volume>             <fpage>909</fpage>             <lpage>912</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Mao1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>SUMO-1 conjugation to topoisomerase I: A possible repair response to topoisomerase-mediated DNA damage.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>97</volume>             <fpage>4046</fpage>             <lpage>4051</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Horie1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tomida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yasugi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>SUMO-1 conjugation to intact DNA topoisomerase I amplifies cleavable complex formation induced by camptothecin.</article-title>             <source>Oncogene</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>7913</fpage>             <lpage>7922</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Lebedeva1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lebedeva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Auffret Vander Kemp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bjornsti</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lavrik</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boiteux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Trapping of DNA topoisomerase I on nick-containing DNA in cell free extracts of Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</article-title>             <source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>799</fpage>             <lpage>809</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Lebedeva2"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lebedeva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rechkunova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boiteux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lavrik</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Trapping of human DNA topoisomerase I by DNA structures mimicking intermediates of DNA repair.</article-title>             <source>IUBMB Life</source>             <volume>60</volume>             <fpage>130</fpage>             <lpage>134</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Collins1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maas</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roguev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fillingham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Functional dissection of protein complexes involved in yeast chromosome biology using a genetic interaction map.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>446</volume>             <fpage>806</fpage>             <lpage>810</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Potts1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Potts</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>The Yin and Yang of the MMS21-SMC5/6 SUMO ligase complex in homologous recombination.</article-title>             <source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>499</fpage>             <lpage>506</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Desai1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Ubiquitin, SUMO-1, and UCRP in camptothecin sensitivity and resistance.</article-title>             <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>             <volume>922</volume>             <fpage>306</fpage>             <lpage>308</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Kanagasabai1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kanagasabai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Salama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Ubiquitin-family modifications of topoisomerase I in camptothecin-treated human breast cancer cells.</article-title>             <source>Biochemistry</source>             <volume>48</volume>             <fpage>3176</fpage>             <lpage>3185</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Desai2"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Bauman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Ubiquitin/26S proteasome-mediated degradation of topoisomerase I as a resistance mechanism to camptothecin in tumor cells.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Res</source>             <volume>61</volume>             <fpage>5926</fpage>             <lpage>5932</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Desai3"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vazquez-Abad</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>D'Arpa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Ubiquitin-dependent destruction of topoisomerase I is stimulated by the antitumor drug camptothecin.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>272</volume>             <fpage>24159</fpage>             <lpage>24164</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Lin1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ban</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>A ubiquitin-proteasome pathway for the repair of topoisomerase I-DNA covalent complexes.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>283</volume>             <fpage>21074</fpage>             <lpage>21083</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Interthal1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Interthal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Champoux</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Human Tdp1 cleaves a broad spectrum of substrates, including phosphoamide linkages.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>280</volume>             <fpage>36518</fpage>             <lpage>36528</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Debethune1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Debethune</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kohlhagen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grandas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pommier</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Processing of nucleopeptides mimicking the topoisomerase I-DNA covalent complex by tyrosyl-DNA phosphodiesterase.</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>             <volume>30</volume>             <fpage>1198</fpage>             <lpage>1204</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Andrews1"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Palecek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sergeant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Nse2, a component of the Smc5-6 complex, is a SUMO ligase required for the response to DNA damage.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>185</fpage>             <lpage>196</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Katyal1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Katyal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>el-Khamisy</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>TDP1 facilitates chromosomal single-strand break repair in neurons and is neuroprotective in vivo.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>4720</fpage>             <lpage>4731</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Liu2"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Begum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sidransky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Westra</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Increased expression and activity of repair genes TDP1 and XPF in non-small cell lung cancer.</article-title>             <source>Lung Cancer</source>             <volume>55</volume>             <fpage>303</fpage>             <lpage>311</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Moreno1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Klar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Molecular genetic analysis of fission yeast Schizosaccharomyces pombe.</article-title>             <source>Methods Enzymol</source>             <volume>194</volume>             <fpage>795</fpage>             <lpage>823</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Noguchi1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garabedian</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>A vector system for genomic FLAG epitope-tagging in Schizosaccharomyces pombe.</article-title>             <source>Biotechnol J</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>1280</fpage>             <lpage>1285</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Pebernard2"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pebernard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlova</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>JR</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Nse1, Nse2, and a novel subunit of the Smc5-Smc6 complex, Nse3, play a crucial role in meiosis.</article-title>             <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>4866</fpage>             <lpage>4876</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Pebernard3"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pebernard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Head</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Localization of Smc5/6 to centromeres and telomeres requires heterochromatin and SUMO, respectively.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>27</volume>             <fpage>3011</fpage>             <lpage>3023</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Hayashi1"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Katou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tazumi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Genome-wide localization of pre-RC sites and identification of replication origins in fission yeast.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>1327</fpage>             <lpage>1339</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Yokobayashi1"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yokobayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Cohesins determine the attachment manner of kinetochores to spindle microtubules at meiosis I in fission yeast.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>3965</fpage>             <lpage>3973</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pgen.1001320-Osman2"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fortunato</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Double-strand break-induced mitotic intrachromosomal recombination in the fission yeast Schizosaccharomyces pombe.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>142</volume>             <fpage>341</fpage>             <lpage>357</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
</ref-list>

</back>
</article>