<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PGENETICS-D-11-02409</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Developmental biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cell differentiation</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genetics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal genetics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Model organisms</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal models</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Mouse</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Endocrinology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Endocrine physiology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Endocrine glands</subject>
                <subject>Hormones</subject>
                <subject>Parathyroid</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Diabetes and Endocrinology</subject>
          <subject>Developmental Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Deletion of PTH Rescues Skeletal Abnormalities and High Osteopontin Levels in <italic>Klotho</italic><sup>−/−</sup> Mice</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Rescued Osteomalacia and Opn Levels in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> Mice</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Yuan</surname>
            <given-names>Quan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sato</surname>
            <given-names>Tadatoshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Densmore</surname>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Saito</surname>
            <given-names>Hiroaki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Schüler</surname>
            <given-names>Christiane</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Erben</surname>
            <given-names>Reinhold G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Lanske</surname>
            <given-names>Beate</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Developmental Biology, Harvard School of Dental Medicine, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Oral Diseases, Sichuan University, Chengdu, China</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Oral Medicine, Infection, and Immunity, Harvard School of Dental Medicine, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Institute of Physiology, Pathophysiology, and Biophysics, Department of Biomedical Sciences, University of Veterinary Medicine, Vienna, Austria</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>White</surname>
            <given-names>Kenneth E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Indiana University School of Medicine, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">beate_lanske@hsdm.harvard.edu</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: QY BL. Performed the experiments: QY TS MD HS CS. Analyzed the data: QY TS RGE BL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: TS CS. Wrote the paper: QY MD BL.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e1002726</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yuan et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>Maintenance of normal mineral ion homeostasis is crucial for many biological activities, including proper mineralization of the skeleton. Parathyroid hormone (PTH), Klotho, and FGF23 have been shown to act as key regulators of serum calcium and phosphate homeostasis through a complex feedback mechanism. The phenotypes of <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and <italic>Klotho<sup>−/−</sup></italic> (<italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>) mice are very similar and include hypercalcemia, hyperphosphatemia, hypervitaminosis D, suppressed PTH levels, and severe osteomalacia/osteoidosis. We recently reported that complete ablation of PTH from <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice ameliorated the phenotype in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup>/PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice by suppressing serum vitamin D and calcium levels. The severe osteomalacia in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, however, persisted, suggesting that a different mechanism is responsible for this mineralization defect. In the current study, we demonstrate that deletion of PTH from <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> (<italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup>/PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> or <italic>DKO</italic>) mice corrects the abnormal skeletal phenotype. Bone turnover markers are restored to wild-type levels; and, more importantly, the skeletal mineralization defect is completely rescued in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup>/PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. Interestingly, the correction of the osteomalacia is accompanied by a reduction in the high levels of osteopontin (Opn) in bone and serum. Such a reduction in Opn levels could not be observed in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup>/PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, and these mice showed sustained osteomalacia. This significant <italic>in vivo</italic> finding is corroborated by <italic>in vitro</italic> studies using calvarial osteoblast cultures that show normalized Opn expression and rescued mineralization in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup>/PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. Moreover, continuous PTH infusion of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice significantly increased Opn levels and osteoid volume, and decreased trabecular bone volume. In summary, our results demonstrate for the first time that PTH directly impacts the mineralization disorders and skeletal deformities of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>, but not of <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, possibly by regulating Opn expression. These are significant new perceptions into the role of PTH in skeletal and disease processes and suggest FGF23-independent interactions of PTH with Klotho.</p>
      </abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary">
        <title>Author Summary</title>
        <p>Maintenance of normal mineral ion homeostasis is crucial for many biological activities, including proper mineralization of the skeleton. PTH, Klotho, and FGF23 are the key regulators of blood mineral ion homeostasis. Klotho is a type-I membrane protein and has been identified as cofactor required for FGF23 to bind and activate its receptor. Loss of either Klotho or Fgf23 activity results in a similar abnormal phenotype, including severe defects in skeletal mineralization and alterations in mineral ion balance. Here we describe a new mouse model in which we eliminated PTH from <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, and we can show that the skeletal mineralization defect was completely rescued in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>/<italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice and that this phenomenon was accompanied by a reduction in the high levels of osteopontin in bone and serum. We also present additional data showing that continuous infusion of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice with PTH results in an elevation in Opn levels and subsequently increased osteoid volume. Interestingly, this result differs from our previous report in which we describe that the osteomalacia and the high Opn levels in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic>/<italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice persisted. Our finding suggests that PTH, possibly by regulating osteopontin, is responsible for the skeletal mineralization defect in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, but not in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by the NIH/NIDDK R01-073944 (BL), Dean's Scholarship, and the Harvard School of Dental Medicine (QY). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Maintaining normal mineral ion homeostasis is crucial for essential biological activities that include but are not limited to energy metabolism, signaling activities, and normal skeletal growth, development and function. Blood calcium and phosphate levels are determined by counterbalance between absorption from the intestine, mobilization from bone and excretion from the kidney into urine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Renkema1">[1]</xref>. This complex process is regulated by several endocrine factors, including parathyroid hormone (PTH), FGF23 and active Vitamin D, which have been widely studied <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Dusso1">[2]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Lee1">[5]</xref>. More recently, another protein, Klotho, has been suggested to have an important role in regulating calcium and phosphate homeostasis.</p>
      <p>Klotho is a type-I membrane protein mainly expressed in kidneys, parathyroid glands, and the choroid plexus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Li1">[6]</xref>. It is also related to β-glucosidases and is found in a soluble form in blood and cerebrospinal fluid <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Matsumura1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-ShirakiIida1">[8]</xref>. Klotho forms a complex with the FGF receptor 1c (FGFR1c), thereby converting this canonical FGF receptor into a receptor specific for FGF23 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Urakawa1">[9]</xref>, a negative regulator of serum phosphate. FGF23 uses the FGFR1c/Klotho complex to directly target the kidney where it induces phosphate wasting by decreasing the expression of the sodium-dependent phosphate co-transporters NaPi2a and NaPi2c <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Saito1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Shimada1">[11]</xref>. Klotho also regulates serum calcium by affecting both parathyroid gland and kidney independent of FGF23. When serum calcium is low, Klotho hydrolyzes extracellular sugar residues on the renal transepithelial calcium channel TRPV5, entrapping the channel in the plasma membrane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Chang1">[12]</xref>. This maintains continuous calcium channel activity and membrane calcium permeability, leading to an increase in tubular reabsorption of calcium in the kidneys and finally increased serum calcium. In the parathyroid gland, Klotho recruits Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase to the cell surface, which results in an increase in PTH production, which in turn elevates serum calcium level <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Bjorklund1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Imura1">[14]</xref>. In addition to Klotho's independent effect on PTH induction, it can act together with FGF23 to decrease PTH levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-BenDov1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Krajisnik1">[16]</xref>. An <italic>in vivo</italic> study has shown that injection of FGF23 protein into rats can lower PTH secretion and expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-BenDov1">[15]</xref>. This was confirmed by <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments using parathyroid gland cultures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Krajisnik1">[16]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The function of Klotho as a cofactor of FGF23 was confirmed in studies by us and others showing that genetic ablation of either <italic>Fgf23</italic> or <italic>Klotho</italic> results in a similar phenotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Sitara1">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Razzaque2">[19]</xref>. Both <italic>Klotho</italic> knockout (<italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>) and <italic>Fgf23</italic> knockout (<italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic>) mice exhibit hypercalcemia, hyperphosphatemia with low to undetectable PTH levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Nakatani1">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Brownstein1">[22]</xref>, and severe osteomalacia. We have previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Yuan1">[23]</xref> that deletion of PTH in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice ameliorated the abnormal phenotype by normalizing serum Ca<sup>2+</sup> and lowering serum vitamin D levels, however, the severe osteomalacia persisted in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup>/PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. Because Klotho also has FGF23-independent functions, we thought it would be important to investigate the effects of deleting PTH from <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. We demonstrate that the skeletal mineralization defect in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup>/PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice was completely rescued and that this phenomenon was accompanied by a reduction in the high levels of osteopontin in bone and serum, a finding that could not be observed in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup>/PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. We also present data showing that continuous infusion of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice with PTH results in an elevation in OPN levels and subsequently increased osteoid volume. Our finding demonstrates for the first time that the skeletal abnormalities and the bone mineralization defect in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> can be rescued by ablation of PTH actions. Our data suggest regulatory actions on osteopontin by PTH, an important observation with clinical significance. The identical levels in serum calcium, phosphate and vitamin D in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup>/PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup>/PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> preclude any effects of these parameters on the regulation of skeletal mineralization and/or Opn levels in these mice. Additional studies are required to identify the mechanisms by which PTH affects osteopontin and mineralization in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> but not in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic>mice.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Deletion of PTH results in healthier <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>/<italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> double-knockout animals</title>
        <p>We successfully generated <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>/<italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> (<italic>DKO</italic>) mice by interbreeding heterozygous <italic>Kl<sup>+/−</sup></italic> and <italic>PTH<sup>+/−</sup></italic> mice. <italic>DKO</italic> mice were more active, healthier and larger in size than <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice and more comparable to wild-type and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> single knock-out littermates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). <italic>DKO</italic> mice did not show any obvious gross abnormalities with regard to movement and physical activities, whereas <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> littermates were severely weakened, showing restricted movement as well as sluggish physical activities. <italic>DKO</italic> mouse body weight was significantly higher than that of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). Compared to the <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, <italic>DKO</italic> mice also showed a clear improvement in life span as evidenced by a right shift of the survival curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). All mice, however, died before 16 weeks of age, probably due to the severe soft tissue calcifications such as found in kidney and lung of both <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and <italic>DKO</italic> mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1002726.s001">Figure S1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pgen-1002726-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Macroscopic phenotype of 6-wk-old mice.</title>
            <p>(A) Overall phenotype of littermates. Complete deletion of <italic>PTH</italic> from <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice resulted in larger, heavier, and more active <italic>DKO</italic> mice compared to <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> littermates. The body weight of <italic>DKO</italic> mice is significantly higher than that of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (B), and the lifespan is slightly improved (C). ###: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001 <italic>vs Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Serum biochemistry</title>
        <p>Six-week old <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice were severely hypercalcemic (10.86±0.52 mg/dL) and hypocalcemic (6.85±1.17 mg/dL), respectively. However <italic>DKO</italic> animals were normocalcemic (8.78±0.42 mg/dL) at 6 weeks, comparable to <italic>WT</italic> control animals (9.52±0.41 mg/dL), (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Serum phosphate levels in both <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> (14.61±0.48 mg/dL) and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> (14.52±1.87 mg/dL) mice were significantly higher compared to those in <italic>WT</italic> mice (9.75±1.34 mg/dL), (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). Interestingly, <italic>DKO</italic> exhibited a further increase in serum phosphate to levels (17.65±1.86 mg/dL) far exceeding those in single <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> or <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. We determined the total mineral content by calculating the calcium/phosphate product and found that <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and <italic>DKO</italic> mice exhibited similarly high levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). Measurements of serum 1,25(OH)<sub>2</sub>D levels showed increased amounts in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> single knockout mice compared to those in <italic>WT</italic> and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. Serum 1,25(OH)<sub>2</sub>D levels in <italic>DKO</italic> mice were significantly reduced compared to those of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> single knockout mice, but were still significantly higher than in wild-type or <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g002">Figure 2D</xref>). We also measured intact serum FGF23 levels and found that <italic>DKO</italic> mice had a 50% decrease in serum FGF23 compared to <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, however the levels were still significantly higher (1000 fold) than those in wild-type or <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g002">Figure 2E</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pgen-1002726-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Serum biochemical measurement.</title>
            <p>Abnormal serum calcium levels observed in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice were normalized in <italic>DKO</italic> mice (A). As for phosphate, <italic>DKO</italic> mice showed a further increase over already high levels in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (B). <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and DKO mice showed similarly high CaPi product (C). The serum levels of intact FGF23 (D) and 1,25(OH)<sub>2</sub>D (E) in <italic>DKO</italic> mice were partially reduced compared to that of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. *: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05, **: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01, ***: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001<italic>vs WT</italic>; ###: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001<italic>vs Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>; and $$: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01, $$$: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001 <italic>vs DKO</italic>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Deletion of <italic>PTH</italic> rescues skeletal abnormalities of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice</title>
        <p>We performed peripheral quantitative computerized tomography (pQCT) to analyze the bone density in the femurs of all genotypes. <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice showed decreased total BMD in the distal femur metaphysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Ablation of the <italic>PTH</italic> gene from these mice significantly increased the BMD, which was now comparable to that of <italic>WT</italic> and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice.</p>
        <fig id="pgen-1002726-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Rescued skeletal phenotype.</title>
            <p>Bone Mineral Density (BMD) of distal ends of femurs from 6-week-old mice (A). Radiographs of the tibiae from all genotypes at 6 wk of age indicate that length and radiopacity of the tibiae were restored in <italic>DKO</italic> mice (B). Alizarin red S and Alcian blue staining shows that the abnormally wide ribs in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (indicated by black arrow) were not observed in the <italic>DKO</italic> mice (C). Representative microCT images of distal femoral metaphyses (D) and midshaft cortical bone (E) and quantitative analysis (F, G). The midshaft cortical thickness (C.Th) of the <italic>DKO</italic> mice was restored to a volume comparable to that of <italic>WT</italic> and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. ***: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001<italic>vs WT</italic>; ##: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01, ###: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001 <italic>vs Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Radiographs showed that the length and radiopacity of the tibiae from <italic>DKO</italic> mice were increased and comparable to those of <italic>WT</italic> and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). We performed Alizarin red S and Alcian blue staining to determine the mineralization pattern of the bones. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g003">Figure 3C</xref>, <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice exhibited abnormally widened ribs, but this abnormality could not be observed in the <italic>DKO</italic> mice, suggesting an improved skeletal architecture.</p>
        <p>MicroCT (μCT) analysis of the femurs was performed on all four genotypes. Representative images of distal femoral metaphyses and midshaft cortex are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g003">Figure 3D and 3E</xref>. Quantification of trabecular bone volume fraction demonstrated that there is no significant difference between each genotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g003">Figure 3F</xref>). As μCT can only detect mineralized bone, <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice didn't show increased trabecular volume. However, the midshaft cortical thickness of the <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (0.132±0.013 mm) was significantly reduced compared to the other groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g003">Figure 3G</xref>). It was restored in <italic>DKO</italic> mice (0.170±0.015 mm) to a volume comparable to that in <italic>WT</italic> (0.184±0.011 mm) and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> (0.186±0.016 mm) mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g003">Figure 3G</xref>).</p>
        <p>We further analyzed the skeletal properties by generating undecalcified methylmethacrylate sections from the distal ends of femurs to confirm the observed improvement in bone mass compared to <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g004">Figure 4A and 4B</xref>). Most importantly, the severe osteoidosis seen in the secondary spongiosa of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice was completely absent in <italic>DKO</italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g004">Figure 4B</xref>), indicating the mineralization defect of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice was rescued by <italic>PTH</italic> ablation. To quantify this observation, we performed histomorphometric analyses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g004">Figure 4C–4N</xref>). The increased trabecular bone volume observed in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (18.1±4.4) was restored in <italic>DKO</italic> mice (13.5±1.9) to values close to those of <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (11.4±1.6). Interestingly, deletion of <italic>PTH</italic> also rescued the severe mineralization defect of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice as evidenced by normalized osteoid volume (OV/TV), osteoid surface (OS/BS) and thickness (OTh) in <italic>DKO</italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g004">Figure 4D–4F</xref>). <italic>DKO</italic> mice also showed normal trabecular thickness (Tb.Th.), trabecular number (Tb.N.) and separation (Tb.Sp.), as well as osteoclast surface (Oc.S/BS) and osteoclast numbers (N.Oc/B.Pm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g004">Figure 4G–4K</xref>). We also found that the dynamic parameters, including mineral surface (MS/BS), bone formation rate (BFR/BS) and mineral apposition rate (MAR) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g004">Figure 4L–4N</xref>), were normalized in <italic>DKO</italic> mice while the bone labeling in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice was unsuccessful due to the severe mineralization defect.</p>
        <fig id="pgen-1002726-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Histological and histomorphometric analyses.</title>
            <p>Undecalcified sections of distal ends of femurs from 6wk-old littermates were stained with von Kossa and McNeal (A, B). High magnification of the secondary spongiosa shows heavily unmineralized osteoid in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice but not in <italic>DKO</italic> mice (B). Histomorphometric analysis (C–N) confirmed that the skeletal architecture and mineralization defect of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice were rescued in <italic>DKO</italic> mice. BV/TV: bone volumes; OV/TV: osteoid volume; OS/BS: osteoid surface/bone surface; OTh; osteoid thickness; Tb.Th: trabecular thickness; Tb.N: trabecular number; Tb.Sp: trabecular separation; Oc.S/BS: osteoclast surface/bone surface; N.Oc/B.Pm: osteoclast number/bone perimeter; MS/BS: mineral surface/bone surface; BFR: bone formation rate, and MAR: mineral apposition rate. *: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05, **: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01, ***: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001<italic>vs WT</italic>; and #: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05, ##: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01, ###: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001 <italic>vs Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We next analyzed the concentration of serum markers for bone turnover. Consistent with histomorphometric data, serum levels of the carboxyl-terminal telopeptide of type 1 collagen (CTX), a biomarker of bone resorption activity, were comparable in <italic>DKO</italic> (31.5±17.2 ng/ml), <italic>WT</italic> (40.8.5±16.2 ng/ml) and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> (31.5±3.6 ng/ml) mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). Similarly, circulating levels of N-terminal propeptide of type I procollagen (PINP), a reliable and sensitive marker of bone formation, were significantly elevated in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (21.8±6.0 ng/ml) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). PINP levels were restored in <italic>DKO</italic> mice (14.5±5.0 ng/ml) to levels observed in <italic>WT</italic> (14.2±4.6 ng/ml) and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> (17.0±1.6 ng/ml).</p>
        <fig id="pgen-1002726-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Measurement of serum CTX and PINP.</title>
            <p>Measurement of serum CTX (A) and PINP (B), indicating normalized bone turnover in <italic>DKO</italic> mice. *: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05, **: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01<italic>vs WT;</italic> ##: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01<italic>vs Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Rescued bone mineralization is accompanied by normalized expression of Opn in <italic>DKO</italic> mice</title>
        <p>To explain the rescue in bone mineralization in <italic>DKO</italic> mice, we compared the expression of osteopontin and other factors associated with skeletal mineralization in all genotypes. As shown by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization and immunohistochemical staining on decalcified paraffin sections (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g006">Figure 6A and 6B</xref>), the expression of Opn, an inhibitor of osteogenic mineralization and member of the SIBLING protein family, is abnormally high in the bone. Interestingly, its expression was normalized in <italic>DKO</italic> mice to levels seen in <italic>WT</italic> and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g006">Figure 6A and 6B</xref>). We also measured serum Opn levels using an ELISA kit and were able to confirm significantly elevated serum Opn levels in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, which were restored to normal levels in <italic>DKO</italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g006">Figure 6C</xref>). Since we previously reported increased Opn expression in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> bones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Sitara1">[17]</xref>, we were interested in also examining their serum Opn levels and found that they were also significantly increased. In contrast, however, deletion of <italic>PTH</italic> from <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice failed to normalize their serum Opn levels (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1002726.s002">Figure S2</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pgen-1002726-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Normalized expression of Opn in <italic>DKO</italic> mice.</title>
            <p>In situ hybridization (A) and immunohistochemical staining (B) on paraffin sections prepared from tibiae of animals at 6 weeks of age. The elevated <italic>Opn</italic> expression in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice was normalized in <italic>DKO</italic> mice. (C) Measurements of the serum Opn levels. Quantitive PCR confirmed the normal expression of <italic>Opn</italic> in the osteoblasts isolated from <italic>DKO</italic> mice (D). <italic>DKO</italic> osteoblasts also exhibited normal mineralization as evaluated by Alizarin red staining (E). *: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05, ***: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001<italic>vs WT</italic>; and #: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05, ###: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001 <italic>vs Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To further confirm the <italic>in vivo</italic> observations in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and <italic>DKO</italic> mice calvarial osteoblasts from 2-day-old littermates were isolated. Cells were cultured in osteogenic medium for 2 weeks and RNA was isolated. qPCR analyses showed normal expression of <italic>Opn</italic> in osteoblasts of <italic>DKO</italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g006">Figure 6D</xref>). These osteoblasts also exhibited normal mineralization as evaluated by Alizarin red staining while the mineralization of the osteoblasts from <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice was markedly impaired (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g006">Figure 6E</xref>). We also evaluated the expression of Dmp1 and Matrix gla protein (Mgp) by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization and/or qPCR. Both were significantly increased in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, but rescued in <italic>DKO</italic> mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1002726.s003">Figure S3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Infusion of PTH increases Opn levels and led to more severe mineralization defect</title>
        <p>To further investigate the role of Opn in regulating the mineralization, we perfused PTH (1–34) peptides into the <italic>WT</italic> and <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice using osmotic minipumps. After continuous infusion for 3 weeks, we observed that the serum Opn levels were significantly elevated in both <italic>WT</italic> and <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g007">Figure 7A</xref>). As expected, serum phosphate levels were significantly decreased in both kinds of mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1002726.s004">Figure S4</xref>). PTH infusion, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g007">Figure 7B–7D</xref>, did not change the bone volume in <italic>WT</italic> mice, but significantly decreased it in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. More importantly, OV/BV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g007">Figure 7E</xref>) and OS/BS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g007">Figure 7F</xref>) of <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice were further increased by the PTH infusion, while the mineralized bone volume (MdV/TV) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g007">Figure 7G</xref>) was significantly decreased, indicating that extraneous PTH induces Opn and thereby worsens the skeletal mineralization defect in the <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. Continuous PTH infusion also increased osteoblast surface (Ob.S/BS), Oc.S/BS and N.Oc/B.Pm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g007">Figure 7K–7M</xref>) in both <italic>WT</italic> and <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. Opn contains a RGD sequence, which is important for osteoclast attachment on the bone. Thus it is not surprising that infusion of PTH resulted in a significant elevation in serum CTX levels, indicating increased osteoclastic resorption (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g007">Figure 7N</xref>). In addition, PTH infusion significantly elevated serum PINP levels in both <italic>WT</italic> and <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1002726-g007">Figure 7O</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pgen-1002726-g007" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Infusion of PTH increases Opn levels and leads to a more severe mineralization defect.</title>
            <p>PTH infusion increased serum Opn levels (A). Undecalcified sections of distal ends of femurs were stained with von Kossa and McNeal (B, C). Histomorphometric analysis (D–M) showed that PTH infusion decreased the bone volume (BV/TV) and increased osteoid volume (OV/BV) in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. Serum CTX (N) and PINP (O) levels were significantly increased after PTH infusion. MdV/TV: mineralized bone volume/total volume. Ob.S/BS: osteoblast surface/bone surface. *: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05, **: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01, ***: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001<italic>vs</italic> vehicle controls.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This is the first study using a genetic mouse model with dual ablation of the <italic>Klotho</italic> and <italic>PTH</italic> genes. The results show that deletion of <italic>PTH</italic> from <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice resulted in healthier mice with normalization of serum calcium levels and complete rescue of the skeletal phenotype, suggesting that PTH is a crucial contributor to the skeletal abnormalities caused by loss of Klotho function. More importantly, we found that deletion of the <italic>PTH</italic> completely rescued the mineralization defect in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, as well as <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, exhibit a severe mineralization defect in their bones despite excesses in serum calcium and phosphate when compared to <italic>WT</italic> mice. The underlying reason for this is largely unknown but FGF23 is recognized as an inhibitor of mineralization. Serum Fgf23 levels in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice are two thousand fold higher than in wild-type littermates. Wang <italic>et al</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Wang1">[24]</xref> show that adenoviral overexpression of FGF23 in rat calvarial cells inhibits bone mineralization independent of its systemic effects on phosphate homeostasis. Our previous report also demonstrated that FGF23 treatment of primary calvarial osteoblasts from wild-type mice leads to an inhibition of mineralization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Sitara2">[18]</xref>. However, FGF23 requires Klotho for its actions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Urakawa1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Nakatani1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Kurosu1">[25]</xref>. In the absence of Klotho, FGF23 has very low affinity to the FGFR1 and cannot induce signal transduction (phosphorylation) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Urakawa1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Kurosu1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Tomiyama1">[26]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Another intriguing possibility is that Klotho may have a specific function in osteoblasts associated with PTH. Although Klotho has been widely accepted as the cofactor of FGF23 signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Urakawa1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Tomiyama1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Razzaque3">[27]</xref>, and <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice share very similar phenotypes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Nakatani1">[20]</xref>, we show here that deletion of <italic>PTH</italic> fully rescues the mineralization defect in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, but could not improve this defect in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Yuan1">[23]</xref>. More recently, Klotho has been reported to be expressed in the osteoblastic cell linage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Rhee1">[28]</xref>. In addition, previous studies have shown that Klotho does exert endogenous actions in calcium homeostasis and control of PTH secretion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Bjorklund1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Imura1">[14]</xref> that are independent of FGF23. Similarly, Klotho directly mediates secretion of PTH through recruitment of Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup> ATPase to the plasma membrane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Imura1">[14]</xref>. Recent studies also showed that <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice have increased trabecular bone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Liu1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Brownstein2">[30]</xref>. In this study, we confirmed elevated bone volume in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice compared to the normal bone volume in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. More importantly, cultured osteoblasts isolated from <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> pups at the age of 2-days showed markedly impaired mineralization, suggesting that Klotho may play a specific role in osteoblasts. Moreover, we detected low Klotho expression by qPCR in both cultured osteoblasts and isolated cortical bone (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1002726.s005">Figure S5</xref>). An osteoblast-specific <italic>Klotho</italic> knockout mouse model may be required to dissect the role of Klotho during skeletogenesis.</p>
      <p>To examine the bone mineralization defect in more detail, we determined the expression of Opn by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization, immunohistochemistry, ELISA and quantitative PCR. Opn is a well-known mineralization inhibitor, and mice deficient in Opn show soft tissue calcification and premature bone mineralization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Luo1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Steitz1">[32]</xref>. Our analyses showed that the increased amount of Opn detected in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice was normalized in <italic>DKO</italic> mice. PTH is known to be an important regulator of Opn and can induce the expression of <italic>Opn</italic> in MC3T3-E1 cells within 3 hours <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Suttamanatwong1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Gopalakrishnan1">[34]</xref>. Therefore, the complete ablation of PTH might be responsible for the normalization of the increased Opn levels in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice and subsequently rescue the mineralization defect. Furthermore, infusion of exogenous PTH into <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice resulted in a significant elevation in Opn levels with a worsened mineralization defect. This further strengthens our hypothesis that PTH could regulate skeletal mineralization in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice via Opn.</p>
      <p>Although studies suggest that phosphate could also regulate the expression of Opn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Foster1">[35]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Fatherazi1">[37]</xref>, our previous study using <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup>/NaPi2a<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice suggested that the elevated expression of Opn in bones of <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice is at least partially independent of systemic phosphate levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Sitara2">[18]</xref>. This was further supported by our observation in this study that <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and <italic>DKO</italic> mice had normal expression of Opn despite very high serum phosphate levels. In addition, we also found in this study that PTH infusion could increase the serum Opn, even while the serum phosphate levels were decreased (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1002726.s004">Figure S4</xref>). Moreover, serum calcium, phosphate and vitamin D levels in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup>/PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup>/PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> are identical and can therefore not contribute to the regulation of skeletal mineralization and/or Opn levels in these mice.</p>
      <p>In summary, the findings in this study demonstrate that genetic ablation of <italic>PTH</italic> resulted in healthier <italic>DKO</italic> mice. More importantly, deletion of PTH completely rescued the skeletal abnormalities, including the severe mineralization defect in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice, and this effect is very likely associated with normalized expression of Opn in <italic>DKO</italic> mice. Interestingly, we previously showed that deletion of <italic>PTH</italic> in <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice could not rescue mineralization, implying an independent function of Klotho in bone. This study demonstrates that the activity of the low level of PTH remaining in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice contributes to the severe mineralization disorder and skeletal abnormalities caused by the loss of Klotho function. Moreover, we show that Klotho affects mineralization independently of its role as a co-factor for FGF23. Further analyses are needed to determine the independent roles of PTH and Klotho in mineral ion homeostasis and skeletal mineralization and their detailed molecular interactions, including those involving OPN.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Animals</title>
        <p>Heterozygous- <italic>Kl<sup>+/−</sup></italic> and <italic>PTH<sup>+/−</sup></italic> animals were interbred to attain wild-type (<italic>WT</italic>), <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>, <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>/<italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> (double knockout, <italic>DKO</italic>) and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> animals for subsequent analyses. Routine PCR was used to genotype various mice as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Nakatani1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Miao1">[38]</xref>. The total body weight of each mouse was measured weekly starting at 3 weeks after birth. All studies performed were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at the Harvard Medical School.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Biochemical analyses</title>
        <p>Blood was obtained by puncturing the cheek pouch of animals. Total serum calcium and phosphorus levels were determined using Stanbio LiquiColor (Arsenazo III) and LiquiUV kits (Stanbio Laboratory, Boerne, TX), respectively. Serum concentrations of FGF23 and Opn were measured using commercial kits from Kainos Laboratories, Inc., (Tokyo, Japan), and R&amp;D Systems, Inc. (Minneapolis, MN), respectively. The ELISA kits for 1,25(OH)<sub>2</sub>D, PINP and CTX were purchased from IDS (Fountain Hills, AZ).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Skeletal mineralization and bone mineral density</title>
        <p>The mineralization pattern of the skeleton was analyzed by Alizarin red S and Alcian blue staining in 6- week-old mice, as described by McLeod <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-McLeod1">[39]</xref>. Femurs of all genotypes at 6 weeks of age were flushed and exposed to X-ray (20 kV, 5 seconds). As described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Yuan2">[40]</xref>, bone mineral density (BMD) and μCT analysis were performed by peripheral quantitative computerized tomography (pQCT) and by using a Scanco Medical μCT 35 system (Scanco), respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Bone histology and histomorphometry</title>
        <p>Processing of undecalcified bone specimens and cancellous bone histomorphometry in the distal femoral metaphysis were performed as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Yuan2">[40]</xref>. The area within 0.25 mm from the growth plate was excluded from the measurements.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Soft tissue calcifications</title>
        <p>Von Kossa staining was performed using 5 µm paraffin sections of kidneys and lungs isolated from 9-week-old animals.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4f">
        <title><italic>In situ</italic> hybridization</title>
        <p>Complementary <sup>35</sup>S-UTP-labeled riboprobe osteopontin (Opn) and dentin matrix protein 1 (Dmp1) were used for performing <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization on paraffin sections, as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Lanske2">[41]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4g">
        <title>Immunohistochemistry</title>
        <p>Immunohistochemistry was performed using mouse Opn antibody (R&amp;D, Minneapolis, MN) with a working concentration of 0.5 µg/ml overnight at 4°C. Tissue was stained with anti-goat HRP substrate and DAB (Vector, Burlingame, CA), and then counterstained with hematoxylin.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4h">
        <title>Mouse calvarial cell culture</title>
        <p>Mouse calvarial cell culture was carried out as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1002726-Sitara2">[18]</xref>. Cells were treated with 50 mg/ml ascorbic acid and 10 mM β-glycerophosphate (βGP) to induce matrix mineralization. Total RNA isolation and Alizarin red S staining were performed 14 days after induction.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4i">
        <title>Quantitative real-time PCR</title>
        <p>Total RNA was from cultured osteoblasts using Trizol reagents (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's protocol. For qRT-PCR, cDNA was prepared using QuantiTec reverse transcription kit (Qiagen) and analyzed with SYBR GreenMaster Mix (SABiosciences) in the iCycler (Bio-Rad) using specific primers designed for each targeted gene. Relative expression was calculated using the 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> method by normalizing with <italic>Gapdh</italic> housekeeping gene expression, and presented as fold increase relative to control.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4j">
        <title><italic>In vivo</italic> continuous PTH (1–34) infusion</title>
        <p>50 µg per kilogram of body weight per day of human PTH 1–34 (Polypeptide Group, France) were delivered into 3-week-old animals for a 3-week period using implanted ALZET osmotic minipumps, Model-1004 (DURECT Corporation, Cupertino, CA). Animals of vehicle group were infused with an equal volume of sterile saline.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4k">
        <title>Statistics</title>
        <p>Statistically significant differences between groups were evaluated by Student's t-test for comparison between two groups or by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey's test for multiple comparisons. And those between vehicle and PTH-infused groups were evaluated by Student's t-test. All values were expressed as mean ± SD. A <italic>p</italic> value of less than 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pgen.1002726.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Von Kossa staining of kidney sections (A) and lung sections (B) isolated from 9-week-old animals. Soft tissue calcification was observed in both <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> and Klotho/PTH double knockout (<italic>DKO</italic>) mice.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pgen.1002726.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Serum osteopontin (Opn) levels in (A) wild-type (WT) and <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice at 3 and 6 weeks of age. (B) Comparison of serum Opn levels between WT, <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic>, <italic>Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic>/<italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup> (DKO),</italic> and <italic>PTH<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice at 6 weeks. ***: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001<italic>vs</italic> vehicle controls, ###: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001 <italic>vs Fgf23<sup>−/−</sup></italic>, $$$: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001 <italic>vs DKO.</italic></p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pgen.1002726.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Gene expression of Dmp1 and Mgp. (A) <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization of bone sections showed that Dmp1 expression was elevated in <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice. (B and C) mRNA expression of Dmp1 and Mgp in osteoblasts was quantified by qPCR analysis. Calvarial osteoblasts were isolated and cultured in osteogenic medium for 2 weeks. *: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05, **: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01 <italic>vs WT</italic>; ##: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01 <italic>vs Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic>.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pgen.1002726.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Serum phosphate measurements. PTH infusion significantly decreased serum phosphate levels in both <italic>WT</italic> and <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> animals. **: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01, ***: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001<italic>vs</italic> vehicle controls.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pgen.1002726.s005" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002726.s005" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Gene expression of Klotho in bone and osteoblasts quantified by qPCR. Klotho expression was detected in the both cultured osteoblasts and cortical bones. However, it was much lower than that observed in the kidney. Tissues from <italic>Kl<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice were used as negative controls. ***: <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We would like to thank Dr. H. Kronenberg for his valuable advice and Drs. Y. Maeda, M. Christov, and D. Seriwatanachai for their technical support. We are also very grateful to the histology core of the Endocrine Unit at Massachusetts General Hospital (MGH) for their support.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Renkema1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Renkema</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bindels</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoenderop</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Calcium and phosphate homeostasis: concerted interplay of new regulators.</article-title>             <source>Ann Med</source>             <volume>40</volume>             <fpage>82</fpage>             <lpage>91</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Dusso1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dusso</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slatopolsky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Vitamin D.</article-title>             <source>Am J Physiol Renal Physiol</source>             <volume>289</volume>             <fpage>F8</fpage>             <lpage>28</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Razzaque1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Razzaque</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanske</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>The emerging role of the fibroblast growth factor-23-klotho axis in renal regulation of phosphate homeostasis.</article-title>             <source>J Endocrinol</source>             <volume>194</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>10</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Lanske1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanske</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Razzaque</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Mineral metabolism and aging: the fibroblast growth factor 23 enigma.</article-title>             <source>Curr Opin Nephrol Hypertens</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>311</fpage>             <lpage>318</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Lee1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Parathyroid hormone signaling in bone and kidney.</article-title>             <source>Curr Opin Nephrol Hypertens</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>298</fpage>             <lpage>302</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Li1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinuta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Immunohistochemical localization of Klotho protein in brain, kidney, and reproductive organs of mice.</article-title>             <source>Cell Struct Funct</source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>91</fpage>             <lpage>99</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Matsumura1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aizawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiraki-Iida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuro-o</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Identification of the human klotho gene and its two transcripts encoding membrane and secreted klotho protein.</article-title>             <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>             <volume>242</volume>             <fpage>626</fpage>             <lpage>630</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-ShirakiIida1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiraki-Iida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aizawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sekine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Structure of the mouse klotho gene and its two transcripts encoding membrane and secreted protein.</article-title>             <source>FEBS Lett</source>             <volume>424</volume>             <fpage>6</fpage>             <lpage>10</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Urakawa1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urakawa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iijima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Klotho converts canonical FGF receptor into a specific receptor for FGF23.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Saito1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kusano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinosaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Human fibroblast growth factor-23 mutants suppress Na+-dependent phosphate co-transport activity and 1alpha,25-dihydroxyvitamin D3 production.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>278</volume>             <fpage>2206</fpage>             <lpage>2211</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Shimada1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urakawa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hino</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>FGF-23 transgenic mice demonstrate hypophosphatemic rickets with reduced expression of sodium phosphate cotransporter type IIa.</article-title>             <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>             <volume>314</volume>             <fpage>409</fpage>             <lpage>414</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Chang1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoefs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Kemp</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topala</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bindels</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>The beta-glucuronidase klotho hydrolyzes and activates the TRPV5 channel.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>310</volume>             <fpage>490</fpage>             <lpage>493</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Bjorklund1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjorklund</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krajisnik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akerstrom</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Type I membrane klotho expression is decreased and inversely correlated to serum calcium in primary hyperparathyroidism.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>             <volume>93</volume>             <fpage>4152</fpage>             <lpage>4157</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Imura1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>alpha-Klotho as a regulator of calcium homeostasis.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>316</volume>             <fpage>1615</fpage>             <lpage>1618</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-BenDov1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Dov</surname><given-names>IZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galitzer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavi-Moshayoff</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goetz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuro-o</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>The parathyroid is a target organ for FGF23 in rats.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Invest</source>             <volume>117</volume>             <fpage>4003</fpage>             <lpage>4008</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Krajisnik1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krajisnik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjorklund</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ljunggren</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akerstrom</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Fibroblast growth factor-23 regulates parathyroid hormone and 1alpha-hydroxylase expression in cultured bovine parathyroid cells.</article-title>             <source>J Endocrinol</source>             <volume>195</volume>             <fpage>125</fpage>             <lpage>131</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Sitara1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sitara</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Razzaque</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St-Arnaud</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Genetic ablation of vitamin D activation pathway reverses biochemical and skeletal anomalies in Fgf-23-null animals.</article-title>             <source>Am J Pathol</source>             <volume>169</volume>             <fpage>2161</fpage>             <lpage>2170</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Sitara2">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sitara</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Razzaque</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergwitz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Genetic evidence of serum phosphate-independent functions of FGF-23 on bone.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Genet</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e1000154</fpage>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000154" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000154</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Razzaque2">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Razzaque</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sitara</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St-Arnaud</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanske</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Premature ageing-like phenotype in fibroblast growth factor 23 null mice is a vitamin-D mediated process.</article-title>             <source>The FASEB Journal</source>             <volume>20</volume>             <fpage>720</fpage>             <lpage>722</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Nakatani1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarraj</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Densmore</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>In vivo genetic evidence for klotho-dependent, fibroblast growth factor 23 (Fgf23) -mediated regulation of systemic phosphate homeostasis.</article-title>             <source>Faseb J</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>433</fpage>             <lpage>441</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Nakatani2">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Razzaque</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Inactivation of klotho function induces hyperphosphatemia even in presence of high serum fibroblast growth factor 23 levels in a genetically engineered hypophosphatemic (Hyp) mouse model.</article-title>             <source>Faseb J</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>3702</fpage>             <lpage>3711</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Brownstein1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Troiano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <article-title>Increased bone volume and correction of HYP mouse hypophosphatemia in the Klotho/HYP mouse.</article-title>             <source>Endocrinology</source>             <volume>151</volume>             <fpage>492</fpage>             <lpage>501</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Yuan1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sitara</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Densmore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>PTH Ablation Ameliorates the Anomalies of Fgf23-Deficient Mice by Suppressing the Elevated Vitamin D and Calcium Levels.</article-title>             <source>Endocrinology</source>             <volume>152</volume>             <fpage>4053</fpage>             <lpage>4061</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Wang1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshiko</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minamizaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Overexpression of fibroblast growth factor 23 suppresses osteoblast differentiation and matrix mineralization in vitro.</article-title>             <source>J Bone Miner Res</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>939</fpage>             <lpage>948</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Kurosu1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurosu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nandi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Regulation of fibroblast growth factor-23 signaling by Klotho.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Tomiyama1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urakawa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Relevant use of Klotho in FGF19 subfamily signaling system in vivo.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>107</volume>             <fpage>1666</fpage>             <lpage>1671</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Razzaque3">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Razzaque</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>The FGF23-Klotho axis: endocrine regulation of phosphate homeostasis.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Endocrinol</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>611</fpage>             <lpage>619</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Rhee1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bivi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lezcano</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plotkin</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <article-title>Parathyroid hormone receptor signaling in osteocytes increases the expression of fibroblast growth factor-23 in vitro and in vivo.</article-title>             <source>Bone</source>             <volume>49</volume>             <fpage>636</fpage>             <lpage>643</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Liu1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fergusson</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castilho</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Augmented Wnt signaling in a mammalian model of accelerated aging.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>317</volume>             <fpage>803</fpage>             <lpage>806</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Brownstein2">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Troiano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Increased bone volume and correction of HYP mouse hypophosphatemia in the Klotho/HYP mouse.</article-title>             <source>Endocrinology</source>             <volume>151</volume>             <fpage>492</fpage>             <lpage>501</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Luo1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ducy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinero</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loyer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Spontaneous calcification of arteries and cartilage in mice lacking matrix GLA protein.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>386</volume>             <fpage>78</fpage>             <lpage>81</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Steitz1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Speer</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liaw</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Osteopontin inhibits mineral deposition and promotes regression of ectopic calcification.</article-title>             <source>Am J Pathol</source>             <volume>161</volume>             <fpage>2035</fpage>             <lpage>2046</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Suttamanatwong1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suttamanatwong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franceschi</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gopalakrishnan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Regulation of matrix Gla protein by parathyroid hormone in MC3T3-E1 osteoblast-like cells involves protein kinase A and extracellular signal-regulated kinase pathways.</article-title>             <source>J Cell Biochem</source>             <volume>102</volume>             <fpage>496</fpage>             <lpage>505</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Gopalakrishnan1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gopalakrishnan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suttamanatwong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franceschi</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Role of matrix Gla protein in parathyroid hormone inhibition of osteoblast mineralization.</article-title>             <source>Cells Tissues Organs</source>             <volume>181</volume>             <fpage>166</fpage>             <lpage>175</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Foster1">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nociti</surname><given-names>FH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsa-Dunn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Regulation of cementoblast gene expression by inorganic phosphate in vitro.</article-title>             <source>Calcif Tissue Int</source>             <volume>78</volume>             <fpage>103</fpage>             <lpage>112</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Julien1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Julien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoshniat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacreusette</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gatius</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bozec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Phosphate-dependent regulation of MGP in osteoblasts: role of ERK1/2 and Fra-1.</article-title>             <source>J Bone Miner Res</source>             <volume>24</volume>             <fpage>1856</fpage>             <lpage>1868</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Fatherazi1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fatherazi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsa-Dunn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somerman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Phosphate regulates osteopontin gene transcription.</article-title>             <source>J Dent Res</source>             <volume>88</volume>             <fpage>39</fpage>             <lpage>44</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Miao1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanske</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>XK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Skeletal abnormalities in Pth-null mice are influenced by dietary calcium.</article-title>             <source>Endocrinology</source>             <volume>145</volume>             <fpage>2046</fpage>             <lpage>2053</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-McLeod1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1980</year>             <article-title>Differential staining of cartilage and bone in whole fetuses by alcian blue and alizarin red S.</article-title>             <source>Teratology</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>299</fpage>             <lpage>301</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Yuan2">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Densmore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Fgf23/Klotho signaling is not essential for the phosphaturic and anabolic functions of PTH.</article-title>             <source>J Bone Miner Res</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>2026</fpage>             <lpage>2035</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pgen.1002726-Lanske2">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanske</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Divieti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>The parathyroid hormone (PTH)/PTH-related peptide receptor mediates actions of both ligands in murine bone.</article-title>             <source>Endocrinology</source>             <volume>139</volume>             <fpage>5194</fpage>             <lpage>5204</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>