<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PGENETICS-D-12-02421</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant science</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant evolution</subject><subject>Plant genetics</subject><subject>Plant growth and development</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Disturbed Local Auxin Homeostasis Enhances Cellular Anisotropy and Reveals Alternative Wiring of Auxin-ethylene Crosstalk in <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> Seminal Roots</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>Brachypodium</italic> Auxin Balance &amp; Root Cell Anisotropy</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacheco-Villalobos</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sankar</surname><given-names>Martial</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>Karin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardtke</surname><given-names>Christian S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Lausanne, Lausanne, Switzerland</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Umeå Plant Science Centre, Department of Forest Genetics and Plant Physiology, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, Umeå, Sweden</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Hao</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>National University of Singapore and Temasek Life Sciences Laboratory, Singapore</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">christian.hardtke@unil.ch</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: DP-V CSH. Performed the experiments: DP-V KL. Analyzed the data: DP-V MS KL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MS KL. Wrote the paper: DP-V CSH.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>e1003564</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Pacheco-Villalobos et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Observations gained from model organisms are essential, yet it remains unclear to which degree they are applicable to distant relatives. For example, in the dicotyledon <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (Arabidopsis), auxin biosynthesis via indole-3-pyruvic acid (IPA) is essential for root development and requires redundant <italic>TRYPTOPHAN AMINOTRANSFERASE OF ARABIDOPSIS 1 (TAA1)</italic> and <italic>TAA1-RELATED (TAR)</italic> genes. A promoter T-DNA insertion in the monocotyledon <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> (Brachypodium) <italic>TAR2-LIKE</italic> gene (<italic>BdTAR2L</italic>) severely down-regulates expression, suggesting reduced tryptophan aminotransferase activity in this mutant, which thus represents a hypomorphic <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> allele (<italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic>). Counterintuitive however, <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants display dramatically elongated seminal roots because of enhanced cell elongation. This phenotype is also observed in another, stronger <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> allele and can be mimicked by treating wild type with L-kynerunine, a specific TAA1/TAR inhibitor. Surprisingly, L-kynerunine-treated as well as <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> roots display elevated rather than reduced auxin levels. This does not appear to result from compensation by alternative auxin biosynthesis pathways. Rather, expression of <italic>YUCCA</italic> genes, which are rate-limiting for conversion of IPA to auxin, is increased in <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> mutants. Consistent with suppression of <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> root phenotypes upon application of the ethylene precursor 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic-acid (ACC), <italic>BdYUCCA</italic> genes are down-regulated upon ACC treatment. Moreover, they are up-regulated in a downstream ethylene-signaling component homolog mutant, <italic>Bd ethylene insensitive 2-like 1</italic>, which also displays a <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> root phenotype. In summary, <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> phenotypes contrast with gradually reduced root growth and auxin levels described for Arabidopsis <italic>taa1</italic>/<italic>tar</italic> mutants. This could be explained if in Brachypodium, ethylene inhibits the rate-limiting step of auxin biosynthesis in an IPA-dependent manner to confer auxin levels that are sub-optimal for root cell elongation, as suggested by our observations. Thus, our results reveal a delicate homeostasis of local auxin and ethylene activity to control cell elongation in Brachypodium roots and suggest alternative wiring of auxin-ethylene crosstalk as compared to Arabidopsis.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>The plant hormone auxin is pivotal for root system development. For instance, its local biosynthesis is essential for root formation and growth in the dicotyledon model Arabidopsis. Thus, increasing interference with auxin biosynthesis results in increasingly shorter roots, partly because of reduced cell elongation. In this study, we isolated a hypomorphic mutant in an auxin biosynthesis pathway enzyme in the monocotyledon model Brachypodium. Counterintuitive, this mutant displays a dramatically longer seminal root, because mature cells are thinner, more elongated and therefore more anisotropic than in wild type. Interestingly, this phenotype can be mimicked in wild type by pharmacological interference with production of a key auxin biosynthesis intermediate, but also by interference with the biosynthesis of another plant hormone, ethylene. The latter controls auxin biosynthesis in Arabidopsis roots. Surprisingly however, auxin levels in the Brachypodium mutant are elevated rather than reduced, because of a simultaneous up-regulation of the second, rate-limiting step of the pathway. Ethylene normally represses this second step, suggesting an inverted regulatory relation between the two hormones as compared to Arabidopsis. Our results point to a complex homeostatic crosstalk between auxin and ethylene in Brachypodium roots, which is fundamentally different from Arabidopsis and might be conserved in other monocotyledons.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by Swiss National Science Foundation grant 31003A_129783 and a Herbette Foundation grant awarded to CSH, as well as internal support of the University of Lausanne for DP-V and MS. KL's contribution was supported by The Swedish Governmental Agency for Innovation Systems (Vinnova) and the Swedish Research Council (Vetenskapsrådet). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The root system plays a fundamental role for plant growth and survival, not only by providing support, water and nutrients for the shoot, but also by participating in secondary functions, such as hormone biosynthesis or storage of photoassimilates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Lynch1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Osmont1">[2]</xref>. Root system architecture, that is the number and arrangement of different root types and their branching pattern, is highly plastic and determined by developmental and environmental factors that interact to optimize soil exploration. This is particularly important for the capture of growth limiting macronutrients, including nitrogen and phosphorus, whose edaphic distribution strongly influences post-embryonic root development and, therefore, root system architecture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Osmont1">[2]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Linkohr1">[4]</xref>. However, the root system can only respond to variation in such resources within its inherent developmental limits of growth rate and branching capacity, which are genetically determined. Optimization of root system architecture through breeding is therefore of particular interest in crops to increase root system plasticity with respect to biotic and abiotic stresses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Aiken1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-deDorlodot1">[6]</xref>.</p>
<p>Our knowledge about the molecular genetic control of root growth and branching has been largely obtained from analyses of the dicotyledon plant model system <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (Arabidopsis) through mutagenesis approaches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Osmont1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Benfey1">[7]</xref>. The genes identified through these efforts have greatly benefitted the isolation of corresponding loci in monocotyledons, such as rice or maize <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Hochholdinger1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Liu1">[11]</xref>. Many of them encode proteins with regulatory functions, and among them components of plant hormone signaling pathways are particularly preeminent. For example, interference with the auxin-signaling pathway by mutation typically impairs primary root elongation or root branching, and in extreme cases even abolishes root formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Hardtke1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Dharmasiri1">[14]</xref>. The same is true for loss-of-function mutations in genes that encode enzymes involved in tryptophan-dependent auxin biosynthesis. In particular, auxin biosynthesis from tryptophan via indole-3-pyruvic acid (IPA) has been shown to be essential for root formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Won1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Stepanova1">[16]</xref>. Two enzyme classes define this pathway: the TRYPTOPHAN AMINOTRANSFERASE OF ARABIDOPSIS 1 (TAA1) and TAA1-RELATED (TAR) proteins, which catalyze the conversion of tryptophan to IPA; and the family of YUCCA cytochrome P450s, which catalyze the conversion of IPA to indole-3-acetic acid (IAA), the major active form of auxin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Won1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Zhao1">[18]</xref>. Whereas the <italic>YUCCA</italic> genes were originally identified through a gain-of-function approach that led to auxin over-accumulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Zhao2">[19]</xref>, <italic>TAA1/TAR</italic> genes were identified through loss-of-function approaches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Stepanova1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Tao1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Yamada1">[21]</xref>. For instance, one study isolated the <italic>taa1</italic> mutant because of its root growth resistance to the application of 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic-acid (ACC), a rate-limiting precursor for the biosynthesis of another hormone, ethylene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Stepanova1">[16]</xref>. This phenotype arises as a consequence of reduced auxin biosynthesis, which is normally up-regulated by ethylene through induction of <italic>TAA1/TAR</italic> gene expression. This finding also illustrates the dosage-dependent action of auxin, because although auxin and its perception are essential for root formation and growth, excess auxin application, biosynthesis or signaling are eventually inhibitory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Garrett1">[22]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Sibout1">[24]</xref>. Indeed, it has been suggested that depending on the species, auxin levels might be supra-optimal for root growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Yin1">[25]</xref>.</p>
<p>Phylogenetic analysis has identified <italic>bona fide TAA1/TAR</italic> homologous genes in monocotyledons, with varying degrees of redundancy. For instance, whereas maize contains five genes of this family, only two are found in both rice and the monocotyledon model system, <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> (Brachypodium) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Phillips1">[26]</xref>. So far, only one <italic>TAA1/TAR</italic>-related mutant has been identified in monocotyledons, the <italic>vanishing tassel 2</italic> (<italic>vt2</italic>) mutant of maize <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Phillips1">[26]</xref>. Despite the presence of multiple <italic>TAA1/TAR</italic> homologs in maize, <italic>vt2</italic> null mutants display rather severe shoot phenotypes, such as dwarfism, reduced axillary meristem formation and associated impaired inflorescence development. Free auxin levels are reduced to ca. one third of wild type levels in <italic>vt2</italic> mutants, suggesting that <italic>VT2</italic> encodes the predominant TAA1/TAR activity in maize. Here we report the isolation and characterization of a Brachypodium mutant in the <italic>TAR2-LIKE</italic> (<italic>BdTAR2L</italic>) gene. Unlike <italic>vt2</italic>, this <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> mutant displays only mild shoot phenotypes. However, we observed dramatic root phenotypes, which surprisingly appear to result from upwardly disturbed auxin homeostasis.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Isolation of a T-DNA insertion mutant of <italic>BdTAR2L</italic></title>
<p>In an effort to identify genetic factors that influence root system architecture in Brachypodium, we monitored seedlings from transgenic lines obtained in our lab through T-DNA transformation in tissue culture. One regenerated line stood out because of the occurrence of longer seminal (primary) roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g001">Fig. 1A–B</xref>), a phenotype that co-segregated recessively with the T-DNA insertion (χ<sup>2</sup> test two-tailed p value = 0.7697). Isolation of the flanking genomic DNA by an inverse PCR strategy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Thole1">[27]</xref> revealed that this line contains only one T-DNA locus, whose integration site is located in the <italic>Bd2g04290</italic> gene. Both the copy number and the insertion site were confirmed by whole genome sequencing of the homozygous mutant line (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1A</xref>). <italic>Bd2g04290</italic> is one of the two <italic>TAA1/TAR</italic> homologs of Brachypodium, the other one being <italic>Bd2g34400</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Phillips1">[26]</xref>. Based on their closest homologs in Arabidopsis, we named them <italic>Brachypodium distachyon TAR2-LIKE</italic> (<italic>BdTAR2L</italic>, <italic>Bd2g04290</italic>) and <italic>Brachypodium distachyon TAR1-LIKE</italic> (<italic>BdTAR1L</italic>, <italic>Bd2g34400</italic>), respectively. Quantitative RT-PCR (qPCR) to monitor expression of both genes in dissected seedling tissues indicated that <italic>BdTAR1L</italic> expression is dominant in the root meristem, whereas relative <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> expression increases strongly in the elongating and mature parts of the root, and in the shoot tissues (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1B</xref>). The T-DNA insertion in this <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> mutant is located 140 bp upstream of the ATG codon, thereby presumably disrupting the 5′ UTR, but not the coding sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). To determine whether and to what extent the T-DNA insertion affects <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> expression, we quantified <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> mRNA levels by qPCR in 4-day-old seedlings. Indeed, expression was still detected both in shoot and root tissue, however at severely reduced levels of less than 20% and 5%, respectively, as compared to wild type or an unrelated transformant (the unrelated transformant line was included in all our assays to control for any tissue culture regeneration effects and contains a single copy T-DNA insert in a non-annotated, possibly repetitive region as determined by whole genome sequencing) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g001">Fig. 1D–E</xref>). Therefore, it appears that our <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> mutation represents a hypomorphic allele, which we thus named <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic>. Interestingly, plants that are homozygous for the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutation display dramatically elongated roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g001">Fig. 1F–G</xref>), compared to which the shoot phenotype is rather mild. We could not detect any difference to wild type in the vegetative growth pattern, but observed a general decrease in overall leaf size to ca. 80% of wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g001">Fig. 1H–M</xref>). Reproductive development in the mutant progresses normal without any apparent defects in inflorescence development, and plants are fully fertile.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003564-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Isolation of the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutant and characterization of macroscopic phenotypes.</title>
<p>(<italic>A</italic>) Four-day-old tissue culture grown seedlings of wild type (accession Bd21), an unrelated control transformant (control) (the unrelated transformant line was included in all our assays to control for any tissue culture regeneration effects) and the transgenic line segregating the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutation. (<italic>B</italic>) Seminal root length quantification of the different genotypes at 4 days after germination (dag). (<italic>C</italic>) Schematic presentation of the <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> gene and the location of the T-DNA insertion in the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutant. (<italic>D–E</italic>) Relative expression level of <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> in different genotypes at 4 dag as determined by qPCR and normalized with respect to the housekeeping gene, <italic>BdUBC18</italic>. (<italic>F</italic>) Root elongation in wild type, control and homozygous <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants, assayed at 4 dag. (<italic>G–H</italic>) Quantification of seedling phenotypes at 4 dag. (<italic>I</italic>) Leaf number at 18 dag. (<italic>J–L</italic>) Different size parameters of the 5<sup>th</sup> leaf of plants, assayed at 18 dag. (<italic>M</italic>) Representative image of adult plants at 18 dag. Size bars are 1 cm; differences as compared to wild type are not significant unless indicated otherwise; error bars indicate standard error; * = p&lt;0.05; ** = p&lt;0.01; *** = p&lt;0.001.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Increased cellular anisotropy in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots</title>
<p>A closer look at the mutant roots revealed that their phenotype is principally due to increased cellular anisotropy, which is most apparent in the post-meristematic, differentiated region. For instance, mature cortical cell length in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots reaches typically ca. 150% of wild type control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g002">Fig. 2A–B</xref>), which would largely account for the overall increase in root length. We did indeed not observe a difference in root meristem size, measured as the number of cells that constitute the division and transition zones of the meristem in the central metaxylem cell file (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g002">Fig. 2C–D</xref>). Also, metaxylem cell length at equal position in the meristem is similar in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> and wild type up to the elongation zone, from where on cells elongate dramatically faster in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> than in wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>). At the same time, the transverse total as well as stele area of mature roots is reduced in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> to ca. 85% of wild type, accompanied by a slight reduction in the number of cells along the circumference of the innermost cortex layer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g002">Fig. 2E–H</xref>). A quantitative analysis of transverse sections using an automated segmentation pipeline indicated that the number of cells in the outer six cell layers is indeed slightly reduced in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g002">Fig. 2I–J</xref>). Moreover, except in the epidermal layer, transverse cell area is in tendency smaller in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g002">Fig. 2K</xref>). Therefore, mature root cells are overall thinner and longer than in wild type. Interestingly, this change in cellular anisotropy also manifests in the morphology of the root hairs, which are extensions of the epidermal cells and shorter in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g002">Fig. 2L–M</xref>). In summary, while the decreased diameter of <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots can be explained by a combination of a slight decrease in cell proliferation and in expansion in the radial dimension, their increased length can be attributed to enhanced cell elongation. Thus, the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> root phenotype largely results from increased cellular anisotropy.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003564-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Cellular root phenotypes of <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants.</title>
<p>(<italic>A</italic>) Representative Nomarski optics images of mature root portions. s: stele; c: cortex layers; e: epidermis; arrowheads point out top and bottom of individual cells in the 3<sup>rd</sup> cortex layer; (<italic>B</italic>) Quantification of mature cortex cell length at 4 dag. (<italic>C</italic>) Confocal image of a 4-day-old Brachypodium wild type (Bd21) root meristem (top) and quantification of the progression of cell elongation per cell position (for the 60 cells above the stem cell niche) in the central metaxylem (cmx) (bottom). co: columella; DZ: division zone; TZ: transition zone; EZ: elongation zone; (<italic>D</italic>) Quantification of meristem size as number of metaxylem cells in the combined DZ and TZ. (<italic>E</italic>) Representative light microscopy images of transverse sections across the mature root. (<italic>F–H</italic>) Quantification of total area and stele area in root sections, as well as number of cells in the circumference of the innermost cortex layer. (<italic>I</italic>) Illustration of the segmentation process for quantification of root sections. Overlay of segmented cell shapes (green) on the section (top), labeling of cell layers after filtering (bottom). (<italic>J</italic>) Combined epidermal and cortical cell number in root sections. (<italic>K</italic>) Transverse cell area in root sections, for different cell layers from outside to inside. (<italic>L</italic>) Representative microscopy images of root hairs at 4 dag. (<italic>M</italic>) Quantification of root hair length in 4-day-old seedlings. Size bars are 100 µm; differences as compared to wild type or mock are not significant unless indicated otherwise; error bars indicate standard error; * = p&lt;0.05; *** = p&lt;0.001.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Characterization of another loss-of-function allele of <italic>BdTAR2L</italic></title>
<p>To independently corroborate the effects of reduced <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> expression, we obtained another mutant allele from the Brachypodium T-DNA collection in which the gene is disrupted by a T-DNA insertion in the second intron (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1C</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Bragg1">[28]</xref>. In semi-quantitative RT-PCR, a cDNA fragment comprising the borders of exons 1 and 2 was nearly undetectable (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1D</xref>), and compared to the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> allele, <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> expression in the root as monitored by qPCR was even more severely reduced, to 1–2% of wild type levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). However, since we could not exclude production of some residual full-length transcript, we designated this allele a quasi-null mutant (<italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic>). Compared to their wild type background, Bd21-3, <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutants again display an elongated root phenotype, which is however not as drastic as in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g003">Fig. 3B–C</xref>). This could again be largely attributed to increased cell elongation, which reaches about 125% of wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g003">Fig. 3D–E</xref>). Moreover, <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutants also display shorter root hairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g003">Fig. 3F</xref>). At the same time, transverse root and stele area are reduced to about the levels observed in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants, without a change in the number of cortical cell layers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g003">Fig. 3G–I</xref>). Therefore, similar to <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic>, <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutants display increased cell elongation and cellular anisotropy in the root. Unlike in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants, however, exaggerated root growth is not sustained in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutants although the enhanced cell elongation is maintained (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g003">Fig. 3J</xref>). This is because of a gradual consumption of the root meristem as development proceeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g003">Fig. 3K</xref>). Compared to <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic>, <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutants also display more severe shoot phenotypes, notably a clearly reduced shoot length in young seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g003">Fig. 3L</xref>) and a dwarf stature as an adult (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g003">Fig. 3M</xref>), which is accompanied by severely reduced fertility. Collectively, our mutant characterizations therefore suggest that the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> and <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutants indeed represent an allelic series that displays the consequences of gradually reduced <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> dosage.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003564-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Phenotypes of the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutant in comparison to its wild type background, Bd21-3.</title>
<p>(<italic>A</italic>) Relative expression level of <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> in different genotypes at 4 dag as determined by qPCR and normalized with respect to the housekeeping gene, <italic>BdUBC18</italic>. (<italic>B–C</italic>) Root elongation in wild type and <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutants, assayed at 4 dag. (<italic>D</italic>) Representative Nomarski optics images of mature root portions. Arrowheads point out top and bottom of individual cells in a cortex layer; (<italic>E</italic>) Quantification of mature cortex cell length at 4 dag. (<italic>F</italic>) Representative microscopy images of root hairs at 4 dag. (<italic>G</italic>) Representative light microscopy images of transverse sections across the mature root. (<italic>H–I</italic>) Quantification of total transverse area and stele area in sections from mature roots. (<italic>J</italic>) Relative seminal root length in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutants during root growth progression. (<italic>K</italic>) Progressive breakdown of root meristem as indicated by shrinkage of the meristematic zone. (<italic>L</italic>) Seedling shoot length at 4 dag. (<italic>M</italic>) Adult shoots. Size bars are 1 cm (<italic>B, M</italic>) or 100 µm (<italic>D,F,G</italic>); differences as compared to wild type or mock are not significant unless indicated otherwise; error bars indicate standard error; * = p&lt;0.05; *** = p&lt;0.001.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Mimic of the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> phenotype by L-kynerunine treatment of wild type plants</title>
<p>The low <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> expression level in the mutants is not compensated by up-regulated <italic>BdTAR1L</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1E</xref>) and therefore should result in overall decreased tryptophan aminotransferase activity. However, the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> long root phenotype is counterintuitive in this respect, because progressive loss-of-function of TAA1/TAR activity in Arabidopsis leads to progressively impaired rather than enhanced root growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Stepanova1">[16]</xref>. The same is true when Arabidopsis wild type plants are grown on a specific competitive inhibitor of TAA1/TAR enzymes, L-kynerunine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-He1">[29]</xref>. To test whether L-kynerunine also inhibits root growth in Brachypodium, we transferred 2-day-old seedlings onto media with different L-kynerunine concentrations and assayed root growth two days later. Strikingly, root elongation was stimulated rather than inhibited already at concentrations as little as 1 µM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g004">Fig. 4A–B</xref>). Higher concentrations, up to 100 µM, strongly promoted root elongation up to 150–200% of the mock controls. Moreover, we observed exaggerated cell elongation upon L-kynerunine treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g004">Fig. 4C–D</xref>), which therefore mimics the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> root phenotype. Interestingly, unlike wild type, the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutant hardly responded to L-kynerunine treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g004">Fig. 4A–D</xref>). Finally, similar to the Arabidopsis <italic>taa1</italic> mutant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Tao1">[20]</xref>, both <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> alleles were hypersensitive to the application of the toxic tryptophan analog, 5-methyl-tryptophan (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g004">Fig. 4E–F</xref>), which is an artificial substrate for TAA/TAR enzymes. 5-methyl-tryptophan can be detoxified by its conversion to IPA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Tao1">[20]</xref>, and therefore 5-methyl-tryptophan hypersensitivity is indicative of reduced IPA production. Thus, the data are consistent with the idea that reduced TAA1/TAR activity in the <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> mutants is indeed responsible for the mutant phenotypes.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003564-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Effect of L-kynerunine (L-kyn) treatment on root elongation of different genotypes.</title>
<p>(<italic>A</italic>) Representative images of 4-day-old seedlings, transferred onto media with indicated L-kyn concentration at 2 dag. (<italic>B</italic>) Quantification of root length after 2 days of indicated L-kyn treatment. (<italic>C</italic>) Representative Nomarski optics images of mature root portions formed during indicated L-kyn treatment. Arrowheads point out top and bottom of individual cells in the 3<sup>rd</sup> cortex layer; (<italic>D</italic>) Quantification of mature cortex cell length after 2 days of indicated L-kyn treatment. (<italic>E–F</italic>) Relative root elongation of indicated mutants and their respective wild type backgrounds after 2 days of indicated 5-methyl-tryptophan treatment. Size bars are 1 cm (<italic>A</italic>) or 100 µm (<italic>C</italic>); differences as compared to wild type or mock are not significant unless indicated otherwise; error bars indicate standard error; * = p&lt;0.05; ** = p&lt;0.01; *** = p&lt;0.001.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Altered root branching patterns in the <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> mutants</title>
<p>While other auxin-dependent processes, such as gravitropism, appeared unaffected in <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1F</xref>), we also observed a root system branching phenotype. In <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants, coleoptile node root formation is slightly reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>), but unlike the seminal roots, coleoptile node roots elongate normally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>). Contrary to the coleoptile node root phenotype, the number of emerged lateral roots from the seminal root is increased in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>). This increase is also evident once lateral root number is normalized for total root length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g005">Fig. 5D</xref>), even if the total number of lateral roots is small. Because it was difficult to follow this phenotype over a longer period in the tissue culture system (due to the limited growth space on our 20 cm dishes) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-PachecoVillalobos1">[30]</xref>, we employed an alternative assay, i.e. lateral root emergence that has been triggered by removal of the seminal root meristem. In this assay, <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants showed enhanced lateral root formation capacity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g005">Fig. 5E</xref>), again also holding up once normalized for seminal root length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g005">Fig. 5F</xref>). Again, this phenotype could be copied by L-kynerunine treatment of wild type (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1G</xref>). Considering that increased <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> root length can be largely explained by cell elongation, it therefore appears that <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants have a genuinely higher capacity of seminal root branching.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003564-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Root branching phenotypes of <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants.</title>
<p>(<italic>A</italic>) Coleoptile node root formation in 25-day-old plants. (<italic>B</italic>) Quantification of coleoptile node root elongation. (<italic>C</italic>) Representative images of 8-day-old seminal roots, note emerged lateral roots. (<italic>D</italic>) Quantification of emerged lateral root number at 8 dag, normalized for seminal root length. (<italic>E</italic>) Representative images of 8-day-old seminal roots, 4 days after removal of the root tip. Note emerged lateral roots. (<italic>F</italic>) Quantification of emerged lateral root number after seminal root tip removal, normalized for seminal root length (per cm). Size bars are 1 cm; differences as compared to wild type are not significant unless indicated otherwise; error bars indicate standard error; ** = p&lt;0.01; *** = p&lt;0.001.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Auxin levels are elevated rather than reduced in <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> roots</title>
<p>Collectively, our genetic as well as pharmacological analyses suggest that reduced tryptophan aminotransferase activity in Brachypodium results in increased root cell elongation and anisotropy. This contrasts with gradually reduced root growth in Arabidopsis <italic>taa1/tar</italic> single and double mutants. As expected, in Arabidopsis this root growth reduction is accompanied by gradually decreased free auxin levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Stepanova2">[17]</xref>. Thus, the most parsimonious explanation for the <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> phenotype is that auxin levels might normally be supra-optimal for cell elongation in Brachypodium, similar to what has been proposed for rice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Yin1">[25]</xref>. To our surprise then, we found that free auxin levels are elevated rather than reduced in <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> seminal roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1H</xref>), in particular in the elongating and mature parts where the expression of <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> is relatively high as compared to <italic>BdTAR1L</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1A</xref>). Consistently, elevated auxin levels where also observed upon L-kynerunine treatment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1I</xref>). To determine whether this could arise from compensatory up-regulation of proposed alternative auxin biosynthesis pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Mano1">[31]</xref>, we checked the expression of various homologs of corresponding rate-limiting enzyme genes in <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> roots, i.e. <italic>AMIDASE-LIKE 1-LIKE</italic> (<italic>BdAMI1L</italic>), <italic>NITRILASE 1-LIKE</italic> (<italic>BdNIT1L</italic>), <italic>ALDEHYDE OXIDASE 1-LIKE</italic> (<italic>BdAO1L</italic>) and <italic>BdAO2L</italic>. However, with the exception of a slight increase in <italic>BdAO1L</italic> expression, no significant upward changes were detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g006">Fig. 6B</xref>). By contrast, the expression of four <italic>YUCCA</italic> homologs, selected for the reported root-specific expression of their respective counterparts in rice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Takehisa1">[32]</xref>, is significantly up-regulated in <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g006">Fig. 6C</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1J</xref>), amounting to more than triple in combined transcript levels in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g006">Fig. 6C</xref>) and one-and-a-half in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic>, corresponding with the respective auxin levels. The increased <italic>BdYUCCA</italic> expression could account for the increased auxin levels, because it has been determined that <italic>YUCCA</italic> gene expression is rate-limiting for auxin biosynthesis via the IPA pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Stepanova2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Mashiguchi1">[33]</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003564-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Auxin homeostasis in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots and its relation to the ethylene pathway.</title>
<p>(<italic>A</italic>) Free auxin (IAA) content in wild type and <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> root segments at 4 dag. The root tip comprised the terminal 8 mm of the roots, the elongated parts all above this. (<italic>B</italic>) Expression levels of the homologs of various genes encoding rate limiting enzymes in alternative auxin biosynthesis pathways in wild type and <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots at 4 dag. (<italic>C</italic>) Expression levels of <italic>YUCCA</italic> homologs in wild type and <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots at 4 dag. (<italic>D</italic>) Expression levels of <italic>BdTAR1L</italic> and <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> in wild type at 3 dag and after 3 h of ACC treatment. (<italic>E</italic>) Expression levels of <italic>YUCCA</italic> homologs in wild type at 3 dag and after 3 h of ACC treatment. All expression levels were determined by qPCR and normalized with respect to the housekeeping gene, <italic>BdUBC18</italic>; differences as compared to wild type or mock are not significant unless indicated otherwise; error bars indicate standard error; * = p&lt;0.05; ** = p&lt;0.01; *** = p&lt;0.001.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2g">
<title><italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots are restored to wild type by application of the ethylene precursor ACC</title>
<p>Root growth resistance to enhanced ethylene production, conferred by application of ACC, contributed to the isolation of the <italic>taa1/tar</italic> mutants in Arabidopsis, because ethylene promotes auxin biosynthesis via the IPA pathway through transcriptional regulation of <italic>TAA1/TAR</italic> and <italic>YUCCA</italic> genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Stepanova1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Liang1">[34]</xref>. By contrast, we found that expression of <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> and <italic>BdTAR1L</italic> is only mildly ethylene-responsive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g006">Fig. 6D</xref>). Moreover, the expression of the four <italic>BdYUCCA</italic> genes tested is negatively regulated by ACC application (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g006">Fig. 6E</xref>). Thus, in Brachypodium, the ethylene pathway might repress rather than promote auxin biosynthesis via the IPA pathway, mainly by down-regulating <italic>BdYUCCA</italic> expression. A prediction from this observation is that the <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> root phenotypes might be rescued by enhanced ethylene signaling. To test this notion, we transferred 2-day-old <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> seedlings onto media containing increasing amounts of ACC and monitored root growth over the two days that followed. Indeed, ACC treatment strongly impaired <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> root elongation and reduced growth to about the level of wild type mock controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g007">Fig. 7A–B</xref>). Moreover, ACC treatment restored cell elongation to wild type length in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g007">Fig. 7E–F</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003564-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Manipulation of the ethylene pathway and its impact on root growth.</title>
<p>(<italic>A</italic>) Representative images of 4-day-old seedlings, transferred onto media with indicated ACC concentration at 2 dag. (<italic>B</italic>) Quantification of root length after 2 days of indicated ACC treatment. (<italic>C</italic>) Representative images of 4-day-old seedlings, transferred onto media with indicated AVG concentration at 2 dag. (<italic>D</italic>) Quantification of root length after 2 days of indicated AVG treatment. (<italic>E</italic>) Representative Nomarski optics images of mature root portions formed during indicated ACC or AVG treatment. Arrowheads point out top and bottom of individual cells in the 3<sup>rd</sup> cortex layer; (<italic>F–G</italic>) Quantification of mature cortex cell length after 2 days of indicated ACC or AVG treatment. (<italic>H</italic>) Schematic presentation of the <italic>BdEIN2L1</italic> gene and the location of the T-DNA insertion in the <italic>Bdein2l1<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutant. (<italic>I</italic>) Relative expression level of <italic>BdEIN2L1</italic> in the <italic>Bdein2l1<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots at 4 dag. (<italic>J</italic>) Representative seedlings of wild type and <italic>Bdein2l1<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants at 4 dag. (<italic>K</italic>) Quantification of root length in wild type and <italic>Bdein2l1<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants at 4 dag. (<italic>L</italic>) Expression levels of <italic>BdTAR1L</italic> and <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> in wild type and <italic>Bdein2l1<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots at 4 dag. (<italic>M</italic>) Expression levels of <italic>YUCCA</italic> homologs in wild type and <italic>Bdein2l1<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots at 4 dag. All expression levels were determined by qPCR and normalized with respect to the housekeeping gene, <italic>BdUBC18</italic>; size bars are 1 cm (<italic>A, C</italic>) or 100 µm (<italic>E</italic>); differences as compared to wild type or mock are not significant unless indicated otherwise; error bars indicate standard error; * = p&lt;0.05; ** = p&lt;0.01; *** = p&lt;0.001.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2h">
<title>The <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> root phenotype can be mimicked by reduced ethylene biosynthesis or signaling</title>
<p>The above results suggested that inhibition of ethylene biosynthesis or signaling in Brachypodium roots should mimic the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> root phenotype. We tested this notion by transferring 2-day-old seedlings onto media that contained aminoethoxyvinylglycine (AVG), an inhibitor of a rate-limiting enzyme in ethylene biosynthesis, ACC synthase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Adams1">[35]</xref>. Following root growth over the two days that followed revealed that <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots are largely resistant to AVG, while wild type roots display a dramatic increase in elongation that approached the levels observed in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g007">Fig. 7C–D</xref>). Investigation of cortical cells revealed that again this effect could be explained by increased cell elongation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g007">Fig. 7E, G</xref>). Higher levels of AVG eventually slowed down elongation rate of <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots, but still promoted root elongation in wild type. A cautionary note on AVG is that it not only inhibits ACC synthase, but also other enzymes that require pyridoxal 5′-phosphate (PLP) as a cofactor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Clausen1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Krupka1">[37]</xref>. Since the activity of TAA1/TAR enzymes is stimulated by PLP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Stepanova1">[16]</xref>, it appears possible that AVG treatment impairs their function to some degree, mimicking L-kynerunine treatment. Thus, for independent confirmation we took advantage of a mutant from the Brachypodium T-DNA collection, in which a homolog of the Arabidopsis gene <italic>ETHYLENE INSENSITIVE 2</italic> (<italic>EIN2</italic>), an essential positive regulator of ethylene signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Alonso1">[38]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Qiao1">[40]</xref>, carries a T-DNA insertion in the promoter, 469 bp upstream of the start codon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g007">Fig. 7H</xref>). As a consequence, expression of this <italic>EIN2-LIKE</italic> (<italic>BdEIN2L1</italic>, <italic>Bd4g08380</italic>) gene is significantly down-regulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g007">Fig. 7I</xref>). Strikingly, this hypomorphic mutant (<italic>Bdein2l1<sup>hypo</sup></italic>) displays a <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> root phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g007">Fig. 7J–K</xref>), and while this is not accompanied by up-regulation of <italic>BdTAR1L</italic> or <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g007">Fig. 7L</xref>), it is accompanied by increased <italic>BdYUCCA</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g007">Fig. 7M</xref>). Finally, similar to <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> mutants, auxin levels are elevated in the elongating parts of <italic>Bdein2l1<sup>hypo</sup></italic> roots (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1K</xref>), thereby corroborating our above findings.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2i">
<title>Root elongation is only slightly stimulated by L-kynerunine or AVG treatment in Arabidopsis</title>
<p>The observed stimulatory effects of L-kynerunine and AVG treatment on root elongation have not been described for Arabidopsis. However, given the morphological differences between Arabidopsis and Brachypodium roots, in particular the more than three-fold difference in thickness, it is conceivable that the concentration of those substances required for root penetration and biological action might be different as well. The described largely inhibitory effect of those treatments on root elongation in Arabidopsis could therefore have resulted from application of too high concentrations. These considerations prompted us to revisit the response of Arabidopsis to an extended concentration range of both L-kynerunine and AVG. Interestingly, relatively low concentrations as compared to Brachypodium of both treatments indeed slightly promote root elongation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1003564.s001">Fig. S1L</xref>–M), although by far not as strong as in Brachypodium.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The root systems of dicotyledons and monocotyledons display some fundamental differences in their organization and ontogeny, as exemplified by the respective model systems, Arabidopsis and Brachypodium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-PachecoVillalobos1">[30]</xref>. Despite these differences, the principal genes involved in root formation, growth vigor and branching are expected to be homologous in the two systems. This is based on experience in other species such as maize, where several causative mutations that affect root system development are in homologs of auxin signaling components <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Hochholdinger2">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Hochholdinger3">[41]</xref>. The effect of manipulating the IPA branch of auxin biosynthesis has been investigated in another monocotyledon crop, rice, through gain- and loss-of-function approaches. For instance, both over-expression and down-regulation of the <italic>YUCCA</italic> homolog <italic>OsYUCCA1</italic> by transgenic means results in strongly reduced root growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Yamamoto1">[42]</xref>, whereas a knockout in another <italic>YUCCA</italic> homolog, <italic>CONSTITUTIVELY WILTED 1</italic>, displays reduced root branching <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Woo1">[43]</xref>. Compared to those mutants, the enhanced root elongation phenotype of <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> mutants is unusual. Our initial interpretation was therefore that auxin levels are supra-optimal for cell elongation in the Brachypodium seminal root, as has been suggested for seminal root growth in rice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Yin1">[25]</xref>. However, repeated independent measurements of multiple samples clearly indicated that auxin levels are increased rather than decreased in <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> mutant roots. This is particularly pronounced in the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> allele, and in tendency also observed in the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> allele, correlating with quantitatively corresponding <italic>BdYUCCA</italic> up-regulation. The comparatively severe shoot phenotypes of the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> allele, its less pronounced root cell elongation, and the observation that the root meristem gradually breaks down as development progresses indicate that compared to the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> allele, IPA levels are eventually limiting in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutants. This idea is supported by the dose-response curve of wild type to L-kynerunine, where increasing amounts promote cell elongation up to a certain threshold, beyond which root growth is inhibited. Further corroborating this idea, a threshold also exists for the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutant, which moreover is hypersensitive to L-kynerunine treatment as concentrations that still promote root elongation in wild type are inhibitory in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic>.</p>
<p>A similar dose-response curve is observed for AVG treatment, which inhibits the rate-limiting step in ethylene biosynthesis, but might also impinge on TAA1/TAR activity because of its generic action on enzymes that use PLP as a co-factor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Stepanova1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Clausen1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Krupka1">[37]</xref>. Stimulation of root growth by AVG treatment has also been reported for rice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Yin1">[25]</xref>, although the reported dosage response is quantitatively different from our assays with Brachypodium. For instance, while in rice 0.05 µM AVG promoted root growth and 1.0 µM was already inhibitory, in Brachypodium 5.0 µM was still stimulating. In part, this could be due to technical issues, for instance the concentration needed in the tissue culture media to reach the same tissue penetration in roots of different thickness or cell permeability. In light of our results, it appears possible that the response of rice to AVG treatment is similar to Brachypodium, i.e. that it could reflect a combined effect of reducing TAA1/TAR as well as ACC synthase activity, thereby boosting auxin levels by removing the inhibitory effect of ethylene on <italic>YUCCA</italic> expression as long as interference with TAA/TAR1 activity does not lead to limiting IPA levels. The finding that <italic>YUCCA</italic> expression is rate limiting for auxin biosynthesis in Arabidopsis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Stepanova2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Mashiguchi1">[33]</xref> supports this interpretation, suggesting that this is also likely the case in Brachypodium and/or rice.</p>
<p>Corroborating the effects of AVG application and circumventing its ambiguity, the root phenotype of the <italic>Bdein2l1<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutant confirms the involvement of the ethylene-signaling pathway in auxin homeostasis. However, based on the observed regulatory logic of this hormone crosstalk, a central finding of our study is that the regulation of the IPA branch of auxin biosynthesis through the ethylene pathway observed in Arabidopsis roots might not be conserved in Brachypodium. This idea is based on several convergent observations, for instance that unlike their Arabidopsis counterparts, expression of <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> as well as <italic>BdTAR1L</italic> is hardly ethylene-responsive or that <italic>BdYUCCAs</italic> are repressed upon ACC treatment and up-regulated in <italic>Bdein2l1<sup>hypo</sup></italic>, consistent with the latter's <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> phenotype. Moreover, unlike Arabidopsis <italic>taa1/tar</italic> mutants, <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants are not ACC-resistant. Rather, ACC treatment essentially restores the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> phenotype to wild type. Thus, our data thus support a scenario in which the effects of auxin biosynthesis through the IPA branch on root cell elongation are mediated by the ethylene pathway rather than <italic>vice versa</italic>. Such an inversion of a regulatory relationship could alternatively reflect a shift in the key nodes of the regulatory network linking auxin and ethylene through feedback loops and is a simple way for evolutionary adaptation. Indeed, feedback of ethylene on auxin biosynthesis by repressing <italic>YUCCA</italic> expression, rather than promoting <italic>TAA1/TAR</italic> as well as <italic>YUCCA</italic> expression as in Arabidopsis, is a central feature of the mutant phenotypes described in our paper (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1003564-g008">Fig. 8</xref>). How this feedback is mediated remains unclear for the moment. The recent discovery of an enzymatic link between auxin and ethylene biosynthesis suggests that this crosstalk might very well respond directly to IPA levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Zheng1">[44]</xref>. Hypomorphic mutants, such as those employed in our study, might become a crucial tool in future efforts to elaborate such a scenario.</p>
<fig id="pgen-1003564-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>A schematic overview of the regulation of tryptophan-dependent auxin (indole-3-acetic acid) biosynthesis via indole-3-pyruvic acid (IPA) by ethylene action in Arabidopsis (<italic>A</italic>) and Brachypodium (<italic>B</italic>).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>Molecular biology and genetics procedures, such as genomic DNA isolation, genotyping, sequencing or qPCR were performed according to standard procedures as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Scacchi1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Sibout2">[46]</xref>.</p>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Plant materials and growth conditions</title>
<p>The community standard diploid inbreed <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> line Bd21 was used for transformation and as a control in all experiments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Vogel1">[47]</xref>, except for the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutant (stock id JJ9248.0) and the <italic>Bdein2l1<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutant (stock id JJ110.0), which together with their Bd21-3 wild type background line were obtained from a Brachypodium T-DNA collection (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brachypodium.pw.usda.gov/TDNA/" xlink:type="simple">http://brachypodium.pw.usda.gov/TDNA/</ext-link>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Bragg1">[28]</xref>. Genotyping, for instance to establish homozygous mutant lines, was performed using oligonucleotides <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CGT GAG AGC TAG TGG GAT AG-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-ATG GGT GGC TGA TGG CGT AG-3′</named-content> (<italic>BdTAR2L</italic> wild type allele for <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CGT GAG AGC TAG TGG GAT AG-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-TTG AAG GAG CCA CTC AGC CGC G-3′</named-content> (<italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> T-DNA insertion); <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GCG GTT CCC TGT TCA TCT TC-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CAC AGC GAA ACA ACA CAC AG-3′</named-content> (<italic>BdTAR2L</italic> wild type allele control for <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GCG GTT CCC TGT TCA TCT TC-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-TAC GAG CCG GAA GCA TA AAG-3′</named-content> (<italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> T-DNA insertion); <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GTA CCT TTC TCC GTC AAG AG-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GAA GGA GGC ATC AGG ACA TG-3′</named-content> (<italic>BdEIN2L1</italic> wild type allele), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′- GTA CCT TTC TCC GTC AAG AG -3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CTC CGC TCA TGA TCA GAT TG-3′</named-content> (<italic>Bdein2l1<sup>hypo</sup></italic> T-DNA insertion); <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> experiments were performed with the standard Col-0 accession. For tissue culture growth, the lemma of mature seeds was carefully peeled off with forceps before seed sterilization in 1 ml of 70% ethanol per seed for 1 min. After ethanol removal, seeds were soaked in a solution of 1.3% sodium hypochlorite plus one drop of Tween-20 per 50 ml for 5 min. with gently rocking, then rinsed with sterile deionized water three times. The sterilized seeds were stratified for 2 days at 4°C to ensure synchronous germination on vertically oriented 10 or 24 cm square plates of half-strength Murashige-Skoog (MS) media (2.45 g/l MS salts with vitamins, 1% sucrose, 1% agar, pH 5.7) in a growth chamber under continuous light of 100–120 µE intensity at 22°C. To quantify leaf number, sheath/blade length and blade width, 2-day-old Brachypodium seedlings were transferred into pots with soil, watered every 2–3 days and incubated at 22°C under a 20 h photoperiod. Leaf features were measured 18 days after germination (dag), crown roots were counted 25 dag. Arabidopsis seedlings were grown as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Sibout2">[46]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Seminal root length and lateral root number quantification, and root gravitropism assays</title>
<p>To determine root length, seedlings growing in vertically oriented plates were either scanned or photographed with a digital camera to measure root length using the ImageJ software, version 1.47b. For lateral root quantification after seminal root meristem removal, 2 mm of the root tip were cut from the seminal root of 4-day-old plants with a scalpel. The number of visible lateral roots was then scored 4 days later. For gravitropism assays, Brachypodium seeds were germinated for 2 days in vertically oriented plates. To induce gravitropic response, plates were then rotated 90° and grown for another 24 hours. Plates were scanned on a flatbed scanner before and after gravitropic stimulation.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Transformation of <italic>Bd21</italic> and FST-retrieval</title>
<p>Embryonic calli generation of Bd21 was performed according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Alves1">[48]</xref>, subsequent transformation with the pVec8GFP plasmid and plant regeneration according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Vogel1">[47]</xref>, and retrieval and mapping of the region flanking the right border of the T-DNA insert in <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutants according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Thole1">[27]</xref>. A total of 48 transgenic lines were produced, among which the <italic>Bdtarl<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutant was a chance hit.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Whole genome sequencing and T-DNA insertion mapping</title>
<p>Whole genome sequencing of genomic DNA isolated from Brachypodium seedlings was performed on the Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform, generating more than 250 mio. paired-end reads of 100 bp length. The Bowtie 2 software <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Langmead1">[49]</xref> was used for the alignment on the <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> reference genome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mips.helmholtz-muenchen.de/plant/brachypodium/download/index.jsp" xlink:type="simple">http://mips.helmholtz-muenchen.de/plant/brachypodium/download/index.jsp</ext-link>), revealing coverage of ca. 100 reads per bp. For detection of T-DNA insertions, reads that aligned on the T-DNA reference sequence were selected for alignment on the genome. This procedure confirmed the localization of the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> insert on chromosome 2 (position: 3,030,511). The precise position of the control line insert remains undetermined because it could not be mapped to a unique annotated region, however it is clear that it does not disrupt any annotated gene. Finally, coverage of the T-DNA reference sequence was similar to genome coverage, confirming the presence of a single insertion in both sequenced genomes.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4e">
<title>Hormone and inhibitor treatments</title>
<p>The hormone and inhibitor treatments were done on plates, except in the case of qPCR, for which treatments were carried out in liquid media for 3 h. Briefly, Brachypodium seeds were germinated on standard plates as described above. At 2 days after germination, seedlings were then transferred to media containing the respective hormone or inhibitor, or mock. For Arabidopsis treatments, 4-day-old seedlings were transferred.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4f">
<title>Auxin measurements</title>
<p>Auxin measurements were performed on eight independent samples of pooled roots per genotype excised from 4-day-old seedlings as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Andersen1">[50]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4g">
<title>Microscopy</title>
<p>Seminal roots of 4-day-old seedlings were fixed in a solution of 1% glutaraldehyde, 4% formaldehyde and 50 mM sodium phosphate buffer (pH 7.2). Fixed roots were thoroughly rinsed four times with water. To determine transverse root and cell area, roots were cut into 0.5–1 cm pieces and embedded in 6% agarose. Sections of 75 µm were obtained approximately 2 cm from the root tip using a Leica-VT 1000S vibratome. Sections were stained with 0.1% toluidine blue solution for 30 s and washed. For quantification of cortical cell length, unstained roots were cleared with 10% potassium hydroxide solution at 95°C for 30 min. Roots were mounted on glass slides with 50% glycerol and photographed either in light field or differential interference contrast using a Leica DM5500B compound microscope. For visualization of meristem structure, seminal roots were stained following the mPS-PI procedure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Scacchi1">[45]</xref> before imaging with a Zeiss LSM 700 confocal microscope. Cortical cell length, root hair length, meristem size and central metaxylem cell length were quantified using the ImageJ software, version 1.47b.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4h">
<title>qPCR and oligonucleotides</title>
<p>qPCR reactions were performed using a Stratagene MxPro 3005P Real-Time PCR System (Stratagene). Three technical replicates were analyzed for each sample. The specificity of each amplification reaction was verified by DNA melting curve analysis and gel electrophoresis of the amplified products. Not reverse transcribed samples and non-template controls were included in every assay to rule out genomic DNA contamination. The final threshold cycle (Ct), efficiency and initial fluorescence (R<sub>0</sub>) for every reaction were calculated with the Miner algorithm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen.1003564-Zhao3">[51]</xref>. Relative expression levels were obtained from the ratio between R<sub>0</sub> of the target gene and R<sub>0</sub> of the reference gene, <italic>UBIQUITIN-CONJUGATING ENZYME 18</italic> (<italic>BdUBC18</italic>). The following oligonucleotides were used: <italic>BdUBC18</italic> (<italic>Bd4G00660</italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GGA GGC ACC TCA GGT CAT TT-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-ATA GCG GTC ATT GTC TTG CG-3′</named-content>; <italic>BdTAR1L</italic> (<italic>Bd2G34400</italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GAA TCG GGA TGG TGG CCT CG-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-ATT GTC GGA TCG CCG TGA TC-3′</named-content>; <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> (<italic>Bd2G04290</italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GGC TCC ATA CTA CTC TTC GTA TC-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CAG TAG TAG GCC AGG TCG TG-3′</named-content>; <italic>BdYUCCA1L</italic> (<italic>Bd1G28967</italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GCA ATG GCT CAA GGG AAG TG-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-TGT GGC AGT TTG ATG CTT CC-3′</named-content>; <italic>BdYUCCA7L</italic> (<italic>Bd1G00587</italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GCA GTG GCT CAA GGG AAG C-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-TGT GGT ATG CTG TGG CGA TG-3′</named-content>; <italic>BdYUCCA8L</italic> (<italic>Bd5G01327</italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CCC AGT TCA TCT CCT ACC TC-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GGT ACT CGA CGG TGG ACT TC-3′</named-content>; <italic>BdYUCCA13L</italic> (<italic>Bd2G10302</italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GTC GTC CGC AGC GAG CTT CA-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GGG GGT TTG GAG CTT CAT GG-3′</named-content>; <italic>BdAMI1L</italic> (<italic>Bd5G27490</italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CGA CTT CTC CCT CGG AAC TG-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GTT GCT GAC GCG AGA CAA TG-3′</named-content>; <italic>BdNIT1L</italic> (<italic>Bd3G49620</italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CCC CTG CCA CCA TTG ATA AAG-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GTC TTC TTT TCC CTT GGC AG-3′</named-content>; <italic>BdAO1L</italic> (<italic>Bd1G52740</italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GGC TGT GGC GAA GGT GGA TG-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-ACC CTC AGT GGT GAT AAC TG-3′</named-content>; <italic>BdAO2L</italic> (<italic>Bd1G56667</italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GTG GAC CCA GTG CAA ATG TG-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CAT ATA CAG CCT CCC CAG AAG-3′</named-content>; <italic>BdEIN2L1</italic> (<italic>Bd4G08380</italic>), <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-AGA ATC TTG CCC AGA TTT GC-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GCA AAC CAT ATG CCT GTG AG-3′</named-content>;</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pgen.1003564.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003564.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><italic>A</italic>) Overview of whole genome sequencing data obtained for the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>hypo</sup></italic> mutant and the unrelated control transformant. Reads are 100 bp paired-end, border refers to reads that connect the T-DNA insert to the genomic location. (<italic>B</italic>) Relative <italic>BdTAR1L</italic> and <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> expression in dissected tissues from 4-day-old seedlings as determined by qPCR and normalized with respect to the housekeeping gene, <italic>BdUBC18</italic> (ratio of the ratios, i.e. ((<italic>BdTAR1L/BdUBC18</italic>)/<italic>(BdTAR2L/BdUBC18</italic>))). (<italic>C</italic>) Schematic presentation of the <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> gene and the location of the T-DNA insertion in the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutant. (<italic>D</italic>) Semi-quantitative RT-PCR of <italic>BdTAR2L</italic> and <italic>BdTAR1L</italic> in the <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> mutant and its wild type background, Bd21-3. (<italic>E</italic>) Relative <italic>BdTAR1L</italic> expression in 4-day-old roots of the two <italic>Bdtar2l</italic> mutants compared to their wild type backgrounds. (<italic>F</italic>) Reorientation of root growth after change of the gravity vector by 90 degrees. (<italic>G</italic>) Quantification of emerged lateral root number at 10 dag in wild type, 8 days after transfer on mock or L-kynerunine, normalized for seminal root length. (<italic>H</italic>) Free auxin (IAA) content in wild type and <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> elongated root segments at 4 dag, i.e. excluding the terminal 8 mm of the root tip. (<italic>I</italic>) Free auxin (IAA) content in wild type root tip and elongated root segments at 4 dag, after a preceding 2 d treatment with mock or 10 µM L-kynerunine. (<italic>J</italic>) Expression levels of <italic>YUCCA</italic> homologs in wild type and <italic>Bdtar2l<sup>qnull</sup></italic> roots at 8 dag. (<italic>K</italic>) Free auxin (IAA) content in wild type and <italic>Bdein2l1</italic> root tips and elongated root segments at 4 dag. (<italic>L</italic>) Time course of root elongation in Arabidopsis wild type (Col-0) seedlings after transfer on media with indicated concentration of L-kynerunine at 2 dag. (<italic>M</italic>) Time course of root elongation in Arabidopsis wild type (Col-0) seedlings after transfer on media with indicated concentration of AVG at 2 dag. Expression levels determined by qPCR were normalized with respect to the housekeeping gene, <italic>BdUBC18</italic>; differences as compared to wild type or mock are not significant unless indicated otherwise; error bars indicate standard error; * = p&lt;0.05; ** = p&lt;0.01; *** = p&lt;0.001.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank A. Amiguet-Vercher, C. Nussbaumer and R. Granbom for excellent technical assistance, B. Tissot-dit-Safin for excellent plant care, and our colleagues M. Bevan, J. Vogel and P. Vain for Brachypodium seeds and plasmids.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Lynch1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Root Architecture and Plant Productivity</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Osmont1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osmont</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sibout</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardtke</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Hidden branches: developments in root system architecture</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Fitter1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linkohr</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Root system architecture determines fitness in an Arabidopsis mutant in competition for immobile phosphate ions but not for nitrate ions</article-title>. <source>Proc Biol Sci</source> <volume>269</volume>: <fpage>2017</fpage>–<lpage>2022</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Linkohr1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linkohr</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fitter</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Nitrate and phosphate availability and distribution have different effects on root system architecture of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>751</fpage>–<lpage>760</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Aiken1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aiken</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smucker</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Root system regulation of whole plant growth</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-deDorlodot1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Dorlodot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pages</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tuberosa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Root system architecture: opportunities and constraints for genetic improvement of crops</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>474</fpage>–<lpage>481</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Benfey1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benfey</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schiefelbein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Getting to the root of plant biology: impact of the Arabidopsis genome sequence on root research</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>992</fpage>–<lpage>1000</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Hochholdinger1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochholdinger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tuberosa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genetic and genomic dissection of maize root development and architecture</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Hochholdinger2"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochholdinger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Conserved and diverse mechanisms in root development</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Inukai1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inukai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ueguchi-Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Crown rootless1, which is essential for crown root formation in rice, is a target of an AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR in auxin signaling</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1387</fpage>–<lpage>1396</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Liu1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>ARL1, a LOB-domain protein required for adventitious root formation in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Hardtke1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardtke</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berleth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis gene MONOPTEROS encodes a transcription factor mediating embryo axis formation and vascular development</article-title>. <source>Embo J</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1405</fpage>–<lpage>1411</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Hardtke2"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardtke</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ckurshumova</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vidaurre</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stamatiou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Overlapping and non-redundant functions of the Arabidopsis auxin response factors MONOPTEROS and NONPHOTOTROPIC HYPOCOTYL 4</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>1089</fpage>–<lpage>1100</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Dharmasiri1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dharmasiri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dharmasiri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weijers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lechner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Plant development is regulated by a family of auxin receptor F box proteins</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Won1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Won</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mashiguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Conversion of tryptophan to indole-3-acetic acid by TRYPTOPHAN AMINOTRANSFERASES OF ARABIDOPSIS and YUCCAs in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>18518</fpage>–<lpage>18523</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Stepanova1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stepanova</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson-Hoyt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benavente</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>TAA1-mediated auxin biosynthesis is essential for hormone crosstalk and plant development</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Stepanova2"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stepanova</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis YUCCA1 flavin monooxygenase functions in the indole-3-pyruvic acid branch of auxin biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>3961</fpage>–<lpage>3973</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Zhao1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hull</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Trp-dependent auxin biosynthesis in Arabidopsis: involvement of cytochrome P450s CYP79B2 and CYP79B3</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>3100</fpage>–<lpage>3112</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Zhao2"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cashman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A role for flavin monooxygenase-like enzymes in auxin biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>291</volume>: <fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Tao1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pojer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Rapid synthesis of auxin via a new tryptophan-dependent pathway is required for shade avoidance in plants</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>164</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Yamada1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prigge</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Estelle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The TRANSPORT INHIBITOR RESPONSE2 gene is required for auxin synthesis and diverse aspects of plant development</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>151</volume>: <fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Garrett1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meents</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackshaw</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackshaw</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A novel, semi-dominant allele of MONOPTEROS provides insight into leaf initiation and vein pattern formation</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>236</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Krogan1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krogan</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ckurshumova</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marcos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caragea</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berleth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Deletion of MP/ARF5 domains III and IV reveals a requirement for Aux/IAA regulation in Arabidopsis leaf vascular patterning</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>194</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Sibout1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibout</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sukumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hettiarachchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muday</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Opposite root growth phenotypes of hy5 versus hy5 hyh mutants correlate with increased constitutive auxin signaling</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e202</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Yin1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Endogenous Auxin is Required but Supraoptimal for Rapid Growth of Rice (Oryza sativa L.) Seminal Roots, and Auxin Inhibition of Rice Seminal Root Growth is Not Caused by Ethylene</article-title>. <source>Journal of Plant Growth Regulation</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Phillips1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skirpan</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slewinski</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>vanishing tassel2 encodes a grass-specific tryptophan aminotransferase required for vegetative and reproductive development in maize</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>550</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Thole1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thole</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Worland</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bevan</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vain</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A protocol for efficiently retrieving and characterizing flanking sequence tags (FSTs) in Brachypodium distachyon T-DNA insertional mutants</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>650</fpage>–<lpage>661</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Bragg1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bragg</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guttman</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thilmony</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Generation and characterization of the Western Regional Research Center Brachypodium T-DNA insertional mutant collection</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e41916</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-He1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brumos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A small-molecule screen identifies L-kynurenine as a competitive inhibitor of TAA1/TAR activity in ethylene-directed auxin biosynthesis and root growth in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>3944</fpage>–<lpage>3960</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-PachecoVillalobos1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacheco-Villalobos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardtke</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Natural genetic variation of root system architecture from Arabidopsis to Brachypodium: towards adaptive value</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source> <volume>367</volume>: <fpage>1552</fpage>–<lpage>1558</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Mano1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nemoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The pathway of auxin biosynthesis in plants</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>2853</fpage>–<lpage>2872</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Takehisa1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takehisa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abiko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antonio</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide transcriptome dissection of the rice root system: implications for developmental and physiological functions</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Mashiguchi1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mashiguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugawara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaide</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The main auxin biosynthesis pathway in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>18512</fpage>–<lpage>18517</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Liang1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Involvement of COP1 in ethylene- and light-regulated hypocotyl elongation</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>236</volume>: <fpage>1791</fpage>–<lpage>1802</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Adams1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Ethylene biosynthesis: Identification of 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid as an intermediate in the conversion of methionine to ethylene</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>170</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Clausen1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clausen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Messerschmidt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pohlenz</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Slow-binding inhibition of Escherichia coli cystathionine beta-lyase by L-aminoethoxyvinylglycine: a kinetic and X-ray study</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>12633</fpage>–<lpage>12643</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Krupka1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krupka</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clausen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Crystal structure of cystalysin from Treponema denticola: a pyridoxal 5′-phosphate-dependent protein acting as a haemolytic enzyme</article-title>. <source>Embo J</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>3168</fpage>–<lpage>3178</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Alonso1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nourizadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>EIN2, a bifunctional transducer of ethylene and stress responses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>284</volume>: <fpage>2148</fpage>–<lpage>2152</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Ju1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shemansky</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>ZI</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>CTR1 phosphorylates the central regulator EIN2 to control ethylene hormone signaling from the ER membrane to the nucleus in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>19486</fpage>–<lpage>19491</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Qiao1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urich</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Processing and subcellular trafficking of ER-tethered EIN2 control response to ethylene gas</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>338</volume>: <fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Hochholdinger3"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochholdinger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woll</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>From weeds to crops: genetic analysis of root development in cereals</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Yamamoto1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morinaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sazuka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Auxin biosynthesis by the YUCCA genes in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>143</volume>: <fpage>1362</fpage>–<lpage>1371</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Woo1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su'udi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Constitutively wilted 1, a member of the rice YUCCA gene family, is required for maintaining water homeostasis and an appropriate root to shoot ratio</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Zheng1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Coordination of auxin and ethylene biosynthesis by the aminotransferase VAS1</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>244</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Scacchi1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scacchi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gujas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santuari</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krogan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Spatio-temporal sequence of cross-regulatory events in root meristem growth</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>22734</fpage>–<lpage>22739</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Sibout2"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibout</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plantegenet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardtke</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Flowering as a condition for xylem expansion in Arabidopsis hypocotyl and root</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>458</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Vogel1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>High-efficiency Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of Brachypodium distachyon inbred line Bd21-3</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Rep</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>478</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Alves1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Worland</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thole</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snape</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bevan</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A protocol for Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of Brachypodium distachyon community standard line Bd21</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>638</fpage>–<lpage>649</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Langmead1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Andersen1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buechel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Requirement of B2-type cyclin-dependent kinases for meristem integrity in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pgen.1003564-Zhao3"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernald</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive algorithm for quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction</article-title>. <source>J Comput Biol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1047</fpage>–<lpage>1064</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>