<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">ppat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="allenpress-id">plpa</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plospath</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07-PLPA-RA-0166R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="sici">plpa-03-06-11</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subject>Virology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Homo (human)</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Regulatory Polymorphisms in the Cyclophilin A Gene, <italic>PPIA,</italic> Accelerate Progression to AIDS</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>PPIA</italic> Polymorphisms and AIDS</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>Ping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Li Hua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutcheson-Dilks</surname><given-names>Holli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>George</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donfield</surname><given-names>Sharyne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goedert</surname><given-names>James J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinaldo</surname><given-names>Charles R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchbinder</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>Gregory D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8"><sup>8</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>Stephen J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>Cheryl A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
				<label>1</label><addr-line> Laboratory of Genomic Diversity, Science Applications International Corporation-Frederick, National Cancer Institute-Frederick, Frederick, Maryland, United States of America
			</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2">
				<label>2</label><addr-line> Basic Research Program, Science Applications International Corporation-Frederick, National Cancer Institute-Frederick, Frederick, Maryland, United States of America
			</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3">
				<label>3</label><addr-line> Laboratory of Genomic Diversity, National Cancer Institute, Frederick, Maryland, United States of America
			</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff4">
				<label>4</label><addr-line> Rho Incorporated, Chapel Hill, North Carolina, United States of America
			</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff5">
				<label>5</label><addr-line> Viral Epidemiology Branch, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, Bethesda, Maryland, United States of America
			</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff6">
				<label>6</label><addr-line> Department of Infectious Diseases and Microbiology, University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Public Health, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, United States of America
			</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff7">
				<label>7</label><addr-line> San Francisco Department of Public Health, San Francisco, California, United States of America
			</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff8">
				<label>8</label><addr-line> Department of Epidemiology, Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, Maryland, United States of America
			</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>Edward C</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Pennsylvania State University, United States of America</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="ack1"><p>PA, SJO, and CAW conceived and designed the experiments and wrote the paper. PA, LHW, and HHD performed the experiments. PA and CAW analyzed the data. GN, SD, JJG, CRR, SB, GDK, and SJO contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">winkler@mail.ncifcrf.gov</email></corresp><fn fn-type="conflict" id="ack3"><p> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e88</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></date></history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Public Domain declaration which stipulates that, once placed in the public domain, this work may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose. </license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Human cyclophilin A, or CypA, encoded by the gene peptidyl prolyl isomerase A <italic>(PPIA),</italic> is incorporated into the HIV type 1 (HIV-1) virion and promotes HIV-1 infectivity by facilitating virus uncoating. We examined the effect of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and haplotypes within the <italic>PPIA</italic> gene on HIV-1 infection and disease progression in five HIV-1 longitudinal history cohorts. Kaplan-Meier survival statistics and Cox proportional hazards model were used to assess time to AIDS outcomes. Among eight SNPs tested, two promoter SNPs (SNP3 and SNP4) in perfect linkage disequilibrium were associated with more rapid CD4<sup>+</sup> T-cell loss (relative hazard = 3.7, <italic>p =</italic> 0.003) in African Americans. Among European Americans, these alleles were also associated with a significant trend to more rapid progression to AIDS in a multi-point categorical analysis (<italic>p</italic> = 0.005). Both SNPs showed differential nuclear protein-binding efficiencies in a gel shift assay. In addition, one SNP (SNP5) located in the 5′ UTR previously shown to be associated with higher ex vivo HIV-1 replication was found to be more frequent in HIV-1-positive individuals than in those highly exposed uninfected individuals. These results implicate regulatory <italic>PPIA</italic> polymorphisms as a component of genetic susceptibility to HIV-1 infection or disease progression, affirming the important role of <italic>PPIA</italic> in HIV-1 pathogenesis.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><sec id="st1"><title/><p>Individual risk of acquiring HIV type 1 (HIV-1) infection and developing AIDS is not equal; some people are more prone to HIV/AIDS than others. Susceptibility to HIV-1/AIDS is likely determined by a combination of environmental, viral, and host genetic factors. Genetic variations in host cellular factors involved in HIV-1 cell entry, replication, and host defense have been found to affect susceptibility to HIV-1/AIDS. In this report, we focused on the gene <italic>PPIA</italic> that encodes cyclophilin A, a human cellular protein that is incorporated into the HIV-1 virion and promotes viral replication. We studied genetic variation in the <italic>PPIA</italic> gene in persons with different susceptibility levels to HIV-1 infection or different rates of disease progression. We found that individuals who processed two functional variants in the promoter region of <italic>PPIA</italic> had higher risk of CD4<sup>+</sup> T-cell loss or progression to AIDS-defining diseases. We also observed that an additional variant occurred more frequently in HIV-1-infected individuals compared to HIV-1-exposed, but uninfected, individuals. These results suggest that genetic variation in <italic>PPIA</italic> may influence host susceptibility to HIV-1 infection or disease progression and targeting <italic>PPIA</italic> might provide therapeutic benefit.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This project has been funded in whole or in part with federal funds from the National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, under contract N01-CO-12400. This research was supported in part by the Intramural Research Program of the National Institutes of Health, National Cancer Institute, Center for Cancer Research, and National Human Genome Research Institute. The National Institute on Drug Abuse, National Institutes of Health, under grant DA-04334 provided funding for the ALIVE cohort. The content of this publication does not necessarily reflect the views or policies of the Department of Health and Human Services, nor does mention of trade names, commercial products, or organizations imply endorsement by the US Government.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts><!--===== Restructure custom-meta-wrap to custom-meta-group =====--><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>citation</meta-name><meta-value>An P, Wang LH, Hutcheson-Dilks H, Nelson G, Donfield S, et al. (2007) Regulatory polymorphisms in the cyclophilin A gene, <italic>PPIA,</italic> accelerate progression to AIDS. PLoS Pathog 3(6): e88. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088</ext-link></meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>As an obligate intracellular parasite, HIV type 1 (HIV-1) utilizes host cell factors for its replication. Human cyclophilin A (CypA), also known as peptidyl prolyl isomerase A (PPIA), is a ubiquitous cytoplasmic protein (by convention, we refer to the protein as CypA and the gene as <italic>PPIA</italic>). CypA has long been known for its incorporation into HIV-1 virions and its important role in facilitating HIV-1 replication in host cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b001">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b002">2</xref>]. CypA is a member of the cyclophilin family, members of which all possess peptidyl-prolyl <italic>cis/trans</italic> isomerase activity. Peptidyl prolyl <italic>cis/trans</italic> isomerases (<italic>PPIA</italic>ses) catalyze the <italic>cis/trans</italic> isomerization of prolyl peptide bonds and are believed to be involved in protein folding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b003">3</xref>]. The incorporation of CypA into the HIV-1 virion capsid is mediated through the direct binding between prolyl peptide bond located in a proline-rich loop of the fourth and fifth helices of the HIV-1 capsid and the active sites of CypA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b004">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b005">5</xref>]. Disruption of CypA incorporation, either by HIV-1 Gag mutations or by cyclosporine A, an immunosuppressive drug that prevents HIV-1 Gag binding to CypA, leads to an attenuation of HIV-1 infectivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b002">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b006">6</xref>]. Braaten and Luban found that HIV-1 replication was decreased in CypA-null human CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, in which the gene encoding CypA <italic>(PPIA)</italic> was deleted through homologous recombination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b007">7</xref>]. CypA is therefore an important host factor that regulates HIV-1 replication.</p><p>Recently, the role of CypA in HIV-1 has gained even greater attention with the discovery of a fusion protein of CypA and TRIM5α, a host restriction factor against HIV-1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b008">8</xref>], which confers HIV-1 resistance in owl monkey [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b009">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b011">11</xref>]. Both TRIM5α and CypA recognize and act on the capsid of HIV-1, but apparently confer opposite effects. TRIM5α restricts HIV-1 by promoting premature disassembly of HIV-1 capsid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b012">12</xref>], while CypA increases viral infectivity by facilitating proper uncoating. Although the interaction between CypA and TRIM5α is still unclear, it appears that the modulation of HIV-1 infectivity by CypA is independent of TRIM5α [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b013">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b015">15</xref>]. It has been postulated that binding of CypA to capsid protects HIV-1 from an unknown restriction factor in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b015">15</xref>].</p><p>The study of the influence of human gene variation on susceptibility to HIV-1 infection and progression is an approach that may reveal the in vivo host factor HIV-1 interactions and their epidemiologic importance at the population level. With this approach we have identified several AIDS-modifying variants in genes <italic>TRIM5</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b016">16</xref>], <italic>APOBEC3G</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b017">17</xref>], and <italic>CUL5</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b018">18</xref>] that encode human innate HIV-1 restriction factors or related proteins. In a recent study performed in the Swiss HIV Cohort Study, a variant of <italic>PPIA</italic> was implicated as a potential factor affecting HIV-1 disease progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b019">19</xref>]. As CypA is an essential human protein for completion of the HIV-1 life cycle, we have assessed the influence of genetic variation in the <italic>PPIA</italic> gene on HIV-1 infection and disease progression in five United States–based HIV-1 natural history cohorts.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Description of <italic>PPIA</italic> Variations</title><p>The <italic>PPIA</italic> gene is approximately 7 kb in length, consisting of five exons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g001">Figure 1</xref>A). Using <italic>PPIA</italic>-specific primers we resequenced virtually the entire <italic>PPIA</italic> gene to screen for single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in 92 European Americans (EA) and 92 African Americans (AA). Seven polymorphisms were discovered: three in the putative promoter region, one in the 5′ UTR, one in the 3′ UTR, one in intron 4, and one in the second Alu repeat region upstream of the putative promoter. No SNPs were found in the coding regions. These SNPs and four additional SNPs available from dbSNP database located in regions not detected by our sequencing were selected for genotyping in the AIDS cohorts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-0030088-t001">Table 1</xref>). SNP1 genotypes deviated from the frequencies expected under the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), probably due to its location in the Alu repetitive element; thus, SNP1 was excluded in the analysis. SNP2 was also excluded from analysis due to its rarity. The genotypic frequencies of all other SNPs conform to Hardy-Weinberg expectations.</p><fig id="ppat-0030088-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Gene Map, SNPs, and Haplotypes in the Human <italic>PPIA</italic> on Chromosome 7p13</title><p>Coding exons are marked by green blocks, and 5′ and 3′ UTRs by light green blocks. Hatched black boxes represent Alu repeats. Haplotype structure and frequencies are shown in the middle panel. The corresponding nucleotides in the chimpanzee and allele frequencies of the SNPs are presented in the bottom panel. MAF, minor allele frequency of SNPs (based on EA frequency).</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.g001" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap content-type="1col" id="ppat-0030088-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characterization of <italic>PPIA</italic> SNPs</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup><col id="tb1col1" align="char" charoff="0" char="."/><col id="tb1col2" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb1col3" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb1col4" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left"><hr/>SNP</td><td><hr/>dbSNP rs Number</td><td><hr/>Nucleotide Position and Changes<sup>a</sup></td><td><hr/>Location</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>rs4720485</td><td>489 A/T</td><td>Alu repeat</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td></td><td>1167 C/T</td><td>Promoter</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td></td><td>1575 C/G</td><td>Promoter, &minus;10 to TATA</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>rs8177826</td><td>1604 C/G</td><td>Promoter, &minus;11 to mRNA initiation site</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>rs6850</td><td>1650 A/G</td><td>5&prime; UTR, &minus;9 to CDS</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>rs6970925</td><td>2629 A/G</td><td>Intron 1</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>rs3735481</td><td>2653 A/C</td><td>Intron 1</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>rs6463247</td><td>4943 C/T</td><td>Intron 4</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>rs10249442</td><td>6193 A/G</td><td>Intron 4</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>rs8177830</td><td>6576&ndash;6577 &minus;/AG</td><td>3&prime; UTR</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>rs6904</td><td>1981 G/A<sup>b</sup></td><td>3&prime; UTR</td></tr></tbody></table> --><!-- <table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p><sup>a</sup>Nucleotide position is numbered according to GenBank sequence X52851.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><p><sup>b</sup>Nucleotide position is numbered according to GenBank sequence NM_021130.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot> --></table-wrap><p>Allele frequency distributions of <italic>PPIA</italic> SNPs differed in EA and AA with Fst values ranging from 0.03 to 0.40 (average 0.22). The difference is particularly pronounced for SNPs 7, 8, 9, 10, and 11 (Fst, 0.30–0.40), where the minor alleles are reversed in the two populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Linkage Disequilibrium and Haplotypes of <italic>PPIA</italic> SNPs</title><p>The extent of linkage disequilibrium (LD) among eight SNPs was assessed by calculating all pairwise D′ values, separately for AA and EA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g002">Figure 2</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g002">2</xref>B). Strong LD was observed among almost all SNPs in AA (D′ range 0.87–1.0) and even stronger LD in EA (D′ range 0.97–1.0). SNP3 and SNP4 were in perfect LD in both populations (D′ = 1, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 1). As each of these two SNPs carries the same information content, SNP4 was selected as a proxy for SNP3 in the analysis. The eight SNPs in both population groups formed a single LD block as defined by the solid spine of LD method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b020">20</xref>]. This provided a justification to use all eight SNPs spanning the entire region as one block for subsequent haplotype-based association analyses.</p><fig id="ppat-0030088-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>LD Structure of <italic>PPIA</italic> SNPs in AA and EA</title><p>LD Structure of <italic>PPIA</italic> SNPs in AA (A) and EA (B). Pairwise D′ plots and haplotype blocks obtained from HAPLOVIEW. Pairwise D′ values (%) were indicated in triangle squares except for those of D′ of 1.0. High D′ values were shown in bright red (LOD &gt;= 2) or light blue squares (LOD &lt; 2), and low D′ values were shown in light red (LOD &gt;= 2) and white squares (LOD &lt; 2). Single haplotype block was defined by the solid spine algorithm.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.g002" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><p>Among AA, SNP6 presented intermediate level of LD (D′ ~0.60) with the SNPs downstream (SNP8–11); SNP6–SNP8 recombinant G-C haplotype had a frequency of 5%. Among EA, SNP5 had weak LD with SNP6–11 (D′ 0.47–0.71); the recombinant haplotype SNP5–SNP6 (G-G) had a frequency of 2.5%. This suggests an occurrence of recombination in the region between SNP5 and SNP8. The presence of multiple Alu elements in <italic>PPIA</italic> may have introduced the recombination event by promoting genomic instability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b021">21</xref>].</p><p>Haplotype structure and maximum likelihood haplotype frequencies were estimated with the EM algorithm. There were, in total, eight haplotypes with minor allele frequency &gt;1% in either population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g001">Figure 1</xref>B). Five or six haplotypes were present in EA or AA, respectively, accounting for &gt;97% of total sampled chromosomes. Among these, only three common haplotypes (minor allele frequency &gt;5%) were shared between AA and EA (hap1, 2, and 4). Diverse distributions of haplotype frequencies between AA and EA were seen as for SNPs.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Effect of <italic>PPIA</italic> SNPs and Haplotypes on Susceptibility to HIV-1 Infection</title><p>We compared the <italic>PPIA</italic> SNP allele and haplotype frequency distributions among three groups with increasing resistance to HIV-1 infection: seroconverters (SCs), seronegatives (SNs) belonging to an HIV-1 risk group, and those with documented high-risk exposures to HIV-1 who remain uninfected (HREU) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-0030088-t002">Table 2</xref>). The minor allele of SNP5 (G) was carried in 13.7% of SCs, 13.5% of SNs, and 9.5% of HREU, respectively (Mantel-Haenszel trend test, <italic>p</italic> = 0.21). The reduced carriage of SNP5G in HREU was significant when SCs were compared to HREU (odds ratio = 1.78, <italic>p</italic> = 0.02), suggesting that the SNP5G allele carriers may have increased susceptibility to HIV-1 infection (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-0030088-t002">Table 2</xref>). No distortion of frequency distribution between risk groups were observed for all other SNPs in AA or EA (unpublished data).</p><table-wrap content-type="2col" id="ppat-0030088-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of <italic>PPIA</italic> SNP4 and SNP5 on HIV-1 Infection Risk in EA</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup><col id="tb2col1" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col2" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col3" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col4" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col5" align="char" charoff="0" char="("/><col id="tb2col6" align="char" charoff="0" char="("/><col id="tb2col7" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb2col8" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2"><hr/>SNP</td><td rowspan="2"><hr/>Risk Group</td><td rowspan="2"><hr/><italic>n</italic></td><td colspan="3"><hr/>Genotype</td><td colspan="2"><hr/>SC versus SN or HREU</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/>Number of Carriers (Frequency)</td><td><hr/>OR (95&percnt; CI)<sup>a</sup></td><td><hr/><italic>p</italic></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>SNP4</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td>CC</td><td>CG</td><td>GG</td><td>CG &plus; GG versus CC</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>SC</td><td>659</td><td>574 (0.871)</td><td>83 (0.126)</td><td>2 (0.003)</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>SN</td><td>447</td><td>392 (0.877)</td><td>53 (0.119)</td><td>2 (0.005)</td><td>1.05 (0.73&ndash;1.52)</td><td>0.77</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>HREU</td><td>155</td><td>130 (0.839)</td><td>23 (0.155)</td><td>1 (0.007)</td><td>0.77 (0.47&ndash;1.25)</td><td>0.29</td></tr><tr><td><bold>SNP5</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td>AA</td><td>AG</td><td>GG</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>SC</td><td>652</td><td>485 (0.744)</td><td>155 (0.238)</td><td>12 (0.002)</td><td>AG &plus; GG versus AA</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>SN</td><td>603</td><td>458 (0.76)</td><td>130 (0.216)</td><td>15 (0.003)</td><td>1.09 (0.84&ndash;1.41)</td><td>0.52</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>HREU</td><td>153</td><td>128 (0.837)</td><td>21 (0.137)</td><td>4 (0.003)</td><td>1.76 (1.11&ndash;2.80)</td><td>0.02</td></tr></tbody></table> --><!-- <table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt201"><p><sup>a</sup>OR represents the odd ratio of being an HIV-1-SC compared to being either HIV-1-SN or HREU.</p></fn><fn id="nt202"><p><italic>n,</italic> number of individuals.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot> --></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><italic>PPIA</italic> SNPs and AIDS Progression</title><p>We analyzed AA and EA separately since the SNP frequencies differed between the two groups. The Cox proportional hazards model was employed to test the potential differential impact of SNPs on the rates of progression to CD4 &lt;200 or to AIDS clinical diseases (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-0030088-t003">Table 3</xref>). To minimize the number of SNPs to be tested, we only tested the unique SNPs represented in each population, i.e., only one SNP was tested for those in perfect LD (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 1). Six and four SNPs were analyzed in AA and EA, respectively. Two SNPs in AA (SNPs 4 and 5) and three SNPs in EA (SNPs 4, 5, and 7) showed significant or near-significant effects (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-0030088-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap content-type="2col" id="ppat-0030088-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effects of <italic>PPIA</italic> SNPs on AIDS Progression in AA and EA</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup><col id="tb3col1" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb3col2" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb3col3" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb3col4" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb3col5" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb3col6" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb3col7" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb3col8" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2"><hr/>SNP Number</td><td rowspan="2"><hr/>Endpoint</td><td colspan="3"><hr/>AA (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 284&ndash;290)</td><td colspan="3"><hr/>EA (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 643&ndash;650)</td></tr><tr><td><hr/>RH</td><td><hr/>95&percnt; CI</td><td><hr/><italic>p</italic></td><td><hr/>RH</td><td><hr/>95&percnt; CI</td><td><hr/><italic>p</italic></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>SNP4(SNP3)<sup>a</sup></bold></td><td>CD4&lt;200</td><td>3.7</td><td>1.59&ndash;8.63</td><td>0.003</td><td>1.19</td><td>0.88&ndash;1.62</td><td>0.26</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>AIDS-87</td><td>2.03</td><td>0.63&ndash;6.53</td><td>0.24</td><td>1.34</td><td>0.97&ndash;1.85</td><td>0.07</td></tr><tr><td><bold>SNP5</bold></td><td>CD4&lt;200</td><td>0.67</td><td>0.44&ndash;1.01</td><td>0.06</td><td>0.95</td><td>0.74&ndash;1.22</td><td>0.70</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>AIDS-87</td><td>0.86</td><td>0.50&ndash;1.48</td><td>0.58</td><td>1.26</td><td>0.98&ndash;1.64</td><td>0.08</td></tr><tr><td><bold>SNP6</bold></td><td>CD4&lt;200</td><td>1.16</td><td>0.78&ndash;1.74</td><td>0.46</td><td>1.16</td><td>0.92&ndash;1.45</td><td>0.21</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>AIDS-87</td><td>1.20</td><td>0.71&ndash;2.04</td><td>0.49</td><td>1.05</td><td>0.82&ndash;1.34</td><td>0.71</td></tr><tr><td><bold>SNP7<sup>b</sup></bold></td><td>CD4&lt;200</td><td>1.04</td><td>0.60&ndash;1.82</td><td>0.88</td><td>1.08</td><td>0.85&ndash;1.37</td><td>0.55</td></tr><tr><td></td><td>AIDS-87</td><td>0.82</td><td>0.40&ndash;1.67</td><td>0.58</td><td>1.32</td><td>1.03&ndash;1.70</td><td>0.03</td></tr><tr><td><bold>SNP8</bold></td><td>CD4&lt;200</td><td>0.72</td><td>0.39&ndash;1.34</td><td>0.30</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>AIDS-87</td><td>0.64</td><td>0.29&ndash;1.43</td><td>0.28</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><bold>SNP11<sup>c</sup></bold></td><td>CD4&lt;200</td><td>0.88</td><td>0.49&ndash;1.60</td><td>0.68</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td>AIDS-87</td><td>0.84</td><td>0.38&ndash;1.87</td><td>0.68</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table> --><!-- <table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt301"><p>The Cox proportional hazards model was employed to test the impact of SNPs on the rates of progression to CD4&lt;200 or to AIDS clinical diseases (AIDS-87); <italic>p</italic>-values were from a Wald test.</p></fn><fn id="nt302"><p><sup>a</sup>SNP3 and SNP4 are in perfect LD.</p></fn><fn id="nt303"><p><sup>b</sup>SNP7 is representative of SNP8, SNP9, and SNP11 in EA.</p></fn><fn id="nt304"><p><sup>c</sup>SNP9 is representative of SNP11 in AA.</p></fn><fn id="nt305"><p><italic>n,</italic> number of individuals.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot> --></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Effect of SNP4 on AIDS Progression</title><p>Among AA SCs, the minor allele of SNP4 (the G allele) was associated with accelerated loss of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (relative hazard [RH] = 3.7, 95% confidence interval [CI] = 1.59–8.63) in a Cox proportional hazards model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-0030088-t003">Table 3</xref>). After stratifying by cohort in the Cox regression analysis, this association became slightly stronger (RH = 4.08, 95% CI = 1.71–9.70). Kaplan-Meier survival analysis presented a clear separation of curves stratified for the SNP4 C/C and C/G genotypes (G/G absent) on progression to CD4 &lt;200 in AA (<italic>p =</italic> 0.002, log-rank test, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Notably, all SNP4 carriers progressed to CD4 &lt;200 within 6 y. The effect on AIDS-1987 was in the same direction but short of significance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-0030088-t003">Table 3</xref>). Identical results were seen for SNP3 (unpublished data). Among EA SCs, a trend of accelerated progression to AIDS-1987 was also observed, though short of significance (RH = 1.34, <italic>p</italic> = 0.07, <xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-0030088-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p><fig id="ppat-0030088-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Kaplan-Meier Survival Curve Analysis of SNP4 on Progression to CD4<sup>+</sup> Cells &lt;200/mm<sup>3</sup> in AA</title></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.g003" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><p>To affirm the observed genetic influence of SNP4, we performed a categorical analysis of HIV-1-infected people that included seroprevalents (SPs) in the long-term survivors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g004">Figure 4</xref>). SPs who had remained AIDS-free for greater than 7.5 y for AA or 10 y for EA after study enrollment (the median time to AIDS for each) were included in this analysis. The frequency distributions of SNP4 in six discrete time intervals progressing to disease outcome after HIV-1 infection were tested for statistical trend using a Mantel-Haenszel test. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g004">Figure 4</xref>, the SNP4 G allele occurred more frequently among fast progressors in both AA and EA. With an increased sample size of 389 patients in AA, a significant trend toward rapid CD4 loss is still preserved (<italic>p</italic> = 0.04, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g004">Figure 4</xref>A). Among 970 EA patients, the trend toward rapid progression to AIDS was more pronounced (<italic>p</italic> = 0.004) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g004">Figure 4</xref>B). Thus, the results from SC plus SP groups corroborate the findings from the SC-alone survival analyses, indicating that the accelerating effect of SNP4 is consistent in both AA and EA populations.</p><fig id="ppat-0030088-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Disease Categorical Analysis Using both SCs and SPs for the Effect of SNP4 on Progression to CD4 &lt;200 in AA and to AIDS-87 in EA</title><p>Only SPs with greater than 7.5 y (for AA [A]) or 10 y (for EA [B]) of survival time, the median survival time of the SCs, were included in the analysis. The frequencies of the SNP4 C/G genotype in five intervals after seroconversion are plotted and tested for statistical trends using Mantel-Haenszel χ<sup>2</sup> test. Numbers of patients are listed above the bar.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.g004" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><italic>PPIA</italic> SNP5 and AIDS Progression</title><p>In a Swiss Caucasian HIV-1 cohort, SNP5G, referred to as 1650A/G [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b019">19</xref>], was reported to be associated with a rapid CD4 cell depletion and with a trend toward higher in vitro HIV-1 replication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b019">19</xref>]. In our analysis of EA SCs, SNP5G showed a nonsignificant trend toward rapid progression to AIDS-1987 (RH = 1.26, <italic>p</italic> = 0.08), but had no effect on CD4 cell depletion, while an opposite trend was observed in AA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-0030088-t003">Table 3</xref>). In a categorical analysis of combined samples from SCs and SPs, SNP5G also had no impact on both outcomes in both EA and AA (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.23, unpublished data). Therefore, this study offers no convincing evidence for SNP5 association with disease progression in either EA or AA.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Effects of <italic>PPIA</italic> Haplotypes on AIDS Progression</title><p>In the haplotype analysis, we first used the Cox regression model to test the global null hypothesis of no association between haplotype frequency and AIDS progression, by comparing a model with all haplotypes to the covariants-only model. This revealed that the global distributions of haplotype frequencies were significantly or near-significantly different for the outcome of CD4 &lt;200 in AA (<italic>p</italic> = 0.01) and AIDS-87 in EA (<italic>p</italic> = 0.08). The distortion of frequency distribution was mainly attributable to one haplotype (Hap7) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-0030088-t004">Table 4</xref>). Hap7, the only haplotype carrying SNP4G (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g001">Figure 1</xref>), was associated with accelerated progression to AIDS in both AA and EA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-0030088-t004">Table 4</xref>), consistent with the results from SNP analysis.</p><table-wrap content-type="1col" id="ppat-0030088-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effects of <italic>PPIA</italic> Haplotypes on AIDS Progression</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.t004" xlink:type="simple"/><!-- <table frame="hsides" rules="none"><colgroup><col id="tb4col1" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col2" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col3" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col4" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col5" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col6" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/><col id="tb4col7" align="left" charoff="0" char=""/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2"><hr/>Haplotype</td><td colspan="3"><hr/>CD4 &lt;200, AA (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 266)</td><td colspan="3"><hr/>AIDS-87, EA (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 603)</td></tr><tr><td><hr/>RH</td><td><hr/>95&percnt; CI</td><td><hr/><italic>p</italic></td><td><hr/>RH</td><td><hr/>95&percnt; CI</td><td><hr/><italic>p</italic></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Hap2</td><td>1.00</td><td>Referent</td><td></td><td>1</td><td>Referent</td><td></td></tr><tr><td>Hap1</td><td>1.09</td><td>0.72&ndash;1.64</td><td>0.70</td><td>1.48</td><td>0.84&ndash;2.60</td><td>0.18</td></tr><tr><td>Hap3</td><td>1.42</td><td>0.85&ndash;2.38</td><td>0.18</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td>Hap4</td><td>1.62</td><td>0.98&ndash;2.68</td><td>0.06</td><td>1.24</td><td>0.86&ndash;1.78</td><td>0.25</td></tr><tr><td>Hap5</td><td>0.97</td><td>0.45&ndash;2.07</td><td>0.93</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td>Hap6</td><td>1.37</td><td>0.52&ndash;3.61</td><td>0.53</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td>Hap7</td><td>5.39</td><td>1.93&ndash;15.0</td><td>0.01</td><td>2.17</td><td>1.07&ndash;4.41</td><td>0.032</td></tr><tr><td>Hap9</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td>2.55</td><td>0.99&ndash;6.60</td><td>0.053</td></tr></tbody></table> --><!-- <table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt401"><p>The Cox proportional hazards model was used to test the impact of haplotypes on the rates of progression to CD4 &lt;200 or to AIDS-87. <italic>p</italic>-values were from a Wald test. Hap2, common in both AA and EA, was used as referent.</p></fn><fn id="nt402"><p><italic>n,</italic> number of individuals.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot> --></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Interactions between <italic>TRIM5</italic> and <italic>PPIA</italic> Variants</title><p>Because TRIM5α interferes with and CypA facilitates post-entry uncoating of the HIV-1 capsid, it is possible that there may be genetic interactions between two genes. Potential interactions were tested only between variants in two genes with functional plausibility or high strength of association. Specifically, <italic>PPIA</italic> SNP4 was tested for its interaction with <italic>TRIM5</italic>-rs16934386 and <italic>TRIM5</italic>-R136Q, which was previously reported using the same patient population to be associated with HIV-1 infection but not progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b022">22</xref>]. In the Cox regression model analysis, we observed no obvious interaction for infection or progression (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.15, unpublished data). This suggests that CypA and TRIM5α likely act independently, consistent with recent in vitro observations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b013">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b015">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b023">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Electrophoretic Mobility-Shift Assay</title><p>As SNP3, 4, and 5 reside in the regulatory region of <italic>PPIA,</italic> we performed gel shift assays to assess whether these SNPs differentially bind to transcriptional factors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g005">Figure 5</xref>). In this experiment, ~25-bp DNA probes containing either of the SNP alleles were incubated with the nuclear extracts from Th1 cytokine-stimulated human T lymphocytes. Both SNPs showed differential binding affinity to nuclear protein(s) with the same mobility (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g005">Figure 5</xref>A, top band). Averaged from two independent experiments, a 4-fold decrease or 2.8-fold increase in the band density was observed for the minor allele of SNP3 (G) and SNP4 (G), respectively. The cold unlabeled oligonucleotides with minor alleles were unable to compete with wild-type oligonucleotides, suggesting the bindings are specific. These results indicate that these two SNPs within the promoter alter the binding affinity with certain transcriptional protein(s). On the contrary, no obvious differential binding was observed for SNP5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g005">Figure 5</xref>A).</p><fig id="ppat-0030088-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Binding Affinity of Nuclear Factors to the SNP-Containing Fragments in the 5′ Regulatory Regions of <italic>PPIA</italic> and the Sequence Context of the Region</title><p>(A) Gel shift analysis of SNP3, SNP4, and SNP5 in the 5′ regulatory region of <italic>PPIA.</italic> Nuclear extracts from human T lymphocytes induced by IL4 were bound to the DNA fragment containing the C or G allele of SNP3, the C or G allele of SNP4, and the A or G allele of SNP5, respectively. The arrowhead indicates the band showing differential binding of nuclear factor(s) to the oligonucleotides. The bands below the arrow may represent nonspecific complexes and the bands at the bottom are free probes.</p><p>(B) Sequence context of SNP3 and SNP4 and comparison to the consensus-binding motifs of transcription factor SP1. SNPs 3 and 4 (located at positions 1575 and 1604 in the sequence X52851, and −85 and −59, to the ATG start codon, respectively) are in perfect LD. SNP3C&gt;G change predicts a loss of binding to a SP1 factor, while SNP4C&gt;G change predicts a stronger binding to a SP1 factor.</p><p>(C) The interspecies alignments of a segment of the <italic>PPIA</italic> promoter containing SNP3 and SNP4. Conserved regions are underlined and SNP sites are colored.</p></caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.g005" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><p>In silico analysis of the sequence at these three SNP sites by using TESS software also predicted differential binding for SNP3 and 4, but not for SNP5. SNP3 and 4 were each located in one of the consensus-binding motifs of transcription factor SP1, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g005">Figure 5</xref>B. The local sequence with SNP3C is identical to the consensus sequence of SP1 site, GGGG<underline>C</underline>C, whereas SNP3C&gt;G change perturbs this motif. In contrast, the sequence with SNP4C has two mismatch sites compared to an alternative consensus sequence of SP1 site, GAGGC<underline>G</underline>GGGC, whereas SNP4C&gt;G reduced the mismatch to one, predicting a stronger binding. There is, therefore, a plausible biochemical basis for the differential binding affinity observed in the gel shift experiment. These results also suggest that SNP3 and SNP4 affect transcription, likely through their interactions with SP1. The sequence of the region of human <italic>PPIA</italic> promoter resided in by SNP3 and SNP4 was compared to the corresponding sequence from other species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-0030088-g005">Figure 5</xref>C). SNP3 and SNP4 are both located in the highly conserved regions. The C allele of SNP3 is present in both primates and rodents. The C allele of SNP4 occurs only in primates and the minor allele G occurs in rodents, suggesting a possible association with speciation. These interspecies data support the hypothesis that SNP3 and SNP4 changes may have functional consequences.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The role of CypA in promoting HIV-1 replication has been well established through extensive in vitro experiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b001">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b002">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b006">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b007">7</xref>]. In this study, we have undertaken a systematic investigation of the association between genetic variations in the <italic>PPIA</italic> gene and susceptibility to HIV-1 infection and disease progression in HIV-1 natural history cohorts. We found that two promoter variants in perfect LD, SNP3 and SNP4, in <italic>PPIA,</italic> were associated with rapid HIV-1 disease progression. This effect was revealed for CD4 cell depletion or for AIDS progression, reflecting early or late stage of disease progression, in AA and EA, respectively. The racial difference in the strength or timing of the effects may be due to interactions with other sequence variations that are distributed differently in two populations or to immunologic and viral variables. We further found that both SNPs had differential binding efficiency to nuclear proteins in the gel shift experiment. These findings suggest that the functional promoter SNP3/SNP4 influences HIV-1 disease progression.</p><p><italic>PPIA</italic> in human encodes a 165-amino acid protein that is highly conserved across species, with 100% and 96% sequence identity to rhesus monkey and mouse, respectively. The nucleotide sequence of <italic>PPIA</italic> is 98% identical between human and chimpanzee. No variation in the coding sequence of human <italic>PPIA</italic> was found in this study or in the dbSNP database. This suggests that differential genetic impact of <italic>PPIA</italic> SNPs and haplotypes on infection and progression are likely due to regulatory region variation affecting protein levels. The regulation and promoter function of human <italic>PPIA</italic> is still undefined. <italic>PPIA</italic> is highly expressed in almost all cell types and is considered a housekeeping gene. Sequence analysis revealed that <italic>PPIA</italic> promoter contains a TATA box and two SP1 binding sites and is highly GC-rich (~70%) with overrepresented CpG dinucleotides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b024">24</xref>]. In this study, we identified two SNPs, each located in two additional SP1 binding elements. SP1 is generally believed to function as a transactivating factor for many housekeeping genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b025">25</xref>]. These two SNP changes, SNP3G and SNP4G, always occurring together through LD, had opposite effects on the nuclear protein binding. Assuming the predicted stronger SP1 binding effect of SNP4 is dominant over the weaker SP1 binding of SNP3, a higher <italic>PPIA</italic> gene expression would be predicted. This would be consistent with more rapid disease course as observed in this study.</p><p>Based on our analyses of eight SNPs covering the entire gene region of <italic>PPIA</italic> and their haplotypes, we found that the <italic>PPIA</italic> disease-modifying effects were most likely afforded by promoter SNP3 or SNP4 and the associations with the downstream SNPs 7–11 were largely due to tracking of these two SNPs through LD. In a previous report, Bleiber et al. studied the ex vivo HIV-1 infectivity in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from healthy individuals carrying the SNP4 and SNP5 alleles (named as <italic>PPIA</italic>-1604 and <italic>PPIA</italic>-1650, respectively, in the Bleiber's report), as well as their impact on the CD4 gradient (from CD4<sup>+</sup> T-cell counts 500/mm<sup>3</sup> to 200/mm<sup>3</sup>) among SPs enrolled in the Swiss HIV cohort, largely comprised of Caucasians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b019">19</xref>]. In the ex vivo experiment, both SNPs showed nonsignificant tendencies toward greater HIV-1 replication, with the effects of SNP5 being more pronounced. In the population study, both SNPs were associated with faster CD4<sup>+</sup> T-cell depletion in a model also containing two other candidate genes (model 2); with the SNP5 of <italic>PPIA</italic> effect again being more pronounced. Thus, the detrimental effect of SNP4 observed from these two studies is largely consistent. In contrast, no evidence supporting a role of SNP5 in AIDS progression was found, although the SNP5 G allele was carried significantly less often in HREU than in SC but was similarly distributed in SC and SN. Thus, the role of CypA polymorphism in HIV-1 infection remains inconclusive and warrants further investigation. Taken together, the association and functional results from these two studies point to a role of <italic>PPIA</italic> genetic variation in HIV-1/AIDS. In future studies, it may be informative to determine the mechanism of association between <italic>PPIA</italic> variants and host susceptibility to HIV-1 infection or disease progression in view of the interaction between CypA and the capsid domain of the Gag polyprotein.</p><p>Population-based genetic association studies provide a powerful approach to uncovering host genes that confer disease susceptibility or resistance. This approach has led to identification of various genetic factors that affect HIV-1/AIDS, and has provided unique insights into the host HIV-1 interaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b027">27</xref>]. The successful identification of true genetic associations requires a large sample size (to minimize the type II error), replication in independent studies (to ward off type I error), and plausible functional evidence (to infer causal relationship). In this study, the plausible genetic-modifying role of <italic>PPIA</italic> is supported by replication in two independent ethnic groups and the demonstration that SNPs 3 and 4 are each associated with altered binding affinities to transcription factors. Moreover, the previous independent study also provides supportive association and functional evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b019">19</xref>].</p><p>Our comprehensive analysis of nearly all variant alleles and their haplotypes in the <italic>PPIA</italic> gene is, in essence, equivalent to a gene-based approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b028">28</xref>]. A major problem facing genetic association studies is the difficulty in replication, particularly for single SNP associations. One reason for failure to replicate previous studies is due to potential differences in allele frequencies and LD structure across populations. Gene-based replication has recently been advocated as a gold standard for replication studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b028">28</xref>]. The entire gene with prior SNP association is considered the functional unit and is examined for association with effectively all genetic variation in the gene. Nonreplication due to population differences may be minimized as local allele frequencies and LD structure from study populations are considered with this approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b028">28</xref>]. Thus, our comprehensive survey of <italic>PPIA</italic> genetic variation and LD structure may facilitate future comparisons of replication studies using a gene-based approach.</p><p>In summary, through genetic epidemiological and functional approaches, we have identified two promoter SNPs in <italic>PPIA</italic> as potential genetic modifiers of HIV-1 disease progression. Our findings corroborate the notion that genetic variation of <italic>PPIA</italic> influences AIDS pathogenesis and provide in vivo evidence that CypA is a critical host protein in interaction with HIV-1. Manipulation of <italic>PPIA</italic> may be considered as a plausible option for anti-HIV-1 therapeutic development as previously explored [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b029">29</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Study participants.</title><p>Study participants were enrolled in five United States–based natural history HIV/AIDS cohorts. AIDS Link to the Intravenous Experience (ALIVE) is a community-based cohort of intravenous injection drug users in Baltimore enrolled in 1988–1989 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b030">30</xref>], consisting of 92% AA; Multicenter AIDS Cohort Study (MACS) is a longitudinal prospective cohort of men who have sex with men (MSM) from four United States cities: Chicago, Baltimore, Pittsburgh, and Los Angeles, enrolled in 1984–1985 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b031">31</xref>], consisting of 83% EA and 10% AA; the San Francisco City Clinic Study (SFCC) is a cohort of MSM originally enrolled in a hepatitis B study in 1978–1980 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b032">32</xref>], consisting of 96% EA; Hemophilia Growth and Development Study (HGDS) is a multicenter prospective study that enrolled children with hemophilia who were exposed to HIV-1 through blood products between 1982 and 1983 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b033">33</xref>], consisting of 72% EA and 11% AA; the Multicenter Hemophilia Cohort Study (MHCS) is a prospective study that enrolled persons with hemophilia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b034">34</xref>], consisting of 90% EA and 6% AA. The participant group is comprised of HIV-1 SCs (infected after study enrollment), SPs (infected at study enrollment), SNs, and HREU. The MACS, MHCS, SFCC, and ALIVE cohorts consist of both SCs and SPs among HIV-1-infected individuals. Due to the potential frailty bias (missing the most rapid progressors to AIDS and death) among SPs, only SCs from these four cohorts were used in the survival analysis. SPs were also included for allele frequency estimation, haplotype inference, and disease categorical analysis. The number of participants studied in each risk or disease category was as follows: SC = 654 EA, 295 AA; SN = 604 EA, 350 AA; HREU = 153 EA, 81 AA; and SP = 1199 EA, 773 AA. Of 290 AA SCs, 237, 42, 5, and 5 were from ALIVE, MACS, MHCS, and HGDS, respectively.</p><p>The date of seroconversion after study enrollment was estimated as the midpoint between the last seronegative and first seropositive HIV-1 antibody test; only individuals with less than 2 y elapsed time between the two tests were included in the seroconverter progression analysis. The censoring date was the earliest of the date of the last recorded visit, or December 31, 1995 for the MACS, MHCS, HGDS, and SFCC or July 31, 1997 for the ALIVE cohort to avoid potential confounding by highly effective anti-retroviral therapy (HAART). The censoring date was extended in the ALIVE cohort because of delayed uptake of HAART in this group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b030">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b035">35</xref>].</p><p>HIV-1-uninfected individuals were classified into two categories based on individual's documented exposure levels to HIV-1. HREU individuals were those 80 AA and 145 EA with documented high-risk exposure through sharing of injection equipment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b036">36</xref>], who had anal receptive sex with multiple partners [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b037">37</xref>], or transfusions with Factor VIII clotting factor prior to 1984, when heat treatment was initiated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b038">38</xref>]. SN individuals (<italic>n</italic> = 420 and 571, respectively, for AA and EA) are those enrolled in the cohorts who remained HIV-seronegative despite ongoing or prior risk activity.</p><p>The study protocols were approved by the Institutional Review Boards of participating institutions and informed consent was obtained from all study participants.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Identification of SNPs.</title><p>Nucleotide polymorphisms were discovered in a panel of 92 EA and 92 AA, representing the extremes of the distribution for rapid and slow progression to AIDS and HREU. A nonisotopic RNA cleavage assay following PCR was employed to screen for polymorphisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b039">39</xref>]. <italic>PPIA</italic> has a high degree of homology to multiple processed pseudogenes that varies from 75% to 95% in the exon regions. <italic>PPIA</italic> also contains six copies of Alu repeats, each with a length of approximately 300 bp, located in the immediate upstream of the putative promoter region and introns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b024">24</xref>]. Sequence comparison and BLAST search were performed to select <italic>PPIA</italic>-specific PCR primers. Overlapping primers covered nearly the entire <italic>PPIA</italic> gene region including the putative promoter region, 5′ and 3′ UTRs, all five exons, as well as the Alu repeat regions. A part of intron 1 was not covered due to the high GC content. Primer sequences are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat-0030088-st001">Table S1</xref> and are numbered according to the GenBank DNA sequence X52851. Additional intronic SNPs were selected from NCBI dbSNP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP</ext-link>) and HapMap databases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hapmap.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.hapmap.org</ext-link>), by considering location, spacing, and allele frequency at least 10%. Haplotype tagging (ht)SNPs were given preference in the SNP selection. The ancestral allele state of the SNPs was based on a reference chimpanzee sequence.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Genotyping of SNPs.</title><p>Genotyping was performed using PCR-restriction fragment length polymorphism (PCR-RFLP) assay or TaqMan assays. PCR-RFLP was carried out with 35 cycles of denaturing at 94 °C for 30 s, annealing at 60 °C for 30 s, and extension at 72 °C for 45 s. The PCR product was digested with respective restriction enzymes (New England Biolabs, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.neb.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.neb.com</ext-link>) overnight and then separated on 3% agarose gels. TaqMan assays were obtained from the Assay-by-Demand service of Applied Biosystems (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.appliedbiosystems.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.appliedbiosystems.com</ext-link>). Genotyping primers and conditions were presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat-0030088-st002">Table S2</xref>. Eight water controls were included on each plate to monitor the potential PCR contamination, and 10% of SC and HREU samples were genotyped twice. The genotypes obtained were free of water contamination or of inconsistencies between duplicates.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Statistical analysis.</title><p>To assess the difference in allele frequency distribution in two populations, we performed a contingency χ<sup>2</sup> test for each marker to test the null hypothesis that the allele frequencies are the same in the two populations. Fst values were estimated by Wier and Cockerham's method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b040">40</xref>].</p><p>Pairwise LD was quantified using the absolute value of D′. Absolute values of D′ range from 0 for independence to 1 for complete LD between the pairs of loci. LD plots were generated utilizing Haploview (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broad.mit.edu/mpg/haploview" xlink:type="simple">http://www.broad.mit.edu/mpg/haploview</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b020">20</xref>]. A triangular matrix of D′ value was used to demonstrate LD patterns within AA and EA. Haplotype blocks were estimated using the solid spine of LD method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b020">20</xref>]. Haplotype blocks were defined with a default algorithm based on confidence intervals of D′ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b041">41</xref>], or the solid spine of LD method, which creates blocks of SNPs that have contiguous pairwise D′ values of greater than 0.8. With the latter method, the first and last SNPs in a block are in strong LD with all intermediate SNPs, but the intermediate SNPs are not necessarily in LD with each other [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b020">20</xref>]. Eight SNP haplotype frequencies were inferred separately for each population by means of an expectation-maximization algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b042">42</xref>].</p><p>Association analyses were conducted using the statistical packages SAS (version 9.0, SAS Institute, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sas.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.sas.com</ext-link>). EA and AA groups were analyzed separately because allele and haplotype frequencies were quite different between the two groups. Conformity to the genotype frequencies expected under Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium was examined for each SNP. The genetic effects of SNPs on HIV-1 infection susceptibility were assessed by comparing allelic and genotypic frequencies between HIV-1 HREU and HIV-1 SC participants using the chi square or Fisher's exact test. Regardless of the exposure route, persons in the HREU or SN groups were at risk to HIV-1 infection based on their inclusion in a HIV-1 risk group; therefore, we combined participants across cohorts to achieve a reasonable statistical power.</p><p>Kaplan-Meier survival statistics and the Cox proportional hazards model (Cox model) were used to assess the effects of SNPs and haplotypes on the rate of progression to AIDS. Two separate endpoints reflecting advancing AIDS pathogenesis were considered for SCs: (1) HIV-1 infection plus a decline of CD4<sup>+</sup> T-cell counts &lt;200 cells/mm<sup>3</sup> (CD4 &lt;200); (2) the 1987 Center for Disease Control definition of AIDS (AIDS-87): HIV-1 infection plus AIDS-defining illness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b043">43</xref>]. The significance of genotypic associations and RH was determined by unadjusted and adjusted Cox model regression analyses. For each SNP, we compared the minor allele genotypes to the most common genotype as a reference group. All <italic>p-</italic>values were two-tailed. Genetic factors previously shown to affect progression to AIDS were pre-determined to be included as confounding covariates in the Cox model analysis: <italic>CCR5</italic> Δ32, <italic>CCR2</italic>-64I, <italic>CCR5</italic>-P1, <italic>HLA</italic>-B*27, <italic>HLA</italic>-B*57, <italic>HLA</italic>-B*35Px group (including HLA-B*3502, B*3503, B*3504, and B*5301), and <italic>HLA</italic> Class I homozygosity for EA (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b027">27</xref>]); <italic>HLA</italic>-B*57 and <italic>HLA</italic> Class I homozygosity for AA. <italic>CCR2</italic>-64I, <italic>HLA</italic>-B*27, and <italic>HLA</italic>-B*35Px were not considered as covariates in AA due to no or weak effects in the AA participants, and <italic>CCR5</italic> Δ32 was not considered due to its rarity in AA. Analyses were stratified by sex and by age at seroconversion: 0–20, &gt;20–40, and &gt;40 y [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b027">27</xref>]. Further stratification by cohort was also performed for the exploratory analyses. In the stratified Cox regression model, the overall log-likelihood of hazards obtained is the sum over strata of the stratum-specific hazards, as estimated by the method of partial likelihood. As the same criteria for determining startpoints (seroconversion date) and endpoints and the similar sampling strategy and follow-up settings were used across cohorts, we combined SCs from all cohorts for the survival analysis to increase the power. Although these cohorts differ in routes of HIV-1 transmission, no appreciable effect of mode of infection on AIDS progression has been found through re-analysis of more than ten thousands of SCs from 38 studies around the world (including three used in this study) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b044">44</xref>].</p><p>To test the association of <italic>PPIA</italic> haplotypes and HIV-1 disease progression, we first performed a global test in the Cox regression model for each of two disease outcomes separately for AA and EA. The global null hypothesis is that the odds ratios of all haplotypes are equal between cases and controls. Likelihood ratio tests were used to compare a full model with all haplotypes and a base model with only covariates. When the significance of the global test exceeded a relaxed nominal level, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.10, the associations of individual haplotypes were further tested.</p><p>To assess the level of correction factor for the number of SNPs, assuming this was a discovery study, we applied spectral decomposition analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b045">45</xref>]. This multiple testing correction method assesses the equivalent level of independent SNPs taking account of the extensive LD across <italic>PPIA.</italic> Based on spectral decomposition analysis of SNPs in this study, a corrected <italic>p-</italic>value of 0.01 would be equivalent to <italic>p</italic> = 0.05. As this study was a confirmation and extension study of markers with previous positive association, uncorrected <italic>p</italic>-values were reported.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Electrophoretic mobility-shift assay.</title><p>Cell culture and an electrophoretic mobility-shift assay were performed as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat-0030088-b046">46</xref>]. Freshly explanted human T lymphocytes were obtained from normal donors, purified by isocentrifugation, and activated for 72 h with 1 mg/ml PHA in RPMI 1640 medium containing 10% FCS (Sigma, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sigmaaldrich.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.sigmaaldrich.com</ext-link>), 2 mM L-glutamine, and penicillin-streptomycin (50 IU/ml and 50 mg/ml, respectively). T lymphocytes were made quiescent by washing and incubating for 24 h in RPMI 1640 medium containing 1% FCS before exposure to cytokines. Cells were then stimulated with 100 nmol/L IL-4 (PeproTech, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.peprotechec.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.peprotechec.com</ext-link>) or 100 nmol/L human rIL-2 (Hoffmann-La Roche, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.roche.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.roche.com</ext-link>) at 37 °C for 10 min. Cell pellets were frozen at −70 °C. The probe sequences were 5′-ttgcgggcggggCcgaacgtggtat-3′ for SNP3C and ttgcgggcggggGcgaacgtggtat-3′ for SNP3G; 5′- ggcgggaggcCaggctcgtgccgtt for SNP4C, and 5′- ggcgggaggcGaggctcgtgccgtt-3′ for SNP4G allele; 5′-aggaaaaccgtgtActattagccatggt-3′ for SNP5A and 5′-aggaaaaccgtgtGctattagccatggt-3′ for SNP5G (SNP site is capped). In cold oligonucleotide competition assay, 100-fold excess of cold unlabeled probe was added as a competitor. The band density was measured by using the software ImageJ (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/index.html" xlink:type="simple">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/index.html</ext-link>). The sequence in and around the SNP sites in the promoter region were searched for the presence of transcription factor binding sites using the program TESS: Transcription Element Search System (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbil.upenn.edu/tess" xlink:type="simple">http://www.cbil.upenn.edu/tess</ext-link>). Sequence alignment was performed using program ClustalW (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/clustalw" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/clustalw</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material id="ppat-0030088-st001" mimetype="application/msexcel" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.st001" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption><title>Primers Used in the Resequencing of the <italic>PPIA</italic> Gene</title><p>(17 KB XLS)</p></caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="ppat-0030088-st002" mimetype="application/msexcel" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030088.st002" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption><title>Genotyping Methods for <italic>PPIA</italic> SNPs</title><p>(18 KB XLS)</p></caption></supplementary-material><sec id="s5a"><title>Accession Numbers</title><p>The Entrez Gene databank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?db=gene" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?db=gene</ext-link>) accession numbers for the genes mentioned in this paper are <italic>PPIA</italic> (5478) and <italic>TRIM5</italic> (85363). The GenBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) accession numbers for the human and chimpanzee <italic>PPIA</italic> genomic sequence are X52851 and NW_001237949, respectively. The Transfac binding site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbil.upenn.edu/cgi-bin/tess/tess" xlink:type="simple">http://www.cbil.upenn.edu/cgi-bin/tess/tess</ext-link>) accession number is R04195 and R03868 for the SP1 factor.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Yuchun Zhou and Beth Binns-Roemer for excellent technical assistance.</p></ack><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AA</term><def><p>African American</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p>confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CypA</term><def><p>cyclophilin A</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EA</term><def><p>European American</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HIV-1</term><def><p>HIV type 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HREU</term><def><p>high-risk exposed uninfected</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LD</term><def><p>linkage disequilibrium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>PPIA</italic></term><def><p>peptidylprolyl isomerase A</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RH</term><def><p>relative hazard</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SC</term><def><p>seroconverter</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SN</term><def><p>seronegative</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNP</term><def><p>single nucleotide polymorphism</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SP</term><def><p>seroprevalent</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ppat-0030088-b001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossolt</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalpana</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1993</year>
					<article-title>Human immunodeficiency virus type 1 Gag protein binds to cyclophilins A and B.</article-title>
					<source>Cell</source>
					<volume>73</volume>
					<fpage>1067</fpage>
					<lpage>1078</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1994</year>
					<article-title>Specific incorporation of cyclophilin A into HIV-1 virions.</article-title>
					<source>Nature</source>
					<volume>372</volume>
					<fpage>359</fpage>
					<lpage>362</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1995</year>
					<article-title>Protein folding. Prolyl isomerases join the fold.</article-title>
					<source>Curr Biol</source>
					<volume>5</volume>
					<fpage>993</fpage>
					<lpage>994</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gamble</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vajdos</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Worthylake</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Houseweart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>1996</year>
					<article-title>Crystal structure of human cyclophilin A bound to the amino-terminal domain of HIV-1 capsid.</article-title>
					<source>Cell</source>
					<volume>87</volume>
					<fpage>1285</fpage>
					<lpage>1294</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Braaten</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1997</year>
					<article-title>The hydrophobic pocket of cyclophilin is the binding site for the human immunodeficiency virus type 1 Gag polyprotein.</article-title>
					<source>J Virol</source>
					<volume>71</volume>
					<fpage>2107</fpage>
					<lpage>2113</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bukovsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenwirth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>1994</year>
					<article-title>Functional association of cyclophilin A with HIV-1 virions.</article-title>
					<source>Nature</source>
					<volume>372</volume>
					<fpage>363</fpage>
					<lpage>365</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Braaten</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2001</year>
					<article-title>Cyclophilin A regulates HIV-1 infectivity, as demonstrated by gene targeting in human T cells.</article-title>
					<source>EMBO J</source>
					<volume>20</volume>
					<fpage>1300</fpage>
					<lpage>1309</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stremlau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perron</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiessling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Autissier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>The cytoplasmic body component TRIM5alpha restricts HIV-1 infection in Old World monkeys.</article-title>
					<source>Nature</source>
					<volume>427</volume>
					<fpage>848</fpage>
					<lpage>853</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayah</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokolskaja</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berthoux</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>Cyclophilin A retrotransposition into TRIM5 explains owl monkey resistance to HIV-1.</article-title>
					<source>Nature</source>
					<volume>430</volume>
					<fpage>569</fpage>
					<lpage>573</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nisole</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoye</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>A Trim5-cyclophilin A fusion protein found in owl monkey kidney cells can restrict HIV-1.</article-title>
					<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
					<volume>101</volume>
					<fpage>13324</fpage>
					<lpage>13328</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berthoux</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sebastian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokolskaja</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Cyclophilin A is required for TRIM5{alpha}-mediated resistance to HIV-1 in Old World monkey cells.</article-title>
					<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
					<volume>102</volume>
					<fpage>14849</fpage>
					<lpage>14853</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stremlau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>Specific recognition and accelerated uncoating of retroviral capsids by the TRIM5alpha restriction factor.</article-title>
					<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
					<volume>103</volume>
					<fpage>5514</fpage>
					<lpage>5519</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokolskaja</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berthoux</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>Cyclophilin A and TRIM5a independently regulate human immunodeficiency virus type 1 infectivity in human cells.</article-title>
					<source>J Virol</source>
					<volume>80</volume>
					<fpage>2855</fpage>
					<lpage>2862</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stremlau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Javanbakht</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sodroski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>Cyclophilin A: An auxiliary but not necessary cofactor for TRIM5alpha restriction of HIV-1.</article-title>
					<source>Virology</source>
					<volume>351</volume>
					<fpage>112</fpage>
					<lpage>120</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokolskaja</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>Cyclophilin, TRIM5, and innate immunity to HIV-1.</article-title>
					<source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>
					<volume>9</volume>
					<fpage>404</fpage>
					<lpage>408</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Javanbakht</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Huigin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>Effects of human TRIM5alpha polymorphisms on antiretroviral function and susceptibility to human immunodeficiency virus infection.</article-title>
					<source>Virology</source>
					<volume>354</volume>
					<fpage>15</fpage>
					<lpage>27</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bleiber</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duggal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>May</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>APOBEC3G genetic variants and their influence on the progression to AIDS.</article-title>
					<source>J Virol</source>
					<volume>78</volume>
					<fpage>11070</fpage>
					<lpage>11076</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duggal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donfield</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2007</year>
					<article-title>Polymorphisms of CUL5 are associated with CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell loss in HIV-1 infected individuals.</article-title>
					<source>PLoS Genetics</source>
					<volume>3</volume>
					<elocation-id>e19.</elocation-id>
					<comment>doi.<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030019" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030019</ext-link></comment>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b019"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bleiber</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>May</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meylan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Use of a combined ex vivo/in vivo population approach for screening of human genes involved in the human immunodeficiency virus type 1 life cycle for variants influencing disease progression.</article-title>
					<source>J Virol</source>
					<volume>79</volume>
					<fpage>12674</fpage>
					<lpage>12680</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b020"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Haploview: Analysis and visualization of LD and haplotype maps.</article-title>
					<source>Bioinformatics</source>
					<volume>21</volume>
					<fpage>263</fpage>
					<lpage>265</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b021"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batzer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deininger</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2002</year>
					<article-title>Alu repeats and human genomic diversity.</article-title>
					<source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
					<volume>3</volume>
					<fpage>370</fpage>
					<lpage>379</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b022"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Javanbakht</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Huigin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2006</year>
					<article-title>Effects of human TRIM5alpha polymorphisms on antiretroviral function and susceptibility to human immunodeficiency virus infection.</article-title>
					<source>Virology</source>
					<volume>354</volume>
					<fpage>15</fpage>
					<lpage>27</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b023"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatziioannou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Caballero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bieniasz</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>Cyclophilin interactions with incoming human immunodeficiency virus type 1 capsids with opposing effects on infectivity in human cells.</article-title>
					<source>J Virol</source>
					<volume>79</volume>
					<fpage>176</fpage>
					<lpage>183</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b024"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haendler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1990</year>
					<article-title>Characterization of the human cyclophilin gene and of related processed pseudogenes.</article-title>
					<source>Eur J Biochem</source>
					<volume>190</volume>
					<fpage>477</fpage>
					<lpage>482</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b025"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suske</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1999</year>
					<article-title>The Sp-family of transcription factors.</article-title>
					<source>Gene</source>
					<volume>238</volume>
					<fpage>291</fpage>
					<lpage>300</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b026"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>Human genes that limit AIDS.</article-title>
					<source>Nat Genet</source>
					<volume>36</volume>
					<fpage>565</fpage>
					<lpage>574</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b027"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2000</year>
					<article-title>Polygenic and multifactorial disease gene association in man: Lessons from AIDS.</article-title>
					<source>Annu Rev Genet</source>
					<volume>34</volume>
					<fpage>563</fpage>
					<lpage>591</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b028"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sham</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>The future of association studies: Gene-based analysis and replication.</article-title>
					<source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
					<volume>75</volume>
					<fpage>353</fpage>
					<lpage>362</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b029"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asparuhova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brondani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziekau</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klimkait</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>Inhibition of HIV-1 multiplication by antisense U7 snRNAs and siRNAs targeting cyclophilin A.</article-title>
					<source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
					<volume>32</volume>
					<fpage>3752</fpage>
					<lpage>3759</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b030"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlahov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>1998</year>
					<article-title>Prognostic indicators for AIDS and infectious disease death in HIV-infected injection drug users: Plasma viral load and CD4+ cell count.</article-title>
					<source>JAMA</source>
					<volume>279</volume>
					<fpage>35</fpage>
					<lpage>40</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b031"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaslow</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apple</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>1996</year>
					<article-title>Influence of combinations of human major histocompatibility complex genes on the course of HIV-1 infection.</article-title>
					<source>Nat Med</source>
					<volume>2</volume>
					<fpage>405</fpage>
					<lpage>411</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b032"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchbinder</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hessol</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Malley</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmberg</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1994</year>
					<article-title>Long-term HIV-1 infection without immunologic progression.</article-title>
					<source>AIDS</source>
					<volume>8</volume>
					<fpage>1123</fpage>
					<lpage>1128</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b033"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilgartner</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donfield</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willoughby</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Contant</surname><given-names>CF</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evatt</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>1993</year>
					<article-title>Hemophilia growth and development study. Design, methods, and entry data.</article-title>
					<source>Am J Pediatr Hematol Oncol</source>
					<volume>15</volume>
					<fpage>208</fpage>
					<lpage>218</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b034"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goedert</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aledort</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biggar</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andes</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>1989</year>
					<article-title>A prospective study of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 infection and the development of AIDS in subjects with hemophilia.</article-title>
					<source>N Engl J Med</source>
					<volume>321</volume>
					<fpage>1141</fpage>
					<lpage>1148</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b035"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Celentano</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sethi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strathdee</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2001</year>
					<article-title>Time to initiating highly active antiretroviral therapy among HIV-infected injection drug users.</article-title>
					<source>AIDS</source>
					<volume>15</volume>
					<fpage>1707</fpage>
					<lpage>1715</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b036"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlahov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1988</year>
					<article-title>Perspectives on infection with HIV-1 among intravenous drug users.</article-title>
					<source>Psychopharmacol Bull</source>
					<volume>24</volume>
					<fpage>325</fpage>
					<lpage>329</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b037"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Detels</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hennessey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>1994</year>
					<article-title>Resistance to HIV-1 infection. Multicenter AIDS Cohort Study.</article-title>
					<source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source>
					<volume>7</volume>
					<fpage>1263</fpage>
					<lpage>1269</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b038"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salkowitz</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Purvis</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyerson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2001</year>
					<article-title>Characterization of high-risk HIV-1 seronegative hemophiliacs.</article-title>
					<source>Clin Immunol</source>
					<volume>98</volume>
					<fpage>200</fpage>
					<lpage>211</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b039"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldrick</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimball</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>1996</year>
					<article-title>NIRCA: A rapid robust method for screening for unknown point mutations.</article-title>
					<source>Biotechniques</source>
					<volume>21</volume>
					<fpage>106</fpage>
					<lpage>112</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b040"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cockerham</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1984</year>
					<article-title>Estimating F-statistics for the analysis of population structure.</article-title>
					<source>Evolution</source>
					<volume>38</volume>
					<fpage>1358</fpage>
					<lpage>1370</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b041"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
					<year>2002</year>
					<article-title>The structure of haplotype blocks in the human genome.</article-title>
					<source>Science</source>
					<volume>296</volume>
					<fpage>2225</fpage>
					<lpage>2229</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b042"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urbanek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1995</year>
					<article-title>An E-M algorithm and testing strategy for multiple-locus haplotypes.</article-title>
					<source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
					<volume>56</volume>
					<fpage>799</fpage>
					<lpage>810</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b043"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<collab xlink:type="simple">Centers for Disease Control</collab>
					<year>1987</year>
					<article-title>Revision of the CDC surveillance case definition for acquired immunodeficiency syndrome.</article-title>
					<publisher-name>Council of State and Territorial Epidemiologists; AIDS Program, Center for Infectious Diseases</publisher-name>
					<source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>
					<volume>36</volume>
					<issue>Suppl 1</issue>
					<fpage>1S</fpage>
					<lpage>15S</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b044"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<collab xlink:type="simple">Cascade Collaboration</collab>
					<year>2000</year>
					<article-title>Time from HIV-1 seroconversion to AIDS and death before widespread use of highly active antiretroviral therapy: A collaborative re-analysis. Collaborative Group on AIDS Incubation and HIV Survival including the CASCADE EU Concerted Action. Concerted Action on SeroConversion to AIDS and Death in Europe.</article-title>
					<source>Lancet</source>
					<volume>355</volume>
					<fpage>1131</fpage>
					<lpage>1137</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b045"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyholt</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2004</year>
					<article-title>A simple correction for multiple testing for single nucleotide polymorphisms in linkage disequilibrium with each other.</article-title>
					<source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
					<volume>74</volume>
					<fpage>765</fpage>
					<lpage>769</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat-0030088-b046"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirken</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>1999</year>
					<article-title>JAK3, STAT, and MAPK signaling pathways as novel molecular targets for the tyrphostin AG-490 regulation of IL-2-mediated T-cell response.</article-title>
					<source>J Immunol</source>
					<volume>162</volume>
					<fpage>3897</fpage>
					<lpage>3904</lpage>
				</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>