<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plospath</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">09-PLPA-RA-0128R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Functional Genomics</subject><subject>Microbiology/Cellular Microbiology and Pathogenesis</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The <italic>Chlamydia</italic> Type III Secretion System C-ring Engages a Chaperone-Effector Protein Complex</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Recognition of Secretion Chaperones</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spaeth</surname><given-names>Kris E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Yi-Shan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valdivia</surname><given-names>Raphael H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="aff1">          <addr-line>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology and Center for Microbial Pathogenesis, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stebbins</surname><given-names>C. Erec</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="edit1">The Rockefeller University, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">valdi001@mc.duke.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: KS YSC RHV. Performed the experiments: KS YSC RHV. Analyzed the data: KS YSC RHV. Wrote the paper: KS RHV.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e1000579</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2009</year></date>
</history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Spaeth et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
<p>In Gram-negative bacterial pathogens, specialized chaperones bind to secreted effector proteins and maintain them in a partially unfolded form competent for translocation by type III secretion systems/injectisomes. How diverse sets of effector-chaperone complexes are recognized by injectisomes is unclear. Here we describe a new mechanism of effector-chaperone recognition by the <italic>Chlamydia</italic> injectisome, a unique and ancestral line of these evolutionarily conserved secretion systems. By yeast two-hybrid analysis we identified networks of <italic>Chlamydia</italic>-specific proteins that interacted with the basal structure of the injectisome, including two hubs of protein-protein interactions that linked known secreted effector proteins to CdsQ, the putative cytoplasmic C-ring component of the secretion apparatus. One of these protein-interaction hubs is defined by Ct260/Mcsc (Multiple cargo secretion chaperone). Mcsc binds to and stabilizes at least two secreted hydrophobic proteins, Cap1 and Ct618, that localize to the membrane of the pathogenic vacuole (“inclusion”). The resulting complexes bind to CdsQ, suggesting that in <italic>Chlamydia</italic>, the C-ring of the injectisome mediates the recognition of a subset of inclusion membrane proteins in complex with their chaperone. The selective recognition of inclusion membrane proteins by chaperones may provide a mechanism to co-ordinate the translocation of subsets of inclusion membrane proteins at different stages in infection.</p>
</abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>The obligate intracellular bacteria <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> is a common sexually transmitted pathogen and the leading cause of preventable blindness worldwide. <italic>Chlamydia</italic> co-opts host cells by secreting virulence factors directly into target cells through a multi-protein complex termed a type III secretion system or “injectisome”. The lack of a system for molecular genetic manipulation in these pathogens has hindered our understanding of how the <italic>Chlamydia</italic> injectisome is assembled and how secreted factors are recognized and translocated. In this study, a yeast two-hybrid approach was used to identify networks of <italic>Chlamydia</italic> proteins that interact with components of the secretion apparatus. CdsQ, a conserved structural component predicted to be at the base of the injectisome, interacted with multiple proteins, including a new chaperone that binds to and stabilizes secretory cargo destined for the membrane of the pathogenic vacuole. These results suggest that the base of the secretion apparatus serves as a docking site for a chaperone and a subset of chaperone-cargo complexes. Because the chlamydial injectisome represents a unique and ancestral lineage of these virulence-associated secretion systems, findings made in <italic>Chlamydia</italic> should provide unique insights as to how effector proteins are recognized and stabilized, and how a hierarchy of virulence protein secretion may be established by Gram-negative bacterial pathogens.</p>
</abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by funds from the NIAID/NIH and the Burroughs Wellcome Trust Fund. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The obligate, intracellular bacterium <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> infects the epithelium of the genital tract and conjunctivae, causing a wide range of ailments including the blinding disease trachoma, conjunctivitis, salpingitis, pelvic inflammatory disease and infertility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Schachter1">[1]</xref>. <italic>Chlamydiae</italic> display an elaborate life cycle beginning with the attachment of an elementary body (EB), the infectious form of the bacteria, to the surface of epithelial cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-DautryVarsat1">[2]</xref>. Shortly after invasion, EBs differentiate into reticulate bodies (RBs). The RB-containing vacuole is rapidly segregated from normal endosomal maturation pathways to generate a membrane-bound “inclusion” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fields1">[3]</xref>. As the inclusion expands, chlamydial replication becomes asynchronous to yield both RBs and EBs. Eventually, most of the cytoplasmic space of the host cell is occupied by the inclusion and EBs exit the host cell to infect adjacent cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Hybiske1">[4]</xref>.</p>
<p>All <italic>Chlamydiae</italic> code for the core components of a type III secretion (T3S) apparatus, a protein transport system used by Gram-negative bacteria to translocate effector proteins directly into host cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Peters1">[5]</xref>. T3S systems are macromolecular structures composed of 20–35 proteins that are often referred to as “injectisomes” due to their resemblance to an injection needle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Cornelis1">[6]</xref>. <italic>Chlamydia</italic> injectisome components are present at all stages of infection and needle-like structures have been observed on the surface of EBs and at the sites of RB attachment to inclusion membranes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Matsumoto1">[7]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fields2">[8]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Matsumoto2">[9]</xref>, suggesting that this secretion system is functional. Putative chlamydial targets of T3S have been identified by their ability to be secreted by <italic>Shigella</italic>, <italic>Yersinia</italic> or <italic>Salmonella</italic> injectisomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Clifton1">[10]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fields3">[11]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Subtil1">[12]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Ho1">[13]</xref>. These T3S substrates include &gt;25 soluble proteins and a large family of ∼40–50 integral membrane proteins of unknown function that localize to the inclusion membrane (Incs) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fields2">[8]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Clifton1">[10]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fields3">[11]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Subtil1">[12]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Ho1">[13]</xref>. At least one of these effectors, Tarp, is translocated during EB invasion of epithelial cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Clifton1">[10]</xref>. T3S substrates are likely translocated in a hierarchical fashion to manipulate specific cellular functions at distinct stages of infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Valdivia1">[14]</xref>.</p>
<p>Injectisomes belong to at least seven distinct families <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Troisfontaines1">[15]</xref> of which three (Ysc, SPI-1 and SPI-2) are predominantly found in free-living pathogens of animals and two are more common in plant pathogens (Hrp1 and Hrp2). The remaining injectisome families are limited to the <italic>Chlamydiae</italic> phylum and the <italic>Rhizobiale</italic> order <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Cornelis1">[6]</xref>. In the <italic>Chlamydiales</italic>, the genes encoding the T3S apparatus are scattered in small genomic islands <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Peters1">[5]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Hefty1">[16]</xref>. Remarkably, the content and synteny of these gene clusters is largely conserved among the <italic>Chlamydiaceae</italic>, suggesting that even though members of this phylum diverged over 700 million years ago <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Horn1">[17]</xref>, the genetic blueprint for the assembly of this translocation system has remained largely intact. These findings, combined with the lack of evidence for robust lateral gene transfer of T3S genes in <italic>Chlamydiae</italic>, support the hypothesis that the chlamydial T3S system is the closest to the primordial injectisome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Kim1">[18]</xref>.</p>
<p>A transcriptional analysis of genes encoding chlamydial injectisome components revealed 10 operons containing 37 genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Hefty1">[16]</xref>. Recent work in <italic>C. pneumoniae</italic> indicated that interactions among components of the basal structure of the secretion apparatus are evolutionarily conserved <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Johnson1">[19]</xref>. For example, the putative C-ring component, CdsQ, interacts with the cytoplasmic component CdsL, mimicking similar interactions between YscL and YscQ in <italic>Yersinia</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Johnson1">[19]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Jackson1">[20]</xref>. Although many components of the chlamydial injectisome basal structure are conserved, the needle and needle tip components are not <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Mueller1">[21]</xref>. The identification of needle component, CdsF, and its chaperones CdsE and CdsG, required more sophisticated bioinformatic approaches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Betts1">[22]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Quinaud1">[23]</xref>. Similarly, two sets of translocation pore components, CopB/CopD and CopB2/CopD2 (CT578/CT579 and CT861/CT860, respectively) were identified based on their close linkage to genes encoding secretion chaperones and their similarity in protein topology to the <italic>Yersinia</italic> translocators YopB and YopD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fields4">[24]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Wattiau1">[25]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Cornelis2">[26]</xref>.</p>
<p>The lack of a system for genetic manipulation in <italic>Chlamydia</italic> and the observation that chlamydial proteins cannot functionally substitute for orthologous T3S components in other bacterial systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fields4">[24]</xref> has limited a functional analysis of this ancestral secretion system. As a result, little is known as to how the <italic>Chlamydia</italic> injectisome is assembled, regulated or how the translocation of effector proteins is temporally and spatially controlled. Here, we applied yeast two-hybrid (Y2H) technology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Pierre1">[27]</xref> to identify new core components, regulators and secretory cargo of the chlamydial injectisome. In this manner, we identified two protein-protein interaction nodes linking multiple effector proteins to CdsQ, the putative C-ring component at the base of the injectisome. We provide evidence that one of these protein interaction hubs is a chaperone for a subset of proteins destined for transport to the inclusion membrane and that CdsQ interacts with this chaperone alone and in complex with effector proteins. We propose that the C-ring of the chlamydial injectisome acts as a platform for the recognition and engagement of chaperones complexed to secretory cargo.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Identification of <italic>Chlamydia</italic> protein-protein interaction networks by yeast two-hybrid analysis</title>
<p>The core components of the T3S apparatus are defined by 10 operons dispersed among five different loci in the chromosome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Hefty1">[16]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>). In addition, two unlinked operons encode proteins of the T3S-related flagellar export machinery. Based on protein-protein interactions defined among homologous components (Table 1) in other bacterial pathogens, the chlamydial injectisome has been proposed to have an architecture as outlined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1B</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Peters1">[5]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Cornelis1">[6]</xref>.</p>
<fig id="ppat-1000579-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Yeast two-hybrid analysis defines hubs of protein-protein interactions linking the <italic>Chlamydia</italic> injectisome to secreted effectors.</title>
<p>(A). Operon arrangement of conserved component of the <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> type III secretion system (T3SS) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Hefty1">[16]</xref>. Light grey: secreted proteins, Dark grey: T3S chaperones (B). <italic>Proposed architecture of the Chlamydia injectisome</italic>. Assignments were made based on protein interactions conserved in other bacterial T3SS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Cornelis1">[6]</xref> and as proposed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Peters1">[5]</xref>. Cds: <underline>c</underline>ontact <underline>d</underline>ependent <underline>s</underline>ecretion protein, Cop: <underline>c</underline>hlamydial <underline>o</underline>uter <underline>p</underline>rotein. (C). <italic>Interactions between C. trachomatis T3S chaperones and their putative cargo</italic>. Protein-protein interactions were identified based on reciprocal YTH interactions. (D). <italic>Identification of interactions among core components of the C. trachomatis T3S apparatus, chlamydial proteins of unknown function and known effector proteins</italic>. Networks of putative interacting proteins were identified by Y2H analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000579.s002">Table S2</xref>). Self-interactions are denoted by arcs.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.g001" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>To identify additional injectisome components, regulators, secretion chaperones and their respective cargo, we screened chlamydial proteins for their ability to interact with core components of the injectisome by Y2H analysis. We amplified 208 <italic>Chlamydia</italic>-specific, conserved hypothetical ORFs, and genes encoding putative effectors and injectisome components by PCR and cloned them into Y2H vectors to generate carboxyl terminal fusions to the DNA-binding domain (DBD) or Activator Domain (AD) of the yeast transcription factor Gal4, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000579.s001">Table S1</xref>). For proteins containing large hydrophobic regions which tend to be toxic when expressed in yeast (e.g. inclusion membrane proteins) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Sisko1">[28]</xref>, only the putative cytoplasmic regions were expressed. MATα and MATa yeast strains expressing chlamydial proteins fused to Gal4<sub>AD</sub> or Gal4<sub>DBD</sub> were crossed to generate diploid strains. Positive interactions among these fusion proteins were identified by their ability to transcribe Gal4-dependent reporter genes (<italic>GAL1<sub>UAS</sub>-GAL1<sub>TATA</sub>-HIS3</italic>, <italic>GAL2<sub>UAS</sub>-GAL2<sub>TATA</sub>-ADE2</italic>) and restore growth in histidine and adenine deficient media. We identified 49 proteins that displayed various levels of homotypic and heterotypic interactions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000579.s002">Table S2</xref>). Most of these interactions were among proteins predicted to reside at the inner membrane and the cytoplasmic side of the basal T3S apparatus, although homotypic and heterotypic interactions were also observed among the predicted cytoplasmic domains of Inc proteins, including IncA, Ct565, Ct229 and Ct223.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Identification of T3S chaperone binding partners</title>
<p>We predicted that secretory cargo proteins engaged by known T3S chaperones could be identified based on protein interactions revealed by Y2H analysis. There are three classes of T3S chaperones: class III chaperones prevent the premature polymerization of needle components in the bacterial cytoplasm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Quinaud1">[23]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Yip1">[29]</xref>. An interaction between the needle component CdsF and its chaperone CdsG <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Betts1">[22]</xref> was detected in our Y2H analysis as well as an interaction between CdsG and its co-chaperone CdsE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). Class II chaperones, which in <italic>Chlamydia</italic> include <underline>and Ct274 (LcrH/SycD-like) and</underline> the tetratricopeptide repeat (TPR) containing Scc2 and Scc3 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fields4">[24]</xref>, bind to hydrophobic translocator proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Neyt1">[30]</xref>. We determined that Scc2 binds to both CopB and CopD while Scc3 binds to CopN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>). The interactions between Scc2/CopB and Scc3/CopN are in agreement with previous findings <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fields4">[24]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Slepenkin1">[31]</xref>. In addition, we detected heterotypic interactions between Ct274 and a small (24 kDa), acidic (pI 4.5) protein Ct668. Ct274 also interacted with Ct161, a homologue of the secreted protein Lda2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Kumar1">[32]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>).</p>
<p>Class I chaperones are small (∼15 kDa), acidic (pI&lt;5) proteins that assemble mostly as homodimers to bind effector proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Wattiau1">[25]</xref>. These chaperones have been further subclassified depending on whether they associate with one (class Ia) or several (class Ib) effectors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Page1">[33]</xref>. By amino acid sequence analysis, <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> encodes at least <underline>three</underline> putative T3S chaperones: Ct043, Ssc1 and Ct663 (SycE/CesT-like). Unlike their counterparts in other pathogenic bacteria, we did not detect many homotypic interactions among chlamydial class I T3S chaperones. Instead, we found evidence of potential heterodimeric complexes, including an Scc1-Ct663 interaction.</p>
<p>Overall, these results suggest that chlamydial homologues of Class 1 T3S chaperones may form heterodimeric complexes and thus limit the usefulness of a binary Y2H screen to identify binding partners. However, given that ∼10% of the chlamydial coding potential may be devoted to T3S substrates,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Subtil1">[12]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Bannantine1">[34]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Li1">[35]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Rockey1">[36]</xref> it is apparent that the number of effector proteins is in excess of potential chaperones. This indicates that the secretion of many chlamydial T3S substrates is either chaperone-independent or that many secretion chaperones remain to be identified.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>The C-ring component CdsQ is a central hub of multiple protein-protein interactions</title>
<p>CdsQ (Ct672), a homologue to the C-ring component FliN of the <italic>Salmonella</italic> flagellar apparatus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Brown1">[37]</xref> and the <italic>Shigella</italic> Spa33 protein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-MoritaIshihara1">[38]</xref>, represented a central node of <italic>Chlamydia</italic> protein-protein interactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>). CdsQ interacted with CdsL, an interaction that is conserved among related components in <italic>Yersinia</italic>, <italic>Shigella</italic>, and enteropathogenic <italic>E. coli</italic> (EPEC) injectisomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Jackson1">[20]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-MoritaIshihara1">[38]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Creasey1">[39]</xref>. CdsS and CdsT were also observed to interact with CdsQ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>). These proteins are predicted to reside at the inner membrane and likely interact as components of the inner membrane spanning ring in other bacterial pathogens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fields5">[40]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Moraes1">[41]</xref>. An interaction between CdsQ, CdsL and CdsD has been recently reported in <italic>C. pneumoniae</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Johnson1">[19]</xref>. Unfortunately, we were unable to detect CdsD interacting proteins because this protein was self-activating in our Y2H reporter system. Additional components of the basal T3S apparatus may include the CdsQ-interacting proteins Ct560 and Ct567, an ORF immediately adjacent to this operon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig 1A</xref>). CdsQ did not interact with CdsV (Ct090), a conserved injectisome inner membrane protein, but did interact with the CdsV/FlhA homologue Ct060 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>). This raises the possibility that the <italic>Chlamydia</italic> injectisomes may be formed by a mixture of flagellar and T3S components. A combinatorial assembly of injectisomes may enhance the functionality of the secretion apparatus by adding assembly control checkpoints or by expanding the repertoire of cargo proteins that can be secreted.</p>
<p>We did not detect several of the predicted interactions among integral membrane components of the injectisome or the secretin CdsC. The inability to detect such interactions is likely due to the limitations of the classical Y2H system in identifying interactions among integral membrane proteins and proteins destined to fold outside of cytoplasmic compartments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Kuroda1">[42]</xref>. Nonetheless, we detected interactions between the needle component CdsF and its chaperones, CdsG and CdsE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Betts1">[22]</xref>, and Ct584, a conserved chlamydial ORF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). We postulate that these interactions were detected because they most likely occur in the bacterial cytoplasm.</p>
<p>Despite the known limitations of classical Y2H analysis, our ability to identify previously reported interactions validate the utility of this approach. Importantly, novel interactions identified by Y2H suggest that CdsQ may play a central role in organizing networks of proteins at the base of the injectisome, including secreted effectors.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Ct260 and its interacting partners localize to distinct subcellular sites</title>
<p>T3S effectors require secretion chaperones for efficient translocation by injectisomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Lee1">[43]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Lilic1">[44]</xref>. ATPases in <italic>Yersinia</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic>, YscN and InvC respectively, recognize chaperone-effector complexes and provide the energy for their dissociation, thus facilitating effector protein export <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Akeda1">[45]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Blaylock1">[46]</xref>. Similarly, the inner membrane component YscU in <italic>Yersinia</italic> recognizes translocators as T3S export substrates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Sorg1">[47]</xref>. Indeed, it makes intuitive sense that components at the base of the injectisome provide a platform for the recognition of secretory cargo.</p>
<p>Based on these observations, two chlamydial protein-protein interaction hubs linking known secreted effector proteins to CdsQ were of particular interest. In the first interaction node, Ct700, via its TPR repeat domain could act as a scaffold to dock effectors directly (e.g. Ct223 and Ct226) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Bannantine1">[34]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Li1">[35]</xref> or indirectly (IncA and Lda2) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Kumar1">[32]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-ScidmoreCarlson1">[48]</xref>. These protein interaction networks are linked to CdsQ via the putative protease, Ct824 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>). The relevance of these interactions <italic>in vivo</italic> remains to be determined. The other protein-protein interaction hub has Ct260 at its center and links CdsQ to the inclusion membrane proteins Cap1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fling1">[49]</xref>, Ct618 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Sisko1">[28]</xref> and Ct225 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Li1">[35]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>). Cap1 has been postulated to be a secretion target of the chlamydial injectisome because fusion of the first 15 amino acids of Cap1 to adenylate cyclase is sufficient to impart T3S-dependent export of the fusion protein in <italic>Shigella</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Subtil1">[12]</xref>.</p>
<p>To validate the novel interactions identified by Y2H, we decided to characterize the putative bindings of Ct260 to CdsQ and the secreted effectors Ct618 and Cap1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). We generated specific antisera to Ct260, and CdsQ, and determined by immunoblot analysis that these proteins are expressed in infected cells and in density gradient purified EBs and RBs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g002">Fig. 2B&amp;C</xref>). Next, we determined the subcellular localization of Ct260 and CdsQ in EBs by assessing their fractionation properties upon extraction from EBs with Triton-X114 or Sarcosyl <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Bordier1">[50]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Caldwell1">[51]</xref>. CdsQ and Ct260 phase partitioned with Triton-X114 indicating an association with hydrophobic proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>), although a significant portion of CdsQ was also present in the aqueous, non-hydrophobic phase. Any association of Ct260 with membranes is unlikely to include chlamydial outer membrane complexes (COMC) since the protein was readily extracted from EBs with Sarcosyl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g002">Fig. 2E</xref>). Given its association with CdsQ and translocated effectors, Ct260 could be a core T3S component or a secreted effector. We tested the ability of Ct260 to be secreted from EBs by adapting a recently described <italic>in vitro</italic> secretion system. In this system, EB effectors are released into the culture supernatant by treatment with calcium chelators and bovine serum albumin at 37°C <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Jamison1">[52]</xref>. Under these conditions Ct260 was not released into the extracellular media, while Tarp, a known secreted effector, was efficiently secreted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g002">Fig. 2F</xref>), suggesting that at least in EBs, Ct260 is not an efficient target of T3S.</p>
<fig id="ppat-1000579-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Components of a <italic>Chlamydia</italic> injectisome protein-protein interaction hub localize to distinct subcellular sites.</title>
<p>(A). <italic>Network of predicted Ct260 (Mcsc) protein-protein interactions</italic>. Interactions were defined by Y2H analysis as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>. (B–C). <italic>Ct260 and CdsQ are expressed throughout infection</italic>. (B). HeLa cells were infected with <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> and total protein samples collected at various times post-infection. Ct260, the bacterial major outer membrane protein (MOMP), and the inclusion membrane proteins IncA and Cap1 were detected with specific antibodies. Tubulin levels were serve as protein loading controls. (C). Reticulate bodies (RBs) and EBs were purified from infected cells by density gradient and total proteins were analyzed by immunoblot analysis with antibodies against the indicated chlamydial proteins. (D–E). <italic>Ct260 and CdsQ partition with membranes and hydrophobic proteins</italic>. (D). EBs were extracted with Triton-X114 to separate membrane from non-membrane associated proteins. Ct260 partitioned with the detergent fraction along with integral membrane proteins CdsJ and MOMP, but not the cytoplasmic proteins Hsp60 and RpoD. CdsQ partitioned in both membrane and aqueous fractions. (E). Ct260 is sensitive to Sarcosyl extraction, a detergent that solubilizes all membrane proteins except COMC, suggesting a lack of association with chlamydia outer membrane complexes (COMC) (F–G). <italic>Ct260 is not a target of T3S</italic>. (F). Secretion of T3S was induced by treatment of EBs with 0.5% BSA and 10mM EGTA. Tarp, but not Ct260, was detected in the extracellular media. (G). CdsQ and Ct260 localize to bacteria while Cap1 and Ct618 localize to the inclusion membrane. Ct260 and CdsQ (red) were observed exclusively in association with MOMP or LPS-positive (green) bacteria at early (12 h) and late (24 h) post-infection. Ct618 and Cap1 (red) localize to the extra-bacterial structures, including inclusion membranes. Scale bar range: 1.5 µm (12 h) to 4 µm (24 h). Abbreviations: (h.p.i.) hours post infection, (T) total lysates from purified EBs, (Memb.) and (Aq.) represent the detergent and aqueous phase of Triton-X114 extraction, (S) and (P) denote the soluble and insoluble protein fractions extracted with Sarcosyl respectively. Mcsc: Functional nomenclature for Ct260 (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g003">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.g002" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We performed a detailed analysis of Ct260, CdsQ, Cap1 and Ct618 localization at 12 and 24 h post infection by immunofluorescence microscopy. Consistent with the fractionation experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g002">Fig. 2D&amp;E</xref>), CdsQ and Ct260 associated exclusively with bacteria, while Ct618 and Cap1 were found at the inclusion membrane, even at early time points (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g002">Fig. 2G</xref>). Overall, these results indicated that at steady state, Ct260 and CdsQ reside within the confines of bacterial cells, while Ct618 and Cap1 are largely exported. Therefore, any interaction between Ct260 and C618 or Cap1 is likely to be transitory and occur in the bacterial cytoplasm or in association with bacterial cytoplasmic membranes.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Ct260/Mcsc (<underline>M</underline>ultiple <underline>c</underline>argo <underline>s</underline>ecretion <underline>c</underline>haperone) stabilizes Ct618 and Cap1</title>
<p>PSI-BLAST-based database searches of Ct260 did not reveal homology to any known proteins. However, given that Ct260 is a small (18.8 kDa), acidic (pI 4.6) protein that interacted with itself and T3S effectors by Y2H analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>), we hypothesized that it was a secretion chaperone. In support of this, the predicted secondary structure of Ct260 has a similar arrangement of α-helices and β-strands as T3S chaperones (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000579.s004">Fig. S1</xref>). We propose that Ct260 is a new T3S secretion chaperone, and thus refer to it as <underline>M</underline>ultiple <underline>c</underline>argo <underline>s</underline>ecretion <underline>c</underline>haperone (Mcsc).</p>
<p>We first tested if recombinant Mcsc formed homotypic complexes by treating recombinant protein with low levels of the chemical crosslinker DSP on ice and assessing the formation of higher molecular weight complexes by SDS PAGE and immunoblots. Mcsc was readily cross-linked into a major 36 kDa molecular weight species consistent with the formation of a dimer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). This dimeric form of Mcsc was seen even in the absence of chemical crosslinkers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>) and its relative abundance was sensitive to heat and reducing agents (not shown). Higher order complexes consisting of potential trimers and tetramers were also observed at the highest concentration of crosslinker. The relevance of these higher order complexes is not clear since we have observed a cold-induced aggregation of purified Mcsc (not shown). Next, we determined if Mcsc associated with the effectors Cap1 and Ct618 by co-expressing untagged Mcsc and a hexahistidine-tagged versions of full-length Cap1 (aa 1–298) and the amino-terminal domain of Ct618 (aa1–189) from bicistronic vectors. Mcsc efficiently co-purified with 6xHis-tagged Ct618 or Cap1 on Ni<sup>2+</sup> NTA resin, suggesting a stable interaction between these inclusion membrane proteins and the putative chaperone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). We sized these complexes by gel filtration chromatography and determined that when expressed alone, Mcsc eluted as a ∼35 kDa complex, a size consistent with that of the dimeric forms identified in cross-linking experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). In contrast, when Mcsc was co-expressed with Cap1 or Ct618, it fractionated as a protein complex of 66–78 kDa and 54–65 kDa respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). The size of these complexes is consistent with that of two Mcsc subunits bound to one effector protein.</p>
<fig id="ppat-1000579-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Ct260/Mcsc (<underline>M</underline>ultiple <underline>c</underline>argo <underline>s</underline>ecretion <underline>c</underline>haperone) dimers bind to the inclusion membrane proteins Cap1 and Ct618.</title>
<p>(A). <italic>Mcsc forms a dimer</italic>. Hexahistidine-tagged –Mcsc (Ct260) was treated with various concentrations of the reversible crosslinker DSP, resolved on a 4–20% gradient gel and probed with Mcsc specific antibodies. Arrow marks the dimeric form of Mcsc, which was reduced to monomeric form after boiling in the presence of DTT. (B–C). <italic>Mcsc-Cap1 and Mcsc-Ct618 co-purify as complexes</italic>. (B). Lysates of <italic>E. coli</italic> expressing 6xHis-tagged Mcsc or co-expressing Mcsc and 6xHis-tagged Ct618 (aa1–189) or Cap1 (aa1–298) were incubated with Ni<sup>2+</sup>-NTA agarose beads. Bound proteins were eluted with 150 mM imidazole and detected by SDS PAGE and Coomassie staining. Mcsc co-purified with Ct618-6xHis and Cap1-6xHis on Ni<sup>2+</sup> beads. The numbers above the lanes represent fractions collected after incubation with wash buffer or elution buffers. Untagged Mcsc does not bind to the nickel columns non-specifically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4E</xref>). (C). Proteins eluted from affinity columns were further fractionated by gel filtration chromatography. Mcsc eluted from the column at a size of ∼34 kDa. Mcsc-Cap1 and Mcsc/Ct618 eluted as complexes of ∼66 kDa and 54 kDa, respectively. The identity of all eluted proteins was confirmed by immunoblot analysis with anti Mcsc, Cap1 and hexahistidine tags. (D). <italic>Mcsc binds to endogenous Cap1 from infected cells</italic>. Lysate of infected HeLa cells were incubated with purified Mcsc dimers pre-bound to Ni<sup>2+</sup>-NTA agarose beads, and proteins were eluted with 150 mM imidazole. Cap1, but not IncA, preferentially co-eluted with Mcsc. Ponceau staining of nitrocellulose membrane indicate levels of Mcsc eluted from beads. (E). <italic>The central region of Ct618 and Cap1 mediate binding to Mcsc</italic>. The Mcsc binding domains of Ct618 and Cap1 were mapped by Y2H analysis. Positive interactions were assessed by activation of GAL4-dependent <italic>HIS3</italic> and <italic>ADE2</italic> reporter genes and growth in media lacking histidine (H) or adenine (A). Growth on media lacking tryptophan (T) and leucine (L) are shown as controls for maintenance of the Y2H vectors. Cartoon schematic shows Mcsc binding region maps adjacent to the large hydrophobic region at the COOH-terminus of these inclusion membrane proteins.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.g003" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Next, we tested if Mcsc could bind to full-length Cap1 from infected cell lysates. We incubated NP40 solubilized membranes from infected cells with recombinant 6xHis-tagged Mcsc dimers, and assessed the ability of endogenous Cap1 to be purified on Ni<sup>2+</sup>NTA agarose. Cap1, but not the inclusion membrane proteins IncA, specifically bound to Ni<sup>2+</sup>-beads in the presence of Mcsc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g003">Fig. 3D</xref>).</p>
<p>We mapped the regions of Ct618 and Cap1 that interact with Mcsc by Y2H analysis. Truncated forms of Ct618 and Cap1 were fused to the GAL4<sub>DBD</sub> and co-expressed in yeast with GAL4<sub>AD</sub>-Mcsc. Positive interactions were assessed by growth in histidine or adenine deficient media as described above. A region encompassing the central region of both Ct618 and Cap1 was sufficient to mediate an interaction with Mcsc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g003">Fig. 3E</xref>). The Mcsc binding site on its secretory cargo (Ct618 and Cap1) is within the range of what has been observed in other chaperone-effector protein complexes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Lilic1">[44]</xref>.</p>
<p>Our initial attempts at purifying recombinant Cap1 and Ct618 indicated that these proteins were not stable when expressed at high levels in <italic>E.coli</italic>. Given our finding that Mcsc may constitute a chaperone for these effectors, we compared the effect of expressing Cap1 and Ct618 with or without Mcsc from mono and bicistronic <italic>E. coli</italic> expression vectors under the control of a T7 promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). Consistent with our earlier observations, the detected levels of Cap1 and Ct618 protein were significantly lower in the absence of Mcsc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). Interestingly, Cap1 and Ct618 migrated at a higher apparent molecular weight in the absence of Mcsc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>), suggesting that in the presence of the chaperone, these inclusion membrane proteins may be subjected to conformational changes that expose susceptible regions to <italic>E. coli</italic> proteases. Although this processing may be specific to <italic>E. coli</italic>, it is clear that the expression and stability of Cap1 and 618 is dependent on Mcsc, thus establishing its role as a chaperone.</p>
<fig id="ppat-1000579-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Effector protein stability is linked to Mcsc function.</title>
<p>(A). <italic>Schematic of T7 expression vectors used to test the effect of Mcsc in Ct618 and Cap1 expression</italic> (B). <italic>Ct618 and Cap1 display altered mobility in the presence of Mcsc</italic>. Ct618 and Cap1 were expressed with or without Mcsc and total proteins (∼30 µg) were analyzed by immunoblots with specific antibodies. Note decreased levels of expression and altered sizes of Cap1 and Ct618 in the absence of Mcsc. (C–E) <italic>Mcsc mutations in the putative effector binding domain disrupt cargo binding and destabilize Cap1 and Ct618</italic>. (C). Point mutations in the putative effector binding regions of class I chaperones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Lilic1">[44]</xref> were generated in the α1 (L15A) and β1 strand (L31, L33 &amp; L35 to A or G) either in Y2H (D) or in <italic>E. coli</italic> expression vectors (E). (D). All Mcsc mutants disrupted the Y2H interactions between Mcsc and Cap1 and Ct618. (E). <italic>E. coli</italic> co-expressing 6xHis-tagged Ct618 or Cap1 with Mcsc mutants were monitored for steady-state expression of recombinant proteins and co-purification on Ni<sup>2+</sup> agarose beads. Mutations in the Mcsc β1 strand led to substantially lower steady-state levels of Ct618 and Cap1. In contrast, L15A mutants altered Ct618, but not Cap1, stability.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.g004" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Based on the crystal structures of various class I secretion chaperones, conserved hydrophobic amino acids in the first α-helix and β-strand are proposed to be important for the recognition of secretory cargo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Lilic1">[44]</xref>. We identified the corresponding amino acids in Mcsc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4C</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000579.s004">S1</xref>) and tested if these residues played a role in the binding of Mcsc to Ct618 and Cap1. First, we generated point mutation in Mcsc's α1-helix (L15A) and β1-strand (I31A, I33A V35A (“3A”) and I31G, I33G V35G (“3G”)) and tested the ability of these mutants to interact with effectors by Y2H. Consistent with their proposed role in binding substrates, all three mutations in Mcsc significantly impaired interactions with Cap1 and Ct618 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4D</xref>). Next, we introduced these mutations into Mcsc-Cap1 and Mcsc-Ct618 bi-cistronic <italic>E. coli</italic> expression vectors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). The 3A and 3G mutations did not affect the expression of Mcsc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4E</xref>) or its ability to form dimers (not shown). However, co-expression of 3A and 3G Mcsc mutants led to significantly lower levels of Ct618 and Cap1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4E</xref>) as assessed by immunoblot analysis of total protein lysates. In contrast, co-expression with the L15A Mcsc mutant had little effect on the total amounts of Cap1observed but Ct618 was not detectable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4D</xref>). We tested if these mutants were still capable of binding either hexahistidine tagged Cap1 or Ct618 by co-isolating effector complexes on Ni-NTA agarose beads. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4D</xref>, Mcsc and Mcsc mutants co-purified with Cap1 in a manner proportional to the levels of Cap1 present in the total lysates. Not surprisingly, Mcsc mutants did not co-purify with Ct618, since the effector was not detectable in the total samples. It is worth noting that Mcsc 3A and 3G mutants had a much greater impact on Cap1 and Ct618 expression levels than the absence of Mcsc, suggesting that Ct618 and Cap1 levels are directly affected by their interaction with Mcsc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4B &amp; E</xref>). We postulate that 3A and 3G Mcsc mutants, like the wild type counterpart, still provides a platform for the binding of Cap1 and Ct618, but the binding interaction is not strong enough to prevent their dissociation from Mcsc and eventual degradation.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>CdsQ binds to Mcsc and Mcsc-Cap1 protein complexes</title>
<p>T3S chaperones are proposed to play a role in targeting secretory cargo to the injectisome, either by providing new targeting information <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Birtalan1">[53]</xref>, or facilitating the exposure of the short amino terminal export signal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Cornelis1">[6]</xref>. Based on these findings we were intrigued by the significance of Mcsc-CdsQ interactions identified by Y2H. First, we confirmed these interactions by demonstrating that purified Mcsc dimers efficiently bound to GST-CdsQ, indicating that the presence of the effector is not required for Mcsc to engage the C-ring (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). Next, we tested if CdsQ can bind to Mcsc-effector complexes by incubating GST-CdsQ with Mcsc-Cap1 complexes isolated by gel filtration chromatography. A complex of Mcsc and Cap1 co-eluted from glutathione sepharose beads when incubated with GST-CdsQ but not GST alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>). Based on CdsQ's homology to the C-ring component Spa33, which localizes to the base of <italic>Shigella</italic> injectisome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-MoritaIshihara1">[38]</xref>, we postulate that CdsQ associates with the base of the chlamydial secretion needle apparatus and provides a platform for the recognition of Mcsc and Mcsc-effector protein complexes.</p>
<fig id="ppat-1000579-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Mcsc-effector complexes bind to CdsQ, the C-ring component of the injectisome.</title>
<p>(A). <italic>CdsQ binds to Mcsc</italic>. Recombinant GST or GST-CdsQ coupled to glutathione Sepharose beads was incubated with 6xHis-tagged Mcsc dimers. Bound proteins were eluted with 5 mM reduced glutathione and analyzed by SDS PAGE followed by Sypro Orange staining and immunoblots (IB). Arrowheads mark GST-CdsQ, GST and 6xHis-Mcsc. Mcsc was preferentially co-precipitated in the presence of CdsQ. (B). <italic>CdsQ binds to Mcsc-Cap1 effector complexes</italic>. Pull-down assays were done as in (A) but using Mcsc/Cap1-6xHis protein complexes purified by gel filtration chromatography (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). By immunoblot analysis, Mcsc/Cap1 protein complex co-purified only in the presence of GST-CdsQ.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.g005" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Greater than 10% of the <italic>Chlamydia</italic> genome is predicted to encode for substrates of T3S <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Valdivia1">[14]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Subtil2">[54]</xref>. This arsenal of effectors is required for efficient cell invasion, establishment of the inclusion, acquisition of nutrients, and avoidance of innate immune responses. How these highly adapted pathogens coordinate the secretion of effector proteins is largely unknown. In one model, a hierarchy of effector secretion is established by the timing of their synthesis. In this manner, temporal gene expression over the early, mid and late cycles dictates effector delivery <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Valdivia1">[14]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Belland1">[55]</xref>. One caveat with this model is that early cycle genes continue to be expressed throughout infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Belland1">[55]</xref>; therefore, all effectors are theoretically present by mid-late cycle (∼20 h for urogenital <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> serovars). The presence of early, mid and late effectors competing to engage a common injectisome would argue that additional components are involved to ensure an orderly translocation of effectors. How do mid-late effectors compete for efficient transport given that all these effectors must engage a common injectisome?</p>
<p>Most effector proteins contain a T3S targeting signal at their extreme amino terminus that is broadly recognized by divergent injectisomes. Additional targeting information contained within approximately the first 200 amino acid residues of the effector provides binding sites for secretion chaperones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Lilic1">[44]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Parsot1">[56]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Michiels1">[57]</xref>. These chaperones are multi-functional: they target effectors to the proper injectisome, stabilize pre-formed effector proteins, mask membrane targeting domains prone to aggregation and possibly impart a translocation hierarchy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Lee1">[43]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-FrithzLindsten1">[58]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Letzelter1">[59]</xref>. T3S chaperones are small, acidic proteins that display a conserved α−β−α fold and form stable homo- and heterodimers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Stebbins1">[60]</xref>. These dimers bind to partially unfolded effector proteins via a hydrophobic patch formed by residues on the α1, β1 and β4-5 strands <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Lilic1">[44]</xref>.</p>
<p>Despite the limited homology among T3S chaperones, six potential <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> chaperones can be identified based on primary amino acid sequences: Ct043, Scc1 (Ct088), Scc2 (Ct568), Scc3 (Ct860), Ct274 and Ct663 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fields6">[61]</xref>. To identify their potential effector cargo, we screened for interacting chlamydial proteins by Y2H analysis. We confirmed previously reported interactions between Scc2 and CopB, and Scc3 and CopN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fields4">[24]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Slepenkin1">[31]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). In addition, we identified a novel interaction between Scc2 and CopD and determined that Ct274 may interact with two small acidic proteins, Ct161 and Ct668 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). Ct668, encoded within an operon of structural injectisome components, was previously identified in a screen for proteins exported from the inclusion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Sisko1">[28]</xref>. PSI-BLAST analysis indicates that Ct668 is related to a large family of hypothetical DNA-binding proteins, raising the intriguing possibility that Ct668 is a transcriptional regulator. Whether Ct668 is a chaperone, a core T3S component, or a regulatory factor remains to be determined.</p>
<p>Given the large number of effectors and the dearth of T3S chaperone interacting partners identified by bioinformatics, we hypothesized that many secretion accessory factors remained to be found. We speculated that these factors may act as adaptors between effector proteins and components of the injectisome. In a subgenomic interactome map of the T3S apparatus, CdsQ emerged as a central node of protein-protein interactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>). Based on its homology to FliN and Spa33, CdsQ is predicted to form the C-ring, a large protein scaffold at the base of the injectisomes. Interestingly, many of the CdsQ interacting factors we identified are conserved among injectisomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Kim1">[18]</xref>, suggesting small deviations in the basic architecture of this secretion apparatus despite the large evolutionary distance between Chlamydiales and other Gram-negative bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Horn1">[17]</xref>. We identified two novel hubs of protein-protein interactions (Ct260 and Ct700) that linked multiple inclusion membrane proteins to the secretion apparatus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>). Ct260/Mcsc was of particular interest because, in addition to its direct interaction with CdsQ and many secretory cargo proteins (Cap1, Ct225 and Ct618) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Li1">[35]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Fling1">[49]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Subtil2">[54]</xref>, it had predicted secondary structural similarity to other T3S chaperones (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000579.s004">Fig. S1</xref>). Mcsc is expressed in both developmental forms of <italic>Chlamydia</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>) and forms stable dimers and complexes with at least two inclusion membrane proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g003">Fig. 3A–D</xref>). In <italic>E. coli</italic>, significantly lower levels of Ct618 and Cap1 were observed in the absence of Mcsc or when Mcsc was mutated to impair effector protein binding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4B, D, E</xref>). These findings suggest that one of the functions of Mcsc is to stabilize these inclusion membrane proteins. While the data presented here implies that Mcsc acts as a bona fide Class I T3S chaperone, at present we cannot assign a role for Mcsc in directing the secretion of Cap1 or Ct618. Proof of such a role will require the development of a proper system for genetic manipulation in <italic>Chlamydia</italic> or the reconstitution of chaperone-dependent secretion in a heterologous T3S system.</p>
<p>In <italic>S. typhimurium</italic>, the SptP-SicP effector chaperone complex binds to the conserved ATPase InvC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Akeda1">[45]</xref>. InvC then dissociates this complex and provides the energy required for the translocation of the SptP across the injectisome. A similar role for the ATPase in substrate selection by chaperone binding has been proposed for the EPEC T3S system and flagellar export <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Gauthier1">[62]</xref>. By analogy to these findings, we propose that CdsQ recruits Mcsc-effector complexes directly to the base of the injectisome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). However, because Mcsc can bind to the C-ring component CdsQ in the absence of its bound substrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>), it is also possible that Mcsc is pre-docked on the C-ring of the injectisome. This latter possibility is consistent with the observation that Mcsc partitions with inner membranes in EBs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>) in the absence of its cognate cargo, which are not synthesized until after 1 h (Cap1) and 8 h (Ct618) post invasion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Belland1">[55]</xref>. Because the stability of effectors require binding by Mcsc, either Mcsc dimers detach from the injectisome and bind to newly synthesized effectors at distal sites or the translating ribosome itself is recruited to the C-ring. In support of a localized translation model, the chlamydial GTPase (HflX) that binds to the 50S ribosome subunit, localizes to the bacterial inner membrane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Polkinghorne1">[63]</xref>, suggesting that some ribosomes may be pre-docked at secretion sites. Furthermore, one of the CdsQ-interacting proteins identified by Y2H is Ct677, a putative ribosome recycling factor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>). These findings raise the intriguing possibility that the injectisome may interact with the bacterial translational machinery. As an obligate intracellular pathogen, it would not be surprising if the chlamydial injectisome, the main portal for communication with the host, is hard wired to interface with the bacterial and transcriptional and translational machinery. Such a system would allow for rapid regulation of effector protein translocation in response to intracellular (pathogen's metabolic status, developmental cues) and extracellular (host responses, inclusion lumen environment) signals.</p>
<fig id="ppat-1000579-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Model of Mcsc recognition by the <italic>Chlamydia</italic> injectisome.</title>
<p>The inclusion membrane proteins Cap1 and Ct618 in complex with Mcsc dimers engage the C-ring of the injectisome (CdsQ). These docked complexes are presumably placed in proximity to the ATPase CdsN to initiate secretion of the effector proteins. HP: Hydrophobic patches common to many inclusion membrane proteins (Inc).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.g006" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The prominence of CdsQ as a hub of protein-protein interactions, including secretion chaperones, suggests a central role in regulating the recognition of effector proteins. In the flagellar system, the CdsQ-related C-ring component FliM binds to the flagellar general chaperone FliJ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-GonzlezPedrajo1">[64]</xref>. Similarly, the <italic>Shigella</italic> CdsQ homologue, Spa33, can be co-isolated with effector proteins indicating that recognition of chaperone-effector complexes by C-ring components may be evolutionarily conserved <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-MoritaIshihara1">[38]</xref>. Based on these observations and our own findings with the <italic>Chlamydia</italic> injectisome, we hypothesize that proteins at the base of the translocon integrate multiple intracellular signals to regulate the production and secretion of virulence factors. Interestingly, in the flagellar systems, the C-ring protein FliG was recently shown to bind to fumarate reductase to control the direction of flagellar rotation in response to fumarate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-CohenBenLulu1">[65]</xref>. These findings suggest that in addition to the recognition of secretion substrates, the C-ring may provide a mechanism for the integration of intracellular cues by binding to “sensor” proteins not typically thought to be associated with T3S (e.g. envelope assembly, intermediary metabolism, stress). Global screens for proteins that interact with components at the base of the injectisome, such as those described in this study, should help elucidate the intricacies of T3S function and regulation.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Bacterial strains and plasmids</title>
<p>Bacteria, yeast strains and plasmids are listed in Supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000579.s003">Table S3</xref>. <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> ORFs were amplified from purified <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> serovar D genomic DNA using the primers listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000579.s003">Table S3</xref> and the Expand High Fidelity PCR system (Roche). PCR products were subcloned into pET24d, pET15b (Novagen) and/or pGEX-4T1 (Invitrogen). Mutation sites, L15→A, 3A (I31, I33, V35→A) and 3G (I31, I33, V35→G), were chosen based on sequence alignments of several T3S chaperones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000579-g004">Fig. 4C</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000579.s004">S1</xref>) and site directed mutagenesis was performed with QuickChange Kit (Stratagene) as instructed by the manufacturer. Mcsc/Cap1-6xHis, Mcsc/Ct618-6xHis and Mcsc(L15A, 3A or 3G)/Ct618-6xHis were vo-expressed as a bicistronic construct in pET-24d(+). Affinity-tagged recombinant proteins were expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 DE3 (Stratagene) with 0.5 mM IPTG.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Creation of Y2H strains library and Y2H screens</title>
<p>The Matchmaker Two-Hybrid System (Clontech) was used in this screen. <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> genes (CT) were amplified from a previously established chlamydial ORF library <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Sisko1">[28]</xref> using the pGAD and pGBT9 primers or directly from genomic DNA using ORF specific primers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000579.s003">Table S3</xref>) with Expand High Fidelity polymerase. PCR products were transformed into both Y2H reporter yeast strains PJ69-4a (MATα) or AH109 (MATa) along with digested Y2H vectors pGAD424 or pGBT9 by the lithium acetate method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-BrownAaT1">[66]</xref>. MATα yeast strains containing <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> ORFs inserted into pGAD424 were arrayed in 96 well plates. This ordered array of yeast strains was mated against individual MATa yeast strains containing pGBT9-CT ORFs. The resulting diploids were selected in synthetic complete (SC) medium lacking leucine and tryptophan. Yeast matings were performed semi-automatically with a RoboMEK-FX (Beckman-Coulter) liquid handler. Positive interactions were assessed by monitoring growth on SC media lacking histidine (His) or adenine (Ade) over 4 days.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Cell culture conditions and propagation of <italic>C. trachomatis</italic></title>
<p>HeLa cell monolayers were grown in Dulbecco's minimal essential medium (DMEM)(Gibco) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Mediatech) at 37°C/5% CO<sub>2</sub>. <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> LGV (serotype L2) EBs were purified by density gradient centrifugation as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Caldwell1">[51]</xref>. Infections were initiated by adding EBs to HeLa monolayers (multiplicity of infection (MOI) ∼1) followed by centrifugation at 3,500×<italic>g</italic> for 25 min at 10°C.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Generation of antibodies and immunodetection methods</title>
<p>GST-Mcsc, GST-CdsQ and GST-Ct618 (aa1–96) were expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> and purified with glutathione coated Sepharose 4-Fast Flow beads (GE Healthcare) at 4°C for 2 hr. Recombinant GST-Mcsc was eluted with 20 mM reduced glutathione in PBS (pH 8.0) and used to immunize female White New Zealand rabbits (5∼6 lbs) (Robinson Services, Inc.). Antisera was depleted of anti-GST antibodies and affinity purified over a GST-Mcsc or GTS-CdsQ column. Bound antibodies were eluted with 0.2 M Glycine (pH 2.5) and neutralized with 1 M K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>. The resulting antibodies was then dialyzed in PBS and stored in −80°C. For immunoblot analysis, protein samples were separated by SDS-PAGE, transferred to 0.45 µm nitrocellulose membranes and blocked in 2% non-fat powder milk in TBST (50 mM Tris-Base, 150 mM NaCl, 0.2% Tween pH 7.4). Membranes were incubated with primary antibody diluted in 1% milk-TBST, followed by incubation with secondary antibody conjugated to horseradish peroxidase and detection by chemiluminescence (Pierce). Primary antibodies include anti-Tarp (T. Hackstadt, RML), Hsp60, MOMP and CdsJ (K. Fields, U. of Miami), Cap1 (A. Subtil, Pasteur Institute), RpoD (M. Tang, UC Irvine), actin (Sigma-Aldrich), α-tubulin (Sigma-Aldrich), hexahistidine (Rockland Inc.) and IncA (generated in our laboratory).</p>
<p>For indirect immunofluorescence detection, HeLa cells were seeded on glass coverslips and infected at MOI∼1 for the indicated times. Infected cells were fixed in methanol, blocked with 2% bovine serum albumin (BSA) in PBS and incubated with polyclonal anti-Mcsc, CdsQ, Ct618 or Cap1 antibodies (1∶100 in PBS/2% BSA) and mouse monoclonal anti-MOMP antibodies (RDI) (1∶300 in PBS/2% BSA) for 1 hr at 4°C. Immunoreactive material was detected with Alexafluor conjugated secondary antibodies (Invitrogen, CA). Images were acquired with a Leica TCS SL confocal microscope and processed with Leica imaging software.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4e">
<title>Subcellular fractionations</title>
<sec id="s4e1">
<title>Outer membrane complexes</title>
<p>Density gradient purified EBs were solubilized in 2 mls of Sarcosyl extraction buffer (PBS pH 7.4, 2% Sarcosyl, 1.5 mM EDTA) at 37°C for 1 h. The resulting lysates were centrifuged at 100,000×<italic>g</italic> for 1 h at 4°C. Sarcosyl-insoluble pellets (<italic>Chlamydia</italic> Outer Membrane complexes-COMC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Caldwell1">[51]</xref>) were washed three times in Sarcosyl extraction buffer. COMC pellets were resuspended in PBS pH 7.4/10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and incubated with 25 µg of DNase at 37°C for 2 hrs. COMC pellets were centrifuged as described above and resuspended in PBS. Sarcosyl insoluble and soluble protein fractions were acetone precipitated and resuspended in SDS-PAGE loading buffer prior to immunoblot analysis.</p>
<p>Triton X114 fractionation of membrane proteins. EBs (∼10<sup>10</sup> IFUs) were centrifuged at 20,000×<italic>g</italic> for 5 min at 4°C, resuspended in 50 µl of PBS/5 mM dithiotheritol (DTT) for 10 min at 4°C, and integral membrane proteins were extracted using 1% Triton-X114 as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Bordier1">[50]</xref>. The resulting aqueous fraction containing cytoplasmic proteins and the detergent fraction containing membrane proteins were acetone precipitated and resuspended in SDS-PAGE loading buffer.</p>
<p><italic>In vitro</italic> induction of T3S. In vitro secretion of T3S substrates was performed as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Jamison1">[52]</xref>. Briefly, density gradient purified EBs were washed 5 times in potassium acetate (KAc) buffer (50 mM potassium acetate, pH 4.8) and resuspended in KAc with or without 0.5% BSA/10 mM EGTA. After 30 min incubation at 37°C, bacteria were centrifuged at 20,000×<italic>g</italic> for 5 min at 4°C. Supernatants were re-centrifuged and the secreted proteins in the clarified samples were subjected to immunoblot analysis.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4f">
<title>Biochemical analysis of Mcsc</title>
<sec id="s4f1">
<title>Crosslinking</title>
<p>Purified 6xHis-Mcsc was treated with the reversible chemical crosslinker DSP (dithiobis[succinimidylpropionate]) (Pierce) at concentrations between 0.25–1 mM in Dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO). After 20 min incubation at 4°C, reactions were quenched in TNE and solubilized in sample buffer devoid of reducing agents. The samples were divided equally and 50 mM dithiothreitol (DTT) was added to half of the samples. Samples were analyzed by immunoblot.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4f2">
<title>Purification of Mcsc and Mcsc/effector protein complexes</title>
<p>Mcsc, Ct618-Mcsc, and Cap1-Mcsc complexes were purified from bacteria expressing pET15b-Mcsc, pET-24d-Mcsc/Cap1 or pET24d-Mcsc/CT618 by incubation of clarified supernatants with Ni<sup>2+</sup>-nitriloacetic acid (NTA) agarose beads (Qiagen, Ca). Beads were washed 4 times with wash buffer (50 mM Phosphate buffer pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 10 mM Imidazole) and recombinant proteins were eluted with 4×0.5 ml of 50 mM Phosphate Buffer containing 150 mM NaCl and150 mM imidazole. Co-eluted proteins were identified by Coomasie staining and immunoblots with anti-Mcsc and anti-6xHis antibodies. For gel filtration, hexahistidine-tagged Mcsc, Cap1/Mcsc or CT618/Mcsc protein samples were loaded on a 16/60 Sephacryl S-100 HR column (GE Healthcare) and proteins eluted in 10 mM Tris-HCl/50 mM phosphate Buffer/150 mM NaCl pH 8.0 at a flow rate of 0.5 ml/min and at a pressure of 0.5 MPa. Proteins were collected in fraction sizes of 2.5 ml and detected with anti-6xHis or the anti-Mcsc antibodies. Size of the eluted complexes was determined with a low molecular weight gel filtration calibration kit (GE Healthcare).</p>
</sec><sec id="s4f3">
<title>Mcsc-Cap1 pull-down assays</title>
<p>HeLa cell monolayers were infected with <italic>C. trachomatis</italic> serovar L2 at an MOI of ∼5 for 28 hours, lysed in 1% NP40 (50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 50 mM NaCl, 1 mM PMSF, protease inhibitor cocktail). Approximately 400 µg of lysates from infected or uninfected cells were incubated with 50 µg of purified 6xHis-Mcsc at 4°C for 30 min and isolated with Ni<sup>2+</sup>-NTA agarose beads. The beads were washed five times with binding buffer and bound proteins were subjected to immunoblot.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4g">
<title>GST-CdsQ binding assays</title>
<p>Freshly purified GST or GST-CdsQ coupled to glutathione sepharose beads was incubated with 6xHis-Mcsc dimers or Mcsc/Cap-6xHis complexes purified by gel filtration and incubated overnight at 4°C in binding buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, 150 mM NaCl, 2 mM EDTA and 0.5% TritonX-100) After extensive washing, bound proteins were eluted with 25 mM glutathione and subjected to SDS PAGE followed by staining with Sypro orange (Molecular Probes) and detection with a Typhoon 9410 Phosphoimager, (GE Healthcare). Parallel samples were analyzed by immunoblot.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="ppat.1000579.s001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.s001" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p>Summary of chlamydial genes characterized by yeast two-hybrid analysis</p>
<p>(0.36 MB DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="ppat.1000579.s002" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.s002" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p>Summary of Y2H-based protein-protein interactions identified between chlamydial proteins</p>
<p>(0.18 MB DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="ppat.1000579.s003" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.s003" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S3</label><caption>
<p>Strains, plasmids and primers</p>
<p>(0.06 MB DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="ppat.1000579.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000579.s004" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p>Mcsc structural models. A–C. Predicted three dimensional structure of Mcsc. A putative 3D model of Mcsc (yellow) was generated with the neural network folding prediction program I-TASSER (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zhang.bioinformatics.ku.edu/I-TASSER/" xlink:type="simple">http://zhang.bioinformatics.ku.edu/I-TASSER/</ext-link>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000579-Schachter1">[1]</xref>. Modeling of Mcsc and SigE structure were performed with PyMOL (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pymol.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.pymol.org/</ext-link>). Overlay of Mcsc monomers (A) on SigE (magenta) monomers and dimers (blue) (B), and a model of a Mcsc dimer (C). D. Conservation among amino terminal residues in Class I T3S chaperones required for effector protein binding. Conserved amino acids (blue) in Mcsc align with α-helix and β-strand 1 as assessed by secondary structure predictions performed with PSIPRED (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinf.cs.ucl.ac.uk/psipred/" xlink:type="simple">http://bioinf.cs.ucl.ac.uk/psipred/</ext-link>).</p>
<p>(3.34 MB TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material>
</sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank K. Fields, T. Hackstadt, M. Tang, and P. Zhou for sharing reagents, K. Shiana and A. Xavier for help with robotics in yeast matings, Ashely Artis, Marelisa Lopez and KellyAnn Jones for help in creating the yeast two-hybrid library, Micah Luftig for assistance with protein folding models of Mcsc, J. Cocchiaro for comments on the manuscript, and S. Grass and J. St. Geme for assistance with gel filtration chromatography methods. We particularly acknowledge A. Subtil for pointing out structural similarities between Ct260 and T3S chaperones, helpful discussions, and providing anti-Cap1 antisera.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Schachter1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schachter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Infection and Disease Epidemiology.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name name-style="western"><surname>RS</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <source>In <italic>Chlamydia: Intracellular Biology, Pathogenesis and Immunity</italic></source>             <publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>139</fpage>             <lpage>170</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-DautryVarsat1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dautry-Varsat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Subtil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hackstadt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Recent insights into the mechanisms of <italic>Chlamydia</italic> entry.</article-title>             <source>Cell Microbiol</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>1714</fpage>             <lpage>1722</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Fields1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hackstadt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>The chlamydial inclusion: escape from the endocytic pathway.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>221</fpage>             <lpage>245</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Hybiske1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hybiske</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Mechanisms of host cell exit by the intracellular bacterium <italic>Chlamydia</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>11430</fpage>             <lpage>11435</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Peters1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Timms</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bavoil</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Type III secretion a la <italic>Chlamydia</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Trends Microbiol</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>241</fpage>             <lpage>251</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Cornelis1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelis</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>The type III secretion injectisome.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Micro</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>811</fpage>             <lpage>825</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Matsumoto1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1982</year>             <article-title>Electron microscopic observations of surface projections on <italic>Chlamydia</italic> psittaci reticulate bodies.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>150</volume>             <fpage>358</fpage>             <lpage>364</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Fields2"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dooley</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hackstadt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title><italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> type III secretion: evidence for a functional apparatus during early-cycle development.</article-title>             <source>Molecular Microbiology</source>             <volume>48</volume>             <fpage>671</fpage>             <lpage>683</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Matsumoto2"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>Isolation and electron microscopic observations of intracytoplasmic inclusions containing <italic>Chlamydia psittaci</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>145</volume>             <fpage>605</fpage>             <lpage>612</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Clifton1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Clifton</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grieshaber</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dooley</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>A chlamydial type III translocated protein is tyrosine-phosphorylated at the site of entry and associated with recruitment of actin.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>101</volume>             <fpage>10166</fpage>             <lpage>10171</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Fields3"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hackstadt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Evidence for the secretion of <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> CopN by a type III secretion mechanism.</article-title>             <source>Molecular Microbiology</source>             <volume>38</volume>             <fpage>1048</fpage>             <lpage>1060</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Subtil1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Subtil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Delevoye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Balana</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tastevin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perrinet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>A directed screen for chlamydial proteins secreted by a type III mechanism identifies a translocated protein and numerous other new candidates.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>1636</fpage>             <lpage>1647</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Ho1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Starnbach</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>The <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar typhimurium-encoded type III secretion systems can translocate <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> proteins into the cytosol of host cells.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>73</volume>             <fpage>905</fpage>             <lpage>911</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Valdivia1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Valdivia</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title><italic>Chlamydia</italic> effector proteins and new insights into chlamydial cellular microbiology.</article-title>             <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>53</fpage>             <lpage>59</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Troisfontaines1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Troisfontaines</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelis</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Type III Secretion: More Systems Than You Think.</article-title>             <source>Physiology</source>             <volume>20</volume>             <fpage>326</fpage>             <lpage>339</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Hefty1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hefty</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Chlamydial type III secretion system is encoded on ten operons preceded by sigma 70-like promoter elements.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>189</volume>             <fpage>198</fpage>             <lpage>206</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Horn1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Collingro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz-Esser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beier</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Purkhold</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Illuminating the Evolutionary History of <italic>Chlamydiae</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>304</volume>             <fpage>728</fpage>             <lpage>730</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Kim1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Revisiting the chlamydial type III protein secretion system: clues to the origin of type III protein secretion.</article-title>             <source>Trends in Genetics</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>65</fpage>             <lpage>69</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Johnson1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mahony</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Interactions between CdsD, CdsQ, and CdsL, Three Putative <italic>Chlamydophila pneumoniae</italic> Type III Secretion Proteins.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>190</volume>             <fpage>2972</fpage>             <lpage>2980</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Jackson1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Plano</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Interactions between type III secretion apparatus components from <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> detected using the yeast two-hybrid system.</article-title>             <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>             <volume>186</volume>             <fpage>85</fpage>             <lpage>90</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Mueller1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Broz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ringler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Erne-Brand</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>The V-antigen of <italic>Yersinia</italic> forms a distinct structure at the tip of injectisome needles.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>310</volume>             <fpage>674</fpage>             <lpage>676</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Betts1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Twiggs</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sal</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wyrick</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Bioinformatic and biochemical evidence for the identification of the type III secretion system needle protein of <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>190</volume>             <fpage>1680</fpage>             <lpage>1690</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Quinaud1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Quinaud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ple</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Job</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Contreras-Martel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simorre</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Structure of the heterotrimeric complex that regulates type III secretion needle formation.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>7803</fpage>             <lpage>7808</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Fields4"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hackstadt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Analysis of Putative <italic>Chlamydia</italic> trachomatis Chaperones Scc2 and Scc3 and Their Use in the Identification of Type III Secretion Substrates.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>187</volume>             <fpage>6466</fpage>             <lpage>6478</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Wattiau1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wattiau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bernier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Deslee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Michiels</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelis</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <article-title>Individual chaperones required for Yop secretion by <italic>Yersinia</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>91</volume>             <fpage>10493</fpage>             <lpage>10497</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Cornelis2"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelis</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf-Watz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>The <italic>Yersinia</italic> Yop virulon: a bacterial system for subverting eukaryotic cells.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>861</fpage>             <lpage>867</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Pierre1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pierre</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Luc</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Genome-wide protein interaction maps using two-hybrid systems.</article-title>             <source>FEBS letters</source>             <volume>480</volume>             <fpage>32</fpage>             <lpage>36</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Sisko1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sisko</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spaeth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Valdivia</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Multifunctional analysis of <italic>Chlamydia</italic>-specific genes in a yeast expression system.</article-title>             <source>Molecular Microbiology</source>             <volume>60</volume>             <fpage>51</fpage>             <lpage>66</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Yip1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Finlay</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Strynadka</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Structural characterization of a type III secretion system filament protein in complex with its chaperone.</article-title>             <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>75</fpage>             <lpage>81</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Neyt1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Neyt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelis</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Role of SycD, the chaperone of the <italic>Yersinia</italic> Yop translocators YopB and YopD.</article-title>             <source>Molecular Microbiology</source>             <volume>31</volume>             <fpage>143</fpage>             <lpage>156</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Slepenkin1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Slepenkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>de la Maza</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Interaction between Components of the Type III Secretion System of <italic>Chlamydiaceae</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>187</volume>             <fpage>473</fpage>             <lpage>479</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Kumar1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cocchiaro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Valdivia</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>The Obligate Intracellular Pathogen <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> Targets Host Lipid Droplets.</article-title>             <source>Current Biology</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>1646</fpage>             <lpage>1651</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Page1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Parsot.</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Chaperones of the type III secretion pathway: jacks of all trades.</article-title>             <source>Molecular Microbiology</source>             <volume>46</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>11</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Bannantine1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bannantine</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Viratyosin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rockey</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>A secondary structure motif predictive of protein localization to the chlamydial inclusion membrane.</article-title>             <source>Cell Microbiol</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>35</fpage>             <lpage>47</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Li1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Characterization of Fifty Putative Inclusion Membrane Proteins Encoded in the <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> Genome.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>76</volume>             <fpage>2746</fpage>             <lpage>2757</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Rockey1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rockey</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Scidmore</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bannantine</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Proteins in the chlamydial inclusion membrane.</article-title>             <source>Microbes Infect</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>333</fpage>             <lpage>340</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Brown1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>MAA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Joss</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Crystal Structure of the Flagellar Rotor Protein FliN from <italic>Thermotoga maritima</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>187</volume>             <fpage>2890</fpage>             <lpage>2902</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-MoritaIshihara1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morita-Ishihara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sagara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title><italic>Shigella</italic> Spa33 is an essential C-ring component of type III secretion machinery.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>281</volume>             <fpage>599</fpage>             <lpage>607</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Creasey1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Creasey</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Delahay</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Daniell</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Yeast two-hybrid system survey of interactions between LEE-encoded proteins of enteropathogenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Microbiology</source>             <volume>149</volume>             <fpage>2093</fpage>             <lpage>2106</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Fields5"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Plano</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Straley</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <article-title>A low-Ca2+ response (LCR) secretion (ysc) locus lies within the lcrB region of the LCR plasmid in <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>176</volume>             <fpage>569</fpage>             <lpage>579</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Moraes1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moraes</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spreter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Strynadka</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Piecing together the type III injectisome of bacterial pathogens.</article-title>             <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>258</fpage>             <lpage>266</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Kuroda1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mima</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Systems for the detection and analysis of protein–protein interactions.</article-title>             <source>Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology</source>             <volume>71</volume>             <fpage>127</fpage>             <lpage>136</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Lee1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title><italic>Salmonella</italic> type III secretion-associated chaperones confer secretion-pathway specificity.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>51</volume>             <fpage>483</fpage>             <lpage>495</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Lilic1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lilic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vujanac</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stebbins</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>A Common Structural Motif in the Binding of Virulence Factors to Bacterial Secretion Chaperones.</article-title>             <source>Molecular Cell</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>653</fpage>             <lpage>664</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Akeda1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Akeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Chaperone release and unfolding of substrates in type III secretion.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>437</volume>             <fpage>911</fpage>             <lpage>915</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Blaylock1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blaylock</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Riordan</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Missiakas</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schneewind</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Characterization of the <italic>Yersinia enterocolitica</italic> type III secretion ATPase YscN and its regulator, YscL.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>188</volume>             <fpage>3525</fpage>             <lpage>3534</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Sorg1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sorg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Amstutz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Broz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>YscU recognizes translocators as export substrates of the <italic>Yersinia</italic> injectisome.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>3015</fpage>             <lpage>3024</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-ScidmoreCarlson1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Scidmore-Carlson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dooley</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hackstadt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Identification and characterization of a <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> early operon encoding four novel inclusion membrane proteins.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>753</fpage>             <lpage>765</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Fling1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fling</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>D'Orazio</surname><given-names>SEF</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>CD8+ T cells recognize an inclusion membrane-associated protein from the vacuolar pathogen <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>             <volume>98</volume>             <fpage>1160</fpage>             <lpage>1165</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Bordier1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bordier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>Phase separation of integral membrane proteins in Triton X-114 solution.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>256</volume>             <fpage>1604</fpage>             <lpage>1607</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Caldwell1"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kromhout</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schachter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>Purification and partial characterization of the major outer membrane protein of <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>31</volume>             <fpage>1161</fpage>             <lpage>1176</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Jamison1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hackstadt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Induction of type III secretion by cell-free <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> elementary bodies.</article-title>             <source>Microbial Pathogenesis</source>             <volume>45</volume>             <fpage>435</fpage>             <lpage>440</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Birtalan1"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Birtalan</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Three-dimensional secretion signals in chaperone-effector complexes of bacterial pathogens.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>971</fpage>             <lpage>980</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Subtil2"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Subtil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blocker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dautry-Varsat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Type III secretion system in <italic>Chlamydia</italic> species: identified members and candidates.</article-title>             <source>Microbes Infect</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>367</fpage>             <lpage>369</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Belland1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Belland</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sturdevant</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Genomic transcriptional profiling of the developmental cycle of <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>             <volume>100</volume>             <fpage>8478</fpage>             <lpage>8483</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Parsot1"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Parsot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamiaux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>A-L</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>The various and varying roles of specific chaperones in type III secretion systems.</article-title>             <source>Current Opinion in Microbiology</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>7</fpage>             <lpage>14</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Michiels1"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Michiels</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelis</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Secretion of hybrid proteins by the <italic>Yersinia</italic> Yop export system.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>173</volume>             <fpage>1677</fpage>             <lpage>1685</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-FrithzLindsten1"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Frithz-Lindsten</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rosqvist</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Forsberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>The chaperone-like protein YerA of <italic>Yersinia pseudotuberculosis</italic> stabilizes YopE in the cytoplasm but is dispensible for targeting to the secretion loci.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>635</fpage>             <lpage>647</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Letzelter1"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Letzelter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sorg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mota</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stalder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>The discovery of SycO highlights a new function for type III secretion effector chaperones.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>3223</fpage>             <lpage>3233</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Stebbins1"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stebbins</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Structural microbiology at the pathogen-host interface.</article-title>             <source>Cell Microbiol</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>1227</fpage>             <lpage>1236</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Fields6"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hackstadt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>The <italic>Chlamydia</italic> Type III Secretion System: Structure and Implications for Pathogenesis.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wyrick</surname><given-names>PMBaP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <source><italic>Chlamydia</italic> Genomics and Pathogenesis</source>             <publisher-loc>Norfolk, UK</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Horizon Bioscience</publisher-name>             <fpage>219</fpage>             <lpage>234</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Gauthier1"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Finlay</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Translocated intimin receptor and its chaperone interact with ATPase of the type III secretion apparatus of enteropathogenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>185</volume>             <fpage>6747</fpage>             <lpage>6755</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-Polkinghorne1"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Polkinghorne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Hernandez</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pospischil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Timms</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title><italic>Chlamydophila pneumoniae</italic> HflX belongs to an uncharacterized family of conserved GTPases and associates with the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> 50S large ribosomal subunit.</article-title>             <source>Microbiology</source>             <volume>154</volume>             <fpage>3537</fpage>             <lpage>3546</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-GonzlezPedrajo1"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>González-Pedrajo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Minamino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Namba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Interactions between C ring proteins and export apparatus components: a possible mechanism for facilitating type III protein export.</article-title>             <source>Molecular Microbiology</source>             <volume>60</volume>             <fpage>984</fpage>             <lpage>998</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-CohenBenLulu1"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen-Ben-Lulu</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shimoni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Noy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davidov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>The bacterial flagellar switch complex is getting more complex.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>27</volume>             <fpage>1134</fpage>             <lpage>1144</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="ppat.1000579-BrownAaT1"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown AaT</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <source><italic>Yeast Gene Analysis</italic></source>             <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>53</fpage>             <lpage>66</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
</ref-list>

</back>
</article>