<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plospath</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PPATHOGENS-D-11-02875</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002582</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Pearls</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mutation and Selection of Prions</article-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Weissmann</surname>
            <given-names>Charles</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">          <addr-line>Department of Infectology, Scripps Florida, Jupiter, Florida, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>True-Krob</surname>
            <given-names>Heather</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Washington University School of Medicine, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">charlesw@scripps.edu</email></corresp>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The author has declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e1002582</elocation-id><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Charles Weissmann</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health (1RO1NSO59543, 1R01NSO67214) and the Alafi Family Foundation. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="4"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Prion Diseases</title>
      <p>Prion diseases, or transmissible spongiform encephalopathies (TSEs), occur naturally in several species, including humans, cattle, sheep, and deer, and can be transmitted experimentally to many others. Typically, incubation times are relatively long, extending to 40 years or more in humans; however, after appearance of clinical symptoms, death mostly ensues within less than a year, as a consequence of neurodegeneration accompanied by accumulation of abnormal conformers of the host protein PrP. Natural transmission usually occurs perorally, as exemplified by the kuru epidemic among the Fore people of Papua New Guinea, attributed to cannibalistic practices; the bovine spongiform encephalopathy (BSE) epizootic in the United Kingdom at the end of last century, caused by feeding of contaminated meat-and-bone meal to cattle; or the current epizootic of chronic wasting disease afflicting cervids in 19 states of the United States. Transmission of BSE prions to young humans gave rise to a limited outbreak of a novel illness, variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD), almost exclusively in the UK. Sporadic cases of prion disease occur at very low frequency in human populations (sCJD) and in cattle herds (atypical BSE), and are attributed to spontaneous generation of prions in the affected individuals. Finally, familial forms of human prion disease are linked to a variety of different, dominant mutations in the <italic>PRNP</italic> gene, and while afflicted families are rare, penetrance is very high.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Replication of Prions</title>
      <p>Prions consist mainly, if not solely, of PrP<sup>Sc</sup> (scrapie prion protein), aggregated conformers of the GPI-linked host glycoprotein PrP<sup>C</sup> (cellular prion protein). PrP<sup>Sc</sup> propagates by converting PrP<sup>C</sup> to a replica of itself (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002582-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). PrP<sup>C</sup> may exist as an equilibrium mixture of conformers, some of which can accrete to PrP<sup>Sc</sup> “seeds” at a critical rate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Collinge1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Weissmann1">[2]</xref>. This seeding model is supported by the protein misfolding cyclic amplification (PMCA) reaction, in which brain homogenate, as a source of PrP<sup>C</sup>, is spiked with a seed of infected brain homogenate and subjected to multiple cycles of sonication and incubation, ultimately yielding a vast excess of infectious prions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Castilla1">[3]</xref>. Infectious prions arose spontaneously in PMCA-mediated, cell-free reactions from defined components <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Deleault1">[4]</xref>, in particular from recombinant PrP, a phospholipid, and poly(A) or poly(dT) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Wang1">[5]</xref>, definitively laying to rest the perennial proposal that the infectious agent is a virus-like entity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Manuelidis1">[6]</xref>. Prion-like, seeded conversion into an aggregated state has been proposed for several mammalian proteins such as Abeta, α-synuclein, or serum amyloid, which underlie protein misfolding diseases, and for several fungal, in particular yeast, proteins.</p>
      <fig id="ppat-1002582-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002582.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Propagation, mutation, and selection of prions in cultured cells.</title>
          <p>(A) The seeding model of prion propagation predicates that PrP<sup>C</sup> monomers add to the termini of PrP<sup>Sc</sup> fibrils and in doing so, adopt the conformation of the constituent PrPSc subunits. (B) Prion populations are thought to constitute quasi-species, consisting of a major species and numerous variants at low levels. Brain-adapted 22L prions are resistant to swainsonine treatment when assayed on PK1 cells and are able to infect R33 cells (R33 competent). When propagated in PK1 cells, swainsonine-sensitive, R33-incompetent prions gradually (passages P0 to P12) become the major species in the population because they multiply faster. (C) PK1 cell-adapted 22L prions (a) were cloned (b) in PK1 cells. The populations become heterogeneous as mutations arise during propagation (c–e). The red circles represent swainsonine-resistant prions; when challenged with the drug, some populations (top and middle row) acquire the capacity to become resistant while others (bottom row) do not. Schematic representation of data from reference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Li2">[16]</xref>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002582.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Prion Strains</title>
      <p>Prion populations may present as distinct strains: these differ in their phenotypic properties but are associated with PrP<sup>Sc</sup> having the same amino acid sequence. Murine prion strains, originally characterized by the incubation time and the neuropathology they elicit, can be propagated indefinitely in mice homozygous for the PrP gene. Many “classical” strains currently propagated in mice and hamsters, such as 79A, 22L, and ME7, originated from scrapie-infected sheep or goats <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Dickinson1">[7]</xref> and were cloned by endpoint dilution in mice.</p>
      <p>Strain-specific properties of the prion are believed to be enciphered in the conformation of the cognate PrP<sup>Sc</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Prusiner1">[8]</xref>, and indeed, distinct strains are often associated with PrP<sup>Sc</sup> species differing in physicochemical properties. Experiments with yeast prion strains have shown that specific conformations can be propagated in vitro by pure, unglycosylated proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Tanaka1">[9]</xref>. Nonetheless, in view of the vast multiplicity of mammalian prion strains and their tropism for particular cell lines, it is conceivable that post translational modifications of PrP, such as glycosylation or association with some cellular components, might favor certain PrP conformations and hence account for cell-specific preferential propagation of particular strains.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>The Species Barrier</title>
      <p>In general, there is a considerable barrier to transmission of prions between animal species, in that even massive intracerebral trans-species inoculation causes disease at only low frequency (low “attack rate”) and/or only after very long incubation times, if at all. This barrier was abolished in some instances by replacing the PrP gene of the recipient by its counterpart from the donor, but clearly factors other than mismatch of PrP sequences contribute to the incompatibility. Importantly, when prions are serially transmitted from the initial trans-species recipients to further animals of the same species, attack rates increase and incubation times decrease, reflecting “adaptation” to the new host <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Kimberlin1">[10]</xref>. “Adaptation” implies as a first step accretion of PrP<sup>C</sup> from the recipient host to the incoming PrP<sup>Sc</sup> seed, which may be a very inefficient process if the amino acid sequence of the host PrP entrains a spectrum of conformations that are poorly compatible with that of the seed. Efficient propagation may only be enabled when the conformation of the seed changes, perhaps initially at the “growing end” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Li1">[11]</xref>, resulting in a “mutation” at the conformational level. Subsequently, prions may evolve to replicate more rapidly in the new host, accounting for the striking reduction of their incubation period as they are sequentially transferred within the new species.</p>
      <p>In some instances, transfer of a prion strain from one species to another, followed by several passages in the original host species, led to emergence of mutant strains. For example, when cloned murine 139A prions were passaged through hamster and subsequently passaged repeatedly in mouse a new strain, 139A-H2M, was recovered; however, ME7 subjected to the same procedure remained apparently unchanged <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Kimberlin2">[12]</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Evolution of Prions</title>
      <p>The finding that many murine prion strains replicated efficiently in selected murine cell lines created important new experimental opportunities. In particular, the slow, expensive, and imprecise mouse-based bioassay for murine prions could be replaced by a humane, rapid, and precise cell-based procedure, the standard scrapie cell assay (SSCA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Klohn1">[13]</xref>. The differential susceptibility of cell lines to various prion strains provided the basis of the cell panel assay (CPA), which rapidly differentiates between various prion strains on the basis of their cell tropism and their susceptibility to various drugs, such as swainsonine or kifunensine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Mahal1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Browning1">[15]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The CPA revealed that serial propagation of brain-derived 22L prions in PK1 cells led to progressive change in their properties; while initially able to propagate in R33 cells (“R33 competent”) or in PK1 cells in the presence of swainsonine (“swainsonine resistant”), the prions gradually became completely R33 incompetent and swainsonine-sensitive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002582-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). When these “cell-adapted” prions were returned to mouse brain, they gradually re-acquired their former properties and became indistinguishable from the original 22L strain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Li2">[16]</xref>. Along similar lines, when swainsonine-sensitive prions were propagated in PK1 cells in the presence of the drug, a swainsonine-resistant prion population emerged after a few passages, documenting adaptation to the new environment. After withdrawal of the drug, further propagation for several splits again yielded drug-sensitive prions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Li2">[16]</xref>. These findings suggested that prion populations constitute so-called quasispecies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Eigen1">[17]</xref>, that is, they are composed of a variety of conformational variants, each present at a low level; when the environment changes, the most efficiently replicating variant becomes the predominant component of the population, which then constitutes a distinct sub-strain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Collinge1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Li2">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Weissmann2">[18]</xref>. Indeed, PK1 cell-adapted 22L populations were found to contain about 0.5% swainsonine-resistant variants before ever being exposed to the drug <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Li2">[16]</xref>. Because the 22L prions used in these experiments had been cloned by endpoint dilution years earlier, heterogeneity must have arisen by a mutation-like process in the interim. Mutations in the case of prions represent conformational changes and not modifications at the level of the protein sequence, because PrP is encoded by the host genome and the mutation is inherent to the proteinaceous particle. To verify whether heterogeneity of prion populations came about by mutation, swainsonine-sensitive prions were cloned by endpoint dilution into PK1 cells, and the infected cells were propagated serially for up to 100 doublings and challenged with swainsonine to determine at which stage the prion populations acquired the capacity for becoming resistant to the drug. Early after cloning the populations were incapable of doing so, but most clones developed this capability after 31–86 doublings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002582-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). However, at least one of nine populations failed to do so even after 116 doublings, suggesting that the prions were heterogeneous in regard to their ability to develop swainsonine resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Li1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Li2">[16]</xref>. Acquisition of drug resistance by murine prions has also been reported by Ghaemmaghami et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Ghaemmaghami1">[19]</xref> and by yeast prions by Shorter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Shorter1">[20]</xref>. Most if not all of the prion variants, or sub-strains, described above were reversible, suggesting that the underlying conformations were readily interconvertible. In contrast, strains are very stable, at least as long as they are propagated in the same species. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002582-g002">Figure 2</xref>, this suggests a low activation energy barrier between sub-strains, readily surmountable under physiological conditions, while high activation energy barriers prevent conversion between strains.</p>
      <fig id="ppat-1002582-g002" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002582.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Conjectural free energy landscape for prion strains and sub-strains.</title>
          <p>Sub-strains are depicted as distinguishable collectives of prions that can interconvert readily because they are separated by activation energy barriers that can be overcome in a particular environment under physiological conditions, while strains are separated by high energy barriers. The extent to which the individual wells are populated (red blocks) is determined by the accumulation rate of the particular sub-strain. When the environment changes, for example when prions are transferred between distinct tissues, different sub-strains may be favored. Adapted from reference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Weissmann2">[18]</xref>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002582.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s6">
      <title>Concluding Thoughts</title>
      <p>The finding that prions can acquire resistance to drugs has significant implications for drug design. Drugs targeted to PrP<sup>Sc</sup> may have to be administered in combination, as in the case of viruses, in particular HIV. Alternatively, drugs could be targeted to bind and stabilize PrP<sup>C</sup> or, in view of the finding that ablation of PrP<sup>C</sup>, at least in animals, is not detrimental to health <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Beler1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002582-Richt1">[22]</xref>, to suppress its synthesis. At present no therapeutically useful drugs are available, but deepening insight into the molecular biology of prions may pave the way to novel approaches.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>I thank Corinne Lasmezas for constructive comments.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Collinge1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collinge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>A general model of prion strains and their pathogenicity.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>318</volume>             <fpage>930</fpage>             <lpage>936</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Weissmann1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Thoughts on mammalian prion strains.</article-title>             <source>Folia Neuropathol</source>             <volume>47</volume>             <fpage>104</fpage>             <lpage>113</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Castilla1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castilla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hetz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>In vitro generation of infectious scrapie prions.</article-title>             <source>Cell</source>             <volume>121</volume>             <fpage>195</fpage>             <lpage>206</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Deleault1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deleault</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Supattapone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Formation of native prions from minimal components in vitro.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>9741</fpage>             <lpage>9746</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Wang1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zha</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2012</year>             <article-title>Genetic informational RNA is not required for recombinant prion infectivity.</article-title>             <source>J Virol</source>             <volume>86</volume>             <fpage>1874</fpage>             <lpage>1876</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Manuelidis1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manuelidis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Transmissible encephalopathy agents: virulence, geography and clockwork.</article-title>             <source>Virulence</source>             <volume>1</volume>             <fpage>101</fpage>             <lpage>104</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Dickinson1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1976</year>             <article-title>Scrapie in sheep and goats.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimberlin</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Slow virus diseases of animals and man</source>             <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Elsevier/North Holland</publisher-name>             <fpage>209</fpage>             <lpage>241</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Prusiner1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prusiner</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Molecular biology of prion diseases.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>252</volume>             <fpage>1515</fpage>             <lpage>1522</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Tanaka1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toyama</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>The physical basis of how prion conformations determine strain phenotypes.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>442</volume>             <fpage>585</fpage>             <lpage>589</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Kimberlin1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimberlin</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1977</year>             <article-title>Characteristics of a short incubation model of scrapie in the golden hamster.</article-title>             <source>J Gen Virol</source>             <volume>34</volume>             <fpage>295</fpage>             <lpage>304</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Li1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahal</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demczyk</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Mutability of prions.</article-title>             <source>EMBO Rep</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>191</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Kimberlin2">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimberlin</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>The genomic identity of different strains of mouse scrapie is expressed in hamsters and preserved on reisolation in mice.</article-title>             <source>J Gen Virol</source>             <volume>70</volume>             <fpage>2017</fpage>             <lpage>2025</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Klohn1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klohn</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoltze</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flechsig</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>A quantitative, highly sensitive cell-based infectivity assay for mouse scrapie prions.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>100</volume>             <fpage>11666</fpage>             <lpage>11671</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Mahal1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahal</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demczyk</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Prion strain discrimination in cell culture: the cell panel assay.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>20908</fpage>             <lpage>20913</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Browning1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Browning</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahal</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herva</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Abrogation of complex glycosylation by Swainsonine results in strain- and cell-specific inhibition of prion replication.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>19</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Li2">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Browning</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahal</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oelschlegel</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Darwinian evolution of prions in cell culture.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>327</volume>             <fpage>869</fpage>             <lpage>872</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Eigen1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eigen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1971</year>             <article-title>Selforganization of matter and the evolution of biological macromolecules.</article-title>             <source>Naturwissenschaften</source>             <volume>58</volume>             <fpage>465</fpage>             <lpage>523</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Weissmann2">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahal</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Browning</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Prions on the move.</article-title>             <source>EMBO Rep</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>1109</fpage>             <lpage>1117</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Ghaemmaghami1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaemmaghami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lessard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Legname</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Continuous quinacrine treatment results in the formation of drug-resistant prions.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Pathog</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>e1000673</fpage>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000673" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000673</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Shorter1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shorter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Emergence and natural selection of drug-resistant prions.</article-title>             <source>Mol Biosyst</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>1115</fpage>             <lpage>1130</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Beler1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Büeler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguzzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sailer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greiner</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Autenried</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Mice devoid of PrP are resistant to scrapie.</article-title>             <source>Cell</source>             <volume>73</volume>             <fpage>1339</fpage>             <lpage>1347</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002582-Richt1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasinathan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamir</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castilla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sathiyaseelan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Production of cattle lacking prion protein.</article-title>             <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>132</fpage>             <lpage>138</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>