<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plospath</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PPATHOGENS-D-11-00136</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Computational biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genomics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genome sequencing</subject>
                <subject>Metagenomics</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Microarrays</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genomics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genome sequencing</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Microbiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Virology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Emerging viral diseases</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Infectious diseases</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Viral diseases</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Pulmonology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Respiratory infections</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Veterinary science</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Veterinary diseases</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Veterinary virology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Virology</subject>
          <subject>Infectious Diseases</subject>
          <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
          <subject>Respiratory Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cross-Species Transmission of a Novel Adenovirus Associated with a Fulminant Pneumonia Outbreak in a New World Monkey Colony</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Cross-Species Transmission of a Novel Adenovirus</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Eunice C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Yagi</surname>
            <given-names>Shigeo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kelly</surname>
            <given-names>Kristi R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mendoza</surname>
            <given-names>Sally P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Maninger</surname>
            <given-names>Nicole</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Rosenthal</surname>
            <given-names>Ann</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Spinner</surname>
            <given-names>Abigail</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bales</surname>
            <given-names>Karen L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Schnurr</surname>
            <given-names>David P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Lerche</surname>
            <given-names>Nicholas W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Chiu</surname>
            <given-names>Charles Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Laboratory Medicine, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>UCSF-Abbott Viral Diagnostics and Discovery Center, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Viral and Rickettsial Disease Laboratory, California Department of Public Health, Richmond, California, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>California National Primate Research Center, University of California Davis, Davis, California, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Department of Psychology, University of California Davis, Davis, California, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>Department of Medicine, Division of Infectious Diseases, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Nemerow</surname>
            <given-names>Glen R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">The Scripps Research Institute, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">charles.chiu@ucsf.edu</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: ECC SY KLB DPS NWL CYC. Performed the experiments: ECC SY SPM NM AR AS CYC. Analyzed the data: ECC SY KRK NM KLB DPS NWL CYC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: ECC SY SPM NM AR AS KLB DPS NWL CYC. Wrote the paper: ECC SY KRK KLB DPS NWL CYC.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors received a viral discovery award from Abbott Diagnostics (to CYC). The University of California, San Francisco (UCSF) has also filed a patent application related to TMAdV. This does not alter the authors' adherence to all PloS Pathogens policies on sharing data and materials.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e1002155</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chen et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>Adenoviruses are DNA viruses that naturally infect many vertebrates, including humans and monkeys, and cause a wide range of clinical illnesses in humans. Infection from individual strains has conventionally been thought to be species-specific. Here we applied the Virochip, a pan-viral microarray, to identify a novel adenovirus (TMAdV, <underline>t</underline>iti <underline>m</underline>onkey <underline>ad</underline>eno<underline>v</underline>irus) as the cause of a deadly outbreak in a closed colony of New World monkeys (titi monkeys; <italic>Callicebus cupreus</italic>) at the California National Primate Research Center (CNPRC). Among 65 titi monkeys housed in a building, 23 (34%) developed upper respiratory symptoms that progressed to fulminant pneumonia and hepatitis, and 19 of 23 monkeys, or 83% of those infected, died or were humanely euthanized. Whole-genome sequencing of TMAdV revealed that this adenovirus is a new species and highly divergent, sharing &lt;57% pairwise nucleotide identity with other adenoviruses. Cultivation of TMAdV was successful in a human A549 lung adenocarcinoma cell line, but not in primary or established monkey kidney cells. At the onset of the outbreak, the researcher in closest contact with the monkeys developed an acute respiratory illness, with symptoms persisting for 4 weeks, and had a convalescent serum sample seropositive for TMAdV. A clinically ill family member, despite having no contact with the CNPRC, also tested positive, and screening of a set of 81 random adult blood donors from the Western United States detected TMAdV-specific neutralizing antibodies in 2 individuals (2/81, or 2.5%). These findings raise the possibility of zoonotic infection by TMAdV and human-to-human transmission of the virus in the population. Given the unusually high case fatality rate from the outbreak (83%), it is unlikely that titi monkeys are the native host species for TMAdV, and the natural reservoir of the virus is still unknown. The discovery of TMAdV, a novel adenovirus with the capacity to infect both monkeys and humans, suggests that adenoviruses should be monitored closely as potential causes of cross-species outbreaks.</p>
      </abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary">
        <title>Author Summary</title>
        <p>Infection from adenoviruses, viruses that cause a variety of illnesses in humans, monkeys, and other animals, has conventionally been thought to be species-specific. We used the Virochip, a microarray designed to detect all viruses, to identify a new species of adenovirus (TMAdV, or <underline>t</underline>iti <underline>m</underline>onkey <underline>a</underline>deno<underline>v</underline>irus) that caused a deadly outbreak in a colony of New World titi monkeys at the California National Primate Research Center (CNPRC), and also infected a human researcher. One-third of the monkeys developed pneumonia and liver inflammation, and 19 of 23 monkeys died or were humanely euthanized. The unusually high death rate (83%) makes titi monkeys unlikely to be natural hosts for TMAdV, and the genomic sequence of TMAdV revealed that it is very different from any other known adenovirus. The researcher developed an acute respiratory illness at the onset of the outbreak, and was found to be infected by TMAdV by subsequent antibody testing. A clinically ill family member with no prior contact with the CNPRC also tested positive. Further investigation is needed to identify whether TMAdV originated from humans, monkeys, or another animal. The discovery of TMAdV suggests that adenoviruses should be monitored closely as potential causes of cross-species outbreaks.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work is supported in part by CNPRC NIH grant NCRR P51-RR000169, NIH grant HD053555 (to KLB, SPM, and WAM), NIH grants K08-AI074913 and R56-AI089532 (to CYC), and an Abbott Viral Discovery Award (to CYC). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="16"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Adenoviruses, first isolated in the 1950s from explanted adenoid tissue, are double-stranded nonenveloped DNA viruses that naturally infect many vertebrates, including humans and nonhuman primates. The human adenoviruses in the <italic>Mastadenovirus</italic> genus, comprised of all mammalian adenoviruses, are classified into 7 species A-G, and at least 51 different serotypes (and 5 proposed types, HAdV-52 to HAdV-56) have been described to date <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Robinson1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Harrach1">[2]</xref>. Adenoviruses are the cause of an estimated 5–10% of febrile illnesses in children worldwide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Fox1">[3]</xref>. Some serotypes, such as human adenovirus type 14 (HAdV-14), have been associated with severe and potentially fatal outbreaks of pneumonia in residential facilities and military bases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Lewis1">[4]</xref>. Adenoviruses have also been associated with other clinical syndromes including conjunctivitis, hepatitis, and diarrhea <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Ruuskanen1">[5]</xref>. In nonhuman primates, most epidemiologic studies of adenoviruses have focused on their identification in fecal samples from asymptomatic animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Banyai1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Roy1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wevers1">[8]</xref>. Overt respiratory disease associated with simian adenoviruses has also been observed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Tong1">[9]</xref>. Although adenoviruses are significant pathogens, genetically modified strains are being actively explored as potential vectors for vaccines and gene therapy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Ghosh1">[10]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Infection by adenoviruses has generally been thought to be species-specific. Human adenoviruses do not usually replicate in monkey cells in the absence of helper viruses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Rowe1">[11]</xref>, and do not productively infect rodents (and vice versa) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Ginsberg1">[12]</xref>. Studies of sera from animal handlers and zoo workers exposed to chimpanzees in captivity fail to detect antibodies to chimpanzee adenoviruses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Basnight1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Xiang1">[14]</xref>. However, recent serological surveys have found antibodies to New World and Old World monkey adenoviruses in donor human sera from regions where the monkeys are endemic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Xiang1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Ersching1">[15]</xref>. In addition, phylogenetic analyses of adenoviruses from greater apes reveal that they fall precisely into “human” adenoviral species B, C, and E <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Roy1">[7]</xref>. The high degree of sequence relatedness within members of each species suggests that at least some adenoviral strains may be capable of infecting both nonhuman primates and humans.</p>
      <p>Beginning in May of 2009, a deadly outbreak of fulminant pneumonia and hepatitis occurred in a closed colony of New World titi monkeys of the <italic>Callicebus</italic> genus at the California National Primate Research Center (CNPRC). Routine microbiological testing for an infectious etiology was negative. We previously developed the Virochip (University of California, San Francisco) as a broad-spectrum surveillance assay for identifying viral causes of unknown acute and chronic illnesses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Chiu1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Chiu2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Chiu3">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Chiu4">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Urisman1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wang1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wang2">[22]</xref>. The Virochip, a pan-viral microarray containing ∼19,000 probes derived from all viral species in GenBank (n∼2500) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wang1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Greninger1">[23]</xref>, has been previously successful in detection of novel outbreak viruses such as the SARS coronavirus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wang2">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Rota1">[24]</xref> and the 2009 pandemic H1N1 influenza virus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Greninger1">[23]</xref>. Here we apply the Virochip to identify a novel and highly divergent adenovirus as the cause of the titi monkey outbreak. In addition, we present clinical and serological evidence that this virus may have infected a researcher at the CNPRC and a family member, thus demonstrating for the first time the potential for cross-species infection by adenoviruses.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>An outbreak of fulminant pneumonia in a titi monkey colony</title>
        <p>In early 2009, the CNPRC housed 65 titi monkeys in one quadrant of an animal building. The index case, a healthy adult titi monkey, presented on May 14, 2009 with cough, lethargy, and decreased appetite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>, T1). Despite aggressive treatment with intravenous fluids and antibiotics, the animal developed severe respiratory distress and was humanely euthanized 5 days later. A second case presented 4 weeks later near the entrance to the building (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>, T54). In the interim period, 3 healthy titi monkeys had been relocated from a separate building (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>, T2, T3, and T19), with 2 of the 3 monkeys placed into the cage formerly occupied by the index case, reflecting a total at-risk population of 68. Over the ensuing 2 months, 21 additional monkeys, including one of the relocated monkeys, presented with clinical signs similar to those shown by the index case (attack rate  = 23/68, or 34%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">Figs. 1A and 1B</xref>). Clinical signs in affected animals included cough, lethargy, poor appetite, tachypnea, and abdominal breathing. These symptoms progressed to overt respiratory distress and death or humane euthanasia within an average of 8 days. Chest radiographs typically revealed diffuse interstitial pulmonary changes and bronchoalveolar consolidation indicative of pneumonia, with right middle lobe predominance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). Animals displaying clinical signs were quarantined and aggressively treated by veterinarians with supplemental oxygen, anti-inflammatory medications, bronchodilators (nebulized albuterol), broad-spectrum antibiotics, and antivirals (oseltamivir and/or ribavirin). In total, 19 animals died or were euthanized due to the illness during the outbreak (case fatality rate  = 19/23, or 83%). Only 4 monkeys survived, even though the majority of sick animals (17/23, or 74%) consisted of apparently healthy adults and juveniles. Interestingly, none of the 133 rhesus macaques (<italic>Macaca mulatta</italic>) housed in the same building became sick during the outbreak, and neither did any of the Old World monkeys from surrounding outdoor colonies of rhesus and cynomolgus macaques (<italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic>).</p>
        <fig id="ppat-1002155-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Clinical and epidemiologic features of the titi monkey outbreak.</title>
            <p>(<bold>A</bold>) Map of the titi monkey cages situated in one quadrant of a building, showing the locations of asymptomatic, at-risk monkeys (brown or green), affected surviving monkeys (black), and monkeys who died from their illness (skeleton). 3 monkeys were moved into the building (arrows pointing down and to the left) and 4 monkeys out of the building (arrows pointing up and to the right) during the 3<sup>rd</sup> week of the outbreak. The upper left photograph shows an image of an adult male titi monkey and his infant. The upper right inset shows the location of the titi monkey cages relative to other rhesus monkey cages in the building. Asymptomatic monkeys with positive serum antibody titers to TMAdV 4 months after the outbreak are shown in green. (<bold>B</bold>) Epidemic curve of the outbreak, with the number of cases in blue and cumulative attack rate in red. (<bold>C</bold>) Anteroposterior chest radiograph of an affected titi monkey, showing bilateral basilar infiltrates and a prominent right middle lobe consolidation. (<bold>D</bold>) <bold><italic>1</italic></bold> – gross photograph of lungs at necropsy; the lungs failed to fully collapse upon opening the chest, and a single ∼1.5 cm focus of dark red discoloration (hemorrhage) can be seen in the left caudal lobe. <bold><italic>2</italic></bold> – photomicrograph of H&amp;E stained lung tissue showing a severe diffuse necrotizing bronchopneumonia characterized by the presence of hemorrhage and intranuclear inclusions (arrows). <bold><italic>3</italic></bold> – photomicrograph of H&amp;E stained liver tissue showing a multifocal necrotizing hepatitis with numerous intranuclear inclusions (arrows). <bold><italic>4</italic></bold> – transmission electron micrograph of an affected lung alveolus (scale bar  = 1 µm) filled with adenovirus-like particles (inset, scale bar  = 0.1 µm).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Gross necropsy findings were similar in all titi monkeys and were characterized primarily by diffuse, consolidated pneumonias, with occasional evidence of fibrinous pleuritis, pericardial/pleural edema, and hemorrhage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">Fig. 1D-1</xref>). Some livers, spleens, and lymph nodes were found to be abnormally enlarged. Hepatic necrosis and hemorrhage, along with ascites, were occasionally appreciated. On histologic examination, the normal cellular architecture of the lung and trachea was destroyed, and prominent intranuclear inclusion bodies were observed in the liver, lung, and trachea (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">Figs. 1D-2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">1D-3</xref>).</p>
        <p>A routine microbiological workup for infectious causes of the outbreak, including bacterial, mycoplasma, and fungal cultures, was negative. Respiratory viral testing failed to detect evidence of respiratory syncytial virus, adenovirus, influenza virus A and B, human metapneumovirus, and parainfluenza virus types 1, 2, and 3.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Virochip identification, PCR screening and electron microscopic (EM) confirmation of TMAdV</title>
        <p>Given the clinical presentation of a severe acute viral respiratory illness and the appearance of intranuclear inclusion bodies on histological examination, we strongly suspected that a virus that had eluded detection by conventional assays was the cause of the titi monkey outbreak. Nasal, lung, and liver swab samples collected during necropsy were analyzed using the Virochip <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wang1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Greninger1">[23]</xref>. Microarrays were analyzed using ranked Z-scores to assess the highest-intensity viral probes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Chiu3">[18]</xref>. From a lung swab sample from an affected monkey, 4 of the top 80 probes on the Virochip corresponded to adenoviruses. Other viruses or viral families with ≥4 probes among the top 80, including chimpanzee herpesvirus (<italic>Herpesviridae</italic>), bovine viral diarrhea virus (<italic>Flaviviridae</italic>), and endogenous retroviruses (<italic>Retroviridae</italic>), were regarded as less likely to cause fulminant pneumonia and hepatitis, so were not pursued any further. The 4 adenovirus probes mapped to 2 different gene regions corresponding to the DNA polymerase and penton base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). Interestingly, the 4 viral probes were derived from 2 different <italic>Adenoviridae</italic> genera (SAdV-23, simian adenovirus 23, PAdV-A, porcine adenovirus A, and HAdV-5, human adenovirus 5, in the <italic>Mastadenovirus</italic> genus; FAdV-D, fowl adenovirus D, in the <italic>Aviadenovirus</italic> genus), suggesting the presence of a divergent adenovirus that was not a member of any previously known species.</p>
        <fig id="ppat-1002155-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Discovery and whole-genome characterization of the novel adenovirus TMAdV.</title>
            <p>(<bold>A</bold>) The locations of the 4 Virochip probes derived from adenovirus sequences and used to detect TMAdV are mapped onto the ∼37 kB genome. The 4 Virochip probe sequences are also aligned with the corresponding sequence in the TMAdV genome, with mismatches highlighted in pink. (<bold>B</bold>) Coverage map of deep sequencing reads corresponding to TMAdV using BLASTN (blue) and TBLASTX (transparent blue) alignments to SAdV-18. The actual coverage achieved by deep sequencing as determined by alignments to the fully sequenced genome of TMAdV is much higher (red). (<bold>C</bold>) Genome organization of TMAdV. Predicted protein coding regions are shown as boxes. Boxes above the central black line represent open reading frames (ORFs) that are encoded on the forward strand, while boxes underneath the black line represent reverse-strand encoded ORFs. Early region ORFs are shaded in gray. The x-axis refers to the nucleotide position along the ∼37k genome of TMAdV. Abbreviations: FAdV, fowl adenovirus; SAdV, simian adenovirus; PAdV, porcine adenovirus; HAdV, human adenovirus, TMAdV, titi monkey adenovirus.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To confirm the Virochip finding of an adenovirus, we used consensus primers to amplify a 301 bp fragment from the hexon gene by PCR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Echavarria1">[25]</xref>. The fragment shared ∼86% nucleotide identity with its closest phylogenetic relatives in GenBank, SAdV-18, an Old World vervet monkey adenovirus, and the human species D adenoviruses. The newly identified adenovirus was designated TMAdV, or <underline>t</underline>iti <underline>m</underline>onkey <underline>ad</underline>eno<underline>v</underline>irus. Specific PCR for TMAdV was then used to screen body fluids and tissues from affected monkeys (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t001">Table 1</xref>). PCR results were positive from post-necropsy liver and lung tissues as well as from sera, conjunctival swabs, oral swabs, and nasal swabs collected at time of quarantine in 8 different affected monkeys, but were negative from a throat swab from an asymptomatic animal whose other 5 cage mates had become sick. In addition, nasal swabs were negative in 3 asymptomatic, minimal-risk titi monkeys housed in a separate building. To confirm the presence of virus in diseased tissues, we examined lung tissue from affected monkeys by transmission electron microscopy, revealing abundant icosahedral particles characteristic of adenovirus filling the alveoli (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">Fig. 1D-4</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="ppat-1002155-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>PCR screening for TMAdV.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="ppat-1002155-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sample</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sample Type</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCR Result</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Date Presenting with Clinical Signs</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Date of Necropsy</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Affected, at-risk titi monkeys (died)</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">§</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5/14/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5/19/2009</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T26</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/23/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/30/2009</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T28</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">conjunctival swab<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/16/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/25/2009</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nasal swab<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">liver swab<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">lung swab<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T29</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/26/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/31/2009</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T30</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/25/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/30/3009</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T33</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">lung swab<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6/23/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6/29/2009</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nasal swab<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T36</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">lung swab<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/7/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/14/2009</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">lung swab<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T60</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/15/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/22/2009</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T63</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6/20/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8/1/2009</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T67</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nasal swab<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">#</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/7/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8/13/2009</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nasal swab<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Affected, at-risk titi monkeys (survived)</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T31</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/10/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T32</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/12/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T34</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6/23/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T62</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7/8/2009</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Asymptomatic at-risk and minimal-risk titi monkeys</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T27</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">throat swab (n = 1)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">at-risk titi</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">stool from cages (n = 14)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">at-risk titi</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum (n = 29)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">minimal-risk titi</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">oral swab (n = 3)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">¶</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">minimal-risk titi</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">stool from cages (n = 5)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">minimal-risk titi</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum (n = 8)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">minimal-risk titi</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">stool from cages (n = 8)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">minimal-risk titi</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum (n = 8)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Other</italic>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rhesus</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rectal swabs (n = 26)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">human</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum (n = 15)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">∞</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rodent</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">droppings (n = 2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>For titi monkey cage designations (TXX), please refer to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label>§</label>
              <p>initial case.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label>#</label>
              <p>collected prior to outbreak.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label>¶</label>
              <p>collected during outbreak.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label/>
              <p>*collected 2 months after outbreak.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt106">
              <label>∞</label>
              <p>collected 4 months after outbreak.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>Next, to assess persistent subclinical infection from TMAdV, we analyzed serum samples from at-risk asymptomatic or affected surviving monkeys 2 months after the outbreak (n = 41). All post-outbreak serum samples were negative for TMAdV by PCR (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t001">Table 1</xref>). To assess potential TMAdV shedding, stool samples collected from all cages housing titi monkeys 2 months post-outbreak were analyzed by PCR (n = 27), and were found to be negative. In addition, we checked for TMAdV in rectal swab samples from rhesus macaques housed in the same building as the titi monkeys (n = 26) and in pooled droppings from wild rodents (n = 2) living near the titi monkey cages. All macaque and rodent fecal samples were negative for TMAdV by PCR.</p>
        <p>We also sought to determine whether PCR assays commonly used to detect human adenoviruses in clinical or public health settings could detect TMAdV. Adenovirus PCR was performed on a TMAdV-positive clinical sample, a TMAdV culture, and a human adenovirus B culture (as a positive control) using an additional 5 pairs of primers, according to previously published protocols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Hierholzer1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Lee1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Xu1">[28]</xref> Three of the 5 primer pairs, designed to detect human respiratory adenoviruses B, C, and E, failed to amplify TMAdV <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Lee1">[27]</xref>. The remaining 2 pairs of primers, both derived from highly conserved sequences in the hexon gene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Hierholzer1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Xu1">[28]</xref>, were able to detect TMAdV in culture as well as directly from clinical material.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Whole-genome sequencing, features, and phylogenetic analysis of TMAdV</title>
        <p>To facilitate whole-genome sequencing of TMAdV, deep sequencing of a lung swab from one affected titi monkey and lung tissue from another affected monkey was performed. Out of ∼11.9 million high-quality reads, 2,782 reads and 3,767 reads aligned to the SAdV-18 genome by BLASTN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>, blue) and TBLASTX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>, transparent blue), respectively, with reads mapping to sites across the genome. <italic>De novo</italic> assembly of the complete TMAdV genome from reads that aligned to SAdV-18 was not possible due to insufficient sequence coverage (&lt;46%). The poor apparent coverage was the result of high sequence divergence of the TMAdV genome from SAdV-18, which hindered the identification of most of the 16,524 actual deep sequencing reads derived from TMAdV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>, red). Thus, after partial assembly of TMAdV using overlapping reads aligning to the SAdV-18 genome, remaining gaps were closed by specific PCR. The complete genome of TMAdV was found to be 36,842 base pairs in length, with a base composition of 20.8% A, 29.8% C, 29.8% G, and 19.6% T, and a GC content of 59.6%, comparable to that of adenoviral species Groups C, D, and E in the <italic>Mastadenovirus</italic> genus. The deduced genomic structure of TMAdV was also similar to that of other mastadenoviruses and consists of 34 open reading frames (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>).</p>
        <p>Whole-genome phylogenetic analysis placed TMAdV in an independent species group separate from the known human adenoviral species A–G (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). Among all 95 fully-sequenced adenovirus genomes in GenBank, the closest simian adenoviral relatives to TMAdV were SAdV-3, SAdV-18, and SAdV-21, with pairwise nucleotide identities ranging from 54.0% to 56.3% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). The closest human adenoviral relatives were the species D adenoviruses, which share 54.3% to 55.1% identity to TMAdV, with human adenoviruses of other species slightly less similar (51.1%–54.6%). The placement of TMAdV into a separate group by phylogenetic analysis was also observed when looking individually at the hexon, polymerase, penton base, and fiber genes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002155.s001">Fig. S1</xref>). Scanning nucleotide pairwise identity plots revealed that, among the major adenovirus genes, the DNA polymerase and hexon are more conserved, whereas the E1A and fiber are more divergent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). The significant overall sequence divergence of TMAdV from known human and simian adenoviruses is highlighted by the finding that PAdV-A (porcine adenovirus A), a non- primate mammalian adenovirus, shared only a slightly less similar whole-genome pairwise identity to TMAdV of 47.0% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). In fact, in the DNA polymerase gene, TMAdV shared a pairwise identity with PAdV-A of 67.2%, comparable to its pairwise identities with the other human adenoviruses, 59%–71.7% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g004">Figs. 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002155.s001">S1</xref>). Although TMAdV was found to be highly divergent from other adenoviruses, different isolates of TMAdV from 3 affected titi monkeys were remarkably conserved, sharing 100% identity across the full-length hexon gene (data not shown).</p>
        <fig id="ppat-1002155-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Whole-genome phylogenetic analysis of TMAdV.</title>
            <p>The whole-genome nucleotide phylogenetic tree is reconstructed from a multiple sequence alignment of all 95 unique, fully-sequenced adenovirus genomes in GenBank and TMAdV. Both rectangular cladogram and radial tree layouts are displayed. The branch corresponding to TMAdV is highlighted in boldface red. Abbreviations: HAdV, human adenovirus; SAdV, simian adenovirus; MAdV, mouse adenovirus, FrAdV, frog adenovirus; TAdV, turkey adenovirus; SnAdV, snake adenovirus; DAdV, duck adenovirus; OAdV, ovine adenovirus; BAdV, bovine adenovirus; PAdV, porcine adenovirus; TSAdV, tree shrew adenovirus; CAdV, canine adenovirus.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="ppat-1002155-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Scanning pairwise alignment of representative adenoviruses with TMAdV.</title>
            <p>The scanning nucleotide pairwise identities of TMAdV relative to representative human (yellow) or simian (brown) adenoviruses in species A–G, porcine adenovirus (red), and fowl adenovirus (green) are shown. The window size is 400 bp with a step size of 40 bp. The x-axis refers to the nucleotide position along the ∼37 k genome of TMAdV. Abbreviations: HAdV, human adenovirus; SAdV, simian adenovirus; PAdV, porcine adenovirus; FAdV, fowl adenovirus.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The high level of sequence divergence in TMAdV held true at the amino acid level as well, with amino acid identities relative to other mastadenoviruses ranging from 20.8% to 27.5% for the fiber, the most divergent protein, to 68.7%–78.2% for the hexon (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t002">Table 2</xref>). Although bearing low sequence similarity to other adenoviruses, the penton base of TMAdV contained an RGD motif that presumably binds α<sub>v</sub> integrins. By both nucleotide and amino acid comparisons, the closest phylogenetic relative to TMAdV in GenBank overall was SAdV-3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g004">Fig. 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t002">Table 2</xref>). Bootscanning analysis revealed no evidence for recombination of TMAdV with other adenoviruses at either the whole-genome or individual gene level (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002155.s002">Fig. S2</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="ppat-1002155-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <title>Amino acid identity of TMAdV relative to other adenoviruses.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="ppat-1002155-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">fiber (IV)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E1A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DBP</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DNApol</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">penton base (III)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pTP</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hexon (II) whole</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hexon (II) ε:L1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hexon (II) ε:L2</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SAdV-3 (rhesus monkey)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.2%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.6%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.2%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.8%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.0%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SAdV-18 (vervet monkey)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.2%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.5%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.9%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HAdV-12 (species A)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.2%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.2%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.9%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HAdV-3 (species B)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.5%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.9%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SAdV-21 (species B)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.2%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.2%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.2%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HAdV-2 (species C)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.6%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.5%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.5%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.4%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SAdV-42 (species C)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.5%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.5%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.5%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.3%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HAdV-9 (species D)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.0%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HAdV-36 (species D)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.9%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HAdV-4 (species E)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.6%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.3%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SAdV-22 (species E)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.5%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.2%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.2%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.9%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HAdV-40 (species F)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.1%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.3%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SAdV-7 (species G)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.5%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.6%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.6%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HAdV-52 (species G)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.8%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.2%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">*</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.6%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAdV-A (porcine)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.4%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FAdV-A (fowl)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.5%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.0%</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt107">
              <label/>
              <p>The amino acid sequences of selected TMAdV proteins and the epsilon determinant of the hexon (ε: L1, loop 1, and ε: L2, loop 2) are compared to the corresponding proteins from representative human, simian, porcine, and fowl adenoviruses.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt108">
              <label/>
              <p>*For each protein, the entry corresponding to the adenoviral species with the highest percentage identity relative to TMAdV.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>The main neutralization determinant for adenoviruses, the epsilon determinant (ε), is formed by loops 1 and 2 in the hexon protein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Madisch1">[29]</xref>. The epsilon determinant of TMAdV was significantly divergent from that of other mastadenoviruses, with amino acid identities in loop 1 varying from 30.6% to 44.8% and in loop 2 varying from 54.4% to 67.0% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t002">Table 2</xref>). This observation suggested that cross-neutralization of TMAdV with sera reactive against other human/simian adenoviruses is unlikely.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Cultivation of TMAdV in human and monkey cells</title>
        <p>We next attempted to culture TMAdV in an A549 (human lung adenocarcinoma) cell line, a BSC-1 (African green monkey kidney epithelial) cell line, and PMK (primary rhesus monkey kidney) cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). Direct inoculation of cell cultures with a lung swab sample from an affected titi monkey produced a weak initial cytopathic effect in macaque BSC-1 and human A549 cells at day 7. However, despite multiple serial passages, we were unable to propagate the infected cell culture supernatant in either BSC-1 or PMK cells. In contrast, propagation in human A549 cells resulted in viral adaptation by passage 6 and generation of a fully adapted strain of TMAdV by passage 10 that was able to productively infect all 3 cell lines. Thus, culturing and propagation of TMAdV were successful in a human A549 cell line, but not in established or primary monkey kidney cell lines.</p>
        <fig id="ppat-1002155-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Growth and propagation of TMAdV in cell culture.</title>
            <p>The flow chart displays 10 passages (P1–P10) of TMAdV cultured in human lung adenocarcinoma (A549, orange), primary rhesus macaque kidney (PMK, brown), or established African green monkey kidney (BSC-1, green) cells.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>An influenza-like illness in a researcher and family members during the titi monkey outbreak</title>
        <p>In hindsight, only one individual at the CNPRC reported becoming ill during the titi monkey outbreak, the researcher in closest, daily contact with the animals. Symptoms began near the onset of the outbreak, although whether they began prior to or after identification of the index case is unclear. The researcher, with a past medical history of multiple sclerosis, initially developed symptoms of a viral upper respiratory infection (URI), including fever, chills, headache, and sore throat, followed by a dry cough and “burning sensation in the lungs” that was exacerbated by a deep breath or coughing. The researcher endorsed a history of recurrent upper respiratory infections, and did not regard the illness as related to the titi monkey outbreak. Although symptoms persisted for 4 weeks, at no time did the researcher seek medical care, and no antibiotics were taken during the illness.</p>
        <p>We carried out contact tracing to identify family members and other individuals in close contact with the researcher. Interestingly, two family members in the household also developed flu-like symptoms about 1–2 weeks after the researcher initially became sick. Their symptoms – fever, cough and muscle aches – appeared milder than those of the researcher and completely resolved within 2 weeks. Neither individual sought medical care for these symptoms, and notably, neither had ever visited the CNPRC.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Seroprevalence of TMAdV in monkeys and humans</title>
        <p>To explore a potential link between the outbreak and associated illness in humans, we blindly tested available sera from titi monkeys (n = 59), rhesus macaques housed in the same building (n = 36), CNPRC personnel and close contacts (n = 20), and random human blood donors (n = 81) for evidence of recent or prior infection by TMAdV by virus neutralization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). Nineteen serum samples from 15 at-risk affected (symptomatic) titi monkeys were tested. Among 3 affected titi monkeys surviving the outbreak, 2 monkeys mounted a vigorous neutralizing Ab response to TMAdV, with negative pre-outbreak Ab titers (&lt;1∶8) but antibody titers 2 months after the outbreak of &gt;1∶512, while 1 monkey exhibited a positive but much weaker response. Affected titi monkeys who died during the outbreak exhibited a wide range of neutralizing Ab titers, from &lt;1∶8 to &gt;1∶512 (those without Ab likely died before mounting a response).</p>
        <fig id="ppat-1002155-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Seroprevalence of TMAdV in humans and monkeys.</title>
            <p>Sera from titi monkeys (circles), rhesus macaques (squares), and humans (triangles) were tested for antibodies to TMAdV by virus neutralization. Arrows designate pre-outbreak and post-outbreak serum samples from the same individual monkey. Pre-outbreak serum samples were previously banked in 2007. Sera from CNPRC personnel and close contacts (orange triangles) were collected 4 months post-outbreak, except for the two family members of the clinically ill researcher, whose sera were collected 1 year post-outbreak. *, clinically ill researcher; **, family member of the researcher, who was also sick. Abbreviations: CNPRC, California National Primate Research Center; NEG, negative.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To investigate the possibility of subclinical infection by TMAdV, we also examined serum samples from asymptomatic titi monkeys (n = 40) and nearby rhesus macaques (n = 36), collected 2 months after the outbreak. Fourteen of 40 asymptomatic titi monkeys tested (35%) had antibody to TMAdV, indicating that the incidence of subclinical infection was significant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g006">Fig 6</xref>). In fact, one of the 14 asymptomatic titi monkeys with positive Ab titers was located in the minimal-risk building. In contrast, only 1 of 36 rhesus macaque samples was positive, with an Ab titer of 1∶16. The 1 antibody-positive rhesus serum sample was negative by specific PCR for TMAdV (data not shown), as was stool from the cage in which the rhesus monkey was housed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <p>Approximately 4 months after the outbreak, serum samples were collected from CNPRC personnel in direct contact with the titi monkeys. Serum samples were also collected from the two family members of the clinically ill CNPRC researcher 1 year after the outbreak. Only two samples were found positive for neutralizing Abs to TMAdV: (1) Ab titers for the clinically ill researcher were 1∶32, and (2) Ab titers for one of the family members of the clinically ill researcher were 1∶8.</p>
        <p>Among 81 random blood donors from the Western United States, 2 individuals (2/81, 2.5%) had positive Ab titers of 1∶16 and 1∶8. Pooled rabbit sera containing antibodies to human adenovirus serotypes 1 through 35, representing species A–E, were unable to neutralize TMAdV (data not shown). Thus, the results of our serological survey appear unlikely to be due to nonspecific cross-reactivity from prior exposure to known human adenoviruses.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this study, we employed a pan-viral microarray assay, the Virochip, to identify a novel adenovirus associated with a fulminant pneumonia outbreak in a colony of New World titi monkeys. Despite the absence of an animal model, which precludes a strict fulfillment of Koch's postulates, there are several lines of evidence implicating this novel adenovirus, TMAdV, as the cause of the outbreak. First, conventional testing for other pathogens, including other viruses by Virochip, was negative, and affected monkeys did not respond to empiric therapy with antibiotics or antivirals (ribavirin and oseltamivir in anecdotal use are not effective against adenoviral infections) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Echavarria2">[30]</xref>. Second, the clinical presentation of pneumonia and hepatitis is consistent with the known spectrum of disease associated with adenoviral infections. Third, TMAdV sequence was recovered by PCR in various body fluids and tissues from affected monkeys, including blood, respiratory secretions, and lung/liver tissue (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t001">Table 1</xref>). Fourth, the finding of intranuclear inclusions in diseased tissues, as well as direct visualization of adenoviral-like particles (TMAdV) in lung alveoli by electron microscopy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">Figs. 1D-2</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">1D-4</xref>), support a primary role for TMAdV in the pathogenesis of tissue injury in affected monkeys. Finally, there was a significant neutralizing Ab response in surviving animals, with 2 monkeys having titers undetectable prior to the outbreak but rising to &gt;1∶512 at convalescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g006">Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
      <p>Although TMAdV retains the core genomic features common to all adenoviruses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>), phylogenetic analysis clearly places TMAdV within a separate branch, with no closely related neighbors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g003">Figs. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002155.s001">S1</xref>). A phylogenetic distance of &gt;10% combined with the lack of cross-neutralization defines TMAdV as a new species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Harrach2">[31]</xref>. Since emerging adenovirus strains such as HAdV-14 and HAdV-D22/H8 (otherwise known as HAdV-D53) are known to arise from recombination events among related ancestral strains <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Kajon1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Walsh1">[33]</xref>, we performed bootscanning analysis to look for such events in TMAdV. The bootscanning analysis, however, failed to show evidence of recombination, likely because closely related and/or ancestral strains to TMAdV have not yet been identified.</p>
      <p>Entry of adenoviruses into cells involves an initial attachment of the fiber knob to the cell receptor, followed by internalization via a secondary interaction of the penton base with α<sub>v</sub> integrins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Defer1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wickham1">[35]</xref>. The presence of an RGD motif in the TMAdV penton base implies that the virus uses α<sub>v</sub> integrins for internalization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wickham1">[35]</xref>. However, the high sequence divergence in the fiber protein (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t002">Table 2</xref>), as well as the absence of fiber motifs conserved among adenoviruses that bind CAR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Law1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wu1">[37]</xref> (coxsackievirus-adenovirus receptor) or CD46 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Pache1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Pache2">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wu2">[40]</xref> (data not shown), suggest that neither of these two human adenoviral receptors may be the attachment receptor for TMAdV. Further studies will be necessary to identify the preferred cellular attachment and internalization receptors for TMAdV.</p>
      <p>Despite its isolation from affected titi monkeys, we were unable to propagate TMAdV in both established (BSC-1) and primary (PMK) monkey kidney cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). The virus, however, grew efficiently in a human A549 lung adenocarcinoma cell line. One explanation for this finding is that TMAdV may be unable to productively infect cells derived from Old World monkeys (e.g. rhesus and African green monkeys). An alternative possibility is that successful propagation of TMAdV may depend on infection of a specific host cell type, such as A549 lung, and not BSC-1 or PMK kidney cells. Nevertheless, after 10 passages in human A549 cells, the fully adapted strain of TMAdV exhibits an extended host range with the ability to productively infect both monkey and human cells. This observation implies that TMAdV possesses an inherent capacity to cross the species barrier and infect both humans and nonhuman primates. Efforts to identify host range and cell tropism of TMAdV, as well as the specific sequence changes responsible for adaptation to growth in cell culture, are currently underway.</p>
      <p>The virulence of TMAdV in healthy and apparently immunocompetent titi monkeys (83% case fatality rate) is highly unusual for infections by adenovirus. In humans, deaths due to adenovirus infections or outbreaks are generally low (up to 18% for pneumonia associated with HAdV-14 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Lewis1">[4]</xref>). Furthermore, severe infections from human adenoviruses are more commonly associated with older age, immunosuppression, and chronic underlying conditions such as kidney failure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Lewis1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Carrigan1">[41]</xref>. Young, healthy individuals are in general much less likely to succumb to adenoviral-related illness. The severity of TMAdV-related illness in affected titi monkeys suggests that this species of monkey may not be the natural host for the virus. The failure to detect fecal shedding of TMAdV in convalescent or asymptomatic animals also suggests that the virus does not normally infect titi monkeys (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      <p>Although the exact origin of TMAdV remains unclear, we can speculate on several possibilities. One possibility is that a cross-species “jump” from captive macaques to a susceptible colony of titi monkeys precipitated the outbreak. As there have been no new introductions of monkeys into the closed colony for the past 2 years, this conjecture relies on asymptomatic infection and transmission of TMAdV in the captive rhesus/cynomolgus macaque population at the CNPRC. CNPRC personnel who visited macaque areas would occasionally enter titi rooms with no change in personal protective equipment, thus providing a potential route of transmission for the virus. In addition, specific antibodies were detected in 1 of 36 (2.8%) asymptomatic rhesus macaques housed in the same building (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g006">Fig. 6</xref>), indicating that TMAdV has the capacity to infect this species of Old World monkey. Notably, the closest identified phylogenetic relative to TMAdV among the complete genomic sequences available in GenBank is a rhesus monkey adenovirus, SAdV-3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g004">Fig. 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t002">Table 2</xref>). Furthermore, serological evidence for cross-species adenoviral transmission events between different nonhuman primate species has been previously reported in the literature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Mwenda1">[42]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Although we failed to detect TMAdV in rodent droppings found near titi monkey cages (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t002">Table 2</xref>), it is still possible that the virus arose from an unknown animal reservoir. In this regard, the high sequence divergence of TMAdV relative to the known human/simian adenoviruses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g003">Fig. 3</xref>), and comparable sequence similarity in the polymerase gene to a porcine adenovirus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g003">Figs. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002155.s001">S1</xref>) are striking. The four-week interval between the index case and the second case appears overly long given a typical incubation period for adenovirus infections of no more than 1 week <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Lessler1">[43]</xref>. This may be explained by our finding of a high rate of subclinical infection by TMAdV in asymptomatic titi monkeys (35%), but may also be due to separate introductions of TMAdV into the colony from an as-yet unidentified reservoir.</p>
      <p>Our study data also support the potential for cross-species transmission of TMAdV between monkeys and humans. The researcher's fever, cough, and pleuritic symptoms (“burning sensation in the lungs”) are consistent with the development of a prolonged viral respiratory illness. Interestingly, pleurisy has been specifically reported in association with certain human adenovirus infections <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Kass1">[44]</xref>. The clinical presentation, time of illness concurrent with the onset of the outbreak, and presence of neutralizing Abs in convalescent serum all strongly point to primary infection of the researcher by TMAdV. The detection of weakly neutralizing Abs (1∶8) in a serum sample from a sick family member of the researcher also suggests that TMAdV may be capable of human-to-human transmission. The decreased levels of neutralizing Abs to TMAdV in the researcher (1∶32) and a family member (1∶8) relative to those in infected titi monkeys (up to &gt;1∶512) are consistent with a recent study showing much higher levels of neutralizing antibodies in chimpanzees than in humans with adenovirus infections, possibly due to more robust adenovirus-specific T-cell responses in humans than in monkeys <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Calcedo1">[45]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Several lines of evidence support the contention that the direction of TMAdV transmission was zoonotic (monkeys to humans) rather than anthroponotic (humans to monkeys). First, the closest known relative to TMAdV in GenBank is SAdV-3, an Old World monkey adenovirus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g003">Fig. 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t002">Table 2</xref>). Second, our results show that PCR assays for human adenoviruses in common use are capable of detecting TMAdV. Although sequencing of PCR amplicons for human adenoviruses is not performed routinely in diagnostic virology, TMAdV would presumably have been detected previously in large-scale studies of hexon sequencing of Ad field isolates if it were circulating in the community <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Lu1">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-McCarthy1">[47]</xref>. Finally, the available sequence data in GenBank is heavily biased towards human adenoviruses, and much less is known about the potential diversity of the simian adenoviruses. We also cannot formally exclude the possibility that the outbreak arose from anthroponotic transmission. In our study, 2 of 81, or 2.5% of random adult blood donors exhibited borderline titers of neutralizing antibody to TMAdV, indicating either a low prevalence of TMAdV in the human population or cross-reactivity to a related virus (although no evidence of cross-reactivity was found with HAdV serotypes 1 through 35). Future large-scale studies of TMAdV seroepidemiology will be needed to better understand transmission of TMAdV between monkeys and humans. Nevertheless, our discovery of TMAdV, a novel adenovirus with the capacity to cross species barriers, highlights the need to monitor adenoviruses closely for outbreak or even pandemic potential.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Ethics statement</title>
        <p>This study was carried out in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health. The use and care of all animals followed policies and guidelines established by the University of California, Davis Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) and CNPRC (Animal Welfare Assurance #A3433-01). The protocol for the maintenance and breeding of the titi monkey colony was approved by the University of California, Davis IACUC (Protocol #15730). No specific animal research protocol was drafted for this study, as only excess clinical samples were analyzed for diagnostic purposes. Animals in extreme respiratory distress were humanely euthanized by veterinarians. Extensive veterinary care was provided to all animals affected by the outbreak in order to minimize pain and distress.</p>
        <p>Serum samples from staff at the CNPRC, close contacts, and random adult blood donors were collected under protocols approved by institutional review boards of the University of California, Davis (Protocol #200917650-1) and University of California, San Francisco (Protocol #H49187-35245-01). Specifically, written informed consent was obtained from staff at the CNPRC and close contacts for analysis of their samples. Any potentially identifying information has been provided with the explicit permission of the individuals involved.</p>
        <p>Sera from random blood donors were obtained from the Blood Systems Research Institute (San Francisco, CA); sera were derived from affiliated donor banks in California (Blood Centers of the Pacific, San Francisco, CA), Nevada (United Blood Service, Reno, NV), and Wyoming (United Blood Services, Cheyenne, Wyoming) and de-identified prior to analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>The California National Primate Research Center (CNPRC)</title>
        <p>The California National Primate Research Center (CNPRC), which houses over 5,000 nonhuman primates, is a part of the National Primate Research Centers Program and is accredited by the Association for the Assessment and Accreditation of Laboratory Animal Care, International (AAALAC). At the beginning of 2009, the CNPRC maintained a colony of 74 titi monkeys (<italic>Callicebus cupreus</italic>) and a colony of over 4,500 rhesus macaques (<italic>Macaca mulatta</italic>). No new animals have been introduced into either colony for over 2 years. All titi monkeys are maintained in small social groups, while rhesus macaques are maintained in small or large social groups. All animal facilities are maintained in compliance with United States Department of Agriculture specifications.</p>
        <p>Eighty-eight percent of the titi monkey population (n = 65) were housed in 1 quadrant of an indoor animal building, and all titi monkeys demonstrating clinical signs originated from this building (i.e. “at-risk” room) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>). Rhesus macaques (n = 133) were housed in the other 3 quadrants of this same building, and surrounding the building were outdoor housing units with rhesus macaques and cynomolgus macaques (<italic>Macaca fasicularis</italic>). Three additional titi monkeys were moved into the at-risk room less than 2 weeks after presentation of the index case, reflecting a total at-risk population of 68 animals. The remaining 6 titi monkeys were housed in an indoor animal building greater than 500 yards from the at-risk population (i.e. “minimal-risk” room).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Outbreak investigation and microbiological testing</title>
        <p>The outbreak lasted approximately 3 months from May to August of 2009. Affected titi monkeys died from 3–24 days after appearance of clinical signs, with an average time to death or humane euthanasia of 8 days. Clinical and epidemiological data, including daily census reports, were tracked and recorded by veterinary and management staff. All personnel entering the titi monkey rooms (both at-risk rooms and minimal-risk rooms) needed to pass within approximately 20 feet of macaque enclosures prior to entry. CNPRC personal protective equipment (PPE) policy requires a change of PPE between entrance/exit of animal rooms housing different species. Staff compliance of this policy may have been compromised. Measures have since been taken by CNPRC management to ensure compliance with existing policies.</p>
        <p>Bacterial, mycoplasma, and fungal cultures were performed at the CNPRC. Clinical samples were also sent to an outside laboratory (Focus Diagnostics, Cypress, CA) for respiratory viral testing by centrifugation-enhanced shell vial culture followed by direct fluorescent antibody staining for 8 viruses (respiratory syncytial virus, adenovirus, influenza virus A and B, parainfluenza virus types 1, 2, and 3, and human metapneumovirus).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Gross, histopathological, and ultrastructural analyses</title>
        <p>Gross and histopathological analyses of post-mortem tissues were performed by a board-certified veterinary pathologist specializing in nonhuman primate/laboratory animal medicine, a branch of Primate Services at the CNPRC. At necropsy, tissue samples from the trachea, lung, and liver were collected and fixed in 10% formalin. Tissues were routinely processed and embedded in paraffin. 3-µm sections were stained with hematoxylin and eosin (HE) and examined by light microscopy. For transmission electron microscopy, tissue fragments (2×2 mm) were excised from paraffin blocks of lung, deparaffinized, and processed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Woods1">[48]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Nucleic acid extraction and cDNA library preparation</title>
        <p>Total nucleic acid was extracted from body fluid or swab samples using commercially available kits (Qiagen, Valencia, CA). 200 µL of sample were passed through a 0.22 µm filter (Millipore, Temecula, CA) to remove bacteria and cellular debris and then treated with Turbo DNase (Ambion, Culver City, CA) to degrade host genomic DNA prior to extraction. For tissue samples, lung or liver tissue was homogenized in a 15 mL Eppendorf tube using a disposable microtube pestle (Eppendorf, San Diego, CA) and scalpel, and RNA extraction was then performed using TRIzol LS (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), followed by isopropanol precipitation and two washes in 70% ethanol. Extracted nucleic acid was amplified using a random PCR method to generate cDNA libraries for Virochip and deep sequencing analyses as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Chiu3">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wang1">[21]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4f">
        <title>Virochip analysis</title>
        <p>The current 8×60 k Virochip microarrays used in this study contain 19,058 70mer probes representing all viral species in GenBank, and combine probes from all previous Virochip designs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Chiu2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Chiu3">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wang1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Greninger1">[23]</xref>. Four probes derived from 2 different <italic>Adenoviridae</italic> genera (SAdV-23, PAdV-A, HAdV-5, and FAdV-D) yielded an adenovirus signature on the Virochip that was found to be TMAdV. With the exception of SAdV-23, these highly conserved probes are part of the core Virochip design and were derived from all available adenoviral sequences in GenBank as of 2002 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wang1">[21]</xref>. One explanation why more high-intensity probes to simian adenoviruses were not seen by Virochip analysis is that the genomes of many simian Ads, including SAdV-3 and SAdV-18 (the two closest phylogenetic relatives to TMAdV in GenBank), were not sequenced until after 2004 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Roy1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Kovacs1">[49]</xref>, and thus their genomes are not as well-represented on the Virochip microarray.</p>
        <p>Virochip analysis was performed as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Wang1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Greninger1">[23]</xref>. Briefly, samples were labeled with Cy3 or Cy5 fluorescent dye, normalized to 10 pmol of incorporated dye, and hybridized overnight using the Agilent Gene Expression Hybridization kit (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, California). Slides were scanned at 3 µm resolution using an Agilent DNA Microarray Scanner. Virochip microarrays were analyzed with Z-score analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Chiu3">[18]</xref>, hierarchical cluster analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Eisen1">[50]</xref>, and E-Predict, an automated computational algorithm for viral species prediction from microarrays <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Urisman2">[51]</xref>. Only Z-score analysis, a method for assessing the statistical significance of individual Virochip probes, yielded a credible viral signature on the microarray.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4g">
        <title>PCR screening</title>
        <p>We initially used consensus primers derived from a highly conserved region of the hexon gene to confirm the Virochip finding of an adenovirus by PCR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Echavarria1">[25]</xref>. After recovering the full genome sequence, we then designed a set of specific PCR primers for detection of TMAdV, TMAdV-F (<named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GTGACGTCATAGTTGTGGTC</named-content>) and TMAdV-R (<named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CTTCGAAGGCAACTACGC</named-content>). The TMAdV-specific quantitative real-time PCR was performed on a Stratagene MX3005P real-time PCR system using a 25 µL master mix consisting of 18 µL of water, 2.5 µL of 10X <italic>Taq</italic> buffer, 1 µL of MgCl<sub>2</sub> (50 mM), 0.5 µL of deoxynucleoside triophosphates (dNTPs; 12.5 mM), 0.5 µL of each primer (10 µM), 0.5 µL SYBR green, 0.5 µL of <italic>Taq</italic> polymerase (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), and 1 µL of extracted nucleic acid. Conditions for the PCR reaction were 40 cycles of 94°C for 30 s, 55°C for 30 s, and 72°C for 30 s. Amplicons were purified on a 2% agarose gel, cloned into plasmid vectors using TOPO TA (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), and sent to an outside company (Elim Biopharmaceuticals, Hayward, CA) for Sanger sequencing in both directions using vector primers M13F and M13R.</p>
        <p>To assess linearity and limits of sensitivity for the TMAdV PCR assay, 12 serial log dilutions were made of a standard plasmid constructed by cloning the 157-bp TMAdV amplicon into a TOPO plasmid vector. Purified plasmid clones at each serial dilution were quantified using a Nanodrop spectrophotometer and then spiked into negative serum, stool, or oral swab sample matrix, each matrix consisting of a pool of 10 sera, 10 stool samples, or 3 oral swabs, respectively. For each sample type, a standard curve for the TMAdV PCR assay was calculated from 3 PCR replicates at each dilution of nucleic acid extracted from the spiked matrix (data not shown). To determine limits of sensitivity for the assay, probit analysis of results from 6 PCR replicates of 7 serial log dilutions (from a starting concentration of ∼1.2×10<sup>5</sup> copies/mL) was performed using SPSS 16.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL). By probit analysis, the 95% limit of detection for TMAdV was 781, 377, or 35 viral genome equivalents/mL for serum, stool, or oral swab samples, respectively (data not shown).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4h">
        <title>Whole-genome sequencing</title>
        <p>To facilitate whole-genome sequencing of TMAdV, we prepared amplified cDNA/DNA libraries for deep sequencing from lung tissue and a lung swab sample from 2 different monkeys using previously published protocols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Greninger1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Sorber1">[52]</xref>. Briefly, randomly amplified libraries were cleaved with a Type IIs restriction endonuclease (<italic>GsuI</italic>) and truncated adapters were ligated on the resulting strand ends. Full-length adapters containing strict 6-nt barcodes were added via an additional 15 cycles of PCR. Amplified libraries were size-selected on a 2% agarose gel at approximately 350 bp average length and then sent to an outside company (Elim Biopharmaceuticals, Hayward, CA) for deep sequencing on an Illumina Genome Analyzer IIx (Illumina, San Diego, CA). Paired-end reads were sequenced for 73 cycles in each direction. Paired-end reads were subsequently filtered to eliminate low-complexity sequences with a Lempel-Ziv-Welch (LZW) compression ratio below 0.4 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Welch1">[53]</xref>, split into individual reads, classified by barcode, and stripped of any remaining primer sequences using BLASTN alignments (word size = 11, E-value = 1×10<sup>−5</sup>). After low-complexity filtering and barcode/primer trimming, 11,950,557 sequence reads remained, with each read consisting of 67 nucleotides, for a total of ∼800 megabases of sequence. Reads were then aligned using BLASTN (word size = 11, E-value = 1×10<sup>−5</sup>) and TBLASTX (word size = 11, E-value = 1×10<sup>−5</sup>) to the genome sequence of SAdV-18 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>). Overlapping reads aligning to SAdV-18 were used to assemble portions of the TMAdV genome with Geneious software (version 3.6.5) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Drummond1">[54]</xref>, employing the SAdV-18 genome as a reference sequence and requiring a 20-bp minimum overlap and 95% overlap identity. Aligning reads were also used to design PCR primers to close remaining gaps in the TMAdV genome. Amplicons derived from specific TMAdV PCR primers were gel-purified, cloned, and sequenced as described above. The 5′ end corresponding to the inverted terminal repeat (ITR) of TMAdV was obtained by PCR using a forward degenerate consensus primer and a reverse TMAdV-specific primer. The 3′ end was recovered using a forward primer near the 3′ end of the genome and a reverse primer derived from 5′-ITR sequence.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4i">
        <title>Structural features and phylogenetic analysis</title>
        <p>To identify predicted coding regions in the TMAdV genome, we used the fully annotated genome sequence of SAdV-21 in GenBank as a reference. First, we aligned the two genomes and identified all ORFs that were present with Geneious <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Drummond1">[54]</xref>. We then selected the candidate ORF that best matched the corresponding ORF in the annotated reference genome. For adenovirus genes that are spliced (e.g. E1A), the identification of a GT-AG intron start-stop signal was used to pinpoint the correct ORF. To confirm the accuracy of the coding sequence, the sequence of each identified ORF was aligned to a database containing all adenoviral proteins in GenBank by BLASTX.</p>
        <p>To generate whole-genome and individual gene nucleotide phylogeny trees, all 95 fully sequenced unique adenovirus genomes were first downloaded from GenBank. Multiple sequence alignments were then performed on a 48-core Linux system using ClustalW-MPI <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Li1">[55]</xref>. Trees were constructed after bootstrapping to 1000 replicates by the neighbor-joining method (based on Jukes-Cantor distances) in Geneious <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Drummond1">[54]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Saitou1">[56]</xref>. Pairwise alignments were calculated using Shuffle-LAGAN (window size, 400 bp; step size 40 bp; translated anchoring), a glocal alignment algorithm that is able to calculate optimal alignments by using both local alignments and global maps of sequence rearrangements (e.g. duplications of the fiber gene in adenovirus genomes with 2 fibers) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Brudno1">[57]</xref>. Sliding window analysis of the Shuffle-LAGAN pairwise alignments was performed using the online mVISTA platform <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Frazer1">[58]</xref>. More accurate alignments were obtained with Shuffle-LAGAN than with either ClustalW-MPI or Geneious (data not shown). Bootscanning analysis was performed according to the Kimura 2-parameter method using 1000 replicates with Simplot (version 3.5.1) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Robertson1">[59]</xref>. Pairwise amino acid amino acid alignments between predicted TMAdV proteins and corresponding proteins in other adenoviruses (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002155-t002">Table 2</xref>) were performed using Geneious <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1002155-Drummond1">[54]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4j">
        <title>Virus cultivation</title>
        <p>A549 (human lung adenocarcinoma) and BSC-1 (African green monkey kidney epithelial) cell lines as well as PMK (primary rhesus monkey kidney) cells are routinely maintained at the Viral and Rickettsial Disease Laboratory (VRDL) branch of the California Department of Public Health. Media consisting of Hank's medium (for A549 cells) or Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) (for BSC-1 cells) were supplemented with 1×nonessential amino acids (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), 10% fetal bovine serum, 100 U of penicillin/mL and 100 µg of streptomycin/mL. PMK cells were maintained in tubes containing growth media and antibodies to SV-40 and SV-5 polyomaviruses (Viromed, Pasadena, CA). Clinical samples were clarified by centrifugation for 10 min×4000 <italic>g</italic> and passaged through a 0.2-µm filter. Cell culture passages were subjected to 3 freeze-thaw cycles and clarified as above. After achieving 80–90% confluency, cell culture media were changed to maintenance media with 2% FBS and were inoculated with 200 µL of clinical sample or 100 µL of passaged viral supernatant. Viral replication was monitored over 14 days by visual inspection under light microscopy for cytopathic effect (CPE). To confirm the generation of infectious virus, viral supernatants were quantitated by an end-point dilution assay.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4k">
        <title>Virus neutralization assay (human and monkey sera)</title>
        <p>A virus stock of TMAdV (passage 7) was produced on human A549 cells, aliquoted, and quantitated by end-point dilution. To perform the virus neutralization assay, 55 µL of viral supernatant at a concentration of 100 TCID<sub>50</sub> and 55 µL of serum (starting at a 1∶8 dilution) were mixed and incubated for 1 hour at 37°C. As a control for each serum sample, 55 µL of culture media and 55 µL of serum were mixed and treated in an identical fashion. While mixtures were incubating, A549 cells grown in T-25 plates were trypsinized and 4,000 cells in 100 µL of media were added to each well of a 96-well plate. After incubation, 100 µL of mixture were inoculated into appropriate wells containing 4,000 cells per well and the entire plate was placed in a 37°C 5% CO<sub>2</sub> incubator. Cells in the plate wells were observed for evidence of CPE every other day for 1 week. For wells that showed inhibition of viral CPE, the corresponding serum samples were diluted in six 2-fold steps and then retested. The reciprocal of the highest dilution that completely inhibited viral CPE was taken as the neutralizing antibody titer.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4l">
        <title>Virus neutralization assay (rabbit typing sera)</title>
        <p>To assess cross-neutralization of TMAdV by known human adenoviruses, 7 pools of in-house reference sera at the VRDL (rabbit hyperimmune sera) and collectively containing antibodies to human adenovirus serotypes 1 through 35 were available for testing. For each pool, 55 µL of rabbit sera and 55 µL of viral supernatant at a concentration of 100 TCID<sub>50</sub> were mixed, incubated for 1 hour at 37°C, and inoculated onto A549 cells in wells of a 96-well plate as described above. Cells in the plate wells were observed for evidence of CPE every other day for 1 week.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4m">
        <title>Microarray and nucleotide sequence accession numbers</title>
        <p>All Virochip microarrays used in this study have been submitted to the NCBI GEO database (study accession number GSE26898; microarray accession numbers GSM662370-GSM662391; microarray design accession number GPL11662). The annotated, whole-genome sequence of TMAdV has been submitted to GenBank (accession number HQ913600). Deep sequencing reads have been submitted to the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (accession number SRA031285).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="ppat.1002155.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Phylogenetic analysis of the hexon, polymerase, penton base, and fiber genes of TMAdV.</bold> A multiple sequence alignment of selected genes from all 95 unique, fully-sequenced adenovirus genomes in GenBank and TMAdV is performed and the results displayed as a radial phylogenetic tree. The branch corresponding to TMAdV is highlighted in boldface red. Abbreviations: HAdV, human adenovirus, SAdV, simian adenovirus; PAdV, porcine adenovirus; FAdV, fowl adenovirus.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="ppat.1002155.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002155.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Bootscanning recombination analysis of TMAdV.</bold> Bootscanning analysis was initially performed with all 95 unique, fully-sequenced adenovirus genomes in GenBank (data not shown). After removal of similar viral genomes, bootscan plots of the whole genome and individual genes from a subset representing human/simian adenoviruses in species A–G and all non-primate vertebrate adenoviruses were generated. The window size is 400 bp with a step size of 40 bp for the whole genome, and 200 bp with a step size of 20 bp for the individual genes. The x-axis refers to the nucleotide position. For definition of abbreviations, please refer to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002155-g003">Fig. 3</xref>.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Kathy West for providing a titi monkey photograph, Dr. Don Canfield for the gross pathology and histopathology images as well as expert interpretation, and Grete Adamson for the transmission electron microscopy. We thank Kristine Ren, R.N., for phlebotomy assistance. We are grateful to Alexander Greninger and Guixia Yu for technical support, and to Drs. Eric Delwart and Michael Busch at the Blood Systems Research Institute for providing serum samples from random adult blood donors for screening. We also thank Dr. Sarah Arron at UCSF, Dr. Jean Patterson at the Southwest Foundation for Biomedical Research, and Dr. Sharon Messenger at the California Department of Public Health for helpful advice and feedback. Finally, we would like to recognize all of the CNPRC husbandry, management, pathology, research, and veterinary staff who worked diligently to provide excellent care for the titi monkey colony devastated by the outbreak.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Robinson1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henquell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peigue-Lafeuille</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Computational analysis and identification of an emergent human adenovirus pathogen implicated in a respiratory fatality.</article-title>             <source>Virology</source>             <volume>409</volume>             <fpage>141</fpage>             <lpage>147</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Harrach1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrach</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benkõ</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Both</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title><italic>Family Adenoviridae</italic>.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carstens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefkowitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Virus Taxonomy: 9th Report of the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Fox1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooney</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1977</year>             <article-title>The Seattle Virus Watch. VII. Observations of adenovirus infections.</article-title>             <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>             <volume>105</volume>             <fpage>362</fpage>             <lpage>386</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Lewis1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdman</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>A community-based outbreak of severe respiratory illness caused by human adenovirus serotype 14.</article-title>             <source>J Infect Dis</source>             <volume>199</volume>             <fpage>1427</fpage>             <lpage>1434</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Ruuskanen1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruuskanen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meurman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akusjarvi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Adenoviruses.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitley</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Clinical Virology</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Churchill Livingstone</publisher-name>             <comment>xvi</comment> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">1355</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Banyai1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banyai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esona</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Molecular detection of novel adenoviruses in fecal specimens of captive monkeys with diarrhea in China.</article-title>             <source>Vet Microbiol</source>             <volume>142</volume>             <fpage>416</fpage>             <lpage>419</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Roy1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenberghe</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kryazhimskiy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calcedo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Isolation and characterization of adenoviruses persistently shed from the gastrointestinal tract of non-human primates.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Pathog</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>e1000503</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Wevers1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wevers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leendertz</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scuda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boesch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>A novel adenovirus of Western lowland gorillas (Gorilla gorilla gorilla).</article-title>             <source>Virol J</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>303</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Tong1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Identification of adenoviruses in fecal specimens from wild chimpanzees (Pan trogylodytes schweinfurthii) in western Tanzania.</article-title>             <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>             <volume>82</volume>             <fpage>967</fpage>             <lpage>970</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Ghosh1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gopinath</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Adenoviral vectors: a promising tool for gene therapy.</article-title>             <source>Appl Biochem Biotechnol</source>             <volume>133</volume>             <fpage>9</fpage>             <lpage>29</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Rowe1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1962</year>             <article-title>A general review of the adenoviruses.</article-title>             <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>             <volume>101</volume>             <fpage>466</fpage>             <lpage>474</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Ginsberg1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ginsberg</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moldawer</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Redington</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilian</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>A mouse model for investigating the molecular pathogenesis of adenovirus pneumonia.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>88</volume>             <fpage>1651</fpage>             <lpage>1655</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Basnight1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basnight</surname><given-names>M</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gajdusek</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1971</year>             <article-title>Characterization of four new adenovirus serotypes isolated from chimpanzee tissue explants.</article-title>             <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>             <volume>94</volume>             <fpage>166</fpage>             <lpage>171</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Xiang1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellenberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Chimpanzee adenovirus antibodies in humans, sub-Saharan Africa.</article-title>             <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>1596</fpage>             <lpage>1599</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Ersching1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ersching</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cezarotto</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Neutralizing antibodies to human and simian adenoviruses in humans and New-World monkeys.</article-title>             <source>Virology</source>             <volume>407</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>6</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Chiu1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alizadeh</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rouskin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merker</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Diagnosis of a critical respiratory illness caused by human metapneumovirus by use of a pan-virus microarray.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>             <volume>45</volume>             <fpage>2340</fpage>             <lpage>2343</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Chiu2">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greninger</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwok</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Identification of cardioviruses related to Theiler's murine encephalomyelitis virus in human infections.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>105</volume>             <fpage>14124</fpage>             <lpage>14129</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Chiu3">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rouskin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koshy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urisman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Microarray detection of human parainfluenzavirus 4 infection associated with respiratory failure in an immunocompetent adult.</article-title>             <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>             <volume>43</volume>             <fpage>e71</fpage>             <lpage>76</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Chiu4">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urisman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenhow</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rouskin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Utility of DNA microarrays for detection of viruses in acute respiratory tract infections in children.</article-title>             <source>J Pediatr</source>             <volume>153</volume>             <fpage>76</fpage>             <lpage>83</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Urisman1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urisman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molinaro</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Identification of a novel Gammaretrovirus in prostate tumors of patients homozygous for R462Q RNASEL variant.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Pathog</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>e25</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Wang1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coscoy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zylberberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avila</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boushey</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Microarray-based detection and genotyping of viral pathogens.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>99</volume>             <fpage>15687</fpage>             <lpage>15692</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Wang2">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urisman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ksiazek</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Viral discovery and sequence recovery using DNA microarrays.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>1</volume>             <fpage>E2</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Greninger1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greninger</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sittler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheinerman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roubinian</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>A metagenomic analysis of pandemic influenza A (2009 H1N1) infection in patients from North America.</article-title>             <source>PLoS One</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>e13381</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Rota1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rota</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberste</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monroe</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nix</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campagnoli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Characterization of a novel coronavirus associated with severe acute respiratory syndrome.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>300</volume>             <fpage>1394</fpage>             <lpage>1399</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Echavarria1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Echavarria</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ticehurst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumler</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charache</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>PCR method for detection of adenovirus in urine of healthy and human immunodeficiency virus-infected individuals.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>             <volume>36</volume>             <fpage>3323</fpage>             <lpage>3326</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Hierholzer1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hierholzer</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halonen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlen</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonough</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Detection of adenovirus in clinical specimens by polymerase chain reaction and liquid-phase hybridization quantitated by time-resolved fluorometry.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>             <volume>31</volume>             <fpage>1886</fpage>             <lpage>1891</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Lee1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grindle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>High-throughput, sensitive, and accurate multiplex PCR-microsphere flow cytometry system for large-scale comprehensive detection of respiratory viruses.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>             <volume>45</volume>             <fpage>2626</fpage>             <lpage>2634</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Xu1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonough</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdman</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Species-specific identification of human adenoviruses by a multiplex PCR assay.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>             <volume>38</volume>             <fpage>4114</fpage>             <lpage>4120</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Madisch1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madisch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harste</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pommer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of the main neutralization and hemagglutination determinants of all human adenovirus prototypes as a basis for molecular classification and taxonomy.</article-title>             <source>J Virol</source>             <volume>79</volume>             <fpage>15265</fpage>             <lpage>15276</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Echavarria2">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Echavarria</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Adenoviruses in immunocompromised hosts.</article-title>             <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>704</fpage>             <lpage>715</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Harrach2">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrach</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benkõ</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Both</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Family Adenoviridae.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carstens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefkowitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Virus Taxonomy (9th Report of the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses)</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Kajon1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kajon</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdman</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Louie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schnurr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Molecular epidemiology and brief history of emerging adenovirus 14-associated respiratory disease in the United States.</article-title>             <source>J Infect Dis</source>             <volume>202</volume>             <fpage>93</fpage>             <lpage>103</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Walsh1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chintakuntlawar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madisch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrach</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Evidence of molecular evolution driven by recombination events influencing tropism in a novel human adenovirus that causes epidemic keratoconjunctivitis.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e5635</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Defer1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Defer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belin</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caillet-Boudin</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boulanger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Human adenovirus-host cell interactions: comparative study with members of subgroups B and C.</article-title>             <source>J Virol</source>             <volume>64</volume>             <fpage>3661</fpage>             <lpage>3673</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Wickham1">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathias</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheresh</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemerow</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Integrins alpha v beta 3 and alpha v beta 5 promote adenovirus internalization but not virus attachment.</article-title>             <source>Cell</source>             <volume>73</volume>             <fpage>309</fpage>             <lpage>319</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Law1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Law</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>What does it take to bind CAR?</article-title>             <source>Mol Ther</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>599</fpage>             <lpage>609</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Wu1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemerow</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Virus yoga: the role of flexibility in virus host cell recognition.</article-title>             <source>Trends Microbiol</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>162</fpage>             <lpage>169</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Pache1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pache</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venkataraman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemerow</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Conservation of fiber structure and CD46 usage by subgroup B2 adenoviruses.</article-title>             <source>Virology</source>             <volume>375</volume>             <fpage>573</fpage>             <lpage>579</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Pache2">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pache</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venkataraman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemerow</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Structural variations in species B adenovirus fibers impact CD46 association.</article-title>             <source>J Virol</source>             <volume>82</volume>             <fpage>7923</fpage>             <lpage>7931</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Wu2">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trauger</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pache</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Seggern</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Membrane cofactor protein is a receptor for adenoviruses associated with epidemic keratoconjunctivitis.</article-title>             <source>J Virol</source>             <volume>78</volume>             <fpage>3897</fpage>             <lpage>3905</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Carrigan1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrigan</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Adenovirus infections in immunocompromised patients.</article-title>             <source>Am J Med</source>             <volume>102</volume>             <fpage>71</fpage>             <lpage>74</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Mwenda1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mwenda</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyachieo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langat</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Serological detection of adenoviruses in non-human primates maintained in a colony in Kenya.</article-title>             <source>East Afr Med J</source>             <volume>82</volume>             <fpage>371</fpage>             <lpage>375</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Lessler1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lessler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brookmeyer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perl</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Incubation periods of acute respiratory viral infections: a systematic review.</article-title>             <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>291</fpage>             <lpage>300</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Kass1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kass</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reamy</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Pleurisy.</article-title>             <source>Am Fam Physician</source>             <volume>75</volume>             <fpage>1357</fpage>             <lpage>1364</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Calcedo1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Calcedo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenberghe</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somanathan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Host immune responses to chronic adenovirus infections in human and nonhuman primates.</article-title>             <source>J Virol</source>             <volume>83</volume>             <fpage>2623</fpage>             <lpage>2631</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Lu1">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdman</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Molecular typing of human adenoviruses by PCR and sequencing of a partial region of the hexon gene.</article-title>             <source>Arch Virol</source>             <volume>151</volume>             <fpage>1587</fpage>             <lpage>1602</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-McCarthy1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lebeck</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capuano</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schnurr</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Molecular typing of clinical adenovirus specimens by an algorithm which permits detection of adenovirus coinfections and intermediate adenovirus strains.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Virol</source>             <volume>46</volume>             <fpage>80</fpage>             <lpage>84</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Woods1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swift</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horzinek</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordhausen</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Systemic adenovirus infection associated with high mortality in mule deer (Odocoileus hemionus) in California.</article-title>             <source>Vet Pathol</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>125</fpage>             <lpage>132</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Kovacs1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zakhartchouk</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrach</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Analysis of the first complete genome sequence of an Old World monkey adenovirus reveals a lineage distinct from the six human adenovirus species.</article-title>             <source>J Gen Virol</source>             <volume>85</volume>             <fpage>2799</fpage>             <lpage>2807</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Eisen1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spellman</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Cluster analysis and display of genome-wide expression patterns.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>95</volume>             <fpage>14863</fpage>             <lpage>14868</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Urisman2">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urisman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>E-Predict: a computational strategy for species identification based on observed DNA microarray hybridization patterns.</article-title>             <source>Genome Biol</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>R78</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Sorber1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorber</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruby</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>The long march: a sample preparation technique that enhances contig length and coverage by high-throughput short-read sequencing.</article-title>             <source>PLoS ONE</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>e3495</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Welch1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1984</year>             <article-title>A Technique for High-Performance Data-Compression.</article-title>             <source>Computer</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>8</fpage>             <lpage>19</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Drummond1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heled</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kearse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Geneious v5.3.4.</article-title>             <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneious.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.geneious.com</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Li1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>ClustalW-MPI: ClustalW analysis using distributed and parallel computing.</article-title>             <source>Bioinformatics</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>1585</fpage>             <lpage>1586</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Saitou1">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>The neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees.</article-title>             <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>406</fpage>             <lpage>425</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Brudno1">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brudno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poliakov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Do</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Couronne</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Glocal alignment: finding rearrangements during alignment.</article-title>             <source>Bioinformatics</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <supplement>Suppl 1</supplement>             <fpage>i54</fpage>             <lpage>62</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Frazer1">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frazer</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poliakov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubchak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>VISTA: computational tools for comparative genomics.</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>             <volume>32</volume>             <fpage>W273</fpage>             <lpage>279</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1002155-Robertson1">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Recombination in AIDS viruses.</article-title>             <source>J Mol Evol</source>             <volume>40</volume>             <fpage>249</fpage>             <lpage>259</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>